译者导读

约翰·罗斯金（John Ruskin，1819—1900）是英国维多利亚时代最伟大的艺术及社会评论家。他在知识界的影响力从十九世纪后半叶开始一直延续到今天，可谓影响深远，跨越时代。

罗斯金的一生著述甚丰，其作品涵盖了广阔的领域，体裁也多种多样，然而，罗斯金最具影响力的作品大多集中在艺术及社会评论方面。他最为重要的艺术评论大多出自《现代画家》（1843—1960）和《建筑七灯》（1849）两部著作。作为艺术评论家，他的作品改变了维多利亚时代人们对于艺术的认知，同时他还是“哥特复兴”（Gothic Revival）建筑运动及“前拉斐尔派”（Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood）艺术运动的主要幕后推手。作为社会评论家，他支持改变穷人们的生活窘况，颂扬手工艺劳动的尊严、道德及美学价值，反对工厂劳动的日益机械化，因为他认为这种劳动既枯燥乏味又毁灭灵魂。因此，罗斯金也成为十九世纪“艺术与工艺运动”（Arts&Crafts Movement）的精神领袖。

此书收录了罗斯金在不同时期的四篇重要作品。它们分别是“记忆之灯”“剑桥艺术学校：开学致辞（1858）”“国王的宝藏”“交易”。

“记忆之灯”是出版于1849年的《建筑七灯》中的一篇。罗斯金在书名中以“灯”冠之是为了表明它们是自己所理解的、建筑的七条原则。“记忆之灯”探讨的主要议题是建筑在文化传承方面所应当扮演的角色。罗斯金认为好的建筑应当犹如一座历史的丰碑，向子孙后代永远地传递建造它的那个时代的文化信息。从十九世纪六十年代起，罗斯金开始大量出席各种讲座及演讲活动。本书所收录的后三篇文章就是他在这一时期的演讲词。在“剑桥艺术学校：开学致辞（1858）”中，罗斯金论述了艺术教育的原则。他认为在大众的、通用的艺术学校里面，学生首先要学会的是观察，是提高鉴赏力，是对艺术的热爱，而非从事艺术创作。“国王的宝藏”最早出现在1865年出版的《芝麻与百合》中，是其中的第一篇。这篇演讲连同第二篇“王后的花园”一起，阐明了男人和女人各自的天性及所应承担的责任。罗斯金在“国王的宝藏”中重点探讨了建立并资助公共图书馆的意义所在，并且论述了为什么要阅读经典及如何阅读经典等重要的议题。“交易”是罗斯金在1864年于布拉福德市政厅的演讲。他在演讲中集中讨论了品味和道德的关系。他认为品味不是道德的一部分或是道德的表征，而是道德的全部。罗斯金的作品犹如一座巨大的宝库，然而到底能从其中挖掘到什么，则在很大程度上取决于我们读者自身所具备的禀赋。

翻译是件无比艰辛而又孤独的工作，如同一个人在漆黑的夜里行走在漫长而崎岖的道路上。所幸的是，在这孤独的夜路之上有一位伟大的思想者与我相伴而行，他就是约翰·罗斯金。他手中擎着那永不熄灭的灯盏，用充满睿智的言语照亮了我前进的路程。就像罗斯金在这本书开始时所说的那样：“在我的一生中，有些时刻值得以特别感激的心情去回味。那时，喜悦异常的丰满，教诲也异常的清澈。”——翻译《记忆之灯》的过程就是这样的时刻。

记忆之灯

在我的一生中，有些时刻值得以特别感激的心情去回味。那时，喜悦异常的丰满，教诲也异常的清澈。那是几年前的一个傍晚，我漫步在流经法国东部汝拉省尚帕尼奥勒村的爱恩河河畔的松林中。这里充满了阿尔卑斯山的庄严，却丝毫没有它的荒凉；这里，大地蕴藏着的巨大能量似乎正要显现，绵延起伏的松岗透露出深沉而高贵的和谐；这里，群山奏出交响乐的第一个音符，不久便抬高了调门，如惊涛般拍散在了阿尔卑斯山的群峰之上，然而群山的力量是有节制的；绵延的、长满牧草的山脊层层叠加，像是来自大海的怒涛，涌过平静的水面，发出长长的叹息。在这广袤的单调中弥漫着深深的柔情。中部山脉的破坏力连同他严肃的表情都不见了。柔软的汝拉牧场没有古老冰川冰刨石塞的侵蚀印记；没有成堆的碎石瓦砾破坏汝拉森林的美丽容颜；也没有苍白的、肮脏的，或是暴怒的河流在她的岩石间粗鲁地撕扯、蜿蜒。清澈的、绿色的溪水在熟悉的河床中流淌，耐心地、一个一个地打着旋涡。在静谧的松树的遮盖下，一簇簇的花朵年复一年地冒出头儿，我不知道这世界上还有什么比它们更快乐。那时正值春天，花团锦簇，争相斗艳；尽管空间足够，它们还是把叶子挤压成了各种奇形的怪状，只为了紧紧地挨在一起。银莲花星星点点，三五成群，如天上的星云一般；酢浆草成群结队，如同五月节向童贞女马利亚致敬的游行队伍一样塞满了石灰岩上黑色的垂直裂缝，它们洁白如雪，边上盘绕着像葡萄树枝蔓一样轻快而可爱的常春藤；一眨眼的工夫，紫罗兰便会喷涌而出，而报春花也在有阳光的地方绽放开来；在较为开阔一点的地方，野豌豆、雏菊、瑞香、宝石蓝色的远志的花蕾及野草莓的花儿都沉浸在浓重、温暖、琥珀色的地衣那金黄色的温柔乡里了。我走出松林，来到山涧边上：涧水的隆隆轰鸣声从脚下突然冒了上来，与松枝上画眉鸟的鸣唱混合在了一起；山涧的对面是灰色的石灰岩峭壁，一只猎鹰在峭壁的边缘缓缓滑翔，翅膀几乎碰到了岩壁，松树的影子倒映在它闪闪发光的羽毛上；而在它身下数百英尺的地方，绿色的河水正打着旋涡，泛着令人晕眩的点点金光欢快地流淌着，水中的浪花同天上的猎鹰一起飞翔。感受这种孤独和严肃的美丽是不能掺杂任何私心杂念的。我清楚地记得，当自己试图要更为确切地捕捉到这种令人难忘的美丽背后的根源时——比如暂时把它想象成新大陆原始森林的景象，便瞬间感到头脑空白，身体冰凉。花朵顷刻间失去了光彩，河水停止了歌唱，群山变得压抑而荒芜。幽暗森林中的枝干仿佛在沉痛地诉说，诉说它们先前的力量其实是他人的赐予，而不朽的光辉和持续的重生再造则是诞生于它们珍贵的记忆。那些不断开放的花朵和永不停息的河流被人类的忍耐、勇敢和美德的深色所浸染；在夜空的映衬下，黑色群山的峰顶更是受到了人们的膜拜，因为它们向东投下的长长阴影笼罩住了朱克斯的铁墙及格朗松的四方要塞。

我们应当以最严肃的态度对待建筑，因为她是这种神圣影响的集中体现和守护者。没有了建筑我们可以生存，可以祈祷，却将失去记忆。与一个民族所记载的内容和不朽的大理石所承载的内涵相比，一切历史是多么的冰冷，一切意象又是多么的了无生气！——几块石头的堆砌就会省却我们长篇累牍的含混记述！雄心勃勃的巴别塔的建造者告诉我们，只有两件东西可以征服人类的健忘——诗歌和建筑。而后者在某种意义上包括了前者，而且事实上更为强大，因为它如实地记载了人们生活的全部——人们的所思所感、所创所造、所见所闻。荷马的时代为黑暗所包围，有关他的个性也是众说纷纭，然而伯里克利的时代则清晰得多：毋庸讳言，与古希腊甜美的歌手和士兵历史学家相比，我们从其破碎的雕塑中学到了更多的东西。如果了解历史确有裨益，青史留名又是乐事一件的话（因为这样可以为我们当前的努力注入力量，为现在的坚持提供耐心），那么对于一个民族的建筑来说，我们就肩负着两项责任，而其重要性怎么说也不为过：第一，使当代的建筑彪炳史册；第二，将过去时代的建筑作为最珍贵的遗产加以保护。

就第一项责任来说，记忆确实可以称得上是建筑的第六盏明灯，因为只有具有纪念意义或是不朽的价值，民用和家居建筑才会变得真正完美。之所以如此，是因为带着这样一种观念，建筑会建造得更为牢固；而且建筑装饰会由于其隐喻性和历史性的内涵而显得栩栩如生。

就家居建筑而言，这种观念一定存在着某种局限性，因为无论是人心还是人力都会有所不及。不过我还是认为，某个民族建造房屋仅供一代人居住的做法是罪恶的。在善良人居住的房屋中有一种圣洁，而这种圣洁不是在其废墟上新建住宅就可以获得重生。我认为善良的人们通常会感受到这一点。由于在这幢房子里度过了欢乐和有尊严的一生，因此他们会在生命即将结束的时候感到悲伤，认为这幢见证，或是参与了他们所有的荣誉、欢乐或是痛苦的房子，这个自己在人世间的居所，连同它所承载的所有有关自己的记录，所有他们曾经爱过、拥有过的物质财富，所有他们曾经留下过的印记，就要在自己葬身墓地之后被扫除干净；人们对它不怀敬意，没有感情，孩子们也认为它一无是处；尽管在教堂里竖立着自己的墓碑，家里却不再有自己温暖的栖身之所；他们所有曾经珍视的东西都被厌弃，曾经为他们提供保护和慰藉的房子被夷为平地。我认为一位善良的人会对此感到恐惧；更进一步来说，一位善良的儿子，一位高贵的子嗣，会因为如此对待他父亲的房子而感到恐惧。我认为，如果人们真的像人一样地活着，那么他们的房子就会成为一座座庙宇——我们不敢对它们加以伤害，而居住其中会使我们变得神圣；如果每个人只是为了自己建造房屋，为了满足他自己的，那一点点的，改变生活的需求的话，那么他们的亲情必定会奇怪地瓦解，对家庭的赐予和父母的教诲则会莫名其妙地知恩不报，莫名地意识到自己背叛了父辈的荣誉，或者自己的生命不足以使这幢房子对于孩子们来说成为神圣之所。我看到可怜的石灰和黏土的凝固物正如霉菌一样从我们首都周边的，受尽蹂躏的原野上迅速生长；我看到用木板和假冒石材建成的，如甲壳一样的建筑物，它们形体单薄、摇摇欲坠、毫无根基；我看到一排排阴郁的、千篇一律的小房子，它们彼此雷同却又毫无关联，形单影只却又似曾相识。看着它们，我感觉到的不仅仅是憎恨一瞥后淡漠的厌恶，不仅仅是对被玷污了的景色的痛惜，而且还痛苦地预感到，当我们这个民族的伟大的根系松散地扎根在这片土壤的时候，它们一定已经深度地溃烂了；那些让人丧气，令人羞愧的房屋显示出巨大而且不断蔓延的，普遍的不满情绪。这些房子告诉我们，每个人的居住目标都定在了比他们当前更好的自然环境当中，每个人过去的生活都成了嘲笑的对象；人们都希望建造新房离开旧居，希望忘却过往的岁月；人们不再能感觉到家庭所带来的舒适、和平以及信仰；挣扎的、不安的人们所居住的拥挤的房子与阿拉伯人或是吉卜赛人的帐篷的唯一区别就是，它们不够健康敞亮，地点不够令人满意；人们牺牲了自由却未能换来安宁，牺牲了稳定却未能换来变动所带来的奢华。

这一罪恶并非微不足道，并非影响有限；它是带来其他错误和厄运的不祥之兆、传染之源和孕育的温床。当人们不再爱家，不再尊敬这个栖身之所，就表明他们已经羞辱了它，并且从未承认过基督教信仰中真正的普世价值。事实上，真正超越异教徒偶像崇拜的正是这一价值，而并非一颗虔诚之心。我们的上帝不仅仅活在天堂，还活在家中；他在每个人的居所里都有一座圣坛；因此，当我们轻慢地搬动圣坛，倒掉灰烬的时候，就要多加小心了。一个民族的家居建筑要如何建造，就其耐久性和完整性来说，与单纯的视觉愉悦，知性的骄傲或是文雅而挑剔的想象力毫不相干。它是一种道德责任，一旦缺失就要受到惩罚，因为如何对待建筑取决于微妙而平衡的责任心——一种仔细、耐心、喜爱和坚持到底的决心；一种希望建筑能够跨越一般的国家革命的时期或是整个的区域利益转换的时期的观念。这是最起码的；但是，如果可能的话，人们最好把建造房屋提升到终身事业的高度，这一高度是最初的条件而不是最终的成就；人们建造房屋要尽力而为，使它屹立不倒；要通过房子给子孙后代展示自己的过去及生活的历练。这样的房子建好后，我们就拥有了真正的家居建筑，它是所有其他方面要求的基础。真正的家居建筑，无论大房子还是小房子，都会一视同仁、考虑周到；真正的家居建筑会赋予世俗环境下的狭小空间以尊严，而人们正是依赖这种尊严才能够安居乐业。

我注意到这种光荣、骄傲、平和的泰然自若，这种安居乐业的永恒智慧，很有可能就是所有时代中最伟大智慧的主要源泉之一，而且毫无疑问，它们是古代意大利和法国伟大建筑的最重要源头。时至今日，这两个国家中最美丽的城市所吸引人们的，不是其孤立存在的、富丽堂皇的宫殿，而是它们在辉煌时期遗留下的，珍贵而优雅的房屋装饰，即便这些房屋小之又小。威尼斯最为精美的建筑是位于其大运河起始地段的一幢小房子。这幢房子上下共三层，二层三扇窗户，三层两扇。许多最为精美的建筑都位于较为狭窄的运河两岸，面积并不比这座大。意大利北部最为有趣的十五世纪的建筑中有这样一幢小房子，它并不临街，位于维琴察市场的后面；它始建于1481年，外墙上镌刻着这样的铭文：Il.n’est.rose.sans.épine.——它是无刺的玫瑰；这幢房屋同样上下三层，每层三扇窗户，窗户之间是华丽的花叶装饰；中间阳台的下面起支撑作用的是展开双翅的雄鹰的造型，两边的阳台下面则支撑的是站立在丰饶角上的，长翅膀的狮身鹫首兽。认为房子建得好则必须建得大完全是现代人的想法，这种观念与认为绘画中的人物必须比真实生活中的人物大才会让这幅画具有历史感一样，如出一辙。

我希望普通住宅建得坚固耐久，赏心悦目；里里外外都让人倍感愉悦；至于房屋之间的风格和样式要近似到何种程度，我会在其他标题下另行讨论；但是无论如何，房屋之间要存在差异，而这种差异要能适应并表现出每个人的性格和职业特点，及部分的个人历史。我认为，房屋的首建者拥有这项权利，并且应当受到后代的尊重；房屋建造中要预留一些未经雕琢的石材，以便日后在上面记录下房屋主人的生平和房屋的变迁，如此一来，这一居所便具有了纪念碑的性质，进而演化成为更加系统的说教。这一良好的风俗古已有之，而现如今仍有一些瑞士人和德国人保留了这一传统，作为对上帝恩赐的答谢，因为正是上帝允许自己建造并拥有了这样一处安静的栖身之所。下面这些镌刻在一幢乡间别墅外墙上的甜美文字正可以作为本段的结束语。这幢别墅建成不久，位于格林德瓦村和下游的冰川之间，为绿色的牧场所环抱——

Mit herzlichem Vertrauen

怀着真诚的信仰

Hat Johannes Mooter und Maria Rubi

约翰内斯·莫特和玛利·露比

Dieses Haus bauen lassen.

建造了这幢房子。

Der liebe Gott woll uns bewahren

仁慈的上帝保佑我们

Vor allem Unglück und Gefahren，

免于不幸和危险，

Und es in Segen lassen stehn

并且祝福我们

Auf der Reise durch diese Jammerzeit

经过悲伤的旅途

Nach dem himmlischen Paradiese，

来到美好的天国，

Wo alle Frommen wohnen，

所有虔诚的信徒都齐聚于此，

Da wird Gott sie belohnen

因为上帝将会奖赏他们

Mit der Friedenskrone

和平的冠冕

Zu alle Ewigkeit.

直到永远。

公共建筑传承历史的作用应当更为明确。哥特式建筑的优点之一就是——我所谓的“哥特式”是与其古典含义相较而言最为广义的含义——它记录的丰富性几乎无穷无尽。哥特式建筑细微和繁复的雕刻装饰为所有应当为人所知的民族情感或是成就提供了表达的方式，这种表达可能是象征性的，也可能是直白的。事实上，装饰本身并不足以表达如此崇高的特性；即便是最富思想性的历史时期的装饰也会给想象留下很大的，自由发挥的空间，否则就不得不在装饰中重复地使用代表民族风貌或象征的符号。即使仅仅在表面的装饰物中放弃哥特式建筑精神所独具的多样性与力量也是不明智的；在其他重要的建筑构件方面更是如此——例如圆柱的柱头或凸饰，束带层，以及为大家所公认的浅浮雕等。最粗陋的，能够讲述一个故事或是记录下一个事实的作品也要胜过最富丽堂皇却言之无物的装饰。伟大的城市建筑上所有的装饰物都应当传达某种智慧的思考。对于历史的真实再现在现代社会遇到了困难，这种困难相当讨厌却挥之不去；这就是难以驾驭的服饰：然而，通过足够大胆和富于想象力的处理及对于象征符号的坦率的使用，就可以克服所有这些困难；这恐怕不仅仅可以使得雕塑本身获得满意的效果，而且可以使得它在整个建筑作品的所有构成要件中成为伟大并且富于表现力的一分子。以威尼斯道奇宫的柱头装饰为例，按说历史应当交由宫廷画师去表现，然而道奇宫拱廊的每颗柱头却都被赋予了含义。紧挨大门的，作为整个宫殿基石的那根大柱头象征着“抽象的公正”；上面是一尊“所罗门的裁决”的雕塑，其服务于装饰性目的的处理方式令人赞叹。如果整个雕塑都是由这些人物组成，那么他们就会中断柱子的角线，削弱它的力量；于是在这些人物中间便升起一根粗大的，带有棱纹的树干（事实上它与这些人物毫不相干，位于刽子手和求情的母亲之间），起到支撑并延续角柱的作用，而上面的树叶则荫蔽并装点着整个雕塑。下端的柱头在其叶饰的包围中是一位端坐王位的正义的化身——罗马皇帝图拉真，他正在为一个寡妇讨回公道，此外还有亚里士多德，以及一两个其他的，因为破损而难以分辨的人物。旁边的另一些柱头按照顺序依次代表各种美德和恶行，象征了对于民族和平和强盛的保护或是破坏，其中最后一根柱头代表了信仰，上面镌刻着“Fides optima in Deo est”——真理与上帝同在；柱头的另一侧是一个人在膜拜太阳。之后的一两根柱头上面梦幻般地装饰了鸟儿的图样。接下来是一系列柱头，描绘了各色水果、民族服饰及来自威尼斯治下的各国的动物。

现在先不谈更为重要的公共建筑，我们不妨想象一下以历史的和象征性的雕塑装饰自己在印度的房屋：首先房子要建得牢固；然后雕刻上反映我们在印度的战争的浮雕，再辅之以具有东方韵味的叶饰或是镶嵌上东方的宝石；接下来，在更为重要的装饰雕塑中展现印度的风土人情，并且强调地表现出印度教崇拜中的诸神灵对于十字架的臣服。这样一件作品难道不胜过一千本历史书吗？然而，如果我们不具备进行如此装饰所必需的创造力，或是我们不乐意像欧陆诸民族一样喜欢谈论自己，即便是以大理石代言的话（这可能是我们为自己不善此道所能找到的最为高尚的托词），那么至少在建筑物的耐久性方面我们仍然责无旁贷。由于这一问题与对于各种装饰方式的选择密切相关，所以有必要进一步地探讨。

人类的善意和决心很少能够超越自己这一代人而恩泽后世。他们也许指望着后辈侧耳倾听，专心致志，也许为了博得他们的赞誉而操劳：他们可能盼望着后辈承认那些未被承认的美德，并且要求他们对于现行的错误还以公道，但是所有这一切纯属出于自私的目的，丝毫没有考虑或是照顾到后辈的利益——我们欣然煽动他们对我们阿谀奉承，并且高兴地利用他们的权威支持我们当下颇具争议的诉求。为了子孙后代牺牲自我，为了还未出生的债主厉行节约，为了后人乘凉而栽树，或是为了将来的人们能居住而兴建城市，我认为所有这些想法都从未真正地成为被人们所公认的，努力工作的动机。这并不是说我们可以免除这些职责；除非我们人生在世的用处不仅仅惠及同伴还能泽被后世，否则我们的存在便难以为继。上帝已经赐予了我们生活的土地；这是一笔巨大的遗产。它不仅仅属于我们，而且属于我们的子孙后辈，以及名字已经出现在《创世记》当中的先人们；我们没有权利，无论是通过作为或是不作为，使他们蒙受不必要的惩罚，或是剥夺他们应当获得的，我们有权力传承下去的利益。上帝为人类劳动指定的条件之一就是，果实的丰满程度与播种和收获之间的时间成正比；因此，通常来说，我们将目标锁定得越远就越不会盼望着亲眼看见自己的劳动果实，而我们所获取的成功就越是广泛和丰富。人类并不能像使后辈受益那样，使同辈获得好处；在所有发出人类声音的布道坛中，坟墓的发声最有说服力。

考虑将来并不意味着给当前带来损失。相反，人类的一举一动都会因为未雨绸缪而变得更为可敬、优雅和壮丽。在所有的品质当中，远见，平静的和自信的耐心将人与人区分开来，使得某些人更亲近上帝；没有什么行为或艺术不能用这一方法来验证其高贵。因此，当我们建造房屋的时候，要抱着使其屹立万代的想法。不要让建筑仅仅满足于当下的欢愉和使用；要让它成为我们子孙后代借以感谢我们的作品。当我们一层层地堆砌石头的时候，要想一想，正是因为我们的双手触摸过它们，所以总有一天这些石头会被奉为神明；总有一天，当人们看到这幢建筑，这一劳动的结晶时会说：“看，这就是我的祖上为我们修建的。”的确，一幢建筑最耀眼的光辉不是来自它的石头，也不是来自装饰它的黄金。它的光辉之处在于其年龄，在于其丰富而深刻的内涵，其严肃的外表，神秘的同情心，以及我们在其墙垣上感到的，一直以来被涌动的人性浪潮所不断冲刷的赞许或谴责。建筑见证了历史的变迁，静静地与其他稍纵即逝的事物形成了对照。通过季节交替、时代流转，王朝的衰落和肇始，变换的沧海和桑田，建筑凭借其优美的造像在一个跨越古今的时代里获得了力量，将被遗忘的和即将来临的世纪连接在一起，并且，正如它聚集了人们的共通情感一样，部分地形成了民族身份的认同。正是在那金色的时间斑点上，我们要寻找真正的光明，色彩以及建筑的可贵之处；只有当一幢建筑获得了这种特点，博得了如此声誉，因人们的功绩而变得神圣，其墙垣见证了痛苦，其立柱在死亡的幽灵中屹立，它的存在才会比周围自然界的物体更为长久，才会像语言和生命一样鲜活起来……

我们不再讨论修复的问题了。这种事从始至终就是一句谎言。正如你可以将尸体做成标本一样，你也可以将一幢建筑制成模型，就像标本里保留有骨架一样，你的模型里面也可能会有旧墙的外壳，这样做的优点我既看不到，也不关心：然而旧建筑却毁掉了。这样做比它坍塌成一堆瓦砾，或是化成一坨烂泥还要来得更为彻底和无情：与重建的米兰相比，荒凉的尼尼微能够给予我们的更多。据说，有的时候确实有修复的必要！没错。请仔细审视一下这种必要，按照它自身的逻辑理解一下。其实这是一种摧毁的必要。你可以接受这种摧毁的必要，将整幢建筑推倒，把石头扔到被遗忘的角落里，如果你愿意的话，将它们敲成铺路的碎石，制成盖房的灰浆；但是要诚实地做这件事，不要在它们的旧址上重建一处谎言取而代之。如果在此种必要来临之前仔细研究一下，或许就可以规避。近代的原则（我相信这一原则，至少在法国，被泥瓦匠们系统地加以贯彻，如当地的市政官员为了给流浪汉们提供工作便把圣旺教堂推倒重建）就是首先对这些建筑不闻不问，然后对其加以修复。保护好你们的纪念碑吧，那样就不需要对它们进行修复。请及时地在房顶上放几块铅板，及时地清理排水槽中的落叶和枝条，这样就会使得房顶和墙壁免于毁坏。请诚惶诚恐地照看一幢老建筑，尽可能地保护它，不惜一切代价地使它免于破损。要像清点皇冠上的珠宝一样清点老建筑的石头；像对待被围困的城市的城门一样，派人看守；在松动的地方用铁箍加以固定；在下垂的地方用木料加以支撑；不要管辅助措施是否好看：拄拐杖总比没有腿强；并且要小心翼翼地、虔诚地、持续地做这件事，那么数代人之后的人们就仍然可以在它的庇护下走完一生。建筑的末日终会来临；但是要让它来得光明正大，不要让令人汗颜的、假冒的赝品代替它被人最后铭记。

对于更为荒唐和无知的破坏就是说了也白说；我的话不会传到那些人的耳朵里[1]，然而，不管他们听到与否，我都要说出真理，这就是，我们是否应当保护古旧建筑并不涉及自身利益或是情感因素。无论怎样我们都没有权利碰触它们，它们不属于我们。它们部分地属于其修建者，部分地属于我们的后代。故去的人仍然对它们拥有权利：他们为此而劳作，并且试图通过这些建筑永远地传达诸如对于功绩的表彰，宗教情感的传递，或是其他什么信息，这些我们都无权抹杀。我们自己修建的建筑可以自由地摧毁；但是对于其他人付出了力量、财富和生命才得以完成的建筑，其权利并不会因为他们的故去而丧失；对于他们留下的建筑的使用权并不仅仅属于我们。它属于他们所有的后代。我们为了当下的便利就将这样的建筑推倒，而此后可能引起千百万人的悲痛，给他们带来伤害。我们无权制造这样的悲伤和损失。阿夫朗什大教堂是属于我们这些悲伤的，在它的地基上徘徊的人，还是属于那些将它摧毁的暴民们呢？无论什么建筑都不属于那些对它们施暴的人。他们现在是暴民，而且一直是；无论他们是出于一时激愤，还是出于蓄意的破坏；无论他们是人数众多，还是身居要职；毫无缘由地毁坏东西的人就是暴民，而建筑总是被毫无缘由地毁坏。一幢漂亮的建筑一定无愧于它所占据的土地，并且一直如此，除非中部非洲和美洲拥挤得像英格兰的米德尔塞克斯郡那样。无论出于怎样的因由，这种毁坏都是站不住脚的。也有一种情况可视为正当，当然不是现在，那就是躁动不安、充满渴求的当下占据了我们头脑中本属于过去和未来的位置。自然的静谧正逐渐地离我们远去；成千上万的人们的生活中充斥了无休无止的狂热。曾几何时，与他们漫长的旅途相伴的是寂静的天空和沉睡的大地；这个国家的脉搏正在剧烈地跳动，沿着钢铁的血脉传遍它的机体，每时每刻都变得更为炙热，更为迅速。所有的活力都通过律动的血管集中到了中心城市；走过狭窄的桥梁，对如绿色海洋一般的乡村视而不见，我们被涌动的人潮推向了城市的大门。在城市中，唯一能够替代森林和原野的，就是来自古代建筑的影响力。不要为了整齐的广场，围了篱笆或是种了树的人行道，抑或是漂亮的街道和宽敞的码头，等等，而抛弃古代建筑，因为所有这些都不能给你的城市带来骄傲。把这些留给大众吧；但要记住在不安的墙垣的环绕中确实有一些人，他们会要求到其他的地方走一走；会要求一些不同的形式一饱眼福。就像但丁，他经常会坐在一个夕阳照得到的地方，欣赏佛罗伦萨大教堂的穹顶在深邃的天空中勾画出的轮廓线；再比如皇宫的主人们，他们每天会透过宫殿卧室——他们先辈休息之处——的窗子，眺望维罗纳昏暗街道的交会之处。

剑桥艺术学校：开学致辞（1858）

我想有兴趣为劳工建立一所艺术学校的人们大体上可以分为两类：第一类，是那些主要是想让劳工们变得更快乐、更聪明、状况更好的人们；第二类，是那些想让劳工们生产出更好、更具价值的产品的人们。当然，这两个目标可以并行不悖；不过，我们更关注的是达到这两个目标的动机是什么，因为我们完成目标所需要的精神实质有着很大的不同。我曾经说过，这一不同足可以将所有如此计划的推动者分成两类：一类人的中心目的为慈善，一类人的中心目的为商业；一类人希望劳工自发地获取更多的知识，另一类人则希望劳工能为我们生产出更具价值的商品，以便能与其他国家进行竞争。

这种动机的不同一定会导致工作方法的差别。慈善家们关注的不仅仅是工匠，而且是广义上的劳动者。通过给予劳动者新的娱乐方式和新的思想，慈善家们希望尽一切可能改善他们的习惯，增进整个劳动群体的幸福感。一所目标如此宽泛而且有些模糊的学校所采取的艺术教育原则，是，而且应当是，与那些仅在自己行业内对工匠进行特殊培养的学校所采取的原则大为不同。我认为这种差异并没有引起我们足够的注意，或是在办学计划当中予以考虑。我觉得，迄今为止，我们一直模糊地认为绘画艺术，从某种程度上说，可以以一种普遍的方式教给所有的人，并且使他们都受益；而且之后的每一班技工都可以将这种普遍的知识，根据要求应用于自己的行业，然而，情况并非如此。一位木雕师，根据自己的职业，与一位瓷器画师学习绘画的方式会有很大的不同；宝石匠与铁匠也同样有这样的差别。一定要引导他们在各自不同的作品当中，以自然的形式呈现出不同的特点。教一位铁匠观察桃子上的绒毛是没有用的，同样，教给一位木雕师如何制造朦胧的效果也是没用的。就他们各自的领域而言，这些东西只会白白地占据他们的大脑，而他们则不能集中力量，清楚明白地追求，在他们所能利用的材质上可以表现出来的艺术特质。

现在，我认为，要在单独的一所学校里面，传授给学生各个行业特定的艺术原则是根本不可能的。这种特定的艺术原则只有通过在某种特定的工作中的多年的工作经验才能够获得。每一种材料的力量，对它进行处理时的诸多困难等，与其说是教会的不如说是凭经验获得的；只有通过不断的接触和熔炉旁边持续的试验，金匠才会发现控制黄金的办法，玻璃工才会知道如何摆弄水晶；只有通过观察及在本行业的师傅实际操作的时候打下手，学徒们才会学会高效操作的秘诀，或是认识到原有设计的真正局限之处。因此，我认为，在类似这所刚刚建立的学校中，应当放弃所有针对特定行业的教学计划，因为要使这样的教学发挥效用，就必须具备相应的材料，便利设施，以及师傅的实践经验，而这些我们都不具备。所有特定的艺术教学一定要在为其行业专门建立的学校中实施：当我们的技工对这些事情更为明悉之后，正如我在有关艺术的政治经济学的讲座中所说过的一样，以一种积极的和务实的形式建立各个行业的同业公会就是完全必要的了。同业公会的目的是为了搞清楚适合他们自己行业的艺术原则，要针对各种材料和新发明的程序方法做试验，而且要教导它们行业内的学徒。另外还有很多其他的功能我就不在此一一论述了。我们不能期望，我重复一遍，目前在这样一所学校里实现这一切：不放弃这样的期望，我们就不会得到满意的结果；而且我们要致力于教给技工们，不管他是干什么的——是农户的雇工或是厂商的工人，是机修工、发明家、店员、水手或是农夫——尽我们的一切可能，教给他们唯一的，也是同样的东西——观察。这并非无足轻重，观察可能是所有要教给学生的最为重要的东西。教给你阅读——这有什么用，如果你不知道所读的是真还是假？教给你写或是说——说有什么用，如果你无话可说？教给你如何思考——不，会思考又有什么用，如果你没有什么好思考的？但是教给你去观察，就等于同时让你懂得了如何正确地使用语言和进行思考。在表达对于光明的渴望时，祈祷和赞美诗的常见套话堕落成了单调乏味的隐喻，模糊地扭曲成为其他替代的语言——先是借助拉丁文解释；然后用英文阐明；接着又用拉丁文答疑解惑；再用英文加以澄清；再后来又借助光束、光线、太阳、恒星、灯盏等来表达，直到有时我们希望，至少从宗教的角度来看，根本就不存在光明或是黑暗这类词语。只有此时人们才模糊地认识到观察的重要性。尽管如此，使得人们忍受这种无休止的纠缠的主要动因是真实存在的；不同的是人们最缺少也最应求索的东西不是光明而是观察。如果你不知道如何使用光，那么拥有光的多少就没有意义，它只会骚扰而不会帮助你的眼睛。另外，在这个世界上，我们经常想要在黑暗中看到东西——这是所有人的天赋权利——无论是通过什么样的光我们都想看到事物本来的样子。我保证，如果我们可以得到一点点，哪怕只一点点就好，《天方夜谭》当中苦行僧人的油膏，用以展示给我们世界的真相而不是世上的财宝的话，不久我们就会改变这个世界。

不管这些东西正确与否，毫无疑问，在这样一所学校里，我们的当务之急是培养学生学会观察而不是学会动手；尽量让学生清楚而真实地观察到自然的物体对于他们来说大有裨益。我们不应该过分追求学生再现这些物体的能力。这种能力，可以或多或少地通过练习获得，而这种练习对于观察的精确性而言毫无助益；而且观察的精确性也可以通过练习获得，而这种练习同样也无助于提高学生再现物体的能力。例如，花很长的时间练习点染单一的色调对于绘画能力很有帮助；然而这种手法的练习对于培养学生确定某个物体的真正色调却没有丝毫的帮助。仅仅用一个小时的时间，通过精心的指导和恰当的修改，学生就会更为透彻地了解色彩的运用，而且会获得对于在绘画中所描摹事物的更敏锐的感知。在练习中，他擦来抹去，使色彩变明再变暗，用笔刮擦然后涂抹，耐心地、努力地与色彩运用的要求保持一致，尽管这样做可能会毁掉整张画或是让它完全不像样。当然，对于老师和学生而言，有一点很有诱惑力，就是要尽力获得看得到的结果——在实际绘画中表现出美丽的，可信的或是有卖点的东西，但是我见到过的学校越多就越是有理由质疑那些产生出太多浮华而完整的学生作品的学校。我们仔细检查一下就会发现，一件浮华的作品往往是遵照某种约定俗成的规则完成的，而学生对这些规则盲目地遵照执行却并不知其所以然；他的作品是对真相的再现，而绘画的作者并未亲身观察到这一真相；此类画作的创作手法单调乏味，死气沉沉；它们的明暗处理似是而非、中规中矩，却又漏洞百出。如果学生仅仅学会了各种绘画的技巧，那么他的画作中就一定充斥了谬误和各种问题。因此，建立一所真正大众的，或是通用的艺术学校是非常必要的。在这所学校里，老师们不会试图掩盖这种谬误或是容忍它发生，相反会让学生利用时间获取最为宝贵的理解和心灵的感悟，而不是手上的技巧。

各位请注意，除非你能全身心地投入其中，否则绘画或是制图过程本身就会变得毫无价值。一位爱好者或是工匠的绘画——只要他不是艺术家，就没有什么价值。这样一幅作品作为纪念品、礼物或是记录事实的手段可能是弥足珍贵的；然而作为艺术品，爱好者的画作通常毫无价值；而我们的重要目标之一就是要让学生们明白并且感受到这一点，进而防止他们试图将自己本来毫无价值的作品，通过某种肤浅的、虚伪的、抓人眼球的、骗人钱财的方式装扮得像一幅真正好的作品。

对于那些来自上流社会的学生，我们的主要职责就是使得他们成为好的艺术品鉴人而非艺术家；因为即便是给我一个月，而非一个小时的时间，来给你们讲解我们国内上流社会和中产阶级对于艺术的高明的品鉴能力的缺乏状况的林林总总，也是不可能的。这不是说这种品鉴能力没有手上的训练就可以获得：没有哪个不会画画的人对绘画会有透彻的鉴赏力；而是仅仅应当把绘画作为一种能使得他专注于眼前的艺术品的微妙之处的方式，或是使得他能够记录下必要的自然真相并与之相比较的方式。而且我认为对于呈现给他的艺术品要进行严格的筛选。研究一位大师直至理解他为止，要胜过对于一千个人表面上的熟悉。批评的力量并不在于你知道多少画家的名字或是创作方式，而在于你是否能够洞悉几位画家的卓越之处。

相反，如果我们的教学更为明显地倾向于操作，那么我们就没有必要费力地提升学生的鉴赏能力。在诸多现存的艺术形式当中，学生知道的越少越好。我们应当主要培养他们对于自然的敏感性；如果可能的话，甚至要通过某种程度上对于他们的鉴赏力不利的方式发展他们的想象力。我们宁可学生的作品粗浅清晰，也不要完美无瑕；宁可欢快愉悦，也不要谨小慎微。

顺着这一思路，我们开始讨论第二个问题，也就是有关商业的问题；就是说，在工匠们接受了训练之后，如何才能让他们创作出最好、最珍贵的作品，以使我们能与其他国家展开竞争，或是在我们自己国内开拓出新的商业领域。

可能我们很多人都认为，足够的学校教育就可以达到这一目的；足够多的讲座可以达到这一目的；到国外取经学习可以达到这一目的；或是耐心、时间、金钱以及美好的愿望可以达到这一目的。呜呼，不幸的是，上面这些中没有一项，或是所有这些方面都加起来，也不会达到这一目的。如果你需要真正好的作品，比如在全世界得到认可的作品，那么途径就只有一条，而且并非捷径。你可能会为达此目的设立悬赏，但是你会发现悬赏其实并不管用。你可能会派人学习相反的风格样式，但是你会发现风格样式并不是关键所在。你可能会在我们王国范围内的每所学校里宣讲艺术的原则，而你会发现依照这些原则也不能达此目的。你可能会耐心地等待时代的进步，而你会发现艺术其实并不会随时代而变迁。或是，你可能会不耐烦地利用当代的发明促其形成，而你会发现无论是螺丝钉还是明轮翼都不会将艺术的战车推向前进。没有什么方法可以获得好的艺术品，我重复一遍，只有一条——最简单同时也最困难——享受艺术。查看一下各个民族的历史，你就会发现这一伟大的事实清楚明白地写在上面——只有享受艺术的民族才能产生好的艺术品；他们对待艺术就像对待面包一样，以其充饥；就像对待阳光一样，沐浴其中；他们为之欢呼雀跃，为之手舞足蹈；他们为之争吵，为之战斗，为之忍饥挨饿；事实上，他们对待艺术的态度同我们完全相反：我们拿艺术卖钱，他们则葆有艺术的永恒价值。

对于我们这样一个商业民族来说这确实是一种严重的困难。我们从事这一行业的主要动机本身使得这一行业变得不可能。要使艺术品畅销的首要和绝对的条件是生产它而不是为了销售；相反，则是下定决心，一旦拥有就什么价格都不卖。努力使艺术品广受欢迎而价格低廉，让它成为国外市场的好商品；那么国外市场总会拿出更好的商品。制作艺术品时自己感到愉悦就好，甚至于要下定决心不去讨好其他任何人；接下来你立刻就会发现所有的人都喜欢它。请你注意，这样做存在一个难以逾越的困难：我们为愉悦自己而生产，然而自身却不懂得愉悦。举一个最简单的例子，我们都能理解的，在服装艺术方面。近来我们在丝绸服饰的样式方面大吵大闹，要与法国里昂竞争，要将伦敦打造成巴黎。没错，我们可以一直这样尝试：但只要我们并不是真的喜欢丝绸服饰的样式，就永远都不会有所斩获。而事实上我们确实不喜欢。当然，所有的女士都希望自己的裙子合身而且漂亮；但是我却没有发现有谁，纯粹是出于对于丝绸服饰本身的喜爱而欣赏其美丽；检测有无这种欣赏的方法就是要看，她们是否希望该服饰穿在别人身上也同样的合身、好看。穿着漂亮所带来的快乐，甚至于是看到其他人穿着漂亮而感到的快乐——我猜想在座的听众一定是如此的无私——无论这种快乐是大是小，与美丽所带来的愉悦，与丝绸的褶皱与颜色的华丽和优雅所带来的愉悦是大为不同的。我刚刚获得了一条确凿的证据，证明现代人的这种感觉有多么欠缺。为了研究保罗·委罗内塞的一幅作品，夏天的时候我在都灵住了一段时间。他的这幅画描绘了示巴女王会见所罗门王的故事。画中最显著的特点之一就是丝质服饰的富丽堂皇：特别是有一条白色的锦缎，上面织有金色的图案，而这正是我到都灵去主要要临摹的东西之一。你可能对此感到奇怪，但我要顺便说一句，像所有好的学生和好的画家一样，我也有欣赏服装式样的癖好。弗拉·安吉利科、佩鲁基诺、约翰·贝里尼、乔尔乔涅、提香、丁托列托、委罗内塞、达·芬奇等，无论他们属于哪个流派，也无论在其他方面有多么不同，他们都喜欢服装式样；而且，越是高贵的画家就越是在服装式样方面处理得当。

前面我说过，在都灵停留时我研究了这条白色锦缎。在公共画廊里经常有这样的情况，就是最好的画作却摆放在最不起眼的位置；然而，这幅委罗内塞的画不仅高高挂起，而且就挂在进出画廊必经的门的上方，所以参观者不可能轻易漏掉它，尽管他们可能欣赏不了。为了工作方便，我在门的旁边架起一座高台。由于这座高台有一定的高度并且位于角落，因此我能够观察到参观者们看到这幅画时的表情，而他们却看不到我。我觉得这幅画具备所有艺术品借以吸引大众眼球的要素。它画幅很大；颜色艳丽，题材喜闻乐见。整幅画上大概有二十个人物，主要人物有真人大小：所罗门的形象，尽管是在阴影里，是到目前为止我所知道的，在所有意大利艺术品当中，其最能完美地展现出这位聪明睿智、仪表堂堂的年轻国王的形象；示巴女王是委罗内塞描绘过的最可爱的女性形象之一；所有其他次要人物也都魅力不凡，充满想象；整幅画作如此完美，以至于有一天我在高台上花了两个小时也没能丝毫不差地描摹出两条锦缎褶皱的曲线。有很多来自英国的旅行者走过这间屋子；即便有时他们自己没有看到，也无一例外地被侍从带到了这幅画前。对这幅我花了六个星期仅仅是研究了两个人物的画作，我发现，平均而言，每个英国旅行者花了半分钟或四十五秒进行参观，当然他们对意大利没有偏见，至于该看什么都是发自内心；更有甚者，行动迅速的或时髦的旅行者们，他们匆匆来此就是为了走马观花，所以仅仅是扫了一眼，就立刻转过头去观赏悬挂在右边的一幅糟糕的山水画，画中是一堵着力绘制的白墙以及一条绿色的、没有光泽的护城河。给我印象最深的是，没有一位女士停下来观赏委罗内塞绘制的服装。毫无疑问这些服装要比大广场上商店里卖的服装漂亮得多，然而却没人注意它们。有的时候会有某位相貌出众，明眸善睐的女孩走进来，我通常会一直关注她，心想——“拜托，至少你得看一看示巴女王穿的是什么衣服。”但是没有——她会漫不经心地走过，微微抬一抬头，似乎在说：“这间屋子里没什么值得可看的——除了我自己。”然后就穿门而过，一走了之。

事实上，我们并不在乎绘画：确实不在乎。我们之所以参观皇家艺术学院的展览是为了获得谈资和消遣空闲的时间；出于各种原因，我们当中的富人们会买上一两幅画作，有时是为了装点走廊的角落，有时是为了烘托晚餐前客厅的谈话气氛，有时是因为某个画家很受追捧，间或是因为他穷困潦倒，还经常有这种情况，就是我们有意搜集各种类型的绘画，就像我们搜集矿石或蝴蝶的标本一样，当然，在最好，也是最少见的情形下，我们购买画作是出于对它们的喜爱；而这种喜爱也不过是与喜爱一把漂亮的扶手椅或是一只新做成的玻璃水瓶如出一辙。对于绘画真正的热爱，得到一幅作品时的喜悦之情，恐怕有此感觉的人只是凤毛麟角。

我们的冷漠并不容易消除；即便是冷漠应当消除，我们也应当恰如其分地欣赏绘画作品，而好的作品也确有所增加，因为如此一来一定会增加的——接下来则会出现另外一个问题。可能今晚在座的各位当中有人听说过我经常会自相矛盾——我倒是非常希望自己如此，因为我还从来没见过哪个需要解决的重要问题，不是像一个二次方程一样，需要至少一个肯定以及一个否定的答案。通常来讲，任何重要的事物都是三方面的，四方面的，或是多方面的；所以人们要坚持自己的观点就要严肃地沿着这个多边形巡查。拿我自己来说，至少要自我否定三次，我才会认为已经掌握了某个问题并且感到满意，因此，今晚我还要自我否定一次。我刚刚说过，如果我们不能在艺术中感到快乐就不能得到好的艺术；接下来我要说，同样确信无疑的，如果我们不能在艺术中拒绝快乐的话，就不可能得到好的艺术。我们必须首先爱艺术，然后要对我们的爱加以节制。

这听起来奇怪；而我敢保证这是千真万确的。事实上，如果有什么事儿听起来不怪，通常它的真实性就值得怀疑；因为所有的真理都是奇妙的。举一个物理方面的例子，听起来一样自相矛盾。假定你在给一个小学生讲解天文学上的地球怎样在自己的轨道上保持平稳运行的道理；你会这样对他说——难道不是吗？——地球总是有被太阳吸引的趋势；同时它又总是存在飞离太阳的趋势。在小学生理解地球运动的方式之前，这两种明显矛盾的说法够他消化一段时间了。而与此类似，当我们将艺术置于其真正的和有用的轨道时，它就会一边在闪闪发光的愉悦的诱惑下行进，另一边则带着做点有益工作的，坚定的道德目的而前行。如果艺术家的工作没有乐趣，他就会消失在太空中，死于寒冷：如果他仅为乐趣而工作，就会因为拥抱太阳而化为灰烬。总之，后面这一条就是所谓宿命，我不是说这最可怕，而是说迄今为止艺术多受此折磨，世界上的伟大民族也多遭此磨难。

一方面你能清楚地看到，历史上只有在艺术中获得快乐的民族才能产生出艺术，同样你会毫无疑问地，甚至是更为清楚地看到，那些仅仅是为了获得快乐而追求艺术的民族，他们的力量和生命总是被艺术消耗殆尽。当你审视世界上伟大民族的丰功伟绩的时候，这一事实一定让你震撼。你一定会严肃地提出这样一个疑问，即便是在今天，我们应当在多大程度上追求那似乎只会腐蚀我们灵魂，麻木我们机体的快乐呢？我一直以来都在抱怨英国蔑视艺术；但是，如果更公平一点的话，我似乎应当抱怨的是她对于艺术的畏惧而非蔑视。有史以来，什么是给各民族带来毁灭的根源呢？是瘟疫、饥荒、地震或是火山爆发吗？所有这些都不曾战胜过一个伟大的民族，使他的名字在地球上消失，然而，在每一次民族走向衰败的时间和地点，你都会看到其他的，发挥作用的原因，这就是奢华、娇弱、耽于享受、艺术精良以及花样翻新的行乐。那么，什么才是我们应该从古代历史当中汲取的，从古典著作中获得的，送给年青一代人的经验教训呢？这就是——朴素的生活、语言和举止，其可以给予一个民族以力量；奢华的生活，精妙的语言以及优雅的举止会削弱并且摧毁一个民族。当人们一无所有，寡欲少求的时候，就会勇敢而高尚：当他们嘲笑所有奢华的艺术，而在其他民族看来是野蛮人的时候，他们的刀剑就会所向披靡，统治就会无边无际。当让他们对于高雅的品位变得敏感，对于快乐的追求变得迅捷之后，他们那曾经紧握铁棒的手指就会即刻松开金色的权杖。在这点上我没有丝毫的夸张；怎样强调这一真理及其普适性都不为过。野蛮和朴素的民族从来都比擅长艺术的民族更具美德，更具优势。看一看波斯人是怎样推翻吕底亚人的；雅典人怎样推翻波斯人的；斯巴达人怎样推翻雅典人的；然后整个优雅的希腊是怎样被更为粗野的罗马人推翻的；罗马人又在变得优雅之后怎样被哥特人驯服的：在中世纪的转折点上，正是这一小撮山地牧羊人宣告了欧洲的解放，践行了基督教的美德，证明了它的教义，而他们没有艺术，没有文学，几乎没有语言，却能在条顿骑士团的围攻下屹立不倒，在罗马森严的等级中出淤泥而不染……

因此，综上所述，如果要在英国促进艺术的发展就必须做两件事：首先，要享受艺术的乐趣；其次，要让艺术服务于某种严肃的目的。我所谓的严肃并不一定专指艺术的道德层面，而是指除了应当摈弃的自私、轻率或是懒惰以外，还要兼顾艺术的实用性。在前面的演说中，我确实曾经想要探索出几条能让艺术严肃地、实实在在地服务于我们文化事业的路径，至少我是这样认为的。我曾经希望告诉大家仍然有多少伟大的自然现象还没有通过艺术的方式由我们记录下来；有多少欧洲的重大历史事件正是由于未经记载而正在被人们所遗忘，而我们所要做的不过是一点点真诚的、简单的、辛苦的而又充满爱心的绘画；又有多少最为难忘的历史事件没能发挥它们一半的教育作用，仅仅是因为画家们在对其进行再现的时候，不是忠于历史事实而是凭空想象，不是为了还原历史真相，而是为了给自己的国家歌功颂德。我曾经希望告诉大家有多少最美好的心灵冲动在轻率和耽于声色中迷失，就是因为我们缺少可供凝视的、更为纯粹的美丽，缺少高贵的思想与炽热的、神圣的人类激情相结合；最后，我们失去了多么巨大的，宗教信仰的力量，就是因为我们的艺术没能以某种理性的、真实的和可信的方式去表现那些神圣的历史事件，因为它们清晰可见、易于理解地发生了，所以也应该当得到清晰可见、易于理解地再现，但是至今，我仍然不敢提出所有这一切的希望。在仔细斟酌之后，我感到还不是时候将它们公之于众，然而我想，这一时刻不久就将来临；目前，我们只能对人类的自负、虚荣和空抱幻想提出批评，他们只会在口头上去冒险地追求更高的、各门艺术可能为人类储藏着的、上天的恩赐。现在还没有必要这样做：我们要拜托大家的是，一定要认真地和坦率地努力学习那些逐渐向我们开放的课程；一定要严肃对待这些课程并且是出于严肃的目的，不可将其视为儿戏。最后，我呼吁所有即将入学的同学们清楚地认识到，要将艺术作为业余的艺术爱好加以追求：它可以给你带来快乐，就如同读书使你愉悦一样——但是你从来都没想过将阅读作为业余的艺术爱好；它可以给你带来快乐，就如同学习物理带给你快乐一样，但是你不可能将物理学称为业余的艺术爱好。如果你决意仅仅将艺术视为一场游戏或是一件乐事，那么请赶快放弃艺术，因为你这样做于己无益，而且会使得我们对艺术的追求在他人眼中看来变得肮脏龌龊。毫无疑问，与其你在画廊里闲逛说笑，还不如永远都不进去；与其你攥着画笔仅仅是为了显示陶醉于自己的小聪明，那就还不如从未将其拿起；毫无疑问，与其你的本领仅够在伟大的作品中寻找瑕疵，比如对某个合理的着色妄加推测或是对某个精湛的细节处理说三道四，那还不如对绘画完全没有兴趣，一无所知。最重要的是，只要这些学校的教学面向的是大学低年级学生，我就会为此而申辩。任何以体力劳动为生计的人们都不大可能认为自己学习某某艺术仅仅为了消遣，但是业余艺术爱好者则不同。这一点最重要，而且，这是教给他们什么是绘画的真谛的重中之重。我们不要强求他们创作出好的作品，而要让他们在见到他人好的作品时能够慧眼识珠。好的作品，就其严格意义来说，我之前也说过，是业余艺术爱好者力所不及的；好的作品，无论从什么角度上来说，对其创作者自身或是对其他人都是具有价值的，而他必须从一开始就清楚自己能做什么，什么不能做；什么是可以得到的，什么是得不到的；只有掌握了高贵的、严格的、无所不能的和永恒的艺术法则，他才能创作出好的作品。我这不是在吓唬谁，有谁能够被吓得到，就说明他已经了不起了；除非希望羞辱了我们而理解又让我们战战兢兢，否则，我们的希望就是奢望，理解就是曲解。更进一步说，请恕我直言，你们在这里，所主要要教给年轻人的东西，恐怕他们做不到的要比能做到的更多；因此，要让他们看到，在自然界中有多少东西是不能描摹的，在人类中有多少品格是不能仿效的。只有当他认识到自己所有的作品不过是难以传达的美丽的虚弱标记，不过是进行度量的无力的手段，而同时带着越发的仰慕看到上帝在人类中的天才和普通人之间划定的巨大而难以跨越的鸿沟的时候，才能说他在艺术方面接受了教育。所有人类在通常情况下所能达到的艺术成就，不过是来自对于自然景观本身的、纯粹的喜爱，以及神圣的和忘我的崇敬。这种崇敬，当更为伟大的人出现在他面前的时候，会表现为高贵的自惭形秽和兴奋得浑身颤抖。

国王的宝藏

“你们每人都会得到一块芝麻饼，——以及十英镑。”

琉善《渔民》

今晚，我首先要请求各位的谅解，因为我的演讲题目有些含混不清。实际上我既不会谈论大权在握的国王，也不会谈论代表财富的宝藏；而是要谈一谈另外一种，不是通常意义上的王权和物质财富。我本想先抓住大家的注意力，（就像有的时候，有些人想方设法地带朋友去参观一幕他所得意的景致一样）先把最想要给大家看的东西隐藏起来，然后再在这种漏洞百出的小花招的掩护下蜿蜒前行，最后突然间把大家带到最漂亮的景点。我曾经听擅长演讲的人们说，讲话人不开宗明义而是带着大家兜圈子的做法，会弄得听众们疲惫不堪。因此，我现在就要把这小小的面具扯下，直截了当地告诉大家，我所要讲的是蕴藏在书籍中的宝藏，以及我们找到这些宝藏的路径或是失去它们的缘由。您可能会说这个题目太严肃了，太宽泛了。没错，它太宽泛了，所以我不会试图去探究它所有的内容。我只会呈现给大家一些自己有关阅读的简单的想法。随着我们教育手段的日益扩展，大众的思想在日益改变，而相应的文学水平也在普及与提高之中，这些想法就日复一日地、重重地积压在我的心头。

碰巧我与很多学校的不同层次的学生有一些联系。我从他们家长那里也收到了不少有关孩子教育的信件。在这堆信件当中，有一点让我震惊，这就是孩子的家长们，特别是妈妈们，最为优先考虑的是所谓“社会地位”的问题。在信中，他们常说“适合某某社会地位的教育”。据我所知，他们从来不追求某种自身良好的教育，他们甚至也鲜少提及教育抽象的正确性。他们所跪地祈求的教育，就是一种“能让我儿子穿上一件好的外套，能让他自信地在双铃门前摁响来访者的门铃，并且最终也能让他住上安装有双铃门的房子”的教育——总之一句话，就是能让“生活进步”的教育—除此之外，别无他求。家长们似乎从来没有想过还有这样一种教育存在，这就是，教育本身就是生活的进步；他们没有想过除此之外的任何教育都是迈向死亡；而且，如果方法得当的话，这种基本的教育可能比他们想象的更容易获得或是给予；如果方法不妥的话，无论付出多高的代价，拿出多少的爱心，也不可能得到。

确实，在英国——这个世界上最为忙碌的国家，人们的头脑当中，最为流行和有效的观念是“生活的进步”。人们对此已经最为坦率地承认了，并且将其作为鼓励年轻人奋斗的、最为合适的动机而加以推动。下面请您同我一起思考一下，这个观念实际上包括什么及应当包括什么。

实际上，在目前，“生活的进步”就意味着在生活中出类拔萃；获得一种为其他人所认可的、可敬的或是有名望的地位。通常来说，我们不会认为这种进步就仅仅意味着赚到了钱，而是要让别人知道自己赚到了钱；不是实现了什么伟大的目标，而是让他人看到自己实现了这一目标。一句话，我们要的是，得到别人喝彩时的满足感。这种愿望，对于高贵的人们来说是最无足轻重的弱点，而对于意志薄弱的人们来说，则是首要的缺陷。总体而言，它对普通人的影响力最为强大。这就如同热衷于享乐往往会导致最可怕的灾难一样，一个民族最伟大的成就往往可以追溯到其对于赞美的热爱。

我在这里不是要谴责或是维护这种冲动，而是想要大家感觉到它是如何左右了我们的所作所为，特别是在今天这个时代。这是一种虚荣心的满足。这种虚荣心是我们辛勤劳作的动力，是我们安静休息的止痛膏。因为这种虚荣心与生命的活力紧密相关，所以当它受伤时总会被说成是（而且真正是）生命活力的丧失，我们称之为“坏疽”，这个词原本是用来形容我们身体上坏死的且不可治愈的组织。尽管一些人可能会像医生那样认识到这种热情对于我们健康和精力的种种影响，可我还是相信，大多数诚实的人们都知道并且会立刻承认，它的主要作用是为我们的所作所为提供动机。水手通常不会仅仅因为自己比别人更善于在船上操作就想要成为一名船长，他想成为船长是因为希望能被称为船长；牧师通常不会仅仅因为自己比其他人能更为坚定地带领主教管区克服重重困难就想成为一名主教，他要成为一名主教，从根本上来说是因为他想被称为“大人”；国君通常不会仅仅因为自己比其他人戴上王冠能更好地服务于国家就想扩大或占有一个王国，而是，简而言之，他这样做是为了想要被尽可能多的人称为“陛下”。

这就是“生活的进步”的主旨所在。对于我们所有的人来说，根据我们目前所处的地位，它的力量被主要运用于此种进步的附带结果上，就是促使我们进入到所谓的“上流社会”。我们要进入上流社会，不是为了占有它，而是为了现身其中。我们所理解的“上流”，主要就是它的与众不同。

我想暂停一下，问一个你们可能认为是不相干的问题可以吗？如果不弄清楚听众们是支持还是反对我的观点，我就不敢没完没了地讲下去。开始讲的时候我并不在乎，但是讲过一会儿之后，我就必须知道大家的想法。现在，我马上就想知道你们是不是觉得我把人们一般行为的动机估计得太低了。今晚，我下定决心，为了使大家觉得更可信而把这些动机尽量地低估；因为每当我在有关政治经济学的著作当中，把一点点的诚实或是慷慨，或是其他什么可以称作是“美德”的东西，当作是人类行为动机的时候，人们就会回应我说，“你不要指望那些东西，它们不是人类的本性，除了嫉妒和贪婪以外人类没有其他共通的品质；只有偶尔在商业以外的什么事儿上，人们才会有点其他的情感。”所以，今晚我就从低层次的动机开始谈起，但是我必须知道你们是否同意我的观点。我要问一下，有谁同意，人们追求进步最强烈的动机通常是希望得到表扬，而真心诚意地履行职责完全是次要的。请同意的举一下手。（大概十一二个人举起了手——听众们可能是拿不准我是认真的还是在开玩笑，还有可能是羞于表达自己的观点。）我是认真的——我真的想知道你们的想法；当然，同样的问题我也可以反过来问。请那些认为履行职责是首要的动机，而希望得到表扬是次要动机的人举起手来好吗？（据说只有一个坐在我身后的人举了手。）很好，看来大家同意我的观点，你们认为我并没有把人类动机估计得太低。现在，我不再麻烦大家回答更多的问题了。我大胆地假设一下你们都承认履行职责至少是第二位或是第三位的动机。在大多数人要求进步的愿望当中，尽管你们认为做点儿有用的事，或是得到点儿真正的美德是第二位的，然而它们确实是现实存在并且可以间接获得的。大家都承认，那些稍微诚实的人要取得地位和职权，至少在某种程度上是为了获得做善事的权力；他们希望结交通情达理和见多识广的人，而不是那些傻瓜和无知之徒，不管他们是否确实与通情达理的人们为伍。最后，不用赘述什么有关“朋友的珍贵”，以及“伙伴的影响”之类的老生常谈，你们也一定会承认，毫无疑问，我们是否真心地希望拥有真正的朋友和聪明的伙伴——能否拥有他们与我们作出选择时的认真和谨慎程度成正比——决定了我们是否可以生活得快乐和充实。

即使在择友方面既有意愿又有意识，我们当中又有几个人具备这样的才能呀！或是，至少对于大多数人来说，可供我们择友的范围是多么的有限呀！几乎我们所有的交往都是由运气或是需要所决定的；并且局限在一个狭窄的圈子里。我们不能结交想要结交的人；而那些我们已经结交了的，又不会在我们最需要他们的时候出现在身旁。所有更高一级的人类智慧的圈子，对于下面的人们来说，也只会短暂地和部分地开放。如果运气好的话，我们可能瞄上一眼某位伟大的诗人，听到他说话的声音；或是对某位科学家提出一个问题，然后得到他和蔼的回答。我们可能勉强地与一位内阁大臣谈上十分钟的话，而得到的虚伪回答却还不如沉默不语；或是有时我们能够抓住机会，尽管这样的机会少之又少，在公主行进的路上投出一束鲜花，或是得到女王陛下亲切的一瞥。我们所觊觎的这些片刻机遇，尽管只是如此而已，却会花掉我们数年的时光、热情和精力；而与此同时，却有一个社会群体持续地对我们开放，只要我们愿意，那里的人们就会一直同我们交谈，不管我们是何地位、是何职业——用他们能想到的最好的词语同我们倾心交谈。这个社会群体中的人物数目庞大、脾气温和，而且能够一天到晚地陪伴在我们左右——国王和政治家们耐心地走来走去，不是同意你的觐见而是期待你的造访！——他们就守候在那些布置朴素的，狭窄的前厅里，在我们的书架上——而我们对他们却不理不睬——可能一天下来也没有听他们说上一句话！

你们可能会告诉我，或是在心里这样想：我们之所以冷漠地对待这一群高贵的，恳求我们听他们诉说的人们；之所以满怀热情地追随那样一群可能是卑贱的，鄙视我们或是没什么可赐教的人们，是因为我们真正想要熟悉的是他们活生生的面容，是他们本人，而不是听他们所说的话。事实并非如此！假设你们不可能目睹他们的真容——假设在你们和政要的密室之间，或是在你们和国王的会客厅之间拉上一道屏风，而你们不能跨过这道屏风，难道你们不是很乐意倾听他们的谈话吗？此时我们将屏风变小，折成两折而不是四折，而你们可以隐藏在两块装订书籍的封皮的后面，整天地倾听；不是在听闲话，而是在听最为睿智的人们所作的，深思熟虑的、斩钉截铁的、精挑细选的演说；这种倾听的方式，听这种万人敬仰的枢密院里的高谈阔论，你们怎么会不屑一顾呢？

可能你们会说，我这样做是因为活着的人谈论的是正在发生的事儿，而我只对这些事儿感兴趣。不，情况不像你说的那样，因为活着的人在他们的著作中所讲的当下的事儿要比他们漫不经心的谈话好得多。我也承认，如果你喜爱的是那些一时流行的、短命的，而非传播缓慢且耐久的作品的话——准确来讲应该叫作书籍，那么这种动机确实能够影响到你，因为所有的书籍都可以分为两类：一时之书与永恒之书。请注意这之间的区别，它不光涉及书籍的质量。不仅仅是坏书难以流传，而好书却可以。这是一种类型的区别。好书既可以流行一时也可以传诵万代；同样，坏书也可以是一时的坏书，或是永远的坏书。在继续讲下去之前，我有必要首先对这二者加以界定。

一时的好书——我不讲坏书——就是将某个你不可能与之对话的人的有用或者是令人愉快的谈话刊印出书。它们通常很实用，告诉你应当懂点儿什么；又通常很耐读，就像一位聪明的朋友与你面谈。这些一时之书包括欢快的游记，幽默机智的问题讨论，生动或是伤感的小说故事，确凿的，由那些历史亲历者们讲述的纪事等。这些书籍随着教育的普及而数量大增，是现在这个时代所特有的财富。我们对这些书应当满怀感激，并且，应当因为没能很好地利用它们而满怀羞愧，但是，如果我们让这些书篡夺了真正的书的地位的话，那么这种利用就糟糕至极了，因为严格来说，它们不能叫作书，只不过是印刷精良的书信或是报纸。我们朋友的来信可能在今天读来会让人感到欢喜或是有必要，然而是不是值得将其长期保留却还有待商榷。在吃早餐时读读报纸是完全可以的，但可以肯定的是我们不能一整天都读报纸。因此，一封长信尽管装订成册，并且生动地讲述了去年某地的客栈、道路以及天气，或是告诉你一个有趣的故事，或是描述了某某事件发生时的真实环境，不管它偶尔会有多么大的参考价值，也不能叫作真正意义上的“书”，或是从真正意义上去“读”。书从根本上来讲不是说出来的，而是写出来的；写这种书的目的不仅仅在于交流，而是为了传世。谈话类的书印刷出来仅仅是因为它的作者不能对成千上万的人同时讲话；如果能的话，他会这样做的——这样的书不过是他的扩音器而已。你不能和远在印度的朋友交谈；如果能的话，你会的；于是你选择了写，那不过是为了传声的方便，但是写一本书不仅仅是为了扩大音量或是传递声音，而是要使你的声音不朽。作家要说一些他认为是对的、有用的，或者是对读者而言既有所帮助又能带来美的愉悦的东西。据他所知，因为此事无人曾经谈及，也没有人能谈此事，所以他对此就一定要说上两句，而且说的时候嗓音要尽可能的清晰而甜美，所有细节都要交代得清清楚楚。他发现在自己的生命中这件事或是某一方面的事是他了然于胸的；这是他沐浴阳光、停留人世所得到的真知灼见。于是，他会欣然命笔，可能的话会将其镌刻在岩石之上；说：“这是我最好的作品；过去我像其他人一样，吃饭、饮酒、睡觉、有爱有恨；我的生命曾经虚无缥缈，但现在不是了；如果说我有什么值得您铭记的话，那么就是这部作品。”这就是他的“作品”；他凭借一己之力以及或多或少的灵感，刻写下了如此的铭文，或者叫作经典著作。这，才能叫作“书”。

可能你们会这样想：没有哪本书是这样写成的吧？

可我要问问你们，你们是相信有诚实或是仁慈存在呢，还是认为智者根本就不具备诚实或是仁慈的品德呢？我希望没有人会悲观到有后面这样的想法。那么，智者的作品，无论它多么微不足道，只要是以诚实和仁爱的态度写就的话，就称得上是书或是艺术品，然而，它总是与其他粗制滥造、拖沓冗长、矫揉造作的作品搅和在一起。不过，只要你能正确地阅读，就会轻易地发现其中有价值的作品，那些才是真正的书。

各个时代最伟大的人们都写下过此类书籍：他们是伟大的领袖，伟大的政治家和伟大的思想家。这些书都可供你们选择。生命是短暂的，你们也知道这一点。你们可曾为这短暂的一生以及它的潜在价值做过规划呢？你们知道吗，如果你们读了某些书就不能再读另外一些书——今天所失去的，明天是无法弥补的。这样一来，如果你们可以同国王和王后交谈的话，你们还会跑去和女佣或是马夫闲聊天吗？如果你们有机会走进这样一间永恒的殿宇，里面站满了上流社会的精英，海阔天空，群星璀璨—他们来自于各个国度、各个时代，你们还会自鸣得意地，怀着希望得到别人尊重和钦佩的想法，同饥渴的平民百姓一起挤来挤去，一会儿争夺这里的入场券，一会儿又跑到那里当听众吗？你们随时可以进到那里去；在那里你们可以如己所愿地获得友谊和地位；一旦进到那里，除非你们自己犯错，就永远都不会被驱逐；通过在那里结识的精英，你们自身的高贵将毫无疑问地接受检验；你们力争在生活中爬上社会高位的动机将会得到已经处于社会高位的、掌握真理的、心怀诚挚的逝去者们的度量。

我不得不说，“你们所渴望的地位”也就是你们准备好要获得的地位；请大家注意，这座历史的殿宇不同于所有活在其中的贵族——它只对劳动和美德开放。富贵不能淫，声名不能屈，诡计不能诱的守护人在守卫着极乐世界大门。进一步讲，卑鄙下流之徒永远都进不去。在寂静的巴黎圣日耳曼区的帘幕上面写着这样简短的提问：“你有资格进来吗？你想要与贵族为伍吗？先让你自己高贵起来吧，这样你才会如愿以偿。你想同智者交谈吗？先学会理解谈话的内容，你才会听懂谈话。还有其他要求吗？——没有了。如果你不起身迎接我们，我们是不会俯身屈就你的。活着的贵族会对你彬彬有礼，活着的哲学家会不厌其烦地向你解释他的思想；但是在这里，我们既不会冒充贵族，也不想多费唇舌；如果你想要从我们的思想中获得快乐，分享我们的情感；如果你想要感受到我们的存在，你就必须上升到我们的高度。”

这是你必须做的，我认为这很重要。简言之，如果你想位列其中的话，就必须爱这些人。有野心是不管用的，他们藐视你的野心。你必须爱他们，并且在以下两个方面展现你的爱。

第一，诚心向他们讨教，进入到他们的思想中去。注意，是进入到他们的思想，而不是在他们的表述中寻找你自己的思想。如果写书的人还没有你聪明，那就不要读他的书了；如果他比你聪明，他的所思所想会在很多方面与你不同。

第二，在谈起一本书的时候，我们常常这样说：“这本书真棒——它和我想的一样！”然而正确的感觉应该是，“真奇怪呀！我怎么从来没有想到过，不过我觉得它说得对；或是，如果我现在不明白，希望将来可以搞得懂。”不管这样是不是有点卑躬屈膝，但至少可以肯定的是，你理解了作者的思想，而不是发现了自己的思想。如果你认为自己有资格对书中的思想作出评价的话，你可以稍后作出；不过你首先要明了它的思想。同时，如果这是一位有分量的作者的话，你就一定要清楚自己不可能立刻就理解他的全部思想；而且，无论如何你都不可能在短期内理解他的全部思想。这倒不是因为他闪烁其词，文采不够；而是因为他不可能将所有的思想和盘托出；更为奇怪的是，他也不愿意这样做。他会采取以一种隐藏的、寓言的方式表达思想，为的就是想看看，你是否真的想要得到它。我不大明白他们这样做的原因，也不明白为什么智者们会将他们的思想深藏于心，保持残忍的缄默。他们是通过奖励的方式而不是帮忙的方式给你思想；在你得到它之前，他们一定要确信你有此资格。这就像以物理形态存在着的智慧——黄金一样。你我都希望地球的魔力能将所储藏的黄金立刻运上山顶，于是国王及其子民就会知道他们所要的黄金就在那儿；不用忍受挖掘的艰辛、焦虑、运气和漫长的等待就可以将其取走，而且想铸造多少金币就铸造多少，然而大自然的安排并非如此。她将黄金藏在地下的狭窄缝隙里，没有人知道在哪儿。你可能徒劳而无所获；然而却必须奋力才能有所得。

这与人类的最高智慧是一样的。当你拿到一本好书的时候，你必须问自己，“我会像一位澳大利亚矿工那样去挖掘它吗？我的镐头和铁锹是否井然有序，我的状态是否良好，我的袖子是否挽到了胳膊肘，我的呼吸是否均匀、情绪是否高涨呢？”接下来，保持这种状态时间长一点，尽管你会感到疲惫，因为这非常有用。你正在寻找的宝藏是作家的思想，他的话语就如同岩石，你想要理解它就必须将其碾碎、熔炼。你的镐头就是你的细心、智慧和学识；你的熔炉就是自己善于思索的心灵。不要奢望不假以那些挖掘的工具和燃烧着的烈火就可以得到伟大作家的思想；经常是只有最锋利、最精巧的斧凿，最耐心的熔解才会让你得到一丁点儿的宝藏。

首先，我可以认真且负责任地告诉你们（我确信自己所说的是对的），你们必须要养成密切关注词语的习惯，要确实搞懂它们的含义，一个音节一个音节地，一个字母一个字母地搞清楚。因为，尽管仅仅是因为符号功能中的字母与符号功能中的声音相对立，对于书籍的研究才叫作“文学”（其实应当叫作“字母学”，因为literature源于litters，意为lettered），而精通文学的人，这已经得到了多数国家的认可，才被叫作文人（直译过来应当叫作“字母人”：a man of letters），而不是书人（a man of books）或是字人（a man of words），你却仍然可以将这一偶然得到的术语（a man of letters）与这样一个事实相联系：——你有可能读遍大英博物馆的所有藏书（假定你活得足够长久的话），却还是一个彻头彻尾的“文盲”（illiterate），一个没有受过教育的人；但是如果你一个字一个字地读上十页好书——就是说达到了真正精确的理解——那么从今往后，在某种程度上说，你就是一个受过教育的人。受过和没受过教育的全部差异，仅就理解力的层面而言，就体现在这一精确性上。一位受过良好教育的绅士可能不懂多种语言——除了自己的母语其他都不会说——可能只读过很少几本书，但是他能精确地掌握他所懂的语言；他能正确地读出每个单词的读音；最为重要的是，他熟稔这些单词的族谱；看上一眼当今大众所使用的词汇，他就知道它们真正的传承和古老的血统；他记得所有这些单词的祖先、亲戚、旁支，以及在何种程度上，它们被某一时代、某一国度的贵族阶层所接受，从而登上了大雅之堂。相反，一位没受过教育的人可能会凭借记忆使用多种语言，而且都会说，但是他对其中单词的含义却不甚了解——对自己的母语也是如此。一位智慧和判断力程度一般的水手能够设法在大多数的港口靠岸；然而只要他一张嘴，以某种语言说出话来，就能立刻被识破没有文化：同样，说话的腔调，或是在句中表达方式的变化等，都可以让一位学者立即现形。对于这一点，受过教育的人都已经深切地感受到，并且完全地认可了。因此，在文明国度的议会里，即便是说错一处重音或是一处音节，都会让人永远抬不起头来。

这样做是对的；但令人遗憾的是，我们对精确性的要求还不够，还没有将其应用于严肃的目的。没错，一个拉丁文音节的错误会在下议院里面引发嘲笑；但是我们却对一个英文词义的误用连眉头都不皱一下。大家要留心单词的重音，更要注意它们的含义，这样即使较少的词语也能满足工作的要求。当每个单词都被含混不清地使用的时候，我们可以精心选取一些单词加以澄清，这样就会起到四两拨千斤的功效。确实，如果使用单词时不加小心，有时就会铸成大错。现在欧洲就有这样一些在我们身边不停聒噪的、若隐若现的、戴了面具的单词。过去这些词语的数量并不大，但是现在，由于到处都充斥了浅显、污秽、笨拙、有传染性的“信息”，或是干脆叫作谎言，而且学校里面只教给学生教义问答手册和成语而不是活生生的语言，因此使得这些词语的数量大增。没有人能理解这些单词，但是每个人都在使用它们；而且大多数人还都会为之战斗，为之生，甚至为之死；幻想着它们是这个意思，那个意思，或是其他什么他们所喜爱的东西。这些词语披着变色龙的斗篷——“地狮”的斗篷，它们的颜色就如你想象中土地的颜色一样：它们埋伏在地上会随时一跃而起，将你撕得粉碎。从来没有像这些戴面具的词语一样凶残的猎食者、狡猾的外交官和致命的投毒人；它们是所有人类思想不忠的管家：人类把最钟爱的想象力和天赋都交给了戴假面具的词语来照看；它最终却以无穷的力量控制了人类——没有它的帮忙你就无法交流。

像英语这样来源混杂的语言，会赋予人们一种致命的、模棱两可的力量，因为无论愿意与否，人们总可以使用希腊或是拉丁词汇敬畏地表达某一思想；同样也可以使用撒克逊或是其他的常见词语粗俗地表达这一思想。比方说，如果，我们要么保留、要么拒绝将希腊文中的“biblos”或“biblion”作为“书”的正确表达方式——而不是在我们希望赋予某一思想尊严的时候就使用它，而在其他的场合则将其翻译成英文的话，那么就会对因为这“字”代表了“权力”而已经习惯了靠“字”的形式来生活的人们，产生多么非凡和有益的影响啊。如果在这种地方，比如说《使徒行传》第十九章第十九节，我们保留了希腊的表达方式，而没有翻译过来，人们就会这样读——“平素行邪术的，也有许多人把书拿来，堆积在众人面前焚烧。他们计算书价，便知道共合五万块钱”，这样对于很多淳朴的普通人来说是多么有益心智啊！

或是，如果，从另一方面来讲，我们把应当保留的部分翻译了过来，总是说《圣书》（The Holy Book），而不是《圣经》（Holy Bible），尽管这样可能会使这本书为更多的人所接受，然而，“凭神的命，自古就有了天，凭神的命，天被保留到现在”[2]，这样的话是不能用摩洛哥山羊皮装订起来作为礼物送人的；是不能在蒸汽引犁或是汽压机的帮助下播种在路边的；尽管如此，每天还是有人把它呈送给我们，然后遭到我们傲慢的拒绝；每天还是有人向我们传播，然后被我们迅速地扼杀。

因此，请再次考虑一下，当人们出于善意想要把词语说得更有力的时候，就在翻译希腊文“nαταnδiνω”时使用声音洪亮的拉丁词“下地狱”（damno）；而当人们想要把词语说得更温柔一些的时候，就使用温和的“定罪”（condemn）来替换它；这样会对普通英国人产生怎样的影响呢？尽管没什么文化的牧师会在翻译《希伯来书》第十一章第七节，“拯救了自己的房屋，定了世界的罪”（The saving of his house, by which he damned the world），以及《约翰福音》第八章第十、十一节，“妇人，没有人定你的罪吗？她说，主啊，没有。耶稣说，我也不定你的罪：去吧，别再犯错了”（Woman, hath no man damned thee？She saith, No man, Lord.Jesus answered her, Neither do I damn thee：go and sin no more）的时候会吓得倒退，可是他在布道时所说的——“不信主的人将被定罪”（He that believeth not shall be damned）是多么的出色呀。欧洲各个国家已经为了思想的分歧付出了血流成河的代价，在捍卫各自思想的时候，多少最高贵的灵魂已如秋风扫落叶般被抛弃在疯狂的废墟中——尽管在他们的心中，自己的离去是出于崇高的理想。不过，分裂的欧洲已经采用了ecclesia，它这个来自希腊文，专指市民议会的词，用以特别地敬称出于宗教目的而召开的“教友会”；当然还有其他的一些并行不悖的词语，比如在粗俗的英语中使用“priest”（牧师）来代替“presbyter”（长老）。

这样看来，为了正确地使用词语，你们必须养成这样的习惯。我们语言中的每一个单词几乎最初的时候都来源于其他的语言——撒克逊语、德语、法语、拉丁语或希腊语等（这还没有算上东方的和原始的方言土语）。很多的词汇都经历了这样的演化——最初是希腊语，接下来是拉丁语，然后是法语或德语，最后才演化成英语。在每个民族的唇齿之间流传的过程当中，这些词汇的意义和用法发生了一定的改变；但是其深层次的和本质性的意义却保留了下来，这一点是所有优秀的学者，即便是今天，在使用的过程中都能感觉得到的。如果你不认识希腊字母，就请去学；不管你年轻还是年老，是男孩儿还是女孩儿，如果想要认真地阅读（当然，这就意味着你有空闲的时间可供支配），就要学会希腊字母；然后要设法搞到所有这些语言的好的字典，无论什么时候对某个单词搞不清楚，都要耐心地穷追猛打，直到搞清楚为止。开始的时候要仔细研读一下马克斯·穆勒的讲义；然后，不放过任何一个看上去可疑的单词。阅读是件严肃的事儿，不过你会发现，即使是开始的时候也饶有趣味，而在结束的时候则会带来无尽的享受。同时，你在人格方面的收获，比如思维能力和精确性的提高，将会十分巨大。

请注意，这并不是意味着要求大家掌握或是试图掌握希腊文、拉丁文或法文。要想彻底掌握任何一门语言都需要付出终身的努力，但是，你可以轻而易举地查明一个英文单词含义的演变历程，以及在优秀作家的作品中仍然使用着的，这些单词的含义。

现在，为了举例说明，请允许我为你们从一本真正的书中仔细地读几行，看一看能从中读出些什么。我要挑选一本大家所熟知的书。我们对这里面的英文单词都再熟悉不过了，然而对其中绝大多数的单词却从未认真读过。下面这几行诗选自弥尔顿的《利西达斯》——

“最后一个来，最后一个走，

加利利湖的领航员。

随身带了两把硕大的金属钥匙，

（金的开启，铁的迅速关闭，）

他摇晃着主教的冠冕，严厉地说，

“我本可以将你赦免，年轻的牧羊人，

可我受够了，他们为了填饱肚子而

匍匐，拥挤，并且攀爬进羊圈！

除了在剪毛人的宴会上你争我抢，

推开尊贵的客人，

对于其他很少计算；

瞎眼的馋嘴！自己从来不知道握有

羊钩，或是学会点儿什么其他的，

属于忠诚的牧人的技艺！

他们有何顾虑？有何所需？有人催问牧羊人；

他们听闻后，便在肮脏的麦秆做成的刺耳的风

笛上吹出呕哑啁哳的，

单调轻佻的歌曲；

饥饿的群羊腹内空空，翘首期盼，

但肚里冷风嗖嗖，瘴气吸满，

他们内脏腐烂，传染蔓延；

更有恶狼突施冷箭

每日悄无声响，大肆吞咽。”

让我们思考一下这个段落，研究一下其中的措辞。

首先，弥尔顿不仅仅赋予了圣彼得完全的主教职能，而且还让他行使了新教徒通常最为反对的职责。这难道不是很奇怪吗？他的“戴上了主教冠”（mitred）的头发！弥尔顿并不热爱主教，在这里却为什么给圣彼得“戴上了主教冠”呢？“他随身携带着两把大金属钥匙。”这钥匙是代表了罗马主教所拥有的权力吗？或者说，弥尔顿在这里仅仅是为了诗歌的视觉效果而描写金属钥匙的闪光，从而提升诗歌的表达效果呢？

这不可能。伟大的人物从来不拿生与死的原则问题开玩笑：只有小人物才这么干。弥尔顿所说的就是他真实意思的表达；并且是着力表达的——在表达的时候凝聚了他全部的精神力量。尽管弥尔顿不喜欢冒牌的主教，却喜爱真正的主教；在他的意念当中，这里的湖中领航人正是真正主教权力的代表。因为弥尔顿真心实意地这样说过：“我将把天国的钥匙交给你。”尽管是清教徒，弥尔顿也不会因为曾经的坏主教就将这句话从书中删去；而且，为了理解弥尔顿，我们必须先要理解这首诗；将这首诗看作是一件敌对教派的武器，用怀疑的眼光去看待它或是对它嘀嘀咕咕是不行的。这是一首庄严且具普世意义的诗歌，所有的教派都应牢记在心。如果我们作一下对照的话，或许你就能理解得更好了。很清楚，弥尔顿在这里对于真正的主教权力的坚持是为了让我们更为深切地感觉到什么是被滥用了的主教权力；或是通常来讲，什么是被牧师们所滥用了的权力和等级；因为他们“为了填饱肚子，匍匐、拥挤，并且攀爬进羊圈”。

千万不要以为，弥尔顿使用这三个词是和其他不严谨的作家一样，为了填补诗中的空缺。这三个词缺一不可，恰到好处——“匍匐”“拥挤”以及“攀爬”，没有比它们更好的措辞了，多一个词也加不进去。因为这三个词全面地概括了三种类型，三种性格的人，他们通过欺诈的手段攫取教会的权力。第一种是那些“匍匐”进羊圈的人；他们不在乎职位或是声名，而是为了获取秘密的影响力，于是做什么事都神神秘秘、奸诈狡猾。他们赞同任何卑躬屈膝的仪式或是行为，为的是能够密切地洞悉，并且在不知不觉中操控人们的思想。然后是那些“拥挤”（即硬闯）进羊圈的人；他们通过天生的傲慢，强有力的辩词，以及无畏且固执的专断获得了对普通民众发号施令的权威。最后是那些“攀爬”的人；他们出于个人的野心而付出自私的努力，通过坚定而高效的劳作和学习，获得了高位的礼遇和职权，成为“世袭的主人”，而不是“群众的楷模”。

现在我们接着看——

“除了在剪毛人的宴会上你争我抢，

对于其他很少计算，

瞎眼的馋嘴——”

我再次停下来，因为这个词很奇怪；你可能会认为这是一个由于诗人不小心或是学问不够而用错的暗喻。

其实不然：这个大胆而简洁有力的措辞正是为了引起我们的注意并且记住它。这两个单音节词（英文为单音节词：blind mouths）所代表的正是它们所对应的反面人物，也就是教会中没有履行自己的职责的主教和牧师。

因为“主教”意味着“能看得到的人”。

而“牧师”则意味着“能提供食物的人”。

最不配做主教的人就是瞎眼的人。

最不配做牧师的人就是长着一张馋嘴的人——不给他人提供食物反而等待被他人喂食。

把这两种相反的方面放到一起就是“瞎眼的馋嘴”。我们应当进一步地阐明这一思想。几乎所有教会中的罪恶都起源于主教们不思光明而争夺权力。他们一味追求权威而不司瞭望之职。尽管他们可以积极地劝诫和训斥；然而他们真正的职权并不是统治：国王的职责才是统治；主教的职责是照看羊群；一只一只地点数；对它们的情况了若指掌。如果他没有清点过自己羊群的身体，显然就不可能道出它们的灵魂。因此，主教要做的第一件事就是使自己处于这样一种位置——任何时候，他都能够获知自己辖区内的每一个生灵从童年起的历史及当前的状态。在那条偏僻街道的尽头，比尔和南希正彼此打得满地找牙！——主教对此获悉了吗？关注他们了吗？关注过他们吗？他能够详细地告诉我们比尔是怎么养成了殴打南希头部的习惯吗？如果不能，他就不是主教，哪怕是他的主教冠高得像斯尔兹伯里大教堂的尖顶；他不是主教——他总是想着掌舵指挥，而不是站立在桅顶上去瞭望；他什么也看不到。“然而”，你会说，“在小街道里照看比尔可不是他的职责。”什么！难道你认为他仅仅应当照看那些毛色亮泽的肥羊吗？而与此同时，（听听弥尔顿是怎么说的）“饥饿的群羊腹内空空，翘首期盼，更有恶狼突施冷箭”（主教对此一无所知），“每日悄无声响，大肆吞咽”。

“但是我们眼中的主教不是这样的。”可能不是；但是圣保罗眼中的主教以及弥尔顿眼中的主教是这样的。他们可能是正确的，我们也可能是正确的；但是一定不要以为把我们自己的想法强加给他们的言词，就是在读这本或那本书了。

我接着读：

“但肚里冷风嗖嗖，瘴气吸满。”

这句是为了回应那句俗话——“如果穷人的躯体得不到照看，那么就照看他们的灵魂；让他们有精神的食粮。”

弥尔顿说：“他们没有所谓的精神食粮；他们只有满肚子的冷风。”起先你可能以为这是个粗俗的比喻，晦涩难懂，但是同样，这个说法用词精准。拿起你的拉丁或是希腊语词典，查找一下“神灵”（spirit）的含义。它恰恰是拉丁语中“气息”（breath）的缩写，大体上与希腊语中的“风”（wind）相当。同样一个词还用在“风随心所欲地吹”；还用在“每个诞生于神灵的人都是如此”；这是说诞生于气息；因为它意指上帝的气息，包括灵魂和躯体。我们可以在自己的词汇，如“灵感”（inspiration也指吸气）和“死亡”（expire也指呼气）中发现气息的真正含义。现在，群羊可以呼吸到两种气息，——上帝的气息和人的气息。上帝的气息对于他们来说是健康的、充满活力的、和平的，这就如同空气之于山间的羊群一样；但是人的气息——就是弥尔顿在这里所指的精神，——对于他们来说就是疾病和传染，如同沼泽中的瘴气一样。他们的内脏由于瘴气而腐烂；身体肿胀，就像腐烂后产生臭气的尸体一样。荒谬的宗教说教确实有此功效；最初的、最后的以及最致命的标志就是“肿胀”。皈依了的孩子们教导他们的父母；皈依了的罪犯教导诚实的人；皈依了的傻瓜，半辈子都生活在白痴和麻木的状态，突然间醒过来认识到上帝的存在，就幻想自己变成了他享有特权的子民和信使；每个教派的宗派主义者们都认为他们自己才是正确的，而其他教派是错误的，不论这个教派是大是小，是天主教还是新教，是高教会派还是低教会派；而且，突出的表现是，每个教派中都有人认为人们只要想得对而不需要做得对就可以得救，只要说话而不需要行动就可以得救，只要祈祷而不需要工作就可以得救——所有这些人都受到了真正的毒害；他们没有血肉的尸身只剩下腐败的臭气和一张皮：魔鬼将这张臭皮囊像风笛一样吹起——腐败，并且正在腐败——“肚里冷风嗖嗖，瘴气吸满。”

最后，让我们回到先前讨论过的，有关钥匙的权力的诗句，因为此时我们应该能够领会了。大家要注意，在对这一权力的解读方面弥尔顿和但丁存在着不同：仅此一次，但丁的思想显得更为薄弱一些。他认为两把都是开启天堂大门的钥匙；一把是金的，一把是银的。圣彼得将两把钥匙交给了看门的天使；而且但丁很难确定门前三级台阶的材质以及两把钥匙所代表的含义。弥尔顿认为其中一把金钥匙是用来开启天堂大门的；另一把铁钥匙是用来打开监狱大门的，那里关着邪恶的教师，他们“偷走了智慧之门的钥匙，然而却连自己也进不去”。

我们已经看到了，主教和牧师的职责就是照看和喂食；对于履行了这样责任的人，有如此说法：“浇灌别人的人，自己也将得到浇灌。”但是反过来说也成立。不浇灌别人的人，自己也必将枯干；没有照看别人的人，将会被关到视线之外——关进永久的牢房。那所监牢的大门此时打开着，今后也是如此，想要进天堂的人首先要活在地上。上帝对于以使徒形象示人的，强壮的天使所发布的命令就是：“抓住他，绑住他的手脚，然后将他扔出去。”这里的“他”就是牧师，因为他不愿帮助别人，拒绝接受真理，决意奉行谎言；所以他被戴上比他所打造的镣铐更多的镣铐，被驱逐到比他误导他人所能达到的更远的地方，直到最后，铁笼子的栏杆将他完全罩住，“金的开启，铁的迅速关闭”。

我觉得我们已经从这些诗句中读出了些东西，然而还有更多的东西有待发现；但就举例而言，我们所呈现出的，这种能够称得上是“阅读”的，逐字逐句进行分析的方式，已经做得足够好了；我们关注每一个重读和词语，总是将自己置于作者的位置，放弃我们自己的个性，寻求进入他的个性当中去，为的就是能够言之凿凿地说，“这就是弥尔顿的想法”，而不是“我是这样想的，我按照自己的方式理解弥尔顿”。通过这一过程你会逐步地减少在其他场合对于“我是这样想的”的倚重程度。你会开始将你的所思所想看得无关紧要——你对于某事的想法可能不是最清晰的，也不是最明智的——事实上，除非你是个非同凡响的人，你是不大可能有什么“思想”的；在任何严肃的问题上[3]，你都缺乏表达思想的资本——没有权利去“想”，只可能努力地去学习更多的既成事实。而且，极有可能在你的一生当中（除非，我说过，你是个非同凡响的人）都不会在任何事上面拥有发表“观点”的合法权利，除非这件事直接由你掌控。毫无疑问，你通常都会发现什么是必须做的，以及如何做这些事情。你有房子要收拾，货品要销售，田地要耕犁，沟渠要疏浚吗？通常对于如何处理这些事并不存在分歧；但是，如果要求你对于如何处理这些事拿个“主意”的话，那就危险了。而且，除了你自己的营生以外，总会有那么一两件事，一定需要你拿个主意。流氓和欺骗行为是令人反感的，一经发现就会立刻遭到驱逐；贪婪和喜爱争吵即便是在孩子们的身上也是危险的倾向，在成人和国家身上则是致命的缺点；说到底，主宰人间与天堂的上帝喜爱积极、谦虚和友善的人，痛恨懒惰、骄傲、贪婪和残忍的人；在这些大是大非的事情方面你必须作出选择，而且毫不动摇。至于其他方面，比如说宗教、政治、科学、艺术等，你会发现，总的来说，你一无所知，也不会作出什么判断；尽管你可能是一个受过良好教育的人，你能作出的最好选择，就是保持沉默，每天都努力让自己变得更聪明些，理解更多其他人的思想。如果你能按照上面我所说的，诚恳地去做的话，你就会发现其实即使是最具智慧的人们的思想也不过是提出了相关的疑问而已。他们将困难描述得清晰可见，给你展示出悬而未决的因由，这就是通常来讲，他们能为你所做的一切！而且，如果他们确实能够“用动听的音乐渗入我们的思考，用神圣的质疑让我们悲伤”的话，那么对他们、对我们来说都是好事一件。我刚刚读给大家的这句诗并非出自一流的或是最具智慧的作家，他不过是机敏地看到了他能看到的事，因此，发现他诗句的全部含义并不困难；但是对于那些更为伟大的作家的作品，你并不能看穿它们的含义；甚至连他们自己也不能完全了解，因为它的含义实在太宽广了。假设我要你们找出莎士比亚，而不是弥尔顿，对于教会权威的看法是什么，或者但丁的看法是什么的话，你们中有谁，现在能说出他们中任意一位对于这一问题的，哪怕是一丁点儿的看法呢？你们曾经将《查理三世》中有关主教们的那一幕与克兰麦大主教的性格相比较过吗？你们将对于圣·弗朗西斯和圣·多米尼克的描写与对于让维吉尔为之侧目的那个人的描写——“钉在十字架上的罪人，受到可耻的、永远的放逐；”或是对但丁在其身边站着的那个人的描写，“我站在那里像是修道士聆听奸诈的凶手忏悔”比较过吗？我相信，莎士比亚和但丁比我们绝大多数的人都更了解人类！他们两个都曾经处于世俗和宗教权力斗争的中心。我们猜测，他们一定有自己的观点，但是他们的观点哪儿去了呢？把它带上法庭吧！将莎士比亚或是但丁的信条写成文章，将其推上宗教法庭接受审判吧！

即便是花了很长的时间，我再说一遍，你也不会理解这些伟大人物的真实意图和教义；但是只要稍微地、老老实实地对他们加以研究，你就会认识到自己先前的所谓“判断”不过是冒险的偏见——它随波逐流，与人们所摒弃的思想杂草缠绕在一起；而且，你会看到大多数人们的头脑不过是崎岖的荒野，未经照料、顽固不化，一半儿寸草不生，一半儿又荆棘蔓延，并且长满了邪恶臆断的，随风飘散的毒草。你所要做的第一件事就是，对他们也包括对你自己，急切而轻蔑地将所有这些一把火烧光；将所有的丛林燃成有益身心的灰烬，然后耕犁、播种。要读懂真正的、值得珍藏一生的文学作品，就必须照此行事，“整饬你休耕中的土地，不要在荆棘中播种”。

忠实地聆听了伟大导师的教诲以后，你或许会进入到他们的思想，然而你还可以走得更远——进入到他们的心灵。起先你靠近他们的时候是为了一睹真容，所以必须同他们待在一起，这样才有可能最终分享他们正义而强大的激情。激情，或是“感觉”，我并不害怕这个词，更不害怕它所代表的事。最近人们对于感觉的抗议之声甚嚣尘上；但是，我要告诉你们，我们对于感觉的需求不是应当减少，而是应当增加。人与人之间，动物与动物之间的高贵与否，其区别就在于此——高贵的一方比另外一方更具感觉力。假如我们是块海绵，可能获得感觉并不容易；假如我们是一只蚯蚓，就随时有可能被铁锹斩为两段，这样一来太强的感觉则未必是件好事。作为人类，有感觉一定是好的；而且，只有拥有一颗敏感的心，我们才称得上是人类，而我们所能获得的荣誉正好与激情成正比。

你们一定记得我说过的那座伟大而纯粹的逝去者的殿堂，它不会允许“自大的或是粗俗的人进入”。你们是怎么理解我所说的“粗俗”的人呢？你们又是怎么理解“粗俗”的呢？对于这个问题的思考会使大家收获颇丰，简言之，所有粗俗的核心就是感觉的匮乏。朴素而无知的粗俗不过是未经开发和训练的身心的愚钝；但是真正的、根深蒂固的粗俗，则伴有可怕的冷漠，在其极端的状态下，会抛弃敬畏、愉悦、恐惧和怜悯，养成野兽的习性，犯下发指的罪行。正是迟钝的手脚、枯死的心灵、病态的习性和麻木不仁的良知让人变得粗俗；人们粗俗的程度与同情心的缺乏、反应的迟钝等这些是成正比的，而这一切的感觉又都来自于身体与灵魂，用一个最为精确的词，“触觉”或是“触角”。含羞草有这种触觉，纯洁的女人比其他生物都更有这种触觉；它是一种超越理性的、精细而丰富的感觉，是理性的向导和净化器。理性可以告诉我们什么是真；而只有上帝赐予的、人性的激情才能告诉我们什么是善。

我们于是来到那些逝去者的伟大的殿堂，不仅仅要从他们那里得知什么是真理，更主要的是要同他们一起感悟正义。现在，同他们一起感悟吧，我们一定要见贤思齐；而且没有谁能不劳而获。就如同真正的知识需要节制和检验，而非突发奇想一样，真正的激情也需要节制和检验，而非一时冲动。一时性起得到的是虚无、谬误和背叛；如果你向它们缴械投降，就会被带到遥远的荒野，在空洞的热情中徒劳地求索，直到你迷失了方向，激情耗尽。这倒不是说人性中有什么感觉自身是有错的，而是说没有节制的感觉就会出错。感觉的崇高之处就在于它的力量和公正；而当它虚弱并且产生于琐碎的事由的时候就是错误的。有一种低级的惊讶，就比方说当一个孩子看到魔术师抛出金球时的惊讶，这是很低级的，我想你们同意我的说法。你们想过没有，当所有人都受到感召去观看制造出金球的上帝之手在夜空中将金球抛出的情景时，他们的惊讶还是低劣的，或是缺乏感觉的吗？有一种低级的好奇心，比方说一个孩子打开一扇禁止打开的门，或是一个仆人窥伺他主人的生意——还有一种高尚的好奇心，直面危险，追问沙丘那边伟大河流的源头，海的那边伟大陆地的所在——还有一种更为高尚的好奇心，探寻生命河流的源头和天堂福地的所在，这些是“天使们意欲窥伺”的东西。因此，当你沉浸于一个低级的故事所讲述的灾难，此时所产生的焦虑就是可耻的；但是，当你注视着，或是应当注视着，一个饱受磨难的国家的生活和她多舛的命运时，你所产生的焦虑难道不是更加高尚了吗？呜呼！在今天的英国，应当受到谴责的是我们感觉的狭隘、自私和琐碎；我们将自己的感觉消耗在了鲜花和掌声中，在狂欢中，在宴饮中；在虚假的争斗和快乐的傀儡戏表演中；而与此同时，我们却看着高尚的民族被杀戮，一个接着一个，既不费力气也没有眼泪。

我说过感觉的“琐碎”和“自私”，然而说成感觉的“不公正”或是“非正义”就已经足够了；因为，要将绅士同粗俗的人区别开来，将高贵的民族（曾有过这样的民族）与暴民区别开来，下面一点就是最好的试金石——看看他们的感情是否坚定而公正，是否是正当的思忖和公平考虑的结果。你可以说服暴民做任何的事情；总体而言，他们的感情可能是，而且通常是，慷慨和正义的；然而这种感情缺乏根基，很难把握；你可以肆意地取笑或是挑逗他们做什么事；大多数暴民的思考方式是传染式的——他们接受一个观点就像得了场感冒，当病情发作的时候，芝麻粒儿大的事儿也会传得沸沸扬扬；当病状过后，就是天大的事儿也会撂爪就忘，但是绅士，或是高贵民族的激情是正义的、有节制的和持久的。一个伟大的民族，比如说，不会竭尽全民之才智，消耗数月之功，来权衡某个恶棍所犯谋杀案的罪证；而且不会在长达两三年的时间里，一直眼睁睁地看着自己的孩子们每天成千上万地彼此杀戮，却仅仅考虑如此情形会对棉花的价格产生怎样的影响，而不去过问战争的哪一方是非正义的。伟大的民族也不会因为可怜的孩子们仅仅是偷了六只胡桃就把他们关进监狱；不会允许偷了成千上万金钱的破产者们鞠躬道歉就算了事，还有一些银行家靠穷人们的存款发家致了富，仅仅写上一句“由于不可控的原因，请您恩准”就关门歇业；不会允许那些跳上在中国海上来回游弋的军舰，依靠大炮打通鸦片贸易而发了横财的人们收购大片的土地，他们为了自身的利益就将马路劫匪的命令由原来的“要钱还是要命”变成了“钱命我都要”。同样，一个伟大的民族也不会允许地主们为了每星期多赚六便士就用瘴气的热病和肮脏的瘟疫把那些无辜穷人的生命肆意摧残；然后假惺惺地、涕泪俱下地辩论是否应该虔诚地拯救、悉心地呵护杀人犯们的生命。而且，一个伟大的民族如果已经认定绞刑是对于杀人犯最为恰当的惩处的话，就一定会本着仁慈之心将杀人犯按其罪恶的轻重加以区别对待；并且不会像一群严寒折磨下的幼狼一样对着不幸的发疯的男孩的血迹发出狂吠，或是像满头银发的、呆傻的奥赛罗一样，派遣一位王室的使者对某个人彬彬有礼地说“这让我极为困惑”，而这个人，正在当着父亲们的面刺杀他们的女儿，正在冷血地杀死高贵的青年，其效率比一个乡下屠夫春天的时候屠杀绵羊还要高。最后，一个伟大的民族不会嘲笑上天及它的权力。它不会一边假装相信对金钱的热爱是所有罪恶的根源，另一边却宣称自己在所有主要的、国家的需求和考量方面，都是受到了金钱的驱使并且乐此不疲。

朋友们，我不知道为什么有人要谈论读书。我们需要比读书更为敏锐的修养；但无论如何，可以肯定的是，我们读不了书。一个心智在如此状态下的民族是不可能读书的。他们不会理解任何伟大作家的任何一句话。此时此刻，英国的公众完全不可能理解任何有思想的作品——他们在贪婪的精神错乱中已经丧失了思考的能力。幸运的是，我们的疾病还仅仅是停留在思考能力的缺乏上，还没有到内在天性泯灭的程度；当有什么东西击中我们的要害时，我们还会发出真实的呐喊；尽管什么东西都得“花钱”买的观念已经深入地传染到了我们行为处事的方方面面，尽管当我们扮演乐善好施的撒马利亚人的时候，不忘在掏出两便士的同时说上一句，“我再来的时候，你要还给我四便士。”在我们的内心深处还是保留有高贵的激情。我们在工作中、在战争中，甚至在那些不公正的家庭情感纠纷中（我们对于一个小的个人过错就大发雷霆，而对于一个影响巨大的公共失误却无动于衷）都显示出这一激情。我们仍旧终日辛勤劳作，尽管我们将赌徒的愤怒也算作是劳动者的耐心；我们仍然勇敢无畏、慷慨赴死，尽管不能辨识战争的真正原因；我们仍然至死爱着自己的父母兄弟，就像海怪和岩鹰一样。一个民族有如此高贵的激情就还有希望。只要它将生命攥在手中，愿意为了荣誉而将其牺牲（即便是愚蠢的荣誉），为了爱而将其牺牲（即便是自私的爱），为了事业而将其牺牲（即便是卑微的事业），就有希望。仅仅是希望而已，因为这种本能的、莽撞的美德难以为继。没有哪个自己是暴民的民族能够生生不息，无论它的内心多么慷慨。它必须约束自己的激情，而且引导它，否则将来某一天，激情就会反过来用毒蝎般的鞭子约束这一民族。总之，一个只知道赚钱的、暴民的民族是不可能长久的：它鄙视文学、鄙视科学、鄙视艺术、鄙视自然、鄙视同情，一心一意地忙于赚钱，这样的民族是不可能生存下去而免受责罚的。你们觉得我所说的话太过刺耳或是激烈了吗？请你们再多一点耐心。我会一条一条地证明给你们看我所说的是对的。

第一条我要说的是，我们鄙视文学。作为一个国家，我们把书籍当回事儿了吗？我们在公共及私人的图书馆上的开销与在马匹上的开销比起来孰多孰少呢？如果有谁在自己的图书馆上大笔地花钱，你们就一定会说他疯了——是个藏书狂，可是你们从来不把谁叫作藏马狂，即便是每天都有人毁于自己的马匹，而从没听说过有谁因为自己的书籍而破产。或者，说得再通俗些，联合王国的，公共的和私人的书架上的藏品，与它的酒窖中的藏品比较起来，哪个能带来更多的收益呢？与在奢华宴饮方面的花费相比，我们在文学方面的支出又处于何种地位呢？我们说精神的食粮就像身体的食粮一样：一本好书所能提供的食物是难以穷尽的；它为我们生命中最好的时光提供了给养；然而又有多少人会在盯着一本最好的书许久以后，以一条大比目鱼的价格将其买下呢？尽管曾经有人为了买一本书而节衣缩食，可是我想，到最后，他们中的大多数，在藏书上的花费还是要比自己在晚宴上的花费少。更为可悲的是，就连有过这样历练的人也很少；因为，只有通过劳作和节俭而获得的珍贵之物才会愈发显得珍贵。假使我们在公共图书馆上的花费能赶得上公共晚宴一半的开销的话，或是书籍的价格能赶得上手镯价格的十分之一的话，那么即便是愚蠢的男男女女们可能有时也会觉得读书确有裨益，就像大快朵颐和珠光宝气一样能给他们带来享受。正是由于文学的廉价使得那些哪怕是聪慧的人们也忘了，如果一本书值得读，就一定值得买。不值一读的书是没有什么价值的；同样，如果我们不对一本书一读再读、一爱再爱的话，它也是不会发挥作用的；而且要在书中做标记，只有如此，我们才能在需要的时候找到相关的章节，就像一个士兵能在军火库里找到他需要的武器，或是一个家庭主妇能在储藏间中拿到她所需的香料一样。面粉做成的面包固然不错；但是在一本好书里面，如果你想吃的话，也有甜如蜂蜜的面包；如果一个家庭买不起这种仅需一次付钱就可终生享用的大麦面包的话，那么它一定很穷。我们自诩是富有的国家，可我们却翻阅着彼此从流通图书馆借出来的书，这是多么龌龊和愚蠢的行为呀！

第二，我说过我们鄙视科学。“什么！”你们惊叫道，“我们不是在所有的探索发现方面都属一流吗[4]，难道全世界不都被我们的发明所具有的理性或非理性搞得晕头转向吗？”没错；不过你们觉得那是国家的作为吗？那些是凭借个人的热情和金钱完成的，而不是国家的作为。我们确实相当乐意从科学中获益；我们会迅速而急切地啃光所有在科学这根骨头上长出来的肉；但是当科学家向我们要一根骨头或是一块面包皮的时候，那就是另一回事儿了。我们公开地为科学做过什么事吗？为了船只航行的安全我们被迫需要了解什么是时间，于是我们花钱建造天文台；每年我们要在议会里不情愿地、费尽周折地，才会为大英博物馆做点什么事；闷闷不乐地认为那里不过是保存鸟类标本，逗孩子们开心的地方。如果有谁自己买了望远镜，辨别出了另一个星云，我们就会像母鸡一样咯咯地叫个没完，仿佛是我们自己下了蛋；如果一万个打猎的乡绅中有一个突然间发现，土地除了用来做猎杀狐狸的场所以外，原来也可以用来干别的事，而且他自己亲自挖洞，告诉我们哪儿有黄金，哪儿有煤炭，那么我们就会觉得他干了点儿有用的事儿，并且非常恰当地授予了他爵士的称号：然而仅凭这一位乡绅知道如何给自己找点正事干的偶然所为，就能让我们脸上有光吗？（如果考虑一下的话，那么其他乡绅对其所作所为的否定就不啻为在我们的脸上抹黑。）如果你还怀疑这些例子的普遍性的话，下面这个事例就值得我们全体去思考，因为它表明了我们对于科学的，所谓的热爱。两年前有一组产自索伦霍芬的化石标本要在巴伐利亚出售；这是一组现存最好的标本，其中有很多标本独一无二且保存完整，而且还有一个标本是某一物种存在过的唯一例证（那块化石代表了一个整个的、未知的生物王国）。这组化石，如果由私人购买的话，市场价值将可能达到一千或是一千二英镑，而卖给我们英国的价格是七百英镑；但这样的出价却遭到了我们的拒绝，要不是欧文教授不惜时间，忍受煎熬地亲自向议会说明情况，并且在当下要到了四百英镑后表示剩下的三百英镑由他个人负责筹集的话，整套化石此时此刻正躺在慕尼黑的博物馆里呢。尽管议员们最终毫无疑问会还给欧文教授三百英镑，可他们却为此极为恼怒，对此事一直不闻不问；只是在等着有什么研究成果出现的时候才会跳出来高谈阔论一番。我请求大家从数学的角度考虑一下这件事到底意味着什么。我们年度的公共支出（其中三分之一用于购买军需设备）至少是五千万英镑。现在是七百英镑对五千万英镑，也就是七便士对两千英镑的比例。大家假想一下，有这样一位绅士，他的收入无从知晓，但是我们可以从他每年花费两千英镑修葺花园的围墙和雇用仆人来推算出他的财富。他宣称自己热爱科学；某天一个仆人急切地跑过来告诉他，有一组独一无二的化石，能够提供新的生命纪元的线索，总共花七便士就可以得到它；然而，这位热爱科学的，每年花两千英镑装点花园的绅士，却在他的仆人苦等了几个月后回答说：“好吧！我先给你四便士，其余的三便士你自己先垫上，等到明年再还给你！”

第三，我说过你们鄙视艺术！“什么！”你们又要嚷了，“我们的艺术展览品不是有几英里长吗？我们不是买一幅画就花掉成千上万英镑吗？我们的艺术学校和机构不是比以前任何时候都多吗？”是的，没错，但是所有这些都是为了商业的目的。你们会欣然地卖掉一幅油画就像卖掉煤炭一样，卖掉瓷器就像卖掉钢铁一样；可能的话你们会从任何一个国家的嘴里抢夺面包；如果不行的话，你们的人生理想就像鲁德门的学徒一样站在世界的各个交通要道上，对着每一个过往的行人大喊，“你们要买点儿什么？”你们对自己的本领和周围的环境一无所知；在湿润的、平坦的和肥沃的粘土地上幻想着能够像在深褐色的葡萄藤包围中的法国人，或是在火山岩壁下站立着的意大利人一样拥有迅捷的艺术想象力；——幻想着艺术可以像记账一样一学就会，而学会后会有更多的账来记。你们对于绘画的关心程度远远逊于贴在冷冰冰的墙上的广告。墙上总会有张贴广告的地方，却从来没有给绘画作品留出空间。你们不知道自己的国家都有什么绘画作品（有声望的作品），也不知道它们的真伪，以及这些画作是不是保存良好。在其他国家，当你们看到世界上最高贵的绘画作品在被遗弃的废墟中腐烂时（例如，在威尼斯，奥地利人的枪炮就曾经故意瞄准藏有这些绘画的宫殿射击），你们表现得无动于衷；而且当你们听到所有欧洲的杰出画作明天都会被装进沙袋垒成奥地利人的碉堡时，你们所感到的烦恼比在一天的狩猎中错失了一两对猎物所带来的烦恼还要少。这就是你们国民对于艺术的热爱。

第四，你们鄙视自然；就是说鄙视所有自然风景所带来的深沉的、神圣的情感。法国的革命者们将法国的大教堂变成了马厩；而你们已经将地球上的大教堂变成了跑马场。你们对于快乐的理解就是坐着火车在大教堂的走廊里兜圈子，而且吃光它们祭坛上的贡品[5]。你们已经在沙夫豪森的瀑布上架设了铁路桥。你们已经在泰尔的礼拜堂边上的，卢塞恩的峭壁上开凿了隧洞；你们已经毁掉了日内瓦湖的克莱恩斯水岸；现在英国所有的寂静的山谷都让你们填满了爆破的火焰；没有哪一寸英国的土地没有被你们践踏上煤炭的灰烬[6]——没有哪个外国的城市，由于你们的到访，而没有在其古老而美丽的街道和快乐的花园当中留下如恶性麻风病所造成的，白色溃疡一样的新建旅馆和香水商店：就连过去你们自己的诗人所虔诚地热爱着的阿尔卑斯山，在你们看来也成了游乐场里的一根根抹了肥皂水的滑竿，你们爬上去再滑下来，“快乐地尖叫着”。尖叫过后，再也发不出什么人类的声音以表达快乐了，于是你们就在阿尔卑斯山寂静的山谷中放上几枪，然后跑回家。此时你们脸上泛出自负的红晕，一边夸夸其谈一边心满意足地打着饱嗝。就其深刻的内在意义而言，我认为有两幅丑态是我所见过的，人性中最为可悲的景象。其一就是英国的暴民们在夏蒙尼山谷发射锈迹斑斑的榴弹炮来自娱自乐；其二就是瑞士苏黎世的葡萄采摘者们对上天的恩赐表达感激的方式：他们三五成群地聚集在“葡萄园的塔楼”里，然后从早到晚，慢悠悠地拿着马枪装弹射击。对于责任的认识模糊不清是可悲的；然而更为可悲的是这种对于快乐的理解。

最后，你们鄙视同情心。我不需要多费唇舌，这一点不证自明。在这里我只是从报纸上选取一个剪下的段落（因为我有剪报的习惯，并且把剪下来的文章塞进抽屉里）；这篇文章来自今年（1865）早些时候的《晨报》；【……】它所讲述的这件事现在每天都会发生；只不过碰巧这件事是从一位验尸官的角度来交代的。我将以红色的字体把这一段刊印出来。请相信，这些事实就是用红色墨水写在一本书里的，我们所有的人，有文化的和没有文化的，总有一天都可以在这本书里读到属于我们的那一页。

“助理验尸官理查兹先生在斯皮特尔菲尔兹区的，基督教堂街的白马客栈，就现年五十八岁的迈克尔·柯林斯的死因进行了质询。证人玛丽·柯林斯，一个表情悲戚的妇女说，她与死者和他的儿子住在基督教堂街，柯布大院二号的一间屋内。死者是一位靴子‘翻修匠’。证人出门收购旧鞋；死者和他的儿子将旧鞋翻新，然后证人再把靴子卖掉，换取微薄的收入。死者和他的儿子常常夜以继日地工作，为的是能挣到钱买点儿面包和茶叶，并支付房租（每周两先令），以确保全家生活在一起。在上周五的晚上，死者从凳子上站起来开始哆嗦。他扔下靴子说，‘这双靴子在我死后要由别人完成了，我干不了了。’屋里没有生火，他接着说，‘要是能暖和点儿就好了。’证人于是拿了两双翻新好了的靴子到店里卖，但是两双靴子只能卖十四便士，店里的人说，‘我们必须有赚头。’证人买了十四便士的煤、一点茶叶和面包。他的儿子一宿没睡‘翻新’靴子挣钱，但死者还是在周六早晨离世了。这家人从来没吃饱过。——验尸官说：‘我觉得你们应该去救济院才对。’证人说：‘我们待在自己家里更舒服些。’一位陪审员问他们家里有什么能提供舒适的东西，因为他只在房间的角落里看到一点稻草，房间的窗户还是破的。证人开始哭了，并且说他们有一床被子和其他一些小东西。死者说过他绝不会去救济院。夏天的时候是旺季，他们有时一个星期能挣十先令。他们一般会把钱节省下来，因为下星期很有可能就挣不到这么多钱了。冬天的时候他们挣得还不到夏天的一半。这三年以来他们的境况越来越糟——科尼利厄斯·柯林斯说，他从1847年就开始帮助爸爸挣钱了。他们通常都工作到深夜，所以两个人都几乎累瞎了眼睛。证人的眼睛上蒙了一层薄翳。五年前死者曾向教区申请过救助。救助官员给了他一块四磅重的面包，然后告诉他，如果再来的话将会“得到石头”。[7]

死者对此颇为反感，从此再没有找过他们。这家人过得越来越差，直到上周五，他们甚至连半便士一根的蜡烛都买不起了。死者于是躺在稻草上，说自己活不过明天了。一位陪审员说：‘你们就快要饿死了，应当搬进救济院一直住到夏天。’证人说：‘如果搬进去我们会死掉的。因为夏天我们搬出来的时候就会像是从天而降一样。没有人认识我们，我们甚至连住的地方都没有。只要有吃的我就能工作，我的视力也会变好些。’G.P.沃克医生说死者是死于过度饥饿导致的晕厥。死者没有被褥。四个月以来除了面包他什么都没吃过。他的身体里面已经没有一丁点儿油水了。他没有病，但是如果之前接受过医药救治的话，他可能不会死于晕厥或昏厥。在验尸官对此令人痛心的事件作出评论后，陪审团得出以下结论：‘死者死于饥饿和生活必需品的缺乏所引起的精力衰竭；而且未得到有效的医疗救助。’”

你们会问：“为什么证人不去救济院呢？”是这样的，穷人们似乎对救济院有着富人们所没有的成见，因为那些从政府领取养老金的人大量地进入了救济院。只有富人的救济院才不会有救济的概念，对他们来说救济院应当叫作娱乐院。[8]穷人们似乎更愿意独立地去死；可能，如果我们把穷人的救济院建得足够漂亮舒适，或是干脆把救济金发放到穷人的家中去，并且拿出一小部分公共财政的支出补贴给他们的话，他们对于救济院的看法可能就会有所改变。同时，请注意下面的事实：我们的救济措施要么使得接受救助的人备感羞辱，要么让他们痛苦不堪，以至于他们宁死也不肯从我们手中接过救助；或是，还有第三种可能，就是我们听任穷人们不受教育、愚昧无知，以至于他们像野兽一样忍饥挨饿，疯狂而麻木，不知道该做什么，也不知道该要些什么。我说过你们鄙视同情心，不是吗？在一个基督教国家里根本就不应该出现那篇报道中所发生的事情，这同允许在大街上蓄意谋杀又有什么区别呢？“基督教。”我刚才说了。唉！即便我们是心智健康的非基督徒，这种事情也是不该发生的。恰恰是我们想象中的基督教帮助我们犯下了如此罪行；因为我们陶醉、沉溺于自己信仰中的低级的感官刺激；像所有其他的东西一样，在想象中将其扮靓。我们的基督教颇具戏剧效果，它有管风琴和教堂的侧廊，晨钟与暮鼓——在基督教里，我们常常采用绘画的方式，在有关撒旦题材的绘画中，比如罗伯特、浮士德的故事等，将对魔鬼的嘲笑与同魔鬼的嬉戏相结合；我们在花饰窗格所营造的背景气氛中唱诗，在变化多端的、模仿的祈祷声中艺术地改变“Dio”的发音：（而第二天当我们为了没文化的，满嘴脏话的人们的便利，为了践行第三条戒律的意义而散发小册子的时候，）这个我们引以为荣的，靠煤气点亮，靠煤气获得灵感的基督教，就会从对它提出异议的异教徒的接触中缩回其长袍的褶边。还是用清楚明白的英语和行动做点儿普通的基督徒应行的正义之事吧；还是将基督教的律法作为生活的准则，并且在此之上订立国家的法律或愿景吧——我们清楚地知道自己的信仰是为了什么！你们从焚香的烟雾中获得神启的速度可能比从现代英国宗教中获得的真实行动和热情来得更快，但是你们最好驱散烟雾，离开琴管：把它们，以及哥特式的窗户、彩绘的玻璃等统统留给道具管理员；你们要在健康的呼气中排出甲烷气体的幽灵，并且照看一下倒在你们台阶下的，像得了麻风病的乞丐拉撒路一样的穷人们。只有人人伸出帮助之手的教会才是真正的教会，才是唯一神圣的、母性的教会。它过去是如此，将来也不会改变。

所有这些喜好，所有这些美德，我重复一遍，你们，在国家的层面上，都加以鄙视。没错，你们当中有人确非如此；正是凭借着他们的工作，他们的力量，他们的生命，他们的死亡，你们才得以生存，然而你们却从未对他们表达感谢。如若不是那些你们轻蔑或是忘记了的人们，你们是不可能拥有财富、快乐和骄傲的。警察们整夜在黑暗的小巷里来回巡视，监视你们在那儿犯下的罪行；他们随时都有可能肝脑涂地，或是落下终生的残疾，然而却从未接受过感谢；水手们与大海的怒涛搏击；安静的学生们对着他们的书籍或是药水瓶苦思冥想；普通工人们，在没有荣誉，甚至没有面包的境况下，在你们乘着马车，漫无目的地闲逛，一骑绝尘的时候，履行着他们的职责：英国是靠这些人生存的；但是他们并不是国家的全部；他们只不过是它的躯体和神经组织，本能而机械地作出反应，而真正的头脑却缺失了。我们的国家愿景和目标仅仅是寻欢作乐；我们的国家宗教不过是教会仪式的表演和对让人昏昏欲睡的真理（或伪真理）的宣教，这样做是为了让暴民们能够安静地工作，而我们可以继续寻欢作乐；就如同伴随热病出现的焦干的喉咙和恍惚的眼神一样，这种享乐的必要性正在紧紧地同我们绑在一起——它毫无意识、毫无节制，并且残忍至极。疾病这个词（英文：disease=dis+ease）多么形象地表达出了我们英国式的勤奋和享乐方式的全部道德状态呀！

当人们忙于正经事的时候，他们的快乐便来自工作，这就像绚丽的花瓣出自结出硕果的花朵——当人们忠实地为他人提供帮助并且献出爱心的时候，他们所有的情感就会变得平和、深沉、持久而生机勃勃，就像人身体的自然脉动一样。现在，由于我们没有什么真正的事业，所以便将全部的力气投入到了错误的赚钱行当中去；由于我们没有什么真正的情感，便将虚情假意装扮起来加以玩弄。我们如此做法不是像孩子那样摆弄玩偶，出于天真无邪，而是像偶像崇拜的犹太人一样，罪恶地、秘密地将图画挂于墙上的洞穴之中，必须挖掘才能探明。我们不行正义之事，却在小说中和舞台上假装正义；我们摧毁掉自然界中的美丽，然后在哑剧中以魔幻的形变取而代之；而且（我们的人性当中迫切地需要某种形式的敬畏和悲伤）对于我们同伴所应当抱有的高尚的同情心，应当同他们一起洒下的纯净的泪水，已经让我们变换成了治安法庭上对于不幸遭遇的幸灾乐祸，和靠收集坟墓上的夜露聊以自乐。

对这些事情的真正意义进行估量是困难的；这些事实足够骇人听闻；然而国家在这些事情方面所犯的错误可能并不像起初看上去那样严重。我们每天允许或是引起数以千计的人死亡，但是我们并无恶意；我们纵火烧了房子，毁掉了农民的田地，然而如果我们发现有谁受到了伤害，我们也会抱有歉意。我们的内心仍然善良，仍然有美德，只不过同孩子们的善良和美德差不多。查莫斯曾经拥有很大的公权力，曾被某个有关“公众舆论”的严重事件搞得焦头烂额。在其漫长生命临终之时，他发出了不耐烦的慨叹，“公众不过是一个体型巨大的婴儿！”我之所以会将所有这些更为严肃的，有关思想方面的问题同对于读书方法的探讨相联系，是因为我看到的，我们国家的过失和痛苦越多，就越明白这些过失和痛苦其实是源自我们像孩子一样的无知状态，以及在最为普通的思考习惯方面的教育的缺失。它不是，我重复一下，我们应当哀悼的恶行、自私或是头脑的愚钝；而是一种我们看不到摸不着的，学童式的莽撞，与真正学童的区别仅仅是在于它不接受老师的教诲。

在距离我们最近的一位伟大画家的作品中，有这样一幅可爱的，但被人们忽视了的画作，它当中描绘了这样一种有好奇心的人。这幅画画的是位于柯克比·朗斯代尔的教堂墓地，包括那里的小溪、山谷、丘陵及远处层层叠叠的早晨的天空。一群学童不顾及这里的风景也不考虑长眠于此的死者，将他们的书本码放在一座坟丘上面，然后用石头将它们打倒。同样，我们也在与能使我们受到教育的、逝去者的文字戏耍，并且充满敌意地、草率地将它们拒于千里之外；而不去想，那些被风吹散的书页其实不仅仅是堆积在了坟头，更是堆积在了被施了魔法的墓穴的封印之上——而且，这里就是通往熟睡着的，国王们的，伟大城市的大门；如果我们能叫出他们的名讳，这些国王们将会苏醒并与我们同行。经常有这样的情况，就是我们虽然开启了大理石的墓门，却只能够在那些睡梦中的老国王们中间游荡，用手摸一摸他们的长袍，碰一碰他们额头上戴的皇冠；然而他们却一言不发，像是落满了灰尘的雕塑；这是因为我们不知道能够将他们唤醒的心灵的咒语——他们一旦听到这一咒语，就会带着自己过去曾有的权威起身与我们相见，仔细地端详我们，对我们作出判断；并且，就像堕入冥界的国王们接见新来者一样，说：“你也如我们一样归西了吗——也成为我们中的一员了吗？”于是这些国王们便戴着闪闪发光的、纹丝不动的王冠接见我们，说：“你也同我们一样有一颗纯净和强大的心灵了吗———你也成为我们中的一员了吗？”

强大的心灵，强大的思想——“宽宏大量”——能做到这一点，在生活中就是伟大的；朝这个方向努力，就是真正的“在生活中进步”——是生活自身的进步，而非生活的外在表现。朋友们，你们还记得那个古老的塞西亚人的风俗吗？当他们的一家之主离世的时候，人们会给他穿上最漂亮的衣服，让他坐上四轮马车，然后把他送到朋友们的家里；接下来朋友们会把他安置在桌子的上首，然后当着他的面大吃大喝。假定有人以简明的话语告诉你说，当你还活着的时候，就会缓慢地获得塞西亚人的荣誉，并且将来一定会享受到此种可怕的待遇。具体的提议是这样的：你将慢慢死去；你的血液将会日渐冷却，你的身体变得僵硬，你的心脏会像一组生了锈的铁阀门一样慢慢停止搏动。你的活力将会离你远去，透过地表沉入冰川；但是，一天天地，你的身体将会被装扮得越发喜庆，装进更高级的马车，胸口上别了更多的勋章，头上戴了更多的王冠，只要你乐意的话。人们会在你面前鞠躬，在你周围凝视叫喊，簇拥着你在街上走来走去；为你营建宫殿，将你置于餐桌的上首，彻夜地与你宴饮；你的灵魂会稍作停留，从而知道他们都做了什么，感觉到肩膀上所披的金色外衣的分量，以及颅骨上被所戴王冠勒出的皱纹——就是这些了。你会接受死亡天使这一口头的提议吗？你认为，我们中的，哪怕是最为卑微的人会接受吗？然而我们每个人，在某种程度上，确实想得到这些；我们中的很多人，甚至会全盘接受这一恐怖的提议。每一个接受它的人都渴望在生活中进步，然而却不知道生活是什么；他们光想着得到更多的马匹、更多的仆人、更多的财产、更多的公众荣誉等，而不是更高尚的个人灵魂。只有心灵变得更为柔软，血液变得更为温暖，头脑变得更为灵活，精神正在进入充满生机的和平当中去的人，才称得上在生活中取得了进步。只有那些如此生活着的人们才是这世上真正的贵族或国王——他们，只有他们才是。其他所有的君主国家，即便是真的有国王，他们也不过是继承王位后的实际结果而已。如果更差一点的话，他们要么是招摇过市的王公贵族——到处炫富，浑身珠光宝气——但仍然不过是国家的玩偶；要么他们根本就不是王族成员，而是暴君，或仅仅是国家愚昧的，现实和生动的体现。正因为如此，我才在别的场合对君主政体说过这样的话：“看得到的政府是某些国家的玩具，另一些国家的疾病，一些国家的羁绊，更多国家的累赘。”

当听到在有思想的人们当中仍然有人提及王权的说法，为此我极为震惊，不知道该说什么好。他们的意思似乎是在说，国家是私人的财产，可以买卖，或是像绵羊一样可以获取———用绵羊的肉喂国王，它们的毛也归国王所有；似乎阿基里斯怒斥卑劣的国王时所说的“吃人”可以作为所有君主的，不变的和恰当的绰号；而且扩大国王的领土就如同增加个人的土地财产一样无可厚非！不管多么强有力的国王，只要有如此想法他就不再是一个国家的真正君主了，正如牛虻不可能成为一匹马的领袖一样；它们吸马儿的血，可能会使它发疯，却不能驾驭它。他们，他们的朝廷和他们的军队，如果你擦亮眼睛就能看得到，不过是夏日里一群沼泽地里的大蚊子，擎着刺刀一般的吸管，吹着乐队一般的号角；尽管成群结队的蚊虫在暮色中如闪光的薄雾一般看上去很漂亮，却不见得有益健康。而与此同时，真正的国王们，即便是真在统治，也会很低调，并且痛恨统治；他们中的很多人会作出“拒绝称帝”的决定；如果不是这样的话，一旦那些暴民觉得情势有机可乘，便会毫不犹豫地取而代之，成为“伟大的帝王”。

如果有一天，现实中的国王对自己统治的评估不是看他国家的地理边界，而是看他统治的力量的话，那么他就可能成为真正的君主。特伦特河在这儿割去一块角地，或是莱茵河在那儿圈走一处城堡，这些都是无关紧要的事。作为君主，你能否肯定地对一个人说“去”他就去了；而对另外一个人说“来”他就来了，这才是至关重要的。你能否指挥你的臣民就像指挥特伦特河一样——能够命令他们何去何从，这才是最重要的。作为君主，你的臣民是恨你，因你而死，还是爱你，为你而生，这才是最重要的。你可以依靠民众的数量而不是英里数来丈量你的疆域；你可以用计算纬度的办法计算一下受民众爱戴的程度，看一看它距离异常温暖和无垠的赤道有多近，而不是离开它有多远。

计算一下吧！——不，你算不出来。有谁能够算出来下面两种权力的区别呢？一种权力属于那些“既亲为又亲授”的人们，他们无论在人间还是在天堂的王国里都是最伟大的人物；另一种权力属于那些只知道破坏和消耗的人们，他们的权力不过是相当于飞蛾和铁锈的作用。怪哉！请想一想，飞蛾的国王们为飞蛾积累财宝；铁锈的国王们，他们锈蚀人民的力量就如同铁锈之于盔甲，为铁锈积累财宝；强盗的国王们为强盗积累财宝；然而，又有几位国王曾经积累过无须守卫的财宝——甚至盼望着光顾它们的盗贼越多越好呢？绣花的长袍早晚要撕裂；头盔和宝剑定会黯然失色；宝石和黄金迟早要散尽——然而有三种国王一直在收集这些东西。假如有第四种国王，他曾经从古代晦涩难懂的著作中得知，这世上还有第四种财宝。这种财宝，黄金和宝石不可与其匹敌，以纯金对其加以度量亦不可行——它是一张漂亮的，用雅典娜的梭子织就的罗网；一副在神火中，由伍尔坎倾力打造的盔甲；一块从太阳的红心中开采出来，放置在神谕的悬崖上的黄金——它是绣有神秘绘画的薄纱，不可刺穿的甲胄，和可供饮用的黄金！有三位伟大的天使：行动、辛劳和思考的天使，在向我们召唤，在我们门前的立柱旁等待，用她们长有羽翼的力量带领我们，用她们如炬的慧眼指引我们，走上一条无人知晓的、贪婪的秃鹫没办法看到的路径。想象一下吧，我们难道不是需要这样一位，听信了这些话语，而且最终为他的人民收集到并且奉献出了这第四种财宝——智慧，的国王吗？

想一想，那该会是一项多么了不起的事业呀！以我们当下的民族智慧，这将是多么的不可思议呀！我们应当将农民们调动起来读书而不是练习刺杀！——发给他们薪资，以具备优秀的领导才能的思想家的团队，而不是刺杀者的团队，对他们进行组织、训练，并且持之以恒。我们不但要在射击场上还要在阅览室里娱乐民众；我们不但要对铅弹击中标靶进行奖励还要对发现真理予以表彰。说白了，我们要将文明国度中，资本家的财富用来支持文学而不是战争，这在某些人看来，是多么荒诞不经的想法呀！

请大家少安毋躁。下面我给大家从我自己写的一本书里面读几句话。这本书是我写的唯一一本可以称得上是书的书。我想，在我所有的作品中，它是最确定无疑的具有恒久价值的（如果确有价值的话）一本。

“在欧洲，财富在以一种极为可怕的形式运作着，这就是，资本家的全部财富都用来支持非正义的战争。正义的战争并不需要如此多的钱财来支持；因为大多数参与正义战争的人们是不要酬劳的；但是对于非正义的战争，人们的身体和灵魂都需要靠金钱来购买；此外，他们在这样的战争中会使用最好的武器，这也使得此类战争的花费高昂到极点；这还没有把国家间卑鄙的恐惧和愤怒的猜忌所造成的损失算在内，这些国家缺乏使得它们的民众获得哪怕是一个小时的心灵的平和所需的仁慈或是诚实；就像现在，法国和英国每年都彼此购买大约价值一千万英镑的恐惧（这是一种相当低产的作物，一半是荆棘一半是山杨树叶；它依靠教唆贪婪而不是传授真理的，现代政治经济学家所谓的‘科学’来播种、收割和储存）。而且，所有接受援助的非正义的战争，要么是靠从敌方掠夺财富，要么就是靠从资本家那里获得贷款。这些贷款会通过随后的，对人民的征税获得偿付，而人民似乎并不能左右事态的发展，只有意志坚定的资本家才是战争的始作俑者；但是，引发战争的真正根源是整个国家的贪婪，这使得它丧失信仰、真诚及公正，于是，早晚有一天，会给自己国家的每个人都带来惩罚和灾难。”

请注意，实际上，法国和英国是在购买彼此的恐慌；这两个国家每年都会购买价值一千万英镑的恐惧。可以试想一下，如果它们不是每年花一千万英镑购买恐慌，而是下定决心和平共处，每年购买价值一千万英镑的知识，每个国家，每年都把这一千万英镑花在兴建皇家图书馆、皇家艺术品展览馆、皇家博物馆、皇家公园，以及其他休闲场所上的话，那么这样一来，对于英法双方不是都有好处吗？

要看到这一局面还有待时日。我希望在不久的将来，皇家或是国家图书馆就可以在每一个较大的城市兴建，其中要收藏皇家系列的图书；每一个图书馆都要有同一系列的图书，它们是每一种类中最好的、精选的图书，以尽可能完美的方式为建立一套全国系列的图书作准备；这些图书的正文要印刷在大小一样的纸张上，要留出足够宽的空白页边，并且要将书籍分成若干合理的卷册，手感轻盈，装帧也需极尽精美牢固；而且这些图书馆要一天到晚随时开放，允许所有干净利落的人进入；要实行严格的规章以保证这种清洁和宁静。

我可以为你们制订出其他的规划来，比如说对于艺术展览馆、自然历史博物馆，以及很多其他珍贵的，我认为是必需的场馆的规划；但是，我们对于图书馆的规划是最容易办到，同时也是最为迫切的，而且这一规划将为我们所谓的英国体质提供重要的滋补——它最近浑身浮肿，呈现出病态的干渴和饥饿，急需更健康的饮食。你们已经废除了不列颠的《谷物法》；可否尝试一下确立新的谷物法，以便购入更好的面包——那种施了魔法的，由古老的阿拉伯谷物——芝麻，所做成的面包，因为那芝麻能够打开大门——不是强盗的大门，而是国王宝藏的大门。

交易

在布拉德福市政厅的演说

【1864年4月21日】

约克郡的朋友们，你们邀请我到这山里来，是为了让我就你们将要建立的交易所谈谈自己的看法，但是，我认真地、严肃地请求你们的谅解，因为我不会讲有关交易所的事。我对这一话题一无所知或是知之甚少。尽管不是有意为之，我还是会谈一谈其他的事情；你们邀请我来谈一个话题，而我却自作主张地谈另外一个话题，所以我不配得到你们的原谅。因为讲自己不感兴趣的题目是不会达到预期效果的，所以一开始，我就不得不直白地和遗憾地告诉各位，我对你们的交易所不感兴趣。

如果当初我接到你们发给我的邀请函时这样回复，“我不来，我对布拉德福的交易所不感兴趣”的话，你们一定会生我的气，因为你们并不了解我如此生硬而冷漠地拒绝邀请到底是为了什么。因此，我来了，希望你们能耐心地让我解释一下为什么。以前，在这样的及很多类似的场合，我会抓住机会向和蔼可亲的听众发表演讲，而现在却总是默不作声。

总之，我对交易所不感兴趣——因为你们不感兴趣；而且因为你们清楚地知道我不可能让你们感兴趣。请看一看整件事情的基本情况吧，尽管你们可能认为我忘了，可是你们作为商人却知道得一清二楚。你们将要花费三万英镑建造交易所，这对于你们来说无足轻重；购买一件新外套，就其花费而言，对于我来说的重视程度，都要远远高于你们对于新建一座交易所的重视程度，但是你们还是想让自己的钱花得其所。你们知道建筑可以有多种古怪的样式；你们不想因此成为别人的笑柄；你们听说，除了别的以外，我还是一位有声望的建筑学上的帽商；于是你们邀请我来，想让我讲一讲当下的潮流；以及，什么是当下，我们商店里最新、最受欢迎的建筑尖顶的式样。

好吧，请恕我直言，仅仅靠听取别人就某一个案发表的建议就能拥有好的建筑是不可能的。所有好的建筑都是民族生活和性格的体现，它产生于普遍和热切的民族品味或是对于美的追求。我想让各位想一想这里“品味”这个词的意义；因为我关于好的品味根本上来说就是一种道德品质的说法，是最饱受人们争议的话题。“错，”很多反对我的人说，“品味是一回事，道德是另一回事。告诉我们什么是漂亮，我们愿闻其详；但是请不要让我们听你的说教——即便是你会说教，其中的道理也未必对。”

因此，请允许我，对我的这一旧的信条加以说明。品味不仅仅是道德的一部分或是它的表征——它是道德的全部。对于任何活着的人来说，如果要了解他的品位，首要、最终和最贴近的提问就是，“你喜欢什么？”告诉我你喜欢什么，我就会知道你是什么样的人。走到街上去，问一问你第一个见到的男人或女人，他们的“品味”是什么；如果他们直率地回答了你的问题，你就可以彻底地了解他们。“你，我衣衫褴褛、步履蹒跚的朋友，你喜欢什么？”“一个烟斗和四分之一品脱的杜松子酒。”我了解你了。“你，可爱的，步履轻盈、头戴利落软帽的女士，你喜欢什么？”“整洁的壁炉，干净的茶几，对面坐着我的丈夫，怀里抱着我的婴儿。”好，我也了解你了。“你，头发金黄、目光温柔的小女孩儿，你喜欢什么？”“我的金丝雀，还有在长满风信子的树林里奔跑。”“你，两手脏兮兮的、低着额头的小男孩儿，你喜欢什么？”“用石头打麻雀，扔铜钱的游戏。”好了，我对他们都了解了。我们还有什么要问的吗？

“不，”可能你会回答，“我们还不如问一问这些人都干了些什么，而不是他们都喜欢什么。如果他们行为端正的话，那么他们即使是喜欢错误的东西也不要紧；如果他们行为不端的话，那么他们即使是喜欢好的东西也于事无补。行动最重要；如果一个人不喝酒，那么他喜欢喝酒也没有关系；同样，一个小女孩儿不好好学习，那么她对金丝雀再好也没用；如果一个小男孩儿去上主日学校，那么他喜欢用石头扔麻雀也没什么大不了的。”的确，在短时间内，暂时看来，这样说是对的。如果人们下定决心做正确的事，那么他们最终就会喜欢上做这件事，但是只有当他们已经喜欢上做这件事的时候，才会处于一种正确的道德状态；而一旦他们不喜欢这事而去做它，就会处于一种不道德的状态。如果某人总是想着壁橱里的酒瓶子，那么他的身体就是不健康的，尽管他奋力地抑制着自己的渴望；相反，如果某人真心地喜欢早晨喝水，晚上喝酒，而且每一样都在喝的时间和数量上恰到好处，那么他就是健康的。真正教育的全部目标就是不仅仅让人们做正确的事，还要喜欢做正确的事——不仅仅勤劳，还要热爱劳动——不仅仅博学，还要热爱知识——不仅仅纯洁，还要热爱纯净——不仅仅公道，还要追逐、渴望着正义。

你们可能会问：“对于，诸如绘画、雕塑、家具、建筑等的外部装饰的喜爱也是一种道德品质吗？”是的，毫无疑问，如果这是一种健康而固定的喜爱的话。只有对好的绘画或是雕塑的品位才称得上是一种道德品质，而不包括对于所有绘画和雕塑的品位。这里我们不得不再一次定义“好”这个词。我所谓的“好”并不是指聪明，或是博学，或是完成的难度大。比如说，坦尼尔斯画了一幅酒鬼们在赌桌上争吵的场面的画；这就是一幅很聪明的画，在此类题材的绘画中无出其右者；但是这仍旧是一幅非常低级和邪恶的画作。因为这幅画表达的是一种对于道德败坏的事物，进行长时间的苦思冥想所带来的快乐，而这种快乐具有一种“粗野的”或“不道德的”品质。从深层次的角度看，这是一种“坏品位”——是对于魔鬼的品位。而另一方面，比如说，一幅提香的画，或是一尊希腊的雕塑，或是一枚希腊的钱币，或是一张特纳的风景画等，传达的则是一种对于好的和完美的事物，进行长时间的苦思冥想所带来的快乐。这是一种完全高尚的道德品质——是对于天使的品位。所有艺术所带来的快乐，所有对于艺术的热爱，都会转变成对于那些配得上爱的事物的单纯的爱。这种“配得上”是一种我们称作“可爱”（loveliness）的品质——我们应当发明一个反义词，可恨（hateliness），来指那些应当受到痛恨的事物；我们选择爱这或是爱那，并不是什么无关痛痒、可有可无的事情；而是一种决定了我们所有本质的关键因素。我们喜欢什么决定了我们是什么样的人，也标志着我们是什么样的人；传授其品味就不可避免地要形成其性格。

有一天我在舰队街走过，心里正想着这个事儿的时候，突然看到书店橱窗里展出的一本书。书名是这样的——《论在社会各阶级中传播品味的必要性》。“天哪，”我心想，“这位探讨社会阶级问题的朋友，如果你已经将品味传播开了，那么哪来的社会各阶级呢？我认为，爱你所爱的人一定跟你同属一个阶级。这一点毋庸置疑。如果你愿意的话，可以让他转行干其他的工作；但是，由于置身其中的环境发生了变化，他会和你一样厌恶这个工作。你可能发现一位拾荒者或是小商贩喜欢读《新兴门监狱日志》，而且喜欢听‘啪！黄鼠狼走开了’这首儿歌，但是，你能让他喜欢读但丁的诗歌并且聆听贝多芬的交响乐吗？但愿你乐意对他进行教导；如果你真的成功了，那么他就会变成一位绅士，而且再也不会重操旧业，回到街上去叫卖了。”

如果今晚我有时间的话，我会证明给你们看，一个民族受到邪恶或虚弱影响的话，就一定会明白而永恒地通过糟糕的艺术或艺术的缺乏表现出来；一个民族的美德，无论大小，都会通过拥有这美德的人们创造的所有艺术彰显出来。这里，我就以你们英国人持久和耐心的勇气这一美德为例，作一说明。在当今的英国只有一种艺术与之有关——这就是炼铁。你们都很了解如何浇铸和锻造铁器。那么，在你们生起的烈焰所熔化的矿石中，在你们建造的熔炉边所锻造的铁块中，在那些铁板之上，你们的勇气和忍耐不是被永远地写就了吗？这种美德不单单是用钢笔写就，而且是镌刻在铁卷之上。再举一个有关罪恶的例子——嫉妒的罪恶。这一罪恶不但属于英国，欧洲，全世界，而且属于所有在宇宙苍穹中，带着地狱的气息转动发光的大千世界。嫉妒心将竞争带进商业，将背叛带进议会，将无耻带进战争——是它让你们身披铠甲，利剑出鞘；是它使得你们和你们的邻国丧失了赖以生存的基础；是它，到了最后，使得你们两个伟大民族的人民大众——他们自诩是世界文明的先锋，身体力行地、机关算尽地实现了，切维厄特丘陵地区野蛮的边境骑兵曾经做过的事——

“他们用钢铁的手套

切开肉片

通过头盔的裂缝饮尽鲜血；”——

难道这种民族的羞耻和心灵的卑鄙不是清清楚楚地写在你们的盔甲上，恰恰是自己右手亲自打造的，每一颗铆钉上的吗？

朋友们，我不知道这事是应当被视为更可笑还是更悲哀，抑或是既可笑又悲哀。假如，不是各位邀请我，而是某位绅士以个人的名义邀请我。这位绅士家住在郊区的一幢房子里，他的庭院与邻居的庭院仅以一排果树的围墙隔开；他邀请我来是为了向我咨询一下如何布置他的客厅。我环视四周，发现屋里的墙面上缺少装饰；我想如果贴上这样或是那样的壁纸可能比较合适——天花板上这里或是那里可能需要一点湿壁画——窗户上需要挂上锦缎的窗帘或是什么类似的东西。“啊，”我的雇主说道，“锦缎的窗帘，没错！这真是太好了，不过你知道现在我还买不起这类的东西！”“可是你的收入相当高呀！”“嗯，是的，”我的朋友说道，“但是你知道吗，现在我几乎把所有的收入都花在买捕兽夹上了。”“捕兽夹！捕谁呀？”“哎呀，当然是墙那边的那个家伙啦；我们是非常好的朋友，最重要的朋友；但是我们不得不把捕兽夹放在墙的两侧；没有这些捕兽夹和弹簧枪我们是不可能友好相处的。最糟糕的是，我们都是聪明人；每天我们都会发现对方布置了新的夹子或是炮管儿之类的东西；总共算起来，我们每年都要花一千五百万英镑买夹子；而且我不知道怎样才能把这一数目削减下来。”对于两位绅士来说这是多么滑稽的生活状态呀！但是对于两个国家来说，这就不光是滑稽的问题了。如果疯人院里只住了一个疯子，那是很滑稽的；如果你们圣诞节的哑剧里只有一个小丑，那也是滑稽的；但是如果整个世界的人都变成了小丑，用自己的鲜血而不是朱砂将身体染红，那可就不是什么滑稽的事儿了。

请注意，我知道很多这种事情都是在做游戏，并且是出于自愿。你们不知道怎样做才能让自己激动万分：猎狐和打板球并不能伴随你度过这漫漫人生。当你们还是学童的时候，你们就喜欢玩玩具枪，而来复枪和安氏炮不过是比玩具枪制作得更精良而已：但最糟糕的是，你们儿时的游戏，对于麻雀来讲可不是游戏；你们现在的游戏，对于小鸟一般的弱国来说也不是游戏；而对于那些黑鹰，如果我没说错的话，你们是不大敢向它们开火的。

我必须回到演讲的主题。请相信我，无须更多的例证，自始至终，每一个国家的罪恶或是美德都书写在其艺术之中了：早期希腊的军事才能；晚期意大利的淫荡；托斯卡纳的预言宗教；威尼斯光辉灿烂的人性力量，如此等等。今晚我没有时间对此一一加以论述（以前我曾经在别处论及此事）；但是我会以一种更为认真的态度将这一原则应用到我们自身。

我注意到，在所有建在曾经的荒山上的新建筑中，大部分的教堂与学校是同工厂和住宅混建在一起的；而且我注意到，教堂和学校的建筑大都是哥特式的，而住宅和工厂则一概不是哥特式的。请允许我问一下，这到底是为什么呢？因为，请记住，这是一种当代才有的现象。哥特式建筑发明之初，不单单教堂是哥特式的，民房也是如此；在意大利风格取代了哥特式风格之后，教堂和民房又都变成了意大利式的。如果安特卫普大教堂有一座尖顶，那么布鲁塞尔的市政厅就一定有一座钟楼；如果伊尼戈·琼斯建了一座意大利风格的白厅，那么克里斯托弗·霍恩爵士就一定要建一座意大利风格的圣保罗大教堂，但是现在，你们在一种建筑风格的房子里面生活却在另外一种建筑风格的教堂里祈祷。你们这样做是为了什么呢？我是不是可以理解为，你们想要将建筑的风格变回哥特式的，所以就拿教堂作实验，因为在教堂建筑方面出了错无关紧要呢？或是说，我是不是可以这样理解，你们认为哥特式是一种极端神圣和美丽的建筑风格，所以就像上等的乳香只能与圣体盒一起使用一样，哥特式的建筑风格也只能服务于你们的宗教仪式？如果你们确实是这样想的，尽管这初听起来似乎很得体、很虔诚，然而你们会发现，说到底，这件事恰好说明了你们将自己的生活同宗教分割开来。

想一想吧，这个事实有着多么广泛的意义；要记住，不仅仅是你们，现如今所有的英国人都是如此行事。

你们都已经习惯了把教堂叫作“上帝的房子”。我见过，在很多教堂门口的上方都雕刻着这样的铭文：“这里是上帝的居所而且是天堂之门。”那么，请留意一下，这句铭文是从哪儿来的，是在什么地方第一次说起的。曾经有个男孩儿离开家，步行了很长的路去拜访他的叔叔：他必须穿过一座渺无人烟的荒山；这就像你们自己的孩子去拜访他家住卡莱尔的叔叔时，不得不穿越一片荒野一样。第二或是第三天，你们的孩子走到了位于霍斯和布拉夫之间的某个地方，在黄昏时分走到了沼泽地中间。地上多是石块和泥沼；那天晚上他一步也走不动了，于是他便在沃恩赛德山躺下来睡觉，在那儿他最多能找到几块石头垫在头下——这地方太荒凉了，除了石头以外什么都没有。就在那儿，在辽阔夜空的笼罩下，他这样躺着，做了一个梦；梦里他看见地上矗立起一把梯子一直伸向天空，天使们通过梯子上下往来。从梦中醒来后，他说道，“这个地方多么可怕呀；不过，这里就是上帝的房子，这里就是天堂的大门。”这个地方，注意；不是这个教堂；不是这座城市；甚至不是这块他留作纪念的石头——他曾经枕着睡觉的那块打火石。但是，是这个地方；这个狂风肆虐的沃恩赛德山坡；这块坑洼的，流水侵蚀、飞雪拍打的高山沼泽地；任何一个上帝放下梯子的地方！你们怎样才能知道这地方会是在哪儿呢？或者说，尽管你们已经随时待命出发，你们怎样才能确定它的位置呢？你们知道下一次的闪电会落在哪儿吗？你们确实部分地知道；因为你们能够引导闪电；但是你们对于圣灵的降临却无从引导，它就如同那闪电一样从东方划向西方。

长久以来，人们一直对于这句有力的铭文进行傲慢的曲解，认为它仅仅是指教堂所发挥的作用。其实，这只不过是我们退化到粗俗的犹太教教义之中的、不可胜数的例证之一。我们管教堂叫作“庙宇”，可是，你们清楚地知道它们并不是庙宇。它们从来没有，也永远不会有什么与庙宇有关的东西。它们是“会堂”——“聚会的地方”——你们大家聚集在一起的地方；如果你们不这样称呼它，就会再次误解另一处强有力的经文——“你，当你祈祷的时候，不要像那些伪君子一样；因为他们喜欢在教堂里祈祷”“他们在众目睽睽下祈祷。但是你，当你祈祷的时候，要进入密室，关上门，向你的圣父祷告，”——就是说，不是在教堂的圣坛或是侧廊里，而是“秘密地”祷告。

现在，你们感到，我在跟你们说这些话的时候——我知道你们会感到——好像我企图要剥夺你们教堂的荣誉。其实并非如此；我是想向你们表明，你们的住房和你们的群山一样拥有荣誉；这并不是说教堂不神圣——而是说整个世界都是神圣的。我想要你们感到，在各种各样的思想中隐藏了多么草率、多么固执、多么具有传染性的罪孽。受这些思想的影响，你们将教堂称作唯一的“圣地”，而将你们的家园称为“渎神之所”；而且，为了将自己同异教徒区分开来，你们便将家中的诸神扔到地上，却不是在诸多虚弱的家庭守护神当中，确认你们全能的上帝为自己唯一的家庭守护神。

“但是所有这一切与我们的交易所又有什么关系呢？”你们会不耐烦地问我。亲爱的朋友，这与交易所有着千丝万缕的联系；因为要解决外在的和细小的问题，首先就要解决内在的和巨大的问题；如果你们是因为对我曾经写过的东西感兴趣而邀请我来这里演讲的话，那么你们就一定知道，我对于建筑的论述都是为了说明这一点。我的那本，我称之为《七盏明灯》的书，就是要证明某些正确的情绪状态和道德感受是所有好的建筑建造出来，无一例外所依靠的魔力。《威尼斯的石头》那本书从始至终只有一个目的，就是要证明威尼斯的哥特式建筑出现于，并且其所有的特点都表明了，一种纯净的民族信仰和家庭美德；而威尼斯文艺复兴时期的建筑则出现于，并且其所有特点都表明了，一种隐藏的民族的背信和家庭的堕落。现在，你们问我使用什么风格建造交易所最好，我怎么回答呢，我知道有两种建筑的风格，但是我要问问你们——你们是想作为基督徒还是想作为异教徒兴建交易所呢？进一步来讲——你们是想作为诚实的基督徒还是诚实的异教徒兴建呢？你们能彻底地、毫不掩饰地告诉我是前者还是后者吗？你们不喜欢被问及如此无礼的问题，但是我不得不问；因为这些问题比建交易所本身还要重要得多；而且，如果这些问题马上就能得到回答的话，建交易所的事立刻就可以敲定了。但是，在我继续追问之前，我必须请求你们允许我阐明一点。

在过去的著作中，我一直致力于证明，好的建筑，从根本上来说，是具有宗教精神的——是虔信和美德的产物，而与异教徒和堕落的人们无关，但是在这一论述过程当中，我不得不同时证明，好的建筑并不是教会的建筑。人们认为宗教只是神职人员的事而与自己无关，所以一听到有什么与“宗教”有关的事，就立刻想到这一定要靠教士完成；因此我不得不采取一种介于两种错误观点之间的立场，以看上去似乎有些自相矛盾的方式与它们对抗。好的建筑是善良和虔信的人们的作品；因此，你们说，至少有些人会说：“好的建筑从根本上来讲，一定是僧侣的作品，而非俗人的创造。”错了——彻底错了；好的建筑一直以来都是出自平民百姓，而非教会人士。“什么，”你们会说，“那些光辉绚烂的大教堂——欧洲的骄傲——难道不是它们的建造者们创造了哥特式建筑吗？”非也；相反，正是他们破坏了哥特式建筑。哥特式建筑形成于贵族的城堡和市民的街道。它是由勤劳的公民和尚武的国王们，以其思想、双手和权力打造的。而在僧侣们的手里，哥特式建筑成了帮助他们宣扬迷信的工具：当迷信演变成为一种美丽的疯狂，当欧洲的精英们在修道院里日渐憔悴、美梦破灭，暴跳如雷却在圣战中一败涂地的时候——通过这种邪恶信仰产生的暴怒和徒劳的战争，哥特式建筑进入到了它最为美丽，最为怪诞，而最终最为愚蠢的梦境；并且在那些梦境中迷失了自我。

现在，我希望，当我要谈及今晚的核心思想的时候，你们不至于对我产生误解。我再次重申，每一座伟大的国家建筑都是其伟大的国家宗教的结果和体现。这些建筑不能东一座，西一座——要么它们到处都是，要么一座也没有。这些建筑不是牧师们的专利——不是神学教条的明证——也不是牧师们发明的象形文字；它们是一个受到坚定的、共同的目标所鼓舞的民族的强有力的语言，这个民族坚定且共同地宣誓，效忠于一个不容置疑的上帝所制定的明晰的律法。

迄今为止，欧洲的建筑出现过三种截然不同的流派。我谈欧洲，是因为亚洲和非洲的建筑完全属于其他的种族和气候条件，所以这里讨论的问题与它们无关；不过，顺便说一句，我可以肯定地告诉你们，在埃及、叙利亚和印度被认为是好的建筑的因由，同样适用于对于博斯普鲁斯海峡这边的欧洲的建筑进行评判。我们欧洲人曾经有过三种伟大的信仰：在古希腊，我们崇拜智慧和力量之神；在中世纪，我们崇拜审判和抚慰之神；在文艺复兴时期，我们崇拜自豪与美丽之神。我们曾经有过的这三种信仰都已经成为历史，现在，我们英国人又有了第四种信仰及我们自己的神，对此我有问题要问你们，然而，我必须首先解释一下这三种旧的信仰。

首先，我重申，希腊人从根本上来说崇拜智慧之神；无论什么东西与他们的信仰产生了矛盾——对于犹太人来说就是一块绊脚石，而对于希腊人来说就是愚蠢。

希腊人的第一个有关神性的观念来自“天”（day）这个词，就是天神，天启者朱庇特。这在我们英文单词“Di-umal”和“Di-vine”——天之神（the God of Day）中依稀可见。雅典娜是朱庇特的女儿，但更是智慧之神的女儿，她周身充满了智慧。我们只是凭借最近的研究才开始弄明白隐蔽在雅典娜身上的象征符号之下的深层含义，在这儿我可以简要地介绍一下。在有关雅典娜的最好的雕塑中大都可以看到这样的形象：她手擎着宙斯盾，身披着缝有蛇形吊穗儿的斗篷，左臂折叠作出保护的动作；而她盾牌上面的戈尔贡则主要象征了阴森的恐怖和悲伤（她能将看到她眼睛的人变成石头）——这些都是最外在和表面的知识。正是这种苦涩、冷酷和悲痛的知识，将成年人和儿童的心灵区别开来。恐怖、纷争、危险和蔑视产生于知识的残缺；而力量和和平则来自完美的知识，它正是由获得了神启的雅典娜所赋予的，其标志就是她头上所戴的、象征和平的橄榄枝、和手中所握的、象征力量的无坚不摧的长矛。

这就是古希腊人对于最纯粹的神性的认识；他们每一处生活的习惯，每一种艺术的形式都来源于这种对于光明的、平静的和无法抗拒的智慧的追寻；这使得他们，作为人，每时每刻都决心行正确之事，勇气之事；[9]他们做事情从来都不会心血来潮或是抱定最终的希望；因为他们知道失败将无法得到安慰，而罪孽也不可能得到赦免，所以他们总是秉持坚决而又自我克制的意志力行事。于是古希腊的建筑便呈现出一种准确的、明快的、清晰的形象，和一种从容不迫的气质。

其次，是欧洲的伟大的基督教信仰。从根本上来说它是一种起安慰作用的信仰。它的主要教义就是罪孽的赦免；正因为如此，在基督教的某些发展阶段才会经常出现这样的情形，就是罪孽和疾病本身在某种程度上被加以颂扬，似乎越是有可供治愈的罪孽和疾病，就越是能显示出治愈过程的神圣。这一教义在艺术中所造成的实际影响就是，人们对于罪孽和疾病的不断的沉思，以及对于从罪孽和疾病中获得净化时的状态的不断的冥想；因此我们便在一种忧郁和渴望相混合的情绪下构思我们的建筑。它一半是严苛，一半是华丽；它服从于我们所有的需求和想象，并且，就像我们自身有强有弱一样，它也同我们一起或强或弱。所有的建筑都是如此，当卑劣的人们修建它的时候，它就是最卑劣的；当高贵的人们修建它的时候，它就是最高贵的。

现在请注意，这两种信仰——古希腊的和中世纪的信仰——都由于它们自身主要目的的谬误而消亡了。古希腊对于智慧的信仰消亡于一种对其错误的热爱与追求——其智慧已成为科学的羁绊。中世纪对于安慰的信仰消亡于一种错误的安慰——通过谎言赦免罪孽。正是出卖赦罪符才终结了中世纪的信仰；而且更进一步讲，正是中世纪末期对于赦罪符的出卖才标志着基督教的虚伪。在纯净的基督教中，只有结束罪孽才能赦免罪孽；然而虚伪的基督教却通过向罪孽妥协将其赦免。这当中有很多向罪孽妥协的方法。我们英国人，无论是在低教会派还是在高教会派中，都有偷偷购买赦罪符的、漂亮的小手段，比起约翰·泰臣曾经的勾当要狡猾得多了。

第三种是对于快乐的信仰。整个欧洲都置身于奢华之中，最终以死亡结束。先是每个沙龙都举办的假面舞会，然后是每个广场都竖起来的断头台。所有这三种崇拜都诞生于恢宏的庙宇之中。希腊人崇拜智慧，于是修建了帕特农神庙——贞洁女的庙宇。中世纪的人们崇拜安慰，于是也修建了贞洁女的庙宇——然而供奉的是救赎女神。文艺复兴运动者崇拜各式的美，于是修建了凡尔赛宫和梵蒂冈宫。那么最后，请你们告诉我，我们崇拜什么，我们修建了什么呢？

大家知道，我们总是在谈论真实的、活跃的、持续的和民族的信仰；人们在有生之年借此信仰而行动；而不是在死后将其作为谈资。确实有一种名义上的宗教，我们拿出十分之一的财产来供奉它，花七分之一的时间来打理它；还有一种实用的、严肃的宗教，为它我们投入了十分之九的财产和七分之六的时间。我们对于这种名义上的宗教争论不休，但是对于这种实用的宗教却是意见一致；我想你们一定同意，我把这种实用宗教的当家女神大致地描述为“进步女神”或是“不列颠市场女神”。雅典人有“市场雅典娜”；不过她在雅典诸神中处于从属的地位，而我们的不列颠市场女神则是我们的主神。当然，你们所有的宏大建筑也都是为她而建。你们已经很久没有修建过伟大的主教堂了；如果此时我建议在周围的这些山冈之上选择一处修建主教堂，并把它打造成为像雅典卫城那样的建筑，那么你们一定会耻笑我。你们的铁路路基要比巴比伦的城墙更为宽阔；你们的铁路站房要比以佛所的庙宇更为宽敞，而且数不胜数；你们的烟囱，要比教堂的尖顶牢固得多，昂贵得多！你们的港口码头；你们的货栈；你们的交易所！——所有这一切都是你们为“进步”女神而修建的；她已经塑造了你们的建筑，只要你们崇拜她，她将继续如此；因此，你们现在来问我如何给她建造庙宇简直就是徒劳无益；因为你们比我知道得更多。

事实上，依据某些理论，确实有可能为交易所设计出令人信服的、好的建筑——就是说，如果确实有什么有关交易的、代表性的英雄事迹，能够雕刻在你们建筑的外墙之上的话，因为，你们知道，所有美丽的建筑必须装饰以雕塑或是绘画；而你们必须有适合雕塑或是绘画的题材。而且迄今为止，世界各国已经形成了共识，就是雕塑或是绘画的唯一合适的题材就是某种类型的英雄主义。即使是在瓦罐和酒壶上，希腊人也会刻画上一幅赫拉克勒斯杀死狮子，或是阿波罗杀死毒蛇，或是酒神巴克斯杀死忧郁的巨人和失魂落魄的俗人的画儿。在他们的庙宇中，希腊人会描绘其伟大的勇士为建立国家而战斗的场景，或是诸神勇斗妖魔的场面。基督徒会在他们的房子里和庙宇中雕刻上天使战胜魔鬼的情形；或是以生命为代价扭转乾坤的殉道者，我想，这个题材对于我们的交易所并不合适。上帝非但没有明令他的追随者们可以在建筑的外墙上刻上有关交易的雕塑，相反，还强烈地表示，并不喜欢他们在建筑的内部从事交易的活动。然而在交易活动中似乎确实存在着英雄主义；所有的商业活动都可能是在出售圣灵，而不是亵渎神灵。我一直以来都很奇怪，为什么人们从来都不认为英雄主义是一种给人们提供食物或是衣服的活动；相反却认为英雄主义就是强占人们的粮食并且剥光他们的衣服。在所有的时代，武力的滥用都被看作英雄的行为；但是卖衣服，不管是新还是旧，从来都没有被认为具有什么崇高的性质。我不明白，为饥饿者提供食物，为衣不蔽体者提供衣服怎么就会成为卑劣的勾当，何况有时这些活动规模巨大，受益者甚众。如果有谁能够创造性地把征服的观念与做买卖结合起来就好了！这样的话，假定在某个地方有某个冥顽不化的种族拒绝接受舒适的生活，而某人就会以为其提供强制性的舒适而感到自豪！[10]而且，这不就是传说中的，以礼物而不是兵戎“占领一个国家”吗？人们应当把田地中播种耕耘看作是与抢夺丰收果实一样的胜利；应当争论谁去建设村庄而非谁去占领村庄。所有形式的英雄主义，不都是在做这些前人栽树后人乘凉的事儿吗？你们还拿不准谁最强大吗？毫无疑问，铁锹和刀剑一样有力。谁最明智呢？策动战争之外，还有更明智的活动。谁最勇敢呢？人们总是要与大自然搏斗，它比人类更强大，几乎像人类一样残忍。

军人职业中唯一绝对的、旁人难以做到的英雄行为就是他们做事只有很少的报酬，而且是固定的收入；而你们掮客和商人，以及其他某些似乎是忙于慈善营生的人们，则喜欢从买卖中多多赚钱——而且是发横财。我永远都不能理解为什么一位游侠会不计报酬地置身险地，而一位游贩却总要唯利是图；为什么人们会不求回报地以身犯险，却从不愿意把缎带卖得更便宜点；为什么人们会狂热地发动圣战去收复一位死去神灵的坟墓，却从来不愿意出趟门满足某位生者的订单；为什么人们愿意赤脚走到任何什么地方为自己的信仰祈祷，却总是非有巨额的贿赂不会对其加以奉行；为什么人们愿意自掏腰包派发免费的福音书，却从不会提供免费的鱼和面包。

如果你们依据军队的原则行事，只为获取固定的工资收入而经商，并且为国家提供给养；就像士兵以最好的火药为人民服务一样，你们也为人们提供最好的食物和最好的布料；那么我就会在你们交易所的墙上雕刻一些值得观赏的东西。目前，我只能建议在交易所的雕带上悬挂上钱包；并且为了粘贴票据的方便，把它立柱的底座建得宽阔一些。在交易所最里面的密室里竖起一尊不列颠市场女神的雕像，建议在她头顶插上松鸡的羽毛作为装饰，以显示出为正义而战的勇气和对于猎物的兴趣；然后，再在雕像的脖颈处刻上金色的铭文，“她不像松鸡一样孵蛋”。[11]接下来，可以用织工的卷轴作为她的长矛；再在她的盾牌上雕刻以不是圣乔治的十字，而是剪了一半毛的米兰公猪，和位于田野中间的，富庶的革尼撒勒城，并且辅之以铭文，“这里是最好的市场”；[12]她皮质的甲胄要在胸前折叠成钱包的形状，上面撕开三十个投币口，以便从此塞进钱去，每个投币口代表每个月中的一天。我敢肯定，经过如此装饰，人们对你们的交易所和其中的女神一定赞赏有加。

我要指出的是，你们的女神具有某些奇怪的特征。她与伟大的希腊和中世纪的诸神在以下两个方面存在着根本的不同：第一，她被赋予的力量所能持续的时间；第二，这一力量的影响范围。

首先，看一看她的力量所能持续的时间吧。

就像基督教的安慰圣灵（或是安慰者）不断地增加安慰一样，古希腊的智慧女神也会不断地释放出更多的智慧。毫无疑问，他们的安慰和智慧是没有限度的，也是不会中途停止的，但是对于你们的市场女神来说，这正是最为重要的问题所在。发展进步——但是去向何方呢？聚敛钱财——但是多少是够呢？你们只要不断地敛财——而从不花钱吗？果真如此的话，但愿你们喜爱自己的女神，因为即便是没有向她朝拜，我也过得和你们一样富裕。可是如果你们不去花钱，自然有别人会去花的，而且肯定会。正是基于此（在诸多类似的错误中此项最甚），我曾经大胆地宣称，你们所谓的政治经济学其实并不是什么科学；因为，换句话说，它忽略了对于商业中的最重要的分支的研究——对于消费的研究。因为最终来讲，你们必须花掉挣到的钱。你们收获了谷物之后，是要把英国埋在谷粒堆下面，还是最终会把它们吃掉呢？你们挣得了黄金之后，是用它盖你们的房顶，还是用它铺你们的街道呢？这当然也是一种花钱的方式，但是，如果你们仅仅是为了储存更多的黄金，我愿意给你们更多的黄金；如果你们能告诉我拿黄金干什么用，那么我就会给你们所有想要的黄金——要多少给多少。你们将会得到成千上万的金条；千百万堆积如山的黄金：你们有地方存放它们吗？你们会在皮利翁金山上再堆上一座奥林匹斯银山，然后压得奥萨山看上去就像是一团让人厌恶的肉瘤吗？你们会觉得从这样的山上流淌下来的雨水和露珠会比从上帝为你们而造的，满是玄武岩和苔藓的山峦上流淌下的雨水和露珠更为神圣吗？这样说来你们所要占有的并不是黄金呀！那是什么呢？美钞吗？不，也不是。那是什么呢？大写的一后面的零吗？不，你们不可以练习写零，而且想写多少就写多少！每天早晨，在大账本上写上一个小时的零，到了晚上的时候就对自己说，我今天的身价比昨天又多了许多零。这样行吗？那么，请以财神普路托斯的名义告诉我，你们到底想要什么？不是黄金，不是美钞，不是大写的一后面的零，还会是什么呢？这样，你们就会不得不回答说：“不，我们想要的，也许说不太清楚，是金钱的价值吧。”好吧，那么这价值是什么呢？就让你们的进步女神找到它，并且学着在那里驻留吧。

第二，还有一个有关这位进步女神的问题需要问，这就是她力量的影响范围。

雅典娜和圣母马利亚是全世界的雅典娜和圣母马利亚，她们可以教化所有的人，安慰所有的人，但是，仔细查看一下你们的进步女神的力量的本质，就会发现，作为女神，她并不保佑所有的人取得进步，而只是保佑某些人取得进步。这一点区别很重要，甚至于很致命。请想一想，这位女神所召唤并且力主的，同时也是你们理想中的，人民的生活状态是怎样的。上次来的时候，我问过你们这一理想的生活状态是什么，可是你们没有回答我。现在，我可以告诉你们什么是这一理想的生活状态了吗？

你们理想中的生活状态就是，我认为，要生活在一个惬意的、绵延起伏的世界上，地下随处都埋藏着铁矿和煤矿。在每一处舒适的坡地上都建有一座漂亮的公馆，它带有两座厢房，还有马厩和马车库，一所大小适中的庄园，一个大花园和几间温室，还有一辆乘坐舒适的马车在灌木丛下面穿行。在这幢公馆里面，生活着受到你们女神眷顾的忠实信徒；他们是一位英国绅士以及他优雅的夫人和漂亮的孩子们；这位绅士总是能给夫人提供化妆间和珠宝，给女儿们提供漂亮的舞裙，给儿子们提供猎犬，给自己提供在苏格兰高地的狩猎权。在坡地的底部是一座工厂；它至少有四分之一英里长，两端各有一台蒸汽机，中间还有两台；竖起的烟囱足有三百英尺高。工厂里长期雇用着八百至一千名工人，他们从不喝酒、从不罢工，每个星期天都去做礼拜，而且说起话来总是彬彬有礼。

概括地、就其主要的特征来说，难道这不就是你们为自己设计的生活吗？如果从上面看过去，这一生活确实非常美好；然而如果从下面看过来，就根本谈不上什么美好了。因为，请注意，对于某个家庭来说，这一神灵确实是进步女神，而对于其他一千个家庭来说，她则是退步女神。“不对，”你们会说，“所有的人都有机会。”没错，就像是每个人都有中奖的机会一样，每个人也都有抓空的机会。“哎呀！抓阄的时候凭借的不是技能和智慧，而是撞大运呀。”那又如何！当权力已经由拳头的力量变为头脑的力量的时候，你们还认为“弱肉强食，胜者为王”的古老法则是公正的吗？你们不欺压弱势的妇女和儿童，难道就可以利用男人们的愚蠢吗？“那倒不是，不过最后一点，活儿一定得有人干，而且一定会有人高高在上，也一定会有人屈居底部。”就算如此，我的朋友们，活儿当然得有人干，干活儿的工头当然也得有；可是如果你们还对我写过的文章有一点点印象的话，那么就一定知道，工头们并不适合这个时代，因为他们一直在坚持统治的必要性，而对于自由则是冷嘲热讽。我请求大家注意，作为工头或是工作的管理者，与从工作中获利之间，存在着很大的不同。这就像是，你是一支军队的将军，却并不见得就应该取得军队所缴获的财宝或是土地，（如果它是为财宝和土地而战的话）同样，你是一国之君，却并不见得就应该消费掉整个国家的劳动果实。相反，真正的国王都无一例外地反其道而行之，他们都尽量少地取得国家的财富。这一点是检验真正的王权无可争辩的试金石。那个戴着王冠的人生活得简单、勇敢、朴素吗？如是之，他可能就是一位国王。他的身上戴满了宝石，桌上摆满了美味佳肴吗？如果是，他就一定不是一位国王。他有可能成为所罗门那样的国王，但条件是他要同人民共享荣耀。所罗门不仅仅用黄金搭建自己的宫殿，而且用它修建耶路撒冷。即便如此，这些光辉灿烂的王国也大都消失在历史的尘芥堆中了，只有真正的、高贵的劳动者管理着忠诚的劳动者的王国才会生存下去；他们共克时艰，一同建立真正的王朝。因此，你们即便是国家的君主，也并不意味着就可以为自己聚敛属于国家的财富；同样，即便你们是国家某地的统治者，掌控着某地的全部财富——土地、工厂、矿山等，也并不意味着就可以为自己牟取所有来源于此地的物产。

你们会告诉我，不要鼓吹反对这些事情了，因为你改变不了什么的。是的，朋友们，我改变不了什么；但是你们能，而且你们应该这样做；或是有其他什么人能够而且愿意这样做。即便是好的东西也不可能拥有持久的力量，更何况是这些罪恶的东西，它们会以胜利者的姿态延续其罪恶吗？当然不会，所有的历史都表明，它们办不到。改变一定会到来；然而这改变是朝向成长还是奔向死亡则取决于我们。你们认为，帕特农神庙会在岩石上成为废墟，博尔顿小修道院会在牧场上变为瓦砾；而你们的工厂则会成为地球上所有建筑的典范，它们的轮子会永不停息，对吗？你们认为“人来人亦往”，而你们的工厂总会屹立不倒，对吗？错了；改变一定会到来，它可能好也可能坏，而决定权在你们的手中。

我知道所有这些不公平都不是人们有意为之。同时我还知道，你们都希望自己的工人们生活得好；你们为他们做了很多，而且如果知道自己的行善于己无害的话，还愿意为他们做得更多。我知道，尽管所有这些不公平和苦难都是由于一种扭曲的责任感所造成，你们还是在努力行善；然而不幸的是，你们并不知道自己的善举所针对的对象应该是谁。而且，我们的心灵都已经被现代经济学家的那句亵渎神灵的花言巧语所蒙蔽，他们说，“为我们自己而努力奋斗，最终就是为他人谋幸福。”朋友们，我们的耶稣基督可没有说过这样的话；而且我确信，这样做天理难容。实际上，应该反过来说，“为他人而努力奋斗，最终就是为自己谋幸福；”但是眼睛仅仅盯着这个问题还不够，因为异教徒们都已经超越了这种眼界。听一听一个异教徒对此是怎么说的；听一听柏拉图在他最后写下的文字当中是怎么说的——也许不是最后的文字（对此我们无从知晓），然而可以肯定的是，这一定是他在告别人世之前所说的话——他竭尽全力对自己一生的思想进行完整的总结，并且以想象中的，伟大神灵的口谕的方式传达出来，但是他的体力和意志没能坚持到最后，所以他的话没有说完就永远地中断了。

柏拉图的话出现在一本叫作《柯里西亚斯》的对话录的结尾处。在书中他描绘了雅典早期的状况，一部分是基于真实的情况，一部分则是来自想象。书中还讲述了传说中的亚特兰蒂斯的起源、社会秩序和宗教。在描绘亚特兰蒂斯起源的时候，他构想出人类最初的完美及最终的堕落，这与我们的圣经传统相类似——神的儿子们与人类的女儿们通婚，因为柏拉图认为最早的种族实际上是神的儿女；然后他们最终走向堕落，直到“通过他们的印记已经不能辨认出是神的孩子”。柏拉图说，这就是故事的结局；的确，“历经数代，当神性还在他们身上完整保存的时候，他们便顺从于神圣的律法，对所有同他们一样具有神性的人们显示出仁爱；因为他们的最高精神忠诚而真切，同时充满了智慧；所以他们彼此之间以礼相待，把握生命中的所有机缘；他们抛弃一切除了美德以外的东西，对于日常事务很少在意，并且对于黄金和财产从不挂心；因为他们知道，如果博爱和美德可以精进，所有这些东西都会一同增长；然而专注于物质财富的不懈追求只会让你失去它，一同失去的还有你的爱心和美德。基于这样的推理及内心存留的神性，他们收获了一切我们曾经谈到过的伟大成就；但是当他们的神性开始减弱并且最终熄灭，与流行的世俗相融合并且被它冲淡的时候，人性最终超越了神性，于是他们不再能抵制财富的诱惑，堕入到了扭曲的、低级的生活当中去，失去了他们最为美好的荣誉；然而对于那些不能明辨是非，一心只想追逐快乐的、被蒙蔽的人们来说，他们看上去似乎既高贵又幸福，因为他们拥有过多的不义之财和权力。因此，依靠律法治国的众神之神——他目睹了一个曾经正义的民族陷入不义之境，所以要对他们施以惩戒，为的是让他们能够幡然悔悟、自我约束——便将所有的神灵召集到了自己的住所——这里是这天堂的中心，俯瞰着大地；然后对他们说”——

柏拉图的话没有说完就停止了。这位最为智慧的异教徒在最后几句话中谈到了对于财富的偶像崇拜；这是你们的偶像——它金光闪闪，高耸入云，巍然屹立在英格兰的绿色原野上，就像杜拉平原上竖立起的尼布甲尼撒王的金像一样：在所有被禁止的偶像崇拜当中，这座偶像是我们的圣主和信仰所最为反对的；它是，在任何时代和民族，那些被认为是能够传达上帝旨意的人们所全体反对的。如果你们继续将那座禁神奉为自己的主要神灵的话，那么用不了多久，你们就会失去艺术，失去科学，失去快乐。灾难即将来临；或是，比灾难更糟糕的是，世界会缓慢地腐朽和枯萎，并且最终堕入地狱。但是，如果你们能够树立某种可以为之奋斗的，真正的人生观念——一种对你们、对所有人都有益的人生观念的话；如果你们能够确定某种诚实和朴素的生存秩序的话；如果你们能够踏上并且探索那些前人开辟的，欢快的、僻静的、通往和平的智慧之路的话[13]——然后，将个人财产升华为“公共福利”（英文：wealth+common=commonwealth）的话，那么你们所有的艺术、文学、日常的劳作、家庭的温暖和公民的责任就会融合在一起，在崇高的和谐中共同增长。如此，你们就知道应该如何兴修好的建筑了；你们就会不仅仅是用石头，而且是用血肉之躯兴修好的建筑；庙宇就不再是用双手建成，而是用心灵筑就；只有这种被鲜血浸染的大理石才会真正的永垂不朽。

[1]肯定不会！——从来没有听说过有谁比我的废话还要多，有谁比我更乐意蹚浑水；我认为，结尾的这一段是第六章中最好的，也是整本书中最好的一段文字，但同时也是最徒劳无益的。

[2]《彼得后书》，第三章第五至七节。

[3]现代“教育”在很大程度上意味着教给了人们，在所能想到的对自己来说重要的方面，进行错误思考的本领。

[4]我既然这样写了就说明答案是否定的；我们已经完全将北极领域内的探索任务交由大陆国家来完成了，因为我们穷得买不起船只。

[5]我的意思是指世界各地的美景——瑞士、意大利、德国南部等——这些地方才是真正的大教堂——才是我们应当虔诚祈祷的地方；然而我们只在乎走马观花：在它们最为圣洁的地方大吃大喝。

[6]由于空气中的烟灰从几英里以外随风吹落下来，所以约克郡里士满地区的河岸变得一片漆黑。几年前看到这一景象时，我深感震惊。

[7]这句对于百无一用的劳工所说的话在措辞上与某一篇文章惊人地相似，我想大家对这篇文章可能有点印象。它也放在我的抽屉里。我想把这篇文章与这里引用的这个段落放在一起，可能会更好地说明一些问题。这篇文章也是我从《晨报》上剪下来的，发表的日期也是在1865年3月10日，星期五。文章内容是这样的：“C夫人巧妙地摆出体面和优雅的架势以尽其地主之谊。在她的沙龙里挤满了亲王、公爵、侯爵和伯爵——事实上，参加的人等与梅特捏公主和朱茵·德·路易斯夫人所举办的聚会中的男宾们是一样的。一些英国的贵族和国会议员也到场了，他们似乎对这里伤风败俗的活泼生动和纸醉金迷欣赏有加。二楼的餐桌上摆满了各类时令的美味佳肴，这些都是供给四点来此就餐的客人的（大约有二百人）。为了让您对巴黎上流社会的大餐有所了解，我在这里把当晚的菜单抄录如下。首先是酒类：精选伊甘堡葡萄酒、约翰内斯堡雷司令、拉斐特葡萄酒、托凯葡萄酒、品质最好的香槟等，供宾客们彻夜畅饮。晚宴过后是更为火爆的舞会，一直持续到第二天清晨七点，直到人们跳完恶魔一般的圆圈舞和地狱一般的康康舞为止。（然后是早餐——“晨光刚刚睁开了她的眼睛，清新的草坪还模糊不清。”）下面是菜单：‘清炖鸡汤，搭配十六样开胃菜，塔列朗馅饼，凉拌酸辣鲑鱼，贝尔维牛里脊肉片，米兰香烤三味，野味儿肉冻、松露火鸡、鹅肝酱、不韦松小龙虾、威尼斯沙拉、各色果冻、曼奇尼蛋糕、巴黎的和巴黎式美食。冰奶酪、菠萝、甜点。’”

[8]请注意这个说法，想一想，一位穷苦的老妇人每个星期从国家领取一先令的救济，她会感到多么的羞辱呀——然而相反，是不会有谁会为领取一年一千英镑的养老金而感到羞耻的。

[9]认为美是古希腊人崇拜或是追求的主要目标的观点是错误的。建立在深谋远虑基础之上的正确和力量才是他们孜孜以求的目标：古希腊艺术的首要特征不是美丽，而是结构设计：多利安人的阿波罗崇拜以及雅典人的处女崇拜都表明了他们对于神圣的智慧和纯洁的倾慕。对于民众的影响力仅次于这些神灵的诸神还有酒神狄俄尼索斯和谷神克瑞斯，他们赐予人类以力量和生命；此外还有代表英雄的大力神赫拉克利斯。在古希腊的辉煌时期并没有对于维纳斯的崇拜：缪斯诸女神主要是司教授真理及其和谐之职。

[10]我并没有开玩笑，尽管听起来像是俏皮话。（1873）

[11]《耶利米书》，第十七章，第十一节（最好的文本在七十子希腊文本《圣经》和拉丁文《圣经》中）。“那不按正道得财的，好像松鸡抱不是自己下的蛋；到了中年，那财都必离开他，他终究成为愚顽人。”

[12]说完整了就是，“我们已经把猪带来了”。（1873）

[13]我猜测希伯来的圣歌仅仅是充满激情的反复吟唱，并没有如此丰富的想象力；然而，我们还是可以在读英文的时候浮想联翩、受益匪浅。

The Lamp of Memory

Among the hours of his life to which the writer looks back with peculiar gratitude, as having been marked by more than ordinary fulness of joy or clearness of teaching, is one passed, now some years ago, near time of sunset, among the broken masses of pine forest which skirt the course of the Ain, above the village of Champagnole, in the Jura. It is a spot which has all the solemnity, with none of the savageness, of the Alps; where there is a sense of a great power beginning to be manifested in the earth, and of a deep and majestic concord in the rise of the long low lines of piny hills; the first utterance of those mighty mountain symphonies, soon to be more loudly lifted and wildly broken along the battlements of the Alps. But their strength is as yet restrained; and the far reaching ridges of pastoral mountain succeed each other, like the long and sighing swell which moves over quiet waters from some far off stormy sea. And there is a deep tenderness pervading that vast monotony. The destructive forces and the stern expression of the central ranges are alike withdrawn. No frost-ploughed, dust-encumbered paths of ancient glacier fret the soft Jura pastures; no splintered heaps of ruin break the fair ranks of her forest; no pale, defiled, or furious rivers send their rude and changeful ways among her rocks. Patiently, eddy by eddy, the clear green streams wind along their well-known beds; and under the dark quietness of the undisturbed pines, there spring up, year by year, such company of joyful flowers as I know not the like of among all the blessings of the earth. It was spring time, too; and all were coming forth in clusters crowded for very love; there was room enough for all, but they crushed their leaves into all manner of strange shapes only to be nearer each other. There was the wood anemone, star after star, closing every now and then into nebulae; and there was the oxalis, troop by troop, like virginal processions of the Mois de Marie, the dark vertical clefts in the limestone choked up with them as with heavy snow, and touched with ivy on the edges - ivy as light and lovely as the vine; and, ever and anon, a blue gush of violets, and cowslip bells in sunny places; and in the more open ground, the vetch, and comfrey, and mezereon, and the small sapphire buds of the Polygala Alpina, and the wild strawberry, just a blossom or two, all showered amidst the golden softness of deep, warm, amber-coloured moss. I came out presently on the edge of the ravine: the solemn murmur of its waters rose suddenly from beneath, mixed with the singing of the thrushes among the pine boughs; and, on the opposite side of the valley, walled all along as it was by grey cliffs of limestone, there was a hawk sailing slowly off their brow, touching them nearly with his wings, and with the shadows of the pines flickering upon his plumage from above; but with the fall of a hundred fathoms under his breast, and the curling pools of the green river gliding and glittering dizzily beneath him, their foam globes moving with him as he flew. It would be difficult to conceive a scene less dependent upon any other interest than that of its own secluded and serious beauty; but the writer well remembers the sudden blankness and chill which were cast upon it when he endeavoured, in order more strictly to arrive at the sources of its impressiveness, to imagine it, for a moment, a scene in some aboriginal forest of the New Continent. The flowers in an instant lost their light, the river its music; the hills became oppressively desolate; a heaviness in the boughs of the darkened forest showed how much of their former power had been dependent upon a life which was not theirs, how much of the glory of the imperishable, or continually renewed, creation is reflected from things more precious in their memories than it, in its renewing. Those ever springing flowers and ever flowing streams had been dyed by the deep colours of human endurance, valour, and virtue; and the crests of the sable hills that rose against the evening sky received a deeper worship, because their far shadows fell eastward over the iron walls of Joux, and the four-square keep of Granson.

It is as the centralization and protectress of this sacred influence, that Architecture is to be regarded by us with the most serious thought. We may live without her, and worship without her, but we cannot remember without her. How cold is all history, how lifeless all imagery, compared to that which the living nation writes, and the uncorrupted marble bears! — how many pages of doubtful record might we not often spare, for a few stones left one upon another! The ambition of the old Babel builders was well directed for this world: there are but two strong conquerors of the forgetfulness of men, Poetry and Architecture; and the latter in some sort includes the former, and is mightier in its reality: it is well to have, not only what men have thought and felt, but what their hands have handled, and their strength wrought, and their eyes beheld, all the days of their life. The age of Homer is surrounded with darkness, his very personality with doubt. Not so that of Pericles: and the day is coming when we shall confess, that we have learned more of Greece out of the crumbled fragments of her sculpture than even from her sweet singers or soldier historians. And if indeed there be any profit in our knowledge of the past, or any joy in the thought of being remembered hereafter, which can give strength to present exertion, or patience to present endurance, there are two duties respecting national architecture whose importance it is impossible to overrate: the first, to render the architecture of the day, historical; and, the second, to preserve, as the most precious of inheritances, that of past ages.

It is in the first of these two directions that Memory may truly be said to be the Sixth Lamp of Architecture; for it is in becoming memorial or monumental that a true perfection is attained by civil and domestic buildings; and this partly as they are, with such a view, built in a more stable manner, and partly as their decorations are consequently animated by a metaphorical or historical meaning.

As regards domestic buildings, there must always be a certain limitation to views of this kind in the power, as well as in the hearts, of men; still I cannot but think it an evil sign of a people when their houses are built to last for one generation only. There is a sanctity in a good man's house which cannot be renewed in every tenement that rises on its ruins: and I believe that good men would generally feel this; and that having spent their lives happily and honourably, they would be grieved, at the close of them, to think that the place of their earthly abode, which had seen, and seemed almost to sympathize in, all their honour, their gladness, or their suffering, — that this, with all the record it bare of them, and of all material things that they had loved and ruled over, and set the stamp of themselves upon — was to be swept away, as soon as there was room made for them in the grave; that no respect was to be shown to it, no affection felt for it, no good to be drawn from it by their children; that though there was a monument in the church, there was no warm monument in the hearth and house to them; that all that they ever treasured was despised, and the places that had sheltered and comforted them were dragged down to the dust. I say that a good man would fear this; and that, far more, a good son, a noble descendant, would fear doing it to his father's house. I say that if men lived like men indeed, their houses would be temples — temples which we should hardly dare to injure, and in which it would make us holy to be permitted to live; and there must be a strange dissolution of natural affection, a strange unthankfulness for all that homes have given and parents taught, a strange consciousness that we have been unfaithful to our fathers' honour, or that our own lives are not such as would make our dwellings sacred to our children, when each man would fain build to himself, and build for the little revolution of his own life only. And I look upon those pitiful concretions of lime and clay which spring up, in mildewed forwardness, out of the kneaded fields about our capital — upon those thin, tottering, foundationless shells of splintered wood and imitated stone — upon those gloomy rows of formalized minuteness, alike without difference and without fellowship, as solitary as similar — not merely with the careless disgust of an offended eye, not merely with sorrow for a desecrated landscape, but with a painful foreboding that the roots of our national greatness must be deeply cankered when they are thus loosely struck in their native ground; that those comfortless and unhonoured dwellings are the signs of a great and spreading spirit of popular discontent; that they mark the time when every man's aim is to be in some more elevated sphere than his natural one, and every man's past life is his habitual scorn; when men build in the hope of leaving the places they have built, and live in the hope of forgetting the years that they have lived; when the comfort, the peace, the religion of home have ceased to be felt; and the crowded tenements of a struggling and restless population differ only from the tents of the Arab or the Gipsy by their less healthy openness to the air of heaven, and less happy choice of their spot of earth; by their sacrifice of liberty without the gain of rest, and of stability without the luxury of change.

This is no slight, no consequenceless evil; it is ominous, infectious, and fecund of other fault and misfortune. When men do not love their hearths, nor reverence their thresholds, it is a sign that they have dishonoured both, and that they have never acknowledged the true universality of that Christian worship which was indeed to supersede the idolatry, but not the piety, of the pagan. Our God is a household God, as well as a heavenly one; He has an altar in every man's dwelling; let men look to it when they rend it lightly and pour out its ashes. It is not a question of mere ocular delight, it is no question of intellectual pride, or of cultivated and critical fancy, how, and with what aspect of durability and of completeness, the domestic buildings of a nation shall be raised. It is one of those moral duties, not with more impunity to be neglected because the perception of them depends on a finely toned and balanced conscientiousness, to build our dwellings with care, and patience, and fondness, and diligent completion, and with a view to their duration at least for such a period as, in the ordinary course of national revolutions, might be supposed likely to extend to the entire alteration of the direction of local interests. This at the least; but it would be better if, in every possible instance, men built their own houses on a scale commensurate rather with their condition at the commencement, than their attainments at the termination, of their worldly career; and built them to stand as long as human work at its strongest can be hoped to stand; recording to their children what they had been, and from what, if so it had been permitted them, they had risen. And when houses are thus built, we may have that true domestic architecture, the beginning of all other, which does not disdain to treat with respect and thoughtfulness the small habitation as well as the large, and which invests with the dignity of contented manhood the narrowness of worldly circumstance.

I look to this spirit of honourable, proud, peaceful self-possession, this abiding wisdom of contented life, as probably one of the chief sources of great intellectual power in all ages, and beyond dispute as the very primal source of the great architecture of old Italy and France. To this day, the interest of their fairest cities depends, not on the isolated richness of palaces, but on the cherished and exquisite decoration of even the smallest tenements of their proud periods. The most elaborate piece of architecture in Venice is a small house at the head of the Grand Canal, consisting of a ground floor with two storeys above, three windows in the first, and two in the second. Many of the most exquisite buildings are on the narrower canals, and of no larger dimensions. One of the most interesting pieces of fifteenth-century architecture in North Italy, is a small house in a back street, behind the marketplace of Vicenza; it bears date 1481, and the motto, Il. n'est. rose. sans. épine.; it has also only a ground floor and two storeys, with three windows in each, separated by rich flower-work, and with balconies, supported, the central one by an eagle with open wings, the lateral ones by winged griffins standing on comucopiae. The idea that a house must be large in order to be well built, is altogether of modern growth, and is parallel with the idea, that no picture can be historical, except of a size admitting figures larger than life.

I would have, then, our ordinary dwelling-houses built to last, and built to be lovely; as rich and full of pleasantness as may be, within and without; with what degree of likeness to each other in style and manner, I will say presently, under another head; but, at all events, with such differences as might suit and express each man's character and occupation, and partly his history. This right over the house, I conceive, belongs to its first builder, and is to be respected by his children; and it would be well that blank stones should be left in places, to be inscribed with a summary of his life and of its experience, raising thus the habitation into a kind of monument, and developing, into more systematic instructiveness, that good custom which was of old universal, and which still remains among some of the Swiss and Germans, of acknowledging the grace of God's permission to build and possess a quiet resting-place, in such sweet words as may well close our speaking of these things. I have taken them from the front of a cottage lately built among the green pastures which descend from the village of Grindelwald to the lower glacier: —

'Mit herzlichem Vertrauen

Hat Johannes Mooter und Maria Rubi

Dieses Haus bauen lassen.

Der liebe Gott woll uns bewahren

Vor allem Unglück und Gefahren,

Und es in Segen lassen stehn

Auf der Reise durch diese Jammerzeit

Nach dem himmlischen Paradiese,

Wo alle Fromrnen wohnen,

Da wird Gott sie belohnen

Mit der Friedenskrone

Zu alle Ewigkeit.'*

In public buildings the historical purpose should be still more definite. It is one of the advantages of Gothic architecture, — I use the word Gothic in the most extended sense as broadly opposed to dassical, — that it admits of a richness of record altogether unlimited. Its minute and multitudinous sculptural decorations afford means of expressing, either symbolically or literally, all that need be known of national feeling or achievement. More decoration will, indeed, be usually required than can take so elevated a character; and much, even in the most thoughtful periods, has been left to the freedom of fancy, or suffered to consist of mere repetitions of some national bearing or symbol. It is, however, generally unwise, even in mere surface ornament, to surrender the power and privilege of variety which the spirit of Gothic architecture admits; much more in important features — capitals of columns or bosses, and string courses, as of course in all confessed basreliefs. Better the rudest work that tells a story or records a fact, than the richest without meaning. There should not be a single ornament put upon great civic buildings, without some intellectual intention. Actual representation of history has in modern times been checked by a difficulty, mean indeed, but steadfast; that of unmanageable costume: nevertheless, by a sufficiently bold imaginative treatment, and frank use of symbols, all such obstacles may be vanquished; not perhaps in the degree necessary to produce sculpture in itself satisfactory, but at all events so as to enable it to become a grand and expressive element of architectural composition. Take, for example, the management of the capitals of the ducal palace at Venice. History, as such, was indeed entrusted to the painters of its interior, but every capital of its arcades was filled with meaning. The large one, the corner stone of the whole, next the entrance, was devoted to the symbolization of Abstract Justice; above it is a sculpture of the Judgment of Solomon, remarkable for a beautiful subjection in its treatment to its decorative purpose. The figures, if the subject had been entirely composed of them, would have awkwardly interrupted the line of the angle, and diminished its apparent strength; and therefore in the midst of them, entirely without relation to them, and indeed actually between the executioner and interceding mother, there rises the ribbed trunk of a massy tree, which supports and continues the shaft of the angle, and whose leaves above overshadow and enrich the whole. The capital below bears among its leafage a throned figure of Justice, Trajan doing justice to the widow, Aristotle 'che die legge,' and one or two other subjects now unintelligible from decay. The capitals next in order represent the virtues and vices in succession, as preservative or destructive of national peace and power, concluding with Faith, with the inscription 'Fides optima in Deo est.' A figure is seen on the opposite side of the capital, worshipping the sun. After these, one or two capitals are fancifully decorated with birds, and then come a series representing, first the various fruits, then the national costumes, and then the animals of the various countries subject to Venetian rule.

Now, not to speak of any more important public building, let us imagine our own India House adorned in this way, by historical or symbolical sculpture: massively built in the first place; then chased with basreliefs of our Indian battles, and fretted with carvings of Oriental foliage, or inlaid with Oriental stones; and the more important members of its decoration composed of groups of Indian life and landscape, and prominently expressing the phantasms of Hindoo worship in their subjection to the Cross. Would not one such work be better than a thousand histories? If, however, we have not the invention necessary for such efforts, or if, which is probably one of the most noble excuses we can offer for our defciency in such matters, we have less pleasure in talking about ourselves, even in marble, than the Continental nations, at least we have no excuse for any want of care in the points which insure the building's endurance. And as this question is one of great interest in its relations to the choice of various modes of decoration, it will be necessary to enter into it at some length.

The benevolent regards and purposes of men in masses seldom can be supposed to extend beyond their own generation. They may look to posterity as an audience, may hope for its attention, and labour for its praise: they may trust to its recognition of unacknowledged merit, and demand its justice for contemporary wrong. But all this is mere selfishness, and does not involve the slightest regard to, or consideration of, the interest of those by whose numbers we would fain swell the circle of our flatterers, and by whose authority we would gladly support our presently disputed claims. The idea of self-denial for the sake of posterity, of practising present economy for the sake of debtors yet unborn, of planting forests that our descendants may live under their shade, or of raising cities for future nations to inhabit, never, I suppose, efficiently takes place among publidy recognized motives of exertion. Yet these are not the less our duties; nor is our part fitly sustained upon the earth, unless the range of our intended and deliberate usefulness include, not only the companions but the successors of our pilgrimage. God has lent us the earth for our life; it is a great entail. It belongs as much to those who are to come after us, and whose names are already written in the book of creation, as to us; and we have no right, by anything that we do or neglect, to involve them in unnecessary penalties, or deprive them of benefits which it was in our power to bequeath. And this the more, because it is one of the appointed conditions of the labour of men that, in proportion to the time between the seed-sowing and the harvest, is the fulness of the fruit; and that generally, therefore, the farther off we place our aim, and the less we desire to be ourselves the witnesses of what we have laboured for, the more wide and rich will be the measure of our success. Men cannot benefit those that are with them as they can benefit those who come after them; and of all the pulpits from which human voice is ever sent forth, there is none from which it reaches so far as from the grave.

Nor is there, indeed, any present loss, in such respect, for futurity. Every human action gains in honour, in grace, in all true magnificence, by its regard to things that are to come. It is the far sight, the quiet and confident patience, that, above all other attributes, separate man from man, and near him to his Maker; and there is no action nor art, whose majesty we may not measure by this test. Therefore, when we build, let us think that we build for ever. Let it not be for present delight, nor for present use alone; let it be such work as our descendants will thank us for, and let us think, as we lay stone on stone, that a time is to come when those stones will be held sacred because our hands have touched them, and that men will say as they look upon the labour and wrought substance of them, 'see! this our fathers did for us.' For, indeed, the greatest glory of a building is not in its stones, nor in its gold. Its glory is in its Age, and in that deep sense of voicefulness, of stern watching, of mysterious sympathy, nay, even of approval or condemnation, which we feel in walls that have long been washed by the passing waves of humanity. It is in their lasting witness against men, in their quiet contrast with the transitional character of all things, in the strength which, through the lapse of seasons and times, and the decline and birth of dynasties, and the changing of the face of the earth, and of the limits of the sea, maintains its sculptured shapeliness for a time insuperable, connects forgotten and following ages with each other, and half constitutes the identity, as it concentrates the sympathy, of nations: it is in that golden stain of time, that we are to look for the real light, and colour, and preciousness of architecture; and it is not until a building has assumed this character, till it has been entrusted with the fame, and hallowed by the deeds of men, till its walls have been witnesses of suffering, and its pillars rise out of the shadows of death, that its existence, more lasting as it is than that of the natural objects of the world around it, can be gift ed with even so much as these possess, of language and of life…

Do not let us talk then of restoration. The thing is a Lie from beginning to end. You may make a model of a building as you may of a corpse, and your model may have the shell of the old walls within it as your cast might have the skeleton, with what advantage I neither see nor care: but the old building is destroyed, and that more totally and mercilessly than if it had sunk into a heap of dust, or melted into a mass of clay: more has been gleaned out of desolated Nineveh than ever will be out of rebuilt Milan. But, it is said, there may come a necessity for restoration! Granted. Look the necessity full in the face, and understand it on its own terms. It is a necessity for destruction. Accept it as such, pull the building down, throw its stones into neglected comers, make ballast of them, or mortar, if you will; but do it honestly, and do not set up a Lie in their place. And look that necessity in the face before it comes, and you may prevent it. The principle of modern times, (a principle which, I believe, at least in France, to be systematically acted on by the masons, in order to find themselves work, as the abbey of St Ouen was pulled down by the magistrates of the town by way of giving work to some vagrants,) is to neglect buildings first, and restore them afterwards. Take proper care of your monuments, and you will not need to restore them. A few sheets of lead put in time upon a roof, a few dead leaves and sticks swept in time out of a water-course, will save both roof and walls from ruin. Watch an old building with an anxious care; guard it as best you may, and at any cost, from every influence of dilapidation. Count its stones as you would jewels of a crown; set watches about it as if at the gates of a besieged city; bind it together with iron where it loosens; stay it with timber where it declines; do not care about the unsightliness of the aid: better a crutch than a lost limb; and do this tenderly, and rever ently, and continually, and many a generation will still be born and pass away beneath its shadow. Its evil day must come at last; but let it come declaredly and openly, and let no dishonouring and false substitute deprive it of the funeral offices of memory.

Of more wanton or ignorant ravage it is vain to speak; my words will not reach those who commit them^1, and yet, be it heard or not, I must not leave the truth unstated, that it is again no question of expediency or feeling whether we shall preserve the buildings of past times or not. We have no right whatever to touch them. They are not ours. They belong partly to those who built them, and partly to all the generations of mankind who are to follow us. The dead have still their right in them: that which they laboured for, the praise of achievement or the expression of religious feeling, or whatsoever else it might be which in those buildings they intended to be permanent, we have no right to obliterate. What we have ourselves built, we are at liberty to throw down; but what other men gave their strength and wealth and life to accomplish, their right over does not pass away with their death; still less is the right to the use of what they have left vested in us only. It belongs to all their successors. It may hereafter be a subject of sorrow, or a cause of injury, to millions, that we have consulted our present convenience by casting down such buildings as we choose to dispense with. That sorrow, that loss, we have no right to inflict. Did the cathedral of Avranches belong to the mob who destroyed it, any more than it did to us, who walk in sorrow to and fro over its foundation? Neither does any building whatever belong to those mobs who do violence to it. For a mob it is, and must be always; it matters not whether enraged, or in deliberate folly; whether countless, or sitting in committees; the people who destroy anything causelessly are a mob, and Architecture is always destroyed causelessly. A fair building is necessarily worth the ground it stands upon, and will be so until Central Africa and America shall have become as populous as Middlesex: nor is any cause whatever valid as a ground for its destruction. If ever valid, certainly not now, when the place both of the past and future is too much usurped in our minds by the restless and discontented present. The very quietness of nature is gradually withdrawn from us; thousands who once in their necessarily prolonged travel were subjected to an influence, from the silent sky and slumbering fields, more effectual than known or confessed, now bear with them even there the ceaseless fever of their life; and along the iron veins that traverse the frame of our country, beat and flow the fiery pulses of its exertion, hotter and faster every hour. All vitality is concentrated through those throbbing arteries into the central cities; the country is passed over like a green sea by narrow bridges, and we are thrown back in continually closer crowds upon the city gates. The only influence which can in any wise there take the place of that of the woods and fields, is the power of ancient Architecture. Do not part with it for the sake of the formal square, or of the fenced and planted walk, nor of the goodly street nor opened quay. The pride of a city is not in these. Leave them to the crowd; but remember that there will surely be some within the circuit of the disquieted walls who would ask for some other spots than these wherein to walk; for some other forms to meet their sight familiarly: like him who sat so often where the sun struck from the west, to watch the lines of the dome of Florence drawn on the deep sky, or like those, his Hosts, who could bear daily to behold, from their palace chambers, the places where their fathers lay at rest, at the meeting of the dark streets of Verona.

Notes

1. No, indeed! — any more wasted words than mine throughout life, or bread cast on more bitter waters, I never heard of. This closing paragraph of the sixth chapter is the best, I think, in the book, — and the vainest. [1880.]

————————————————————

* Mit herzlichem Vertrauen … alle Ewigkeit: 'With heartfelt trust | Have Johannes Mooter and Maria Rubi | Had this house built. | The dear God will shield us | From all misfortune and danger | And let it stand in blessedness | On this journey, through this time of sorrow | To the heavenly Paradise | Where all good people dwell, | There will God reward them | With the Crown of Peace | To all eternity.'

Cambridge School of Art: Inaugural Address (1858)

I suppose the persons interested in establishing a School of Art for workmen may in the main be divided into two classes, namely, first, those who chiefly desire to make the men themselves happier, wiser, and better; and secondly, those who desire to enable them to produce better and more valuable work. These two objects may, of course, be kept both in view at the same time; nevertheless, there is a wide difference in the spirit with which we shall approach our task, according to the motive of these two which weighs most with us — a difference great enough to divide, as I have said, the promoters of any such scheme into two distinct classes; one philanthropic in the gist of its aim, and the other commercial in the gist of its aim; one desiring the workman to be better informed chiefly for his own sake, and the other chiefly that he may be enabled to produce for us commodities precious in themselves, and which shall successfully compete with those of other countries.

And this separation in motives must lead also to a distinction in the machinery of the work. The philanthropists address themselves, not to the artisan merely, but to the labourer in general, desiring in any possible way to refine the habits or increase the happiness of our whole working population, by giving them new recreations or new thoughts: and the principles of Arteducation adopted in a school which has this wide but somewhat indeterminate aim, are, or should be, very different from those adopted in a school meant for the special instruction of the artisan in his own business. I do not think this distinction is yet firmly enough fixed in our minds, or calculated upon in our plans of operation. We have hitherto acted, it seems to me, under a vague impression that the arts of drawing and painting might be, up to a certain point, taught in a general way to every one, and would do every one equal good; and that each class of operatives might afterwards bring this general knowledge into use in their own trade, according to its requirements. Now, that is not so. A wood-carver needs for his business to learn drawing in quite a different way from a china-painter, and a jeweller from a worker in iron. They must be led to study quite different characters in the natural forms they introduce in their various manufacture. It is no use to teach an iron-worker to observe the down on a peach, and of none to teach laws of atmospheric effect to a carver in wood. So far as their business is concerned, their brains would be vainly occupied by such things, and they would be prevented from pursuing, with enough distinctness or intensity, the qualities of Art which can alone be expressed in the materials with which they each have to do.

Now, I believe it to be wholly impossible to teach special application of Art principles to various trades in a single school. That special application can be only learned rightly by the experience of years in the particular work required. The power of each material, and the difficulties connected with its treatment, are not so much to be taught as to be felt; it is only by repeated touch and continued trial beside the forge or the furnace, that the goldsmith can find out how to govern his gold, or the glass-worker his crystal; and it is only by watching and assisting the actual practice of a master in the business, that the apprentice can learn the efficient secrets of manipulation, or perceive the true limits of the involved conditions of design. It seems to me, therefore, that all idea of reference to definite businesses should be abandoned in such schools as that just established: we can have neither the materials, the conveniences, nor the empirical skill in the master, necessary to make such teaching useful. All specific Art-teaching must be given in schools established by each trade for itself: and when our operatives are a little more enlightened on these matters, there will be found, as I have already stated in my lectures on the political economy of Art, absolute necessity for the establishment of guilds of trades in an active and practical form, for the purposes of ascertaining the principles of Art proper to their business, and instructing their apprentices in them, as well as making experiments on materials, and on newly invented methods of procedure; besides many other functions which I cannot now enter into account of. All this for the present, and in a school such as this, I repeat, we cannot hope for: we shall obtain no satisfactory result, unless we give up such hope, and set ourselves to teaching the operative, however employed — be he farmer's labourer, or manufacturer's; be he mechanic, artificer, shopman, sailor, or ploughman — teaching, I say, as far as we can, one and the same thing to all; namely, Sight.

Not a slight thing to teach, this: perhaps, on the whole, the most important thing to be taught in the whole range of teaching. To be taught to read — what is the use of that, if you know not whether what you read is false or true? To be taught to write or to speak — but what is the use of speaking, if you have nothing to say? To be taught to think — nay, what is the use of being able to think, if you have nothing to think of? But to be taught to see is to gain word and thought at once, and both true. There is a vague acknowledgment of this in the way people are continually expressing their longing for light, until all the common language of our prayers and hymns has sunk into little more than one monotonous metaphor, dimly twisted into alternate languages, — asking first in Latin to be illuminated; and then in English to be enlightened; and then in Latin again to be delivered out of obscurity; and then in English to be delivered out of darkness; and then for beams, and rays, and suns, and stars, and lamps, until sometimes one wishes that, at least for religious purposes, there were no such words as light or darkness in existence. Still, the main instinct which makes people endure this perpetuity of repetition is a true one; only the main thing they want and ought to ask for is, not light, but Sight. It doesn't matter how much light you have if you don't know how to use it. It may very possibly put out your eyes, instead of helping them. Besides, we want, in this world of ours, very often to be able to see in the dark — that's the great gift of all; — but at any rate to see no matter by what light, so only we can see things as they are. On my word, we should soon make it a different world, if we could get but a little — ever so little — of the dervish's ointment in the Arabian Nights, not to show us the treasures of the earth, but the facts of it.

However, whether these things be generally true or not, at all events it is certain that our immediate business, in such a school as this, will prosper more by attending to eyes than to hands; we shall always do most good by simply endeavouring to enable the student to see natural objects clearly and truly. We ought not even to try too strenuously to give him the power of representing them. That power may be acquired, more or less, by exercises which are no wise conducive to accuracy of sight: and, vice versâ accuracy of sight may be gained by exercises which in no wise conduce to ease of representation. For instance, it very much assists the power of drawing to spend many hours in the practice of washing in flat tints; but all this manual practice does not in the least increase the student's power of determining what the tint of a given object actually is. He would be more advanced in the knowledge of the facts by a single hour of well- directed and well-corrected effort, rubbing out and putting in again, lightening, and darkening, and scratching, and blotching, in patient endeavours to obtain concordance with fact, issuing perhaps, after all, in total destruction or unpresentability of the drawing; but also in acute perception of the things he has been attempting to copy in it. Of course, there is always a vast temptation, felt both by the master and student, to struggle towards visible results, and obtain something beautiful, creditable, or saleable, in way of actual drawing: but the more I see of schools, the more reason I see to look with doubt upon those which produce too many showy and complete works by pupils. A showy work will always be found, on stern examination of it, to have been done by some conventional rule; — some servile compliance with directions which the student does not see the reason for; and representation of truths which he has not himself perceived: the execution of such drawings will be found monotonous and lifeless; their light and shade specious and formal, but false. A drawing which the pupil has learned much in doing, is nearly always full of blunders and mishaps, and it is highly necessary for the formation of a truly public or universal school of Art, that the masters should not try to conceal or anticipate such blunders, but only seek to employ, the pupil's time so as to get the most precious results for his understanding and his heart, not for his hand.

For, observe, the best that you can do in the production of drawing, or of draughtsmanship, must always be nothing in itself, unless the whole life be given to it. An amateur's drawing, or a workman's drawing — anybody's drawing but an artist's, is always valueless in itself. It may be… most precious as a memorial, or as a gift , or as a means of noting useful facts; but as Art, an amateur's drawing is always wholly worthless; and it ought to be one of our great objects to make the pupil understand and feel that, and prevent his trying to make his valueless work look, in some superficial, hypocritical, eye-catching, penny-catching way, like work that is really good.

If, therefore, we have to do with pupils belonging to the higher ranks of life, our main duty will be to make them good judges of Art, rather than artists; for though I had a month to speak to you, instead of an hour, time would fail me if I tried to trace the various ways in which we suffer, nationally, for want of powers of enlightened judgment of Art in our upper and middle classes. Not that this judgment can ever be obtained without discipline of the hand: no man ever was a thorough judge of painting who could not draw; but the drawing should only be thought of as a means of fixing his attention upon the subtleties of the Art put before him, or of enabling him to record such natural facts as are necessary for comparison with it. I should also attach the greatest importance to severe limitation of choice in the examples submitted to him. To study one good master till you understand him will teach you more than a superficial acquaintance with a thousand: power of criticism does not consist in knowing the names or the manner of many painters, but in discerning the excellence of a few.

If, on the contrary, our teaching is addressed more definitely to the operative, we need not endeavour to render his powers of criticism very acute. About many forms of existing Art, the less he knows the better. His sensibilities are to be cultivated with respect to nature chiefly; and his imagination, if possible, to be developed, even though somewhat to the disadvantage of his judgment. It is better that his work should be bold, than faultless: and better that it should be delightful, than discreet.

And this leads me to the second, or commercial, question; namely, how to get from the workman, after we have trained him, the best and most precious work, so as to enable ourselves to compete with foreign countries, or develop new branches of commerce in our own.

Many of us, perhaps, are under the impression that plenty of schooling will do this; that plenty of lecturing will do it; that sending abroad for patterns will do it; or that patience, time, and money, and goodwill may do it. And, alas, none of these things, nor all of them put together, will do it. If you want really good work, such as will be acknowledged by all the world, there is but one way of getting it, and that is a difficult one. You may offer any premium you choose for it — but you will find it can't be done for premiums. You may send for patterns to the antipodes — but you will find it can't be done upon patterns. You may lecture on the principles of Art to every school in the kingdom — and you will find it can't be done upon principles. You may wait patiently for the progress of the age — and you will find your Art is unprogressive. Or you may set yourselves impatiently to urge it by the inventions of the age — and you will find your chariot of Art entirely immovable either by screw or paddle. There's no way of getting good Art, I repeat, but one — at once the simplest and most difficult — namely, to enjoy it. Examine the history of nations, and you will find this great fact clear and unmistakable on the front of it-that good Art has only been produced by nations who rejoiced in it; fed themselves with it, as if it were bread; basked in it, as if it were sunshine; shouted at the sight of it; danced with the delight of it; quarrelled for it; fought for it; starved for it; did, in fact, precisely the opposite with it of what we want to do with it — they made it to keep, and we to sell.

And truly this is a serious difficulty for us as a commerrial nation. The very primary motive with which we set about the business, makes the business impossible. The first and absolute condition of the thing's ever becoming saleable is, that we shall make it without wanting to sell it; nay, rather with a determination not to sell it at any price, if once we get hold of it. Try to make your Art popular, cheap — a fair article for your foreign market; and the foreign market will always show something better. But make it only to please yourselves, and even be resolved that you won't let anybody else have any; and forthwith you will find everybody else wants it. And observe, the insuperable difficulty is this making it to please ourselves, while we are incapable of pleasure. Take, for instance, the simplest example, which we can all understand, in the art of dress. We have made a great fuss about the patterns of silk lately; wanting to vie with Lyons, and make a Paris of London. Well, we may try for ever: so long as we don't really enjoy silk patterns, we shall never get any. And we don't enjoy them. Of course, all ladies like their dresses to sit well, and be becoming; but of real enjoyment of the beauty of the silk, for the silk's own sake, I find none; for the test of that enjoyment is, that they would like it also to sit well, and look well, on somebody else. The pleasure of being well dressed, or even of seeing well-dressed people — for I will suppose in my fair hearers that degree of unselfishness — be that pleasure great or small, is quite a different thing from delight in the beauty and play of the silken folds and colours themselves, for their own gorgeousness or grace.

I have just had a remarkable proof of the total want of this feeling in the modern mind. I was staying part of this summer in Turin, for the purpose of studying one of the Paul Veroneses there — the pre-sentation of the Queen of Sheba to Solomon. Well, one of the most notable characters in this picture is the splendour of its silken dresses: and, in particular, there was a piece of white brocade, with designs upon it in gold, which it was one of my chief objects in stopping at Turin to copy. You may, perhaps, be surprised at this; but I must just note in passing, that I share this weakness of enjoying dress patterns with all good students and all good painters. It doesn't matter what school they belong to, — Fra Angelico, Perugino, John Bellini, Giorgione, Titian, Tintoret, Veronese, Leonardo da Vinci — no matter how they differ in other respects, all of them like dress patterns; and what is more, the nobler the painter is, the surer he is to do his patterns well.

I stayed then, as I say, to make a study of this white brocade. It generally happens in public galleries that the best pictures are the worst placed; and this Veronese is not only hung at considerable height above the eye, but over a door, through which, however, as all the visitors to the gallery must pass, they cannot easily overlook the picture, though they would find great difficulty in examining it. Beside this door, I had a stage erected for my work, which being of some height and rather in a corner, enabled me to observe, without being observed myself, the impression made by the picture on the various visitors. It seemed to me that if ever a work of Art caught popular attention, this ought to do so. It was of very large size; of brilliant colour, and of agreeable subject. There are about twenty figures in it, the principal ones being life size: that of Solomon, though in the shade, is by far the most perfect conception of the young king in his pride of wisdom and beauty which I know in the range of Italian art; the queen is one of the loveliest of Veronese's female figures; all the accessories are full of grace and imagination; and the finish of the whole so perfect that one day I was upwards of two hours vainly trying to render, with perfect accuracy, the curves of two leaves of the brocaded silk. The English travellers used to walk through the room in considerable numbers; and were invariably directed to the picture by their laquais de place, if they missed seeing it themselves. And to this painting — in which it took me six weeks to examine rightly two figures — I found that on an average, the English traveller who was doing Italy conscientiously, and seeing everything as he thought he ought, gave about half or three-quarters of a minute; but the flying or fashionable traveller, who came to do as much as he could in a given time, never gave more than a single glance, most of such people turning aside instantly to a bad landscape hung on the right, containing a vigorously painted white wall, and an opaque green moat. What especially impressed me, however, was that none of the ladies ever stopped to look at the dresses in the Veronese. Certainly they were far more beautiful than any in the shops in the great square, yet no one ever noticed them. Sometimes when any nice, sharp-looking, bright-eyed girl came into the room, I used to watch her all the way, thinking — 'Come, at least you'll see what the Queen of Sheba has got on.' But no — on she would come carelessly, with a little toss of the head, apparently signifying, 'nothing in this room worth looking at — except myself,' and so trip through the door, and away.

The fact is, we don't care for pictures: in very deed we don't. The Academy exhibition is a thing to talk of and to amuse vacant hours; those who are rich amongst us buy a painting or two, for mixed reasons, sometimes to fill the comer of a passage — sometimes to help the drawing-room talk before dinner — sometimes because the painter is fashionable — occasionally because he is poor — not unfrequently that we may have a collection of specimens of painting, as we have specimens of min erals or butterflies — and in the best and rarest case of all, because we have really, as we call it, taken a fancy to the picture; meaning the same sort of fancy which one would take to a pretty arm-chair or a newly-shaped decanter. But as for real love of the picture, and joy of it when we have got it, I do not believe it is felt by one in a thousand.

I am afraid this apathy of ours will not be easily conquered; but even supposing it should, and that we should begin to enjoy pictures properly, and that the supply of good ones increased as in that case it would increase — then comes another question. Perhaps some of my hearers this evening may occasionally have heard it stated of me that I am rather apt to contradict myself. I hope I am exceedingly apt to do so. I never met with a question yet, of any importance, which did not need, for the right solution of it, at least one positive and one negative answer, like an equation of the second degree. Mostly, matters of any consequence are three-sided, or four-sided, or polygonal; and the trotting round a polygon is severe work for people any way stiff in their opinions. For myself, I am never satisfied that I have handled a subject properly till I have contradicted myself at least three times: but once must do for this evening. I have just said that there is no chance of our getting good Art unless we delight in it: next I say, and just as positively, that there is no chance of our getting good Art unless we resist our delight in it. We must love it first, and restrain our love for it afterwards.

This sounds strange; and yet I assure you it is true. In fact, whenever anything does not sound strange, you may generally doubt its being true; for all truth is wonderful. But take an instance in physical matters, of the same kind of contradiction. Suppose you were explaining to a young student in astronomy how the earth was kept steady in its orbit; you would have to state to him — would you not? — that the earth always had a tendency to fall to the sun; and that also it always had a tendency to fly away from the sun. These are two precisely contrary statements for him to digest at his leisure, before he can understand how the earth moves. Now, in like manner, when Art is set in its true and serviceable course, it moves under the luminous attraction of pleasure on the one side, and with a stout moral purpose of going about some useful business on the other. If the artist works without delight, he passes away into space, and perishes of cold: if he works only for delight, he falls into the sun, and extinguishes himself in ashes. On the whole, this last is the fate, I do not say the most to be feared, but which Art has generally hitherto suffered, and which the great nations of the earth have suffered with it.

For, while most distinctly you may perceive in past history that Art has never been produced, except by nations who took pleasure in it, just as assuredly, and even more plainly, you may perceive that Art has always destroyed the power and life of those who pursued it for pleasure only. Surely this fact must have struck you as you glanced at the career of the great nations of the earth: surely it must have occurred to you as a point for serious questioning, how far, even in our days, we were wise in promoting the advancement of pleasures which appeared as yet only to have corrupted the souls and numbed the strength of those who attained to them. I have been complaining of England that she despises the Arts; but I might, with still more appearance of justice, complain that she does not rather dread them than despise. For, what has been the source of the ruin of nations since the world began? Has it been plague, or famine, earthquake-shock or volcano-flame? None of these ever prevailed against a great people, so as to make their name pass from the earth. In every period and place of national decline, you will find other causes than these at work to bring it about, namely, luxury, effeminacy, love of pleasure, fineness in Art, ingenuity in enjoyment. What is the main lesson which, as far as we seek any in our classical reading, we gather for our youth from ancient history? Surely this — that simplicity of life, of language, and of manners gives strength to a nation; and that luxuriousness of life, subtlety of language, and smoothness of manners bring weakness and destruction on a nation. While men possess little and desire less, they remain brave and noble: while they are scornful of all the arts of luxury, and are in the sight of other nations as barbarians, their swords are irresistible and their sway illimitable: but let them become sensitive to the refinements of taste, and quick in the capacities of pleasure, and, that instant, the fingers, that had grasped the iron rod, fail from the golden sceptre. You cannot charge me with any exaggeration in this matter; it is impossible to state the truth too strongly, or as too universal. For ever you will see the rude and simple nation at once more virtuous and more victorious than one practised in the arts. Watch how the Lydian is overthrown by the Persian; the Persian by the Athenian; the Athenian by the Spartan; then the whole of polished Greece by the rougher Roman; the Roman, in his turn refined, only to be crushed by the Goth: and at the turning point of the Middle Ages, the liberty of Europe first asserted, the virtues of Christianity best practised, and its doctrines best attested, by a handful of mountain shepherds, with out art, without literature, almost without a language, yet remaining unconquered in the midst of the Teutonic chivalry, and uncorrupted amidst the hierarchies of Rome…

Now, therefore, the sum of all is, that you who wish to encourage Art in England have to do two things with it: you must delight in it, in the first place; and you must get it to serve some serious work, in the second place. I don't mean by serious, necessarily moral: all that I mean by serious is in some way or other useful, not merely selfish, careless, or indolent. I had, indeed, intended before closing my address, to have traced out a few of the directions in which, as it seems to me, Art may be seriously and practically serviceable to us in the career of civilization. I had hoped to show you how many of the great phenomena of nature still remained unrecorded by it, for us to record; how many of the historical monuments of Europe were perishing without memorial, for the want of but a little honest, simple, laborious, loving draughtsmanship; how many of the most impressive historical events of the day failed of teaching us half of what they were meant to teach, for want of painters to represent them faithfully, instead of fancifully, and with historical truth for their aim, instead of national self-glorification. I had hoped to show you how many of the best impulses of the heart were lost in frivolity or sensuality, for want of purer beauty to contemplate, and of noble thoughts to associate with the fervour of hallowed human passion; how, finally, a great part of the vital power of our religious faith was lost in us, for want of such art as would realize in some rational, probable, believable way, those events of sacred history which, as they visibly and intelligibly occurred, may also be visibly and intelligibly represented. But all this I dare not do yet. I felt, as I thought over these things, that the time was not yet come for their declaration: the time will come for it, and I believe soon; but as yet, the man would only lay himself open to the charge of vanity, of imagination, and of idle fondness of hope, who should venture to trace in words the course of the higher blessings which the Arts may have yet in store for mankind. As yet there is no need to do so: all that we have to plead for is an earnest and straightforward exertion in those courses of study which are opened to us day by day, believing only that they are to be followed gravely and for grave purposes, as by men, and not by children. I appeal, finally, to all those who are to become the pupils of these schools, to keep clear of the notion of following Art as dilettantism: it ought to delight you, as your reading delights you — but you never think of your reading as dilettantism. It ought to delight you as your studies of physical science delight you — but you don't call physical science dilettantism. If you are determined only to think of Art as a play or a pleasure, give it up at once: you will do no good to yourselves, and you will degrade the pursuit in the sight of others. Better, infinitely better, that you should never enter a picture gallery, than that you should enter only to saunter and to smile: better, infinitely better, that you should never handle a pencil at all, than handle it only for the sake of complacency in your small dexterity: better, infinitely better, that you should be wholly uninterested in pictures, and uninformed respecting them, than that you should just know enough to detect blemishes in great works, — to give a colour of reasonableness to presumption, and an appearance of acuteness to misunderstanding. Above all, I would plead for this so far as the teaching of these schools may be addressed to the junior Members of the University. Men employed in any kind of manual labour, by which they must live, are not likely to take up the notion that they can learn any other art for amusement only; but amateurs are: and it is of the highest importance, nay, it is just the one thing of all importance, to show them what drawing really means; and not so much to teach them to produce a good work themselves, as to know it when they see it done by others. Good work, in the stern sense of the word, as I before said, no mere amateur can do; and good work, in sense, that is to say, profitable work for himself or for any one else, he can only do by being made in the beginning to see what is possible for him, and what not; — what is accessible, and what not; and by having the majesty and sternness of the everlasting laws of fact set before him in their infinitude. It is no matter for appalling him: the man is great already who is made well capable of being appalled; nor do we even wisely hope, nor truly understand, till we are humiliated by our hope, and awe-struck by our understanding. Nay, I will go farther than this, and say boldly, that what you have mainly to teach the young men here is, not so much what they can do, as what they cannot; — to make them see how much there is in nature which cannot be imitated, and how much in man which cannot be emulated. He only can be truly said to be educated in Art to whom all his work is only a feeble sign of glories which he cannot convey, and a feeble means of measuring, with ever enlarging admiration, the great and untraversable gulf which God has set between the great and the common intelligences of mankind: and all the triumphs of Art which man can commonly achieve are only truly crowned by pure delight in natural scenes themselves, and by the sacred and self-forgetful veneration which can be nobly abashed, and tremblingly exalted, in the presence of a human spirit greater than his own.

Traffic

Delivered in the Town Hall, Bradford
[April 21, 1864]

My good Yorkshire friends, you asked me down here among your hills that I might talk to you about this Exchange you are going to build: but, earnestly and seriously asking you to pardon me, I am going to do nothing of the kind. I cannot talk, or at least can say very little, about this same Exchange. I must talk of quite other things, though not willingly; — I could not deserve your pardon, if, when you invited me to speak on one subject, I wilfully spoke on another. But I cannot speak, to purpose, of anything about which I do not care; and most simply and sorrowfully I have to tell you, in the outset, that I do not care about this Exchange of yours.

If, however, when you sent me your invitation, I had answered, 'I won't come, I don't care about the Exchange of Bradford,' you would have been justly offended with me, not knowing the reasons of so blunt a carelessness. So I have come down, hoping that you will patiently let me tell you why, on this, and many other such occasions, I now remain silent, when formerly I should have caught at the opportunity of speaking to a gracious audience.

In a word, then, I do not care about this Exchange — because you don't; and because you know perfectly well I cannot make you. Look at the essential conditions of the case, which you, as business men, know perfectly well, though perhaps you think I forget them. You are going to spend £30,000, which to you, collectively, is nothing; the buying a new coat is, as to the cost of it, a much more important matter of consideration to me, than building a new Exchange is to you. But you think you may as well have the right thing for your money. You know there are a great many odd styles of architecture about; you don't want to do anything ridiculous; you hear of me, among others, as a respectable architectural man-milliner; and you send for me, that I may tell you the leading fashion; and what is, in our shops, for the moment, the newest and sweetest thing in pinnacles.

Now, pardon me for telling you frankly, you cannot have good architecture merely by asking people's advice on occasion. All good architecture is the expression of national life and character; and it is produced by a prevalent and eager national taste, or desire for beauty. And I want you to think a little of the deep significance of this word 'taste'; for no statement of mine has been more earnestly or oftener controverted than that good taste is essentially a moral quality. 'No,' say many of my antagonists, 'taste is one thing, morality is another. Tell us what is pretty: we shall be glad to know that; but we need no sermons — even were you able to preach them, which may be doubted. '

Permit me, therefore, to fortify this old dogma of mine somewhat. Taste is not only a part and an index of morality; — it is the only morality. The first, and last, and closest trial question to any living creature is, 'What do you like?' Tell me what you like, and I'll tell you what you are. Go out into the street, and ask the first man or woman you meet, what their 'taste' is; and if they answer candidly, you know them, body and soul. 'You, my friend in the rags, with the unsteady gait, what do you like?' 'A pipe, and a quartern of gin.' I know you. 'You, good woman, with the quick step and tidy bonnet, what do you like?' 'A swept hearth, and a dean tea-table; and my husband opposite me, and a baby at my breast.' Good, I know you also. 'You, little girl with the golden hair and the soft eyes, what do you like?' 'My canary, and a run among the wood hyacinths.' 'You, little boy with the dirty hands, and the low forehead, what do you like?' 'A shy at the sparrows, and a game at pitch farthing.' Good; we know them all now. What more need we ask?

'Nay,' perhaps you answer; 'we need rather to ask what these people and children do, than what they like. If they do fight, it is no matter that they like what is wrong; and if they do wrong, it is no matter that they like what is fight. Doing is the great thing; and it does not matter that the man likes drinking, so that he does not drink; nor that the little girl likes to be kind to her canary, if she will not learn her lessons; nor that the little boy likes throwing stones at the sparrows, if he goes to the Sunday school.' Indeed, for a short time, and in a provisional sense, this is true. For if, resolutely, people do what is fight, in time to come they like doing it. But they only are in a right moral state when they have come to like doing it; and as long as they don't like it, they are still in a vicious state. The man is not in health of body who is always thinking of the bottle in the cupboard, though he bravely bears his thirst; but the man who heartily enjoys water in the morning, and wine in the evening, each in its proper quantity and time. And the entire object of true education is to make people not merely do the fight things, but enjoy the right things: — not merely industrious, but to love industry — not merely learned, but to love knowledge — not merely pure, but to love purity — not merely just, but to hunger and thirst after justice.

But you may answer or think, 'Is the liking for outside ornaments, — for pictures, or statues, or furniture, or architecture, a moral quality?' Yes, most surely, if a rightly set liking. Taste for any pictures or statues is not a moral quality, but taste for good ones is. Only here again we have to define the word 'good.' I don't mean by 'good,' clever — or learned — or difficult in the doing. Take a picture by Teniers, of sots quarrelling over their dice; it is an entirely clever picture; so clever that nothing in its kind has ever been done equal to it; but it is also an entirely base and evil picture. It is an expression of delight in the prolonged contemplation of a vile thing, and delight in that is an 'unmannered,' or 'immoral' quality. It is 'bad taste' in the profoundest sense — it is the taste of the devils. On the other hand, a picture of Titian's, or a Greek statue, or a Greek coin, or a Turner landscape, expresses delight in the perpetual contemplation of a good and perfect thing. That is an entirely moral quality — it is the taste of the angels. And all delight in fine art, and all love of it, resolve themselves into simple love of that which deserves love. That deserving is the quality which we call 'loveliness' — (we ought to have an opposite word, hateliness, to be said of the things which deserve to be hated); and it is not an indifferent nor optional thing whether we love this or that; but it is just the vital function of all our being. What we like determines what we are, and is the sign of what we are; and to teach taste is inevitably to form character.

As I was thinking over this, in walking up Fleet Street the other day, my eye caught the title of a book standing open in a bookseller's window. It was — On the necessity of the diffusion of taste among all classes. 'Ah,' I thought to myself, 'my classifying friend, when you have diffused your taste, where will your classes be? The man who likes what you like, belongs to the same class with you, I think. Inevitably so. You may put him to other work if you choose; but, by the condition you have brought him into, he will dislike the work as much as you would yourself. You get hold of a scavenger or a costermonger, who enjoyed the Newgate Calendar for literature, and "Pop goes the Weasel" for music. You think you can make him like Dante and Beethoven? I wish you joy of your lessons; but if you do, you have made a gentleman of him: — he won't like to go back to his costermongering. '

And so completely and unexceptionally is this so, that, if I had time to-night, I could show you that a nation cannot be affected by any vice, or weakness, without expressing it, legibly, and for ever, either in bad art, or by want of art; and that there is no national virtue, small or great, which is not manifestly expressed in all the art which circumstances enable the people possessing that virtue to produce. Take, for instance, your great English virtue of enduring and patient courage. You have at present in England only one art of any consequence — that is, iron-working. You know thoroughly well how to cast and hammer iron. Now, do you think, in those masses of lava which you build volcanic cones to melt, and which you forge at the mouths of the Infernos you have created; do you think, on those iron plates, your courage and endurance are not written for ever, — not merely with an iron pen, but on iron parchment? And take also your great English vice — European vice — vice of all the world — vice of all other worlds that roll or shine in heaven, bearing with them yet the atmosphere of hell — the vice of jealousy, which brings competition into your commerce, treachery into your councils, and dishonour into your wars — that vice which has rendered for you, and for your next neighbouring nation, the daily occupations of existence no longer possible, but with the mail upon your breasts and the sword loose in its sheath; so that at last, you have realized for all the multitudes of the two great peoples who lead the so-called civilization of the earth, — you have realized for them all, I say, in person and in policy, what was once true only of the rough Border riders of your Cheviot hills —

'They carved at the meal

With gloves of steel, 　

And they drank the red wine through the helmet barr'd;' —

do you think that this national shame and dastardliness of heart are not written as legibly on every rivet of your iron armour as the strength of the right hands that forged it?

Friends, I know not whether this thing be the more ludicrous or the more melancholy. It is quite unspeakably both. Suppose, instead of being now sent for by you, I had been sent for by some private gentleman, living in a suburban house, with his garden separated only by a fruit wall from his next door neighbour's; and he had called me to consult with him on the furnishing of his drawing-room. I begin looking about me, and find the walls rather bare; I think such and such a paper might be desirable — perhaps a little fresco here and there on the ceiling — a damask curtain or so at the windows. 'Ah,' says my employer, 'damask curtains, indeed! That's all very fine, but you know I can't afford that kind of thing just now!' 'Yet the world credits you with a splendid income!' 'Ah, yes,' says my friend, 'but do you know, at present I am obliged to spend it nearly all in steel-traps?' 'Steel-traps! for whom?' 'Why, for that fellow on the other side the wall, you know: we're very good friends, capital friends; but we are obliged to keep our traps set on both sides of the wall; we could not possibly keep on friendly terms without them, and our spring guns. The worst of it is, we are both dever fellows enough; and there's never a day passes that we don't find out a new trap, or a new gunbarrel, or something; we spend about fifteen millions a year each in our traps, take it altogether; and I don't see how we're to do with less.' A highly comic state of life for two private gentlemen! but for two nations, it seems to me, not wholly comic. Bedlam would be comic, perhaps, if there were only one madman in it; and your Christmas pantomime is comic, when there is only one clown in it; but when the whole world turns clown, and paints itself red with its own heart's blood instead of vermilion, it is something else than comic, I think.

Mind, I know a great deal of this is play, and willingly allow for that. You don't know what to do with yourselves for a sensation: fox-hunting and cricketing will not carry you through the whole of this unendurably long mortal life: you liked pop-guns when you were schoolboys, and rifles and Armstrongs are only the same things better made: but then the worst of it is, that what was play to you when boys, was not play to the sparrows; and what is play to you now, is not play to the small birds of State neither; and for the black eagles, you are somewhat shy of taking shots at them, if I mistake not.

I must get back to the matter in hand, however. Believe me, without farther instance, I could show you, in all time, that every nation's vice, or virtue, was written in its art: the soldiership of early Greece; the sensuality of late Italy; the visionary religion of Tuscany; the splendid human energy of Venice. I have no time to do this to-night (I have done it elsewhere before now); but I proceed to apply the principle to ourselves in a more searching manner.

I notice that among all the new buildings which cover your once wild hills, churches and schools are mixed in due, that is to say, in large proportion, with your mills and mansions; and I notice also that the churches and schools are almost always Gothic, and the mansions and mills are never Gothic. May I ask the meaning of this? for, remember, it is peculiarly a modem phenomenon. When Gothic was invented, houses were Gothic as well as churches; and when the Italian style superseded the Gothic, churches were Italian as well as houses. If there is a Gothic spire to the cathedral of Antwerp, there is a Gothic belfry to the Hôtel de Ville at Brussels; if Inigo Jones builds an Italian Whitehall, Sir Christopher Wren builds an Italian St Paul's. But now you live under one school of architecture, and worship under another. What do you mean by doing this? Am I to understand that you are thinking of changing your architecture back to Gothic; and that you treat your churches experimentally, because it does not matter what mistakes you make in a church? Or am I to understand that you consider Gothic a pre-eminently sacred and beautiful mode of building, which you think, like the fine frankincense, should be mixed for the tabernacle only, and reserved for your religious services? For if this be the feeling, though it may seem at first as if it were graceful and reverent, at the root of the matter, it signifies neither more nor less than that you have separated your religion from your life.

For consider what a wide significance this fact has; and remember that it is not you only, but all the people of England, who are behaving thus, just now.

You have all got into the habit of calling the church 'the house of God.' I have seen, over the doors of many churches, the legend actually carved, 'This is the house of God and this is the gate of heaven.' Now, note where that legend comes from, and of what place it was first spoken. A boy leaves his father's house to go on a long journey on foot, to visit his uncle: he has to cross a wild hill-desert; just as if one of your own boys had to cross the wolds to visit an uncle at Carlisle. The second or third day your boy finds himself somewhere between Hawes and Brough, in the midst of the moors, at sunset. It is stony ground, and boggy; he cannot go one foot farther that night. Down he lies, to sleep, on Wharnside, where best he may, gathering a few of the stones together to put under his head; — so wild the place is, he cannot get anything but stones. And there, lying under the broad night, he has a dream; and he sees a ladder set up on the earth, and the top of it reaches to heaven, and the angels of God are seen ascending and descending upon it. And when he wakes out of his sleep, he says, 'How dreadful is this place; surely this is none other than the house of God, and this is the gate of heaven.' This Place, observe; not this church; not this city; not this stone, even, which he puts up for a memorial — the piece of flint on which his head was lain. But this place; this windy slope of Wharnside; this moorland hollow, torrent-bitten, snow blighted! this any place where God lets down the ladder. And how are you to know where that will be? or how are you to determine where it may be, but by being ready for it always? Do you know where the lightning is to fall next? You do know that, partly; you can guide the lightning; but you cannot guide the going forth of the Spirit, which is as that lightning when it shines from the east to the west.

But the perpetual and insolent warping of that strong verse to serve a merely ecclesiastical purpose, is only one of the thousand instances in which we sink back into gross Judaism. We call our churches 'temples.' Now, you know perfectly well they are not temples. They have never had, never can have, anything whatever to do with temples. They are 'synagogues' — 'gathering places' -where you gather yourselves together as an assembly; and by not calling them so, you again miss the force of another mighty text — 'Thou, when thou prayest, shalt not be as the hypocrites are; for they love to pray standing in the churches' [we should translate it], 'that they may be seen of men. But thou, when thou prayest, enter into thy closet, and when thou hast shut thy door, pray to thy Father,' — which is, not in chancel nor in aisle, but 'in secret.'

Now, you feel, as I say this to you — I know you feel — as if I were trying to take away the honour of your churches. Not so; I am trying to prove to you the honour of your houses and your hills; not that the Church is not sacred — but that the whole Earth is. I would have you feel what careless, what constant, what infectious sin there is in all modes of thought, whereby, in calling your churches only 'holy,' you call your hearths and homes 'profane'; and have separated yourselves from the heathen by casting all your household gods to the ground, instead of recognizing, in the places of their many and feeble Lares, the presence of your One and Mighty Lord and Lat.

'But what has all this to do with our Exchange?' you ask me, impatiently. My dear friends, it has just everything to do with it; on these inner and great questions depend all the outer and little ones; and if you have asked me down here to speak to you, because you had before been interested in anything I have written, you must know that all I have yet said about architecture was to show this. The book I called The Seven Lamps was to show that certain right states of temper and moral feeling were the magic powers by which all good architecture, without exception, had been produced. The Stones of Venice had, from beginning to end, no other aim than to show that the Gothic architecture of Venice had arisen out of, and indicated in all its features, a state of pure national faith, and of domestic virtue; and that its Renaissance architecture had arisen out of, and in all its features indicated, a state of concealed national infidelity, and of domestic corruption. And now, you ask me what style is best to build in, and how can I answer, knowing the meaning of the two styles, but by another question — do you mean to build as Christians or as infidels? And still more — do you mean to build as honest Christians or as honest Infidels? as thoroughly and confessedly either one or the other? You don't like to be asked such rude questions. I cannot help it; they are of much more importance than this Exchange business; and if they can be at once answered, the Exchange business settles itself in a moment. But before I press them farther, I must ask leave to explain one point clearly.

In all my past work, my endeavour has been to show that good architecture is essentially religious — the production of a faithful and virtuous, not of an infidel and corrupted people. But in the course of doing this, I have had also to show that good architecture is not ecclesiastical. People are so apt to look upon religion as the business of the clergy, not their own, that the moment they hear of anything depending on 'religion,' they think it must also have depended on the priesthood; and I have had to take what place was to be occupied between these two errors, and fight both, often with seeming contradiction. Good architecture is the work of good and believing men; therefore, you say, at least some people 'say, 'Good architecture must essentially have been the work of the clergy, not of the laity.' No — a thousand times no; good architecture has always been the work of the commonalty, not of the clergy. 'What,' you say, 'those glorious cathedrals — the pride of Europe — did their builders not form Gothic architecture?' No; they corrupted Gothic architecture. Gothic was formed in the baron's castle, and the burgher's street. It was formed by the thoughts, and hands, and powers of labouring citizens and warrior kings. By the monk it was used as an instrument for the aid of his superstition: when that superstition became a beautiful madness, and the best hearts of Europe vainly dreamed and pined in the cloister, and vainly raged and perished in the crusade, — through that fury of perverted faith and wasted war, the Gothic rose also to its loveliest, most fantastic, and, finally, most foolish dreams; and in those dreams was lost.

I hope, now, that there is no risk of your misunderstanding me when I come to the gist of what I want to say to-night; — when I repeat, that every great national architecture has been the result and exponent of a great national religion. You can't have bits of it here, bits there — you must have it everywhere or nowhere. It is not the monopoly of a clerical company — it is not the exponent of a theological dogma- it is not the hieroglyphic writing of an initiated priesthood; it is the manly language of a people inspired by resolute and common purpose, and rendering resolute and common fidelity to the legible laws of an undoubted God.

Now there have as yet been three distinct schools of European architecture. I say, European, because Asiatic and African architectures belong so entirely to other races and climates, that there is no question of them here; only, in passing, I will simply assure you that whatever is good or great in Egypt, and Syria, and India, is just good or great for the same reasons as the buildings on our side of the Bosphorus. We Europeans, then, have had three great religions: the Greek, which was the worship of the God of Wisdom and Power; the Mediæval, which was the worship of the God of Judgment and Consolation; the Renaissance, which was the worship of the God of Pride and Beauty: these three we have had — they are past, — and now, at last, we English have got a fourth religion, and a God of our own, about which I want to ask you. But I must explain these three old ones first.

I repeat, first, the Greeks essentially worshipped the God of Wisdom; so that whatever contended against their religion, — to the Jews a stumbling-block, — was, to the Greeks — Foolishness.

The first Greek idea of deity was that expressed in the word, of which we keep the remnant in our words 'Di-umal' and 'Di-vine' — the god of Day, Jupiter the revealer. Athena is his daughter, but especially daughter of the Intellect, springing armed from the head. We are only with the help of recent investigation beginning to penetrate the depth of meaning couched under the Athenaic symbols: but I may note rapidly, that her ægis, the mantle with the serpent fringes, in which she often, in the best statues, is represented as folding up her left hand, for better guard; and the Gorgon, on her shield, are both representative mainly of the chilling horror and sadness (turning men to stone, as it were,) of the outmost and superficial spheres of knowledge — that knowledge which separates, in bitterness, hardness, and sorrow, the heart of the full-grown man from the heart of the child. For out of imperfect knowledge spring terror, dissension, danger, and disdain; but from perfect knowledge, given by the full-revealed Athena, strength and peace, in sign of which she is crowned with the olive spray, and bears the resistless spear.

This, then, was the Greek conception of purest Deity; and every habit of life, and every form of his art developed themselves from the seeking this bright, serene, resistless wisdom; and setting himself, as a man, to do things evermore rightly and strongly; I not with any ardent affection or ultimate hope; but with a resolute and continent energy of will, as knowing that for failure there was no consolation, and for sin there was no remission. And the Greek architecture rose unerring, bright, dearly defined, and self-contained.

Next followed in Europe the great Christian faith, which was essentially the religion of Comfort. Its great doctrine is the remission of sins; for which cause, it happens, too often, in certain phases of Christianity, that sin and sickness themselves are partly glorified, as if, the more you had to be healed of, the more divine was the healing. The practical result of this doctrine, in art, is a continual contemplation of sin and disease, and of imaginary states of purification from them; thus we have an architecture conceived in a mingled sentiment of melancholy and aspiration, partly severe, partly luxuriant, which will bend itself to every one of our needs, and every one of our fancies, and be strong or weak with us, as we are strong or weak ourselves. It is, of all architecture, the basest, when base people build it — of all, the noblest, when built by the noble.

And now note that both these religions — Greek and Mediæval — perished by falsehood in their own main purpose. The Greek religion of Wisdom perished in a false philosophy — 'Oppositions of science, falsely so called.'^1 The Mediæval religion of Consolation perished in false comfort; in remission of sins given lyingly. It was the selling of absolution that ended the Mediæval faith; and I can tell you more, it is the selling of absolution which, to the end of time, will mark false Christianity. Pure Christianity gives her remission of sins only by ending them; but false Christianity gets her remission of sins by compounding for them. And there are many ways of compounding for them. We English have beautiful little quiet ways of buying absolution, whether in low Church or high, far more cunning than any of Tetzel's trading.

Then, thirdly, there followed the religion of Pleasure, in which all Europe gave itself to luxury, ending in death. First, bals masqués in every saloon, and then guillotines in every square. And all these three worships issue in vast temple building. Your Greek worshipped Wisdom, and built you the Parthenon — the Virgin's temple. The Mediæval worshipped Consolation, and built you Virgin temples also — but to our Lady of Salvation. Then the Revivalist worshipped beauty, of a sort, and built you Versailles and the Vatican. Now, lastly, will you tell me what we worship, and what we build?

You know we are speaking always of the real, active, continual, national worship; that by which men act, while they live; not that which they talk of, when they die. Now, we have, indeed, a nominal religion, to which we pay tithes of property and sevenths of time; but we have also a practical and earnest religion, to which we devote nine-tenths of our property, and six-sevenths of our time. And we dispute a great deal about the nominal religion: but we are all unanimous about this practical one; of which I think you will admit that the ruling goddess may be best generally described as the 'God dess of Getting-on,' or 'Britannia of the Market.' The Athenians had an 'Athena Agoraia,' or Athena of the Market; but she was a subordinate type of their goddess, while our Britannia Agoraia is the principal type of ours. And all your great architectural works are, of course, built to her. It is long since you built a great cathedral; and how you would laugh at me if I proposed building a cathedral on the top of one of these hills of yours, to make it an Acropolis! But your railroad mounds, vaster than the walls of Babylon; your railroad stations, vaster than the temple of Ephesus, and innumerable; your chimneys, how much more mighty and costly than cathedral spires! your harbour-piers; your warehouses; your exchanges! — all these are built to your great God dess of 'Getting-on'; and she has formed, and will continue to form, your architecture, as long as you worship her; and it is quite vain to ask me to tell you how to build to her; you know far better than I.

There might, indeed, on some theories, be a conceivably good architecture for Exchanges — that is to say, if there were any heroism in the fact or deed of exchange, which might be typically carved on the outside of your building. For, you know, all beautiful architecture must be adorned with sculpture or painting; and for sculpture or painting, you must have a subject. And hitherto it has been a received opinion among the nations of the world that the only right subjects for either, were heroisms of some sort. Even on his pots and his flagons, the Greek put a Hercules slaying lions, or an Apollo slaying serpents, or Bacchus slaying melancholy giants, and earthborn despondencies. On his temples, the Greek put contests of great warriors in founding states, or of gods with evil spirits. On his houses and temples alike, the Christian put carvings of angels conquering devils; or of hero-martyrs exchanging this world for another: subject inappropriate, I think, to our direction of exchange here. And the Master of Christians not only left His followers without any orders as to the sculpture of affairs of exchange on the outside of buildings, but gave some strong evidence of His dislike of affairs of exchange within them. And yet there might surely be a heroism in such affairs; and all commerce become a kind of selling of doves, not impious. The wonder has always been great to me, that heroism has never been supposed to be in anywise consistent with the practice of supplying people with food, or dothes, but rather with that of quartering one's self upon them for food, and stripping them of their clothes. Spoiling of armour is an heroic deed in all ages; but the selling of clothes, old, or new, has never taken any colour of magnanimity. Yet one does not see why feeding the hungry and clothing the naked should ever become base businesses, even when engaged in on a large scale. If one could contrive to attach the notion of conquest to them anyhow! so that, supposing there were anywhere an obstinate race, who refused to be comforted, one might take some pride in giving them compulsory comfort!^2 and, as it were, 'occupying a country' with one's gifts, instead of one's armies? If one could only consider it as much a victory to get a barren field sown, as to get an eared field stripped; and contend who should build villages, instead of who should 'carry' them! Are not all forms of heroism conceivable in doing these serviceable deeds? You doubt who is strongest? It might be ascertained by push of spade, as well as push of sword. Who is wisest? There are witty things to be thought of in planning other business than campaigns. Who is bravest? There are always the elements to fight with, stronger than men; and nearly as merciless.

The only absolutely and unapproachably heroic element in the soldier's work seems to be — that he is paid little for it — and regularly: while you traffickers, and exchangers, and others occupied in presumably benevolent business, like to be paid much for it — and by chance. I never can make out how it is that a knight-errant does not expect to be paid for his trouble, but a pedlar — errant always does; — that people are willing to take hard knocks for nothing, but never to sell ribands cheap; that they are ready to go on fervent crusades, to recover the tomb of a buried God, but never on any travels to fulfil the orders of a living one; — that they will go anywhere barefoot to preach their faith, but must be well bribed to practise it, and are perfectly ready to give the Gospel grafts, but never the loaves and fishes.^3

If you chose to take the matter up on any such soldierly principle; to do your commerce, and your feeding of nations, for fixed salaries; and to be as particular about giving people the best food, and the best doth, as soldiers are about giving them the best gunpowder, I could carve something for you on your exchange worth looking at. But I can only at present suggest decorating its frieze with pendant purses; and making its pillars broad at the base, for the sticking of bills. And in the innermost chambers of it there might be a statue of Britannia of the Market, who may have, perhaps advisably, a partridge for her crest, typical at once of her courage in fighting for noble ideas, and of her interest in game; and round its neck, the inscription in golden letters, 'Perdix fovit quæ non peperit.'^4 Then, for her spear, she might have a weaver's beam; and on her shield, instead of St George's Cross, the Milanese boar, semi-fleeced, with the town of Gennesaret proper, in the field; and the legend, 'In the best market,'^5 and her corslet, of leather, folded over her heart in the shape of a purse, with thirty slits in it, for a piece of money to go in at, on each day of the month. And I doubt not but that people would come to see your exchange, and its goddess, with applause.

Nevertheless, I want to point out to you certain strange characters in this goddess of yours. She differs from the great Greek and Medieval deities essentially in two things — first, as to the continuance of her presumed power; secondly, as to the extent of it.

1st, as to the Continuance.

The Greek Goddess of Wisdom gave continual increase of wisdom, as the Christian Spirit of Comfort (or Comforter) continual increase of comfort. There was no question, with these, of any limit or cessation of function. But with your Agora Goddess, that is just the most important question. Getting on — but where to? Gathering together — but how much? Do you mean to gather always — never to spend? If so, I wish you joy of your goddess, for I am just as well off as you, without the trouble of worshipping her at all. But if you do not spend, somebody else will — somebody else must. And it is because of this (among many other such errors) that I have fearlessly dedared your so-called science of Political Economy to be no science; because, namely, it has omitted the study of exactly the most important branch of the business — the study of spending. For spend you must, and as much as you make, ultimately. You gather corn: — will you bury England under a heap of grain; or will you, when you have gathered, finally eat? You gather gold: — will you make your house-roofs of it, or pave your streets with it? That is still one way of spending it. But if you keep it, that you may get more, I'll give you more; I'll give you all the gold you want — all you can imagine — if you can tell me what you'll do with it. You shall have thousands of gold pieces; — thousands of thousands — millions — mountains, of gold: where will you keep them? Will you put an Olympus of silver upon a golden Pelion — make Ossa like a wart? Do you think the rain and dew would then come down to you, in the streams from such mountains, more blessedly than they will down the mountains which God has made for you, of moss and whinstone? But it is not gold that you want to gather! What is it? greenbacks? No; not those neither. What is it then — is it ciphers after a capital I? Cannot you practise writing ciphers, and write as many as you want! Write ciphers for an hour every morning, in a big book, and say every evening, I am worth all those noughts more than I was yesterday. Won't that do? Well, what in the name of Plutus is it you want? Not gold, not greenbacks, not ciphers after a capital I? You will have to answer, after all, 'No; we want, somehow or other, money's worth.' Well, what is that? Let your Goddess of Getting-on discover it, and let her learn to stay therein.

II. But there is yet another question to be asked respecting this Goddess of Getting-on. The first was of the continuance of her power; the second is of its extent.

Pallas and the Madonna were supposed to be all the world's Pallas, and all the world's Madonna. They could teach all men, and they could comfort all men. But, look strictly into the nature of the power of your Goddess of Getting-on; and you will find she is the Goddess — not of everybody's getting on — but only of somebody's getting on. This is a vital, or rather deathful, distinction. Examine it in your own ideal of the state of national life which this Goddess is to evoke and maintain. I asked you what it was, when I was last here; — you have never told me. Now, shall I try to tell you?

Your ideal of human life then is, I think, that it should be passed in a pleasant undulating world, with iron and coal everywhere underneath it. On each pleasant bank of this world is to be a beautiful mansion, with two wings; and stables, and coach-houses; a moderately-sized park; a large garden and hot-houses; and pleasant carriage drives through the shrubberies. In this mansion are to live the favoured votaries of the Goddess; the English gentleman, with his gracious wife, and his beautiful family; he always able to have the boudoir and the jewels for the wife, and the beautiful ball dresses for the daughters, and hunters for the sons, and a shooting in the Highlands for himself. At the bottom of the bank, is to be the mill; not less than a quarter of a mile long, with one steam engine at each end, and two in the middle, and a chimney three hundred feet high. In this mill are to be in constant employment from eight hundred to a thousand workers, who never drink, never strike, always go to church on Sunday, and always express themselves in respectful language.

Is not that, broadly, and in the main features, the kind of thing you propose to yourselves? It is very pretty indeed, seen from above; not at all so pretty, seen from below. For, observe, while to one family this deity is indeed the Goddess of Getting-on, to a thousand families she is the Goddess of not Getting-on. 'Nay,' you say, 'they have all their chance.' Yes, so has every one in a lottery, but there must always be the same number of blanks. 'Ah! but in a lottery it is not skill and intelligence which take the lead, but blind chance.' What then! do you think the old practice, that 'they should take who have the power, and they should keep who can, ' is less iniquitous, when the power has become power of brains instead of fist? and that, though we may not take advantage of a child's or a woman's weakness, we may of a man's foolishness? 'Nay, but finally, work must be done, and some one must be at the top, someone at the bottom.' Granted, my friends. Work must always be, and captains of work must always be; and if you in the least remember the tone of any of my writings, you must know that they are thought unfit for this age, because they are always insisting on need of government, and speaking with scorn of liberty. But I beg you to observe that there is a wide difference between being captains or governors of work, and taking the profits of it. It does not follow, because you are general of an army, that you are to take all the treasure, or land, it wins; (if it fight for treasure or land;) neither, because you are king of a nation, that you are to consume all the profits of the nation's work. Real kings, on the contrary, are known invariably by their doing quite the reverse of this, — by their taking the least possible quantity of the nation's work for themselves. There is no test of real kinghood so infallible as that. Does the crowned creature live simply, bravely, unostentatiously? probably he is a King. Does he cover his body with jewels, and his table with delicates? in all probability he is not a King. It is possible he may be, as Solomon was; but that is when the nation shares his splendour with him. Solomon made gold, not only to be in his own palace as stones, but to be in Jerusalem as stones. But, even so, for the most part, these splendid kinghoods expire in ruin, and only the true kinghoods live, which are of royal labourers governing loyal labourers; who, both leading rough lives, establish the true dynasties. Condusively you will find that because you are king of a nation, it does not follow that you are to gather for yourself all the wealth of that nation; neither, because you are king of a small part of the nation, and lord over the means of its maintenance — over field, or mill, or mine, — are you to take all the produce of that piece of the foundation of national existence for yourself.

You will tell me I need not preach against these things, for I cannot mend them. No, good friends, I cannot; but you can, and you will; or something else can and will. Even good things have no abiding power — and shall these evil things persist in victorious evil? All history shows, on the contrary, that to be the exact thing they never can do. Change must come; but it is ours to determine whether change of growth, or change of death. Shall the Parthenon be in ruins on its rock, and Bolton priory in its meadow, but these mills of yours be the consummation of the buildings of the earth, and their wheels be as the wheels of eternity? Think you that 'men may come, and men may go, ' but — mills — go on forever? Not so; out of these, better or worse shall come; and it is for you to choose which.

I know that none of this wrong is done with deliberate purpose. I know, on the contrary, that you wish your workmen well; that you do much for them, and that you desire to do more for them, if you saw your way to such benevolence safely. I know that even all this wrong and misery are brought about by a warped sense of duty, each of you striving to do his best; but, unhappily, not knowing for whom this best should be done. And all our hearts have been betrayed by the plausible impiety of the modem economist, telling us that, 'To do the best for ourselves, is finally to do the best for others. ' Friends, our great Master said not so; and most absolutely we shall find this world is not made so. Indeed, to do the best for others, is finally to do the best for ourselves; but it will not do to have our eyes fixed on that issue. The Pagans had got beyond that. Hear what a Pagan says of this matter; hear what were, perhaps, the last written words of Plato, — if not the last actually written (for this we cannot know), yet assuredly in fact and power his parting words — in which, endeavouring to give full crowning and harmonious close to all his thoughts, and to speak the sum of them by the imagined sentence of the Great Spirit, his strength and his heart fail him, and the words cease, broken off for ever.

They are at the dose of the dialogue called Critias, in which he describes, partly from real tradition, partly in ideal dream, the early state of Athens; and the genesis, and order, and religion, of the fabled isle of Atlantis; in which genesis he conceives the same first perfection and final degeneracy of man, which in our own Scriptural tradition is expressed by saying that the Sons of God inter-married with the daughters of men, for he supposes the earliest race to have been indeed the children of God; and to have corrupted themselves, until 'their spot was not the spot of his children.' And this, he says, was the end; that indeed 'through many generations, so long as the God's nature in them yet was full, they were sub missive to the sacred laws, and carried themselves lovingly to all that had kindred with them in divineness; for their uttermost spirit was faithful and true, and in every wise great; so that, in all meekness of wisdom, they dealt with each other, and took all the chances of life; and despising all things except virtue, they cared little what happened day by day, and bore lightly the burden of gold and of possessions; for they saw that, if only their common love and virtue increased, all these things would be increased together with them; but to set their esteem and ardent pursuit upon material possession would be to lose that first, and their virtue and affection together with it. And by such reasoning, and what of the divine nature remained in them, they gained all this greatness of which we have already told; but when the God's part of them faded and became extinct, being mixed again and again, and effaced by the prevalent mortality; and the human nature at last exceeded, they then became unable to endure the courses of fortune; and fell into shapelessness of life, and baseness in the sight of him who could see, having lost everything that was fairest of their honour; while to the blind hearts which could not discern the true life, tending to happiness, it seemed that they were then chiefly noble and happy, being filled with all iniquity of inordinate possession and power. Whereupon, the God of Gods, whose Kinghood is in laws, beholding a once just nation thus cast into misery, and desiring to lay such punishment upon them as might make them repent into restraining, gathered together all the gods into his dwelling place, which from heaven's centre overlooks whatever has part in creation; and having assembled them, he said' —

The rest is silence. Last words of the chief wisdom of the heathen, spoken of this idol of riches; this idol of yours; this golden image, high by measureless cubits, set up where your green fields of England are furnace-burnt into the likeness of the plain of Dura: this idol, forbidden to us, first of all idols, by our own Master and faith; forbidden to us also by every human lip that has ever, in any age or people, been accounted of as able to speak according to the purposes of God. Continue to make that forbidden deity your principal one, and soon no more art, no more science, no more pleasure will be possible. Catastrophe will come; or, worse than catastrophe, slow mouldering and withering into Hades. But if you can fix some conception of a true human state of life to be striven for — life, good for all men, as for your selves; if you can determine some honest and simple order of existence; following those trodden ways of wisdom, which are pleasantness, and seeking her quiet and withdrawn paths, which are peace;^6 — then, and so sanctifying wealth into 'commonwealth,' all your art, your literature, your daily labours, your domestic affection, and citizen's duty, will join and increase into one magnificent harmony. You will know then how to build, well enough; you will build with stone well, but with flesh better; temples not made with hands, but riveted of hearts; and that kind of marble, crimson-veined, is indeed eternal.

Notes

1. It is an error to suppose that the Greek worship, or seeking, was chiefly of Beauty. It was essentially of rightness and strength, founded on Forethought: the principal character of Greek art is not beauty, but design: and the Dorian Apollo-worship and Athenian Virgin-worship are both expressions of adoration of divine wisdom and purity. Next to these great deities, rank, in power over the national mind, Dionysus and Ceres, the givers of human strength and life; then, for heroic examples, Hercules. There is no Venus-worship among the Greeks in the great times: and the Muses are essentially teachers of Truth, and of its harmonies.

2. Quite serious, all this, though it reads like jest. [1873.]

3. Please think over this paragraph, too briefly and antithetically put, but one of those which I am happiest in having written. [1873.]

4. Jerem. xvii. II, (best in Septuagint and Vulgate). 'As the partridge, fostering what she brought not forth, so he that getteth riches, not by right, shall leave them in the midst of his days, and at his end shall be a fool. '

5. Meaning, fully, 'We have brought our pigs to it.' [1873.]

6. I imagine the Hebrew chant merely intends passionate repetition, and not a distinction of this somewhat fanciful kind; yet we may profitably make it in reading the English.

导读

奥古斯丁（Augustine，354—430），罗马教廷官方称其为“希波的奥古斯丁”（Augustine of Hippo），更有尊称为“圣奥古斯丁”。他是罗马帝国末期，也即基督教传播早期的神学家与哲学家，对于基督教教义有着卓越的贡献，曾担任北非城市希波的主教。他主张的“三一论”“救恩论”“圣礼观”等思想都成为了后来教会重要的思想源泉。

奥古斯丁生于罗马帝国统治下的北非的一个柏柏尔人家庭，他的父亲是一位脑中满是世俗的普通罗马税吏，他的母亲却是一位基督教徒，不过奥古斯丁却并未早早皈依基督教。年少的奥古斯丁十分聪慧，年少有为，很早便精通了雄辩术与修辞学。19岁时，奥古斯丁开始信仰摩尼教的善恶二元论，并一直持续了约10年时间。摩尼教由波斯先知摩尼创立于公元三世纪时，吸收了袄教、犹太教、基督教、佛教等教义，独创“二宗三际论”为其神学系统，即“善、恶二宗，过去、现在、未来三际”。

奥古斯丁在29岁时前往罗马教书，也因缘际会开始对摩尼教产生疑惑，并于次年开始跟随时任米兰主教的安波罗修学习基督教信仰与神学，直到33岁正式受洗皈依。从此，他开始猛烈攻击包括摩尼教在内的其他宗派，并成为基督神学届的核心人物。43岁的奥古斯丁出任希波的主教。

基督教诞生于公元一世纪，最初属于犹太教的异端，不过鉴于其包容性更强，所以发展扩张极为迅速。在夹缝中熬过了数百年的被迫害与清除之后，基督教终于成为了罗马帝国的国教。随着罗马帝国慢慢一分为二，基督教也慢慢分裂出东西两大教会，即西方的“天主教会”与东方的“东正教会”，两大教会之间的分歧也是越来越大。16世纪时，在德国神父马丁·路德等人的强力推动下，发起了影响遍及欧洲的宗教改革，并在简化天主教教义与信仰的基础上创立“新教”。天主教、东正教与新教，是基督教的三大教派。但是，今天中国普遍所称的“基督教”一词，其实是指“新教”。而奥古斯丁时所信仰的基督教，应该是指天主教派。

《忏悔录》是一部忏悔形式的自传体文学作品，大约创作于奥古斯丁升任主教之后。全书共13卷，概述了奥古斯丁对其一生罪过的忏悔及皈依基督的心路历程，内容包括赞美天主、少年事迹、母亲病逝、思想斗争、信仰转变、一心皈依等要素。全书共分为两个部分，第1至9卷为自传的部分，第10至13卷为第二部分，其中第10卷审视著书时的思想状况，第11至13卷则为对《旧约圣经·创世纪》第一章的个人诠释。本书两个部分的内容之间并非十分连贯，所以有学者推测，奥古斯丁的本意可能是创作一部逐章诠释《圣经》的伟大作品，却因为种种原因只完成了《创世纪》一章，而第一部分的自传内容则类似于为这部书所作的“序”。这种假说十分合理。

忏悔，是基督教的仪式之一，是忏悔人向神父、牧师或耶稣基督真诚告解自己的罪过，祈求上帝宽恕。圣人奥古斯丁则在书中用文字向世人诠释了何为真正虔诚的忏悔，而当人们坦诚悔过之后，也必将得到上帝的谅解与搭救。《忏悔录》中的文字平白真诚、通俗易懂、强劲有力，而这种直抒胸臆、全篇心理独白的忏悔文体，直接开启了西方文学中一种独特的回忆录类型，影响了一众文学大师，包括托尔斯泰与卢梭等（他们两人也同样各自著有一本《忏悔录》）。当然，我们会怀疑奥古斯丁是否在书中夸大了自己年少时的罪过，也许他并没有自己文字里写的那么罪恶，至少他对自己母亲的尊敬与孝顺是遮掩不住的。他对自己往昔经历的憎恨，应该大多源于那段年月里的心无信仰及10年的摩尼教异端。直到他遇到领路人安波罗修，进入伟大的基督之门，他真的开始用全新的价值观审视自己过去的一切，然后回归正途。他将自己贬入微尘，是对基督最大的尊敬。

通过品读奥古斯丁喃喃自语般文字，希望读者能够体会他的精神思想，这种虔诚其实无关宗教，是每个人对自己心灵的净化。

柴尔

第一卷

1

主啊！你是伟大的，任何赞美都当之无愧。你有无上的能力，无穷的智慧。主啊，人是你所造万物中的一分子，出于本性愿意赞美你。人全身带着死亡的标记，带着原罪的记号，这都提醒着他，你“不接纳骄傲的人”。但是，因为他是你所造的一部分，他仍愿意称颂你。一想到你，他就激动不已，如果不赞美你，他就无法获得满足。因为你造我们就是为了你自己，如不在你怀中安息，我们的心就不会安宁。

[……]

谁追寻主，谁就会赞颂主。因为凡追寻主的，就能寻见，寻见主的，就会赞颂主。主啊，我要追寻你，向你呼求，在我呼求的时候，我要相信你，因为你已经传授给了我们。主，我的信仰让我向你呼求，这信仰已经通过你道成肉身的爱子的感召和布道者的工作传递给了我。

6

我虽然是尘土，但请让我乞求你的怜悯，因为我是在向你的慈爱说话，而不是向那嘲笑我的人说话。或许你也会嘲笑我，但你会动恻隐之心，然后怜悯我。主啊，我想告诉你的是，我不知道自己从何处来到这通向死亡的生命中，或者说，这通向生命的死亡中？对我来说，这些都是隐藏着的。虽然我已记不起这一切，但我知道，从我来到这个世间的那刻起，你的仁慈便时刻准备护佑我。这是我父母告诉我的，我父亲播下种子，母亲孕育了我，你用他们的身体在有限的时间内使我成形。从此女性的乳汁哺育了我。

[……]

我歌颂你，天地的主宰，从我降生起，在我记忆尚且模糊的时候，我就赞美你。你允许人们通过观察别的婴儿来了解自己，并且从妇女的讲述中了解许多。我知道即使在那时，我已是一个活生生的人，在婴儿期行将结束时，我已经试图寻找向别人表达感情的方法了。主啊，这样一个活生生的造物如不是从你而来，他还能来自何处呢？这是任何一个人的技能所能造出来的吗？除你以外还有任何其他渠道可供存在和生命流注到我们身上吗？当然我们只可能把这归结为你，我们的造物主，对你而言，活着与存在并非不同，因为无限的生命与无限的存在是同为一。因为你是无限的，是亘古不变的。你的“今天”永无止境，而我们的“当下”因你而止步不前，因为时间，像其他事物一样存在于你的掌握。若非如此，就不会有时间的流逝。因为你的时间没有穷尽，时间因你而停留在“现在”。我们和我们的祖先在你的“当下”度过了无数的日子，并从中获得对人的生命和存在的准确衡量。未来的岁月也将照此流逝，但是你却亘古不易。在你的“今天”，你创造了明天和以后存在的一切，在你的“今天”，你创造了昨天和过去存在的一切。

如果有人对此表示不解，这与我何干？就让他们去探询其意义吧，让他们欣然地发问。但是他们可能对问题本身心满意足。因为对于他们来说，问题不得而解却找到你，比找到答案却未能找到你更有益处。

7

上帝啊，请听我说。人的罪真是邪恶啊！一个人说了这话，你就怜悯他，因为你造了他，但你没有造他身上的罪。

谁能让我记起儿时犯下的罪呢？在你的眼中没有一个人是无罪的，即使是刚刚出生才一天的婴儿也不例外。谁能展示我的罪呢？也许可以从婴儿身上看到我无从回忆的儿时的罪恶？那么，我儿时犯过什么罪呢？我哭闹着要吸乳是不是罪恶呢？我现在已经年龄大了，不能再吃母乳了，但如果我哭闹着要我这个年龄的食物，一定会受到别人轻蔑的嘲笑和劝诫。所以这意味着我儿时的行为就应该受到斥责。因为我不懂斥责，斥责我的话就显得既不合情理，也不寻常。我们杜绝这些错误，并且在长大后将其摒弃，这足以证明那些行为是错误的，因为我从来没有看见一个人在清理错误时会有目的的抛弃好的方面。对于一个孩子来说，以下行为都不可能是正确的：哭着要可能会伤害他们的任何东西；对年长的人发脾气以为年长者需要服从他；尽其全力打击和伤害那些比他懂得更多的人，包括他自己的父母，因为父母不但不顺从他们，而且拒绝迎合那些只会伤害他的奇思怪想。这表明，如果说婴儿是无罪的，就是说婴儿不是缺乏伤害他人的意愿，而是没有能力。

[……]

主啊，我记不起我的幼年生活了，但是我相信别人告诉我的，通过观察其他婴儿，可以推断，我也像他们那样生活过。但是，尽管我的推断是正确的，我却不想把那段时间作为我现在度过的人生的一部分，因为那段生活晦暗模糊、记忆不清，而且，在这个意义上，它与我在母亲子宫里的时光没什么区别。但是，如果我生来有罪，并且在母胎时，我就有了罪。那么，主啊，我问你，我，你的仆人，在何时何地曾是无罪的呢？但是，我不会再谈论那段时光了，因为在我记忆中，它已经无处可寻，不会再困扰我了。

9

但上帝啊，我的主，现在我正经历一段痛苦和羞辱的时期。别人告诉我，一个男孩必须听老师的话，这才是正确合适的，只有这样才能学好语法，出人头地。这就是在世界上获得别人尊敬、为自己获得财富的途径。于是我被送到学校去读书。我年龄太小，不能领会学习的用处，如果我疏于学习，我就会挨打，因为传统上喜欢用责打来教育孩子。记不清曾经有多少男孩为我们铺就了这条心酸的道路，并且我们也必须走过这条路，为亚当的子孙增添劳累和悲伤。

但是我们发现一些人向你祷告，主啊，并且我们效法他们做同样的事情，用我们唯一能够理解的方式来想象你，把你想象成某些能够倾听并帮助我们的大人物，尽管我们看不见你，听不到你，也触摸不到你。第一次向你祷告时我还很小，你是我的帮助者和避难所。我咿咿呀呀地向你祈求，尽管我还年幼，但我却很虔诚地祈求你不要让我在学校挨打。有时，为了我好，你不应允我的祷告，然后我的兄长甚至我的父母就会在我挨打时嘲笑我，他们当然不希望我受到伤害——在那些日子里挨打是我最大的恐惧。

[……]

11

在我还很小的时候就被告知，上帝屈尊来到我们这些骄傲的罪人中间，他给了我们永生的应许。作为一个望教者，我从出生起就经常被十字架的记号所祝福，并接受圣盐[1]的调理，主啊，我的母亲对你寄予了巨大的期望。我童年时曾因突犯胃病差点夭折。是你，我的主啊，在那时就守护着我，你看见我怀着多么热切强大的信仰，向我的母亲及我们全体的母亲——你的教会，乞求为我施行你的儿子基督——我的主、我的上帝的洗礼。我的生身之母深深地担忧，因为在她心中纯洁的信仰里，从我一出生起，她为使我获得永久的拯救比以往付出了更大的努力。要不是我很快康复，她就会急于看看我是否获准接受获救的圣事，并因承认你主耶稣，而得洁净，因你饶恕了我的罪。于是，我的受洗推迟了，总而言之，只要我继续活着，我必定会让自己重新沾染罪恶，受洗之后，沾染罪责后产生的负罪感就会更大、更危险。即便在那个年龄，我早已相信你，我的母亲和全家也都相信你，只有我父亲除外。但是，在我心中，他并没有超越我母亲的虔诚对我的影响，也没有因自己依然不信仰基督而阻止我信仰基督。主啊，我母亲竭尽全力，让你做我的父亲，而不是他。在这种情况下，你帮助她扭转了对丈夫的态度，她原本一直很顺从丈夫的，因为顺从丈夫就是顺从你的律法，她因此表现出比丈夫更好的美德。

我的主啊，我问你——如果是你的旨意，我希望知道——我当时受洗被推迟的原因是什么？是否是为了我好，放松了让我免于犯罪的羁绊？或者，事实上并没有放松羁绊？要不然，为什么我时至今日还经常听见别人这样说：“别管他，让他做吧，他不是还没有受洗吗？”但是当肉体的健康处于危险之中时，没有人会说：“让他恶化下去，他还没有痊愈呢。”如果我马上被治愈，如果我和我的家人竭尽所能，确保我的灵魂一旦被拯救，我就会在你的庇护中获得安全，因为拯救是源于你的，这样不是更好吗？但是我母亲很清楚，我在成长过程中需要经历诸多风浪，但是她宁愿让不成形的泥土去接受敲打，而不是让那被盖上洗礼印章的、已完全的形象去接受敲打。

17

让我告诉你，我的主，我是怎样在各种愚蠢的妄想上滥用你给予我的心智的。我设立了一个很是困扰我的目标，如果我取得了成功，我会赢得赞誉；如果失败，我害怕蒙羞甚至挨打。我必须背诵朱诺[2]的一段话，这是她因无法阻止埃涅阿斯前往意大利，在痛苦和愤怒之下说的。我早已获悉朱诺没有真的说过这些话，但是我们不得不假装事实如此，并跟随诗人的幻想，把原来诗歌里表达的内容改编为散文。哪个孩子采用了最适合意义的文字，最恰当地表达了悲伤和愤怒的感情，表现了他所模仿的人物的威严，他就赢得了比赛。

主啊，这一切对我真正的生命而言有什么意义呢？为什么我的朗诵会比班上很多其他男孩赢得更多的赞誉呢？这一切都只不过是过眼云烟吗？还有别的方法可以用来训练我的智慧和口才吗？主啊，我原本可以使用智慧和口才，用圣经上的语言来赞美你，那本是我心灵的支撑，可那时我却好像一株新生的葡萄枝，结出无意义的果实，仅供飞鸟啄食。向这些飞鸟、这些堕落天使献祭的方式可不止一种。

19

我小的时候就是站在这样一个世界的门槛上，面临着危险。我已经在准备应对各种挑战了，我接受一项训练，学会对语法错误深恶痛绝，而不是学会当自己犯了语法错误时，不要去嫉妒那些没犯错误的人。主啊，所有这一切，我都向你陈明，并向你忏悔。通过这些行为，我赢得了我所讨好的人的赞誉。因那时我以为，正确的生活方式就是如他们所愿地生活。我被蒙蔽了双眼，看不出邪恶的旋涡已经把我从你的眼前卷走。在你的眼中还有什么比那时的我更糟糕的呢？因为我甚至令那些我希望取悦的人头疼。我无数次地欺骗老师、家人和父母，因为我想玩游戏，或去看无益的表演，或是急于去模仿在舞台看到的场景。我甚至偷父母储藏室和餐桌上的东西，或是出于贪婪，或是为交换其他孩子所喜爱的玩具，他们也乐意与我交易。我与他们做游戏，为了当赢家，我经常搞欺骗，这仅仅是因为想赢的虚荣心浮上心头。当发现别人像我欺骗他们那样欺骗我时，我简直无法忍受，同他们激烈地争吵。同样，如果他们发现我搞欺骗并责备我时，我会勃然大怒，不愿退让。

这是儿童的天真无邪吗？主啊，不是这样的。但是我祈求你的原谅。长官和君主代替了家教和老师，胡桃和皮球及小鸟让位于金钱、地产和仆人，但是这些相同的激情依然保留下来，只是由生命的一个阶段进入到了下一个阶段，就像更严厉的惩罚代替了学校的戒尺。仅仅因为他们，所以你用小孩象征谦卑，我们的君王，你称赞说：“天国是属于他们的。”

20

主啊，即使你让我活不过童年，我也应该感谢你，因为你是我们的主，你是善的极致，宇宙的创造者和统治者。即便我只是作为一个小孩而存在，但我活着，我有感觉的能力，我有一种保护自身安全和完好的本能，保护我的存在，这是一个迹象，来自你这位独一的不可见者。我的内在感觉控制我身体的感觉，并保持它们完全的活力。而且即使在占据我思想的小事中，我也能因发现真理而快乐，我不喜欢被欺骗。我有良好的记忆力，我掌握了知识。我享受朋友的陪伴，并且远离痛苦、无知和悲伤。一个如此渺小的创造物得以拥有这么美好的品质，难道我还不应该感恩吗？但是它们都是上帝的礼物，不是给我自己的。他的礼物是好的，其总和就是我自己。因此，造我的上帝一定是善的，并且我身上所有的美善都是他的。我为着自己生命中的美善感谢他，赞美他，甚至为我童年中的美善也是如此。但是，我的罪在于，我不是从他那里，而是在我自己和其他受造物中，追寻享乐、美丽和真理，我因此陷入了痛苦、混乱和谬误。我的上帝是我的快乐，我的荣耀和我的信靠，我感谢你的赐予并祈求你为我保留它们。请继续保守我，使你的赐予增长并达致完美，我应该和你在一起，我的存在都是你赐予的。

第二卷

1

我现在必须回想我做过的极坏的事，那败坏了我灵魂的肉体之罪。主啊，我如此做不是我喜欢那些罪恶，而是为了爱你。因为爱你的爱，我将回顾那邪恶的过去。回忆是苦涩的，但是这将帮助我品尝你的甘甜，这甘甜不是欺骗性的，而是能带来真正的喜乐，并且永不消逝的。因为爱你的爱，我将从极大的堕落中重新找回自己，当我远离你时，这堕落将我撕碎，只有你是我本该追寻的，但我却因为许多不同的渴求而迷失了自己。我进入成年以后，因沉溺于地狱般的享乐而为欲望所驱使。我有勇无谋，迷失在纷繁复杂而又疯狂滋生的欲望中。在你看来，我的美丽褪去，我的灵魂腐烂发臭，然而我却满足于自身的状态，并力求取悦于人。

2

除了爱与被爱之外，我别无他求。但是我的爱超出了一个人对另一个人的感情，超出了友谊之光的纯度。肉体的欲望像泥沼，青春期的性欲在我身体里膨胀，冒出迷雾，遮蔽并暗淡了我的心灵，以致我不能从肉欲的阴暗中区别真爱的清晰光线。爱和肉欲在我体内混杂在一起。它们将我年轻的性情横扫至肉欲的悬崖边，企图将我淹没于罪恶的旋涡。你对我越来越愤怒，但我毫无意识。死亡的铁链已经发出响声，振聋发聩，这是你对我心灵骄傲的惩罚。我离你越来越远，你不约束我。我横冲直撞、不断摔跤，在淫乱的欲海中挣扎，你沉默不语。等到认识到你才是我真正的喜乐，这是一个多么漫长的过程啊！你在那时沉默，而我却偏行己路，渐行渐远，以自己的痛苦为骄傲，在疲惫中无法安息，播下越来越多的种子，唯一收获的却只有悲伤。

[……]

3

在同一年中，我的学业被中断。我已经开始在附近的马都拉城[3]学习文法和雄辩术[4]，但是我被带回家，我的父亲，一个塔加斯特城普通公民，他的决定十分坚定，要省钱送我去更远的迦太基[5]。我不必将这一切向你陈明，我的上帝，然而当着你的面我要向我的同类讲述，告诉那些可能会拿起这本书来读的人，尽管人数很少。这是为了使我和读者都能够意识到我们在怎样的深渊中向你哭求。你的耳朵一定听见了那忧伤痛悔的心的哭求，这心持守着信仰而活着。

[……]

4

主啊，偷窃无疑会受到你的律法的惩罚，尽管他们都是罪人，但律法写在人们的心中并且不可能被擦掉。没有哪个小偷可以忍受另一个小偷对他的偷窃，即便他很有钱，而且另一个人是出于渴求的冲动。我之所以想偷窃，并去偷了，虽不是被匮乏驱使，无非是因为缺乏正义感，或是不喜欢正确的事情，并对做错事有一种贪婪的爱。我偷窃之前就已经拥有很多了，而且比那被偷的还好，我并不愿享受这些贪求而偷来的东西，而仅仅是享受犯罪和偷窃本身。我家葡萄园附近有一棵梨树，结满了果子，无论是看起来还是尝起来都很诱人。一个深夜，包括我在内的一群无赖去把果子都摇下来带走，我们在外继续游玩直到深夜，这是我们的恶习。我们带走了大量的梨，自己没有吃，而是扔给了猪。也许我们吃了一些，但是我们真正的快乐是做了被禁止的事情。

[……]

6

如果16岁的那天晚上我犯下的偷窃罪行是一个活生生的事实，我会对它说并问，到底我爱这可耻之事里面的什么？我毫无美善，因这是强盗行径。而我们所偷的梨是美的，因为它们是你所创造的，良善的天父，你是所有存在中最美的，是所有事物的创造者，是最高的善和我自己真正的善。那梨不是我闷闷不乐的心灵所渴求的。我有很多比这更好的东西，我偷梨只是为了偷窃。我把梨刚摘下来就扔掉了，我吃的只是我的罪，我品尝并享受着这种罪。如果这些梨中的任何一个经过我的口，那都是罪的味道。

[……]

那时，在偷窃中让我感到愉快的是什么呢？难道是用堕落的和邪恶的方式来模仿我主的能力？因为我没有真正的能打破他的律法，于是我享受表面上这样做，就像囚犯不惧怕惩罚的时候，在对权力持有虚弱的幻觉之下，通过做错事来为他制造一种虚幻的自由？这是一个奴隶，从主人那里逃跑，转而去追逐自己的影子！这多么令人厌恶啊！这是对生活多么拙劣的模仿！这是多么难以测度的死亡啊！除了那是错事以外，还能找到任何别的原因让我以做错事为乐吗？

第三卷

1

我去了迦太基，发现自己置身于一口嘶嘶作响的欲望大锅之内。我还没有坠入爱河，但是我渴求爱，并且当我感到失去了什么时，我会憎恨自己没有去热烈地满足这种需求。我环顾四周寻找爱的目标，因为我极度渴望爱上某物。我不喜欢脚下没有陷阱的人生，尽管我真正的需要是你，我的上帝，我心灵的食粮，我还没有意识到这种饥饿。我没有对不朽的食粮的需要，不是因为我已经拥有了，而是因为我越是饥饿，食粮越是不好吃。为此，我的灵魂病了，我得了溃疡，并且极力寻找一些物质的东西，也就是说，企图用世界的方法，来解决溃疡引起的瘙痒。但是物质是没有灵魂的，不能作为我爱的真正对象。渴求爱与被爱是我心中的欲望，如果能够享受爱我之人的肉体，对当时的我而言，那将是最美的事。

[……]

3

然而，你的仁慈总是在高处信实地庇护着我。我在堕落和渎神的好奇心中筋疲力尽。我离弃你，沉入怀疑主义的最底层，还模仿魔鬼式的崇拜。我的罪是给魔鬼的献祭，为了这一切你责罚我。我竟然冒犯你，在教堂举行你神秘的盛典之时，我竟充满肉欲的思想，并从中获得满足。因这一行为我理应被判处死刑，你用重重的鞭挞惩罚我。但是与我的罪相比，这惩罚算不得什么。主啊！你的慈爱是多么的无限，你是我所经之极危险之境的避难所，就是当我在高处走，却执意后退、更加远离你的时候。我喜欢我自己的方式，而不是你的，但我所爱的这种自由是不负责任的自由。

除了这些追求以外，我也学习法律。这样的抱负是被尊崇的，我决定继续下去。我越是无耻，我就越有名，人们都瞎了眼，以致以其瞎眼为荣。那时我在雄辩学校名列前茅。我很满意自己高高在上的状态并且傲慢自大。尽管如此，主啊，你很清楚，我的行为比“破坏分子”安静很多，“破坏分子”是对喜欢恶作剧的人的称呼，这是当时流行的称号。我不参与他们突发的暴力行径，但我和他们在一起生活，我还有一些羞耻感，毕竟我不像他们。我与他们为伍，也经常从这种友谊中找到乐子，但是当他们做那些符合他们的称号的事情时，我也总会感到可怕。胆小的新人即便不招惹他们，他们也会捉弄他，无端地冒犯其尊严并以此为乐，并将其尴尬作为恶意玩笑的素材。如果这不是魔鬼自己的行为，也离魔鬼不远了。“破坏分子”是一个适合于他们的名字，他们放荡不羁，并完全伤害了他们自己。他们喜欢嘲笑和作弄别人，对别人设下魔鬼的秘密圏套，而这实则也是在嘲笑和作弄他们自己。

4

这些就是我在那个易动感情的年龄学习雄辩术时的同伴。我的抱负是成为一个优秀的演说家，为了满足人类虚荣心这个渎神且愚蠢的目的。西塞罗[6]的一部作品因着其中所宣扬的精神，成了我必修课的一本读物。几乎人人都崇拜他的作品。这本书的书名是《荷尔顿西乌斯》（Hortensuu），它建议读者学习哲学，它改变了我对人生的看法，使我转而向你祷告，主啊，它还给了我新的希望和理想。我所有空虚的梦在瞬间失去了魅力，我的心开始为永恒真理所搏动，这真理有迷惑人的激情。我开始从自己的沉沦中爬出来，希望重新回到你的身边。我不是用书作为我的磨刀石来使我变得伶牙俐齿。我之所以被它吸引不是因为形式而是内容，虽然母亲付给我的学费本来是要花在我的口才训练上的。我那时已经19岁了，她还供养我，因为父亲两年前已经去世。

[……]

但是，我心灵的光明，你知道在那个时候，尽管对保罗[7]的话我还一无所知，唯一让我高兴的事情就是西塞罗在书中建议不要简单崇拜哲学流派中的这个人或那个人，而是要爱智慧本身，无论它是什么，都要去探寻它、追求它、拥有它，并牢牢地将它占据。这些话使我感到万分激动并在我心中燃起了烈火。只是在这燃烧的热情中没有提到基督的名字。主啊，出于你的怜悯，从母亲哺育我时，我婴儿的内心就已经恭敬地吮吸了他的名字，你儿子的名字，我的救主。在我内心深处，他的名字保留着，无论有多少学问，多么正确清晰的表达，除非他的名字在里面，否则没有什么能够完全俘获我。

5

于是我下决心研究《圣经》，看一下这到底是什么书。我发现某些东西不是骄傲之人能够理解的，也不是小孩子可以掌握的。他的步伐是谦卑的，但是他所达到的高度是壮丽的。他被神秘所包裹，我不是有进入资格的人，也不是可以低头遵从他引导的人。但是当我第一次读《圣经》时，我有一种前所未有的感觉。对我来说，他们好像根本不值得与西塞罗庄严的散文相比，因为我太自负以致不能接受《圣经》的质朴，并且也没有足够的洞察力去穿透其深度。无疑，《圣经》的意义是随着孩子的成长而丰满起来的。但是我太骄傲了，以致不能把自己叫作小孩。我被自尊所填满，这使得我认为自己是一个伟大的人。

11

但是你从高天中伸手帮助我，从黑暗的深渊中将我的灵魂拯救。因为我的母亲，你虔诚的仆人，为了我向你哭诉，为我灵性的死亡比其他失去儿子肉身的母亲流了更多的眼泪。根据你给她的信仰精神，她视我如死亡一般。你听到她的哭泣，并没有因为她流泪而鄙视她，这些眼泪落下来，浇灌着她在各地祈祷时脸所贴近的土地。你聆听她，不然我怎样解释你安慰她的梦，故而她同意与我一同居住并与我同桌吃饭呢？在这之前她是拒绝这样做的，因为她厌恶并回避我错误信仰导致的渎神行为。

她梦见她站在一把木尺上，一个闪着神圣光芒的青年向她走来，尽管她自己悲伤得难以承受，然而那青年却快乐地向她微笑。青年问她每天悲伤流泪的原因，之所以问她不是因为他不知道，而是因为他有一些事情要告诉她，而这些事是他在异象中看见的。当她告诉青年，她是为了她唯一的儿子所丧失的灵魂而流泪时，青年告诉母亲要留意观察，如果她仔细观察的话，她将看见她在哪里，我就在哪里。于是她照着青年的话去做，果然她看见我正站在她的旁边，在同一把尺子上。

这个梦会从哪里来，除非你听了她内心的祷告？你的善是有大能的。你看顾我们每一个人，好像在你的关心中没有其他人，你看顾每一个人时也在看顾所有人。无疑，正是因为相同的原因，当她告诉我那个梦，我试图把它解释为她不用为我某一天成为那个样子而绝望时，母亲毫不犹豫地回答说：“不！他没有说‘他在哪里，你就在哪里’，而是说‘你在哪里，他就在哪里’。”

[……]

12

我记得当时你给了她另一个关于她祷告的回答，有一些无关的事情我忘记了，而且我要省略很多，因为我急于略去其他的事情，我急于向你忏悔。

你通过你的一个教士给了她回答，那个主教一生都住在教堂，并且熟悉《圣经》经文。我的母亲请他来与我谈一谈，或许他可以驳斥我的错误，把罪从我心中驱除，并用善来取代。当他发现合适的学生时他经常这样做，但是他拒绝为我这样做——这是一个明智的决定，我后来意识到这一点。他告诉我母亲我还没有达到接受这种教导的程度，因为就像母亲告诉主教的一样，我正因新近接受的异端思想而骄傲，并且用几个难题难倒了好些学问不高的人。主教说：“让他一个人待着吧，你只要向上帝祷告就可以了，他在阅读中会发现自己的错误和不虔诚的。”

同时，他告诉母亲，当他还是孩子的时候，他那迷失方向的母亲把儿子交给了摩尼教。他不仅读遍了摩尼教的书籍，还把它们抄写下来，没有任何人与他争论或是规劝他，他便自我觉醒，意识到必须离开这个教派，后来就真的离开了。听了这些之后，母亲依然不能平静，还是泪如泉涌地苦苦哀求他与我谈一谈。最后主教都有点不耐烦了，说道：“请走吧，就这样了，你流了这么多泪，你是不会失去你的儿子的。”

几年后，当我与母亲谈话时，她常说当时她是将这些话当作来自天国的信息来接受的。

第四卷

1

在接下来的9年中，从我19岁到28岁，我迷失了自己，反过来也误导了别人。我们是一样的骗子，并且我们利用各自不同的目标和野心进行欺骗，当我们详细解释那些所谓的人文思想时，这都是公开的，而在我们为所谓的宗教服务时却是秘密的。我们在公开场合很自信，私下里却很迷信，在任何地方都是空虚和无意义的。一方面我们追求无意义的流行盛名和观众的喝彩、诗歌的荣誉及比赛中转瞬即逝的花环。我们喜爱舞台上悠闲的消遣和不被约束的自我放纵。另一方面我们渴望通过向神圣选民的献祭，以净化这些低级的享乐，像他们说的那样，在他们肠胃的作坊中将这些东西加工成天使和神灵，使我们得到拯救。这就是我追求的目标，我和像我一样的朋友都在同样的幻象之下完成自己的事情，而且也与我犯同样的错误。

[……]

2

那时，我是一名讲授雄辩术的教师。对钱财的欲望征服了我，我又通过出售教人在论辩中取胜的技巧征服其他人。但是，主啊，你知道，我宁愿拥有最诚实的学生，即使当今诚实没有任何意义，我教会他们狡诈时并没有恶意，我从来不希望他们利用狡诈去伤害无辜的人；相反，如果时机合适，我希望他们去拯救有罪的人。我的上帝啊，你从远处看见我以这种背信弃义的理由失去了自己的立足之地，但是透过云雾，你依然看见我内心闪耀着美好信仰的火花。因为，虽然我在教导我的学生时，仅仅煽动他们做徒劳的设计，耍欺骗的伎俩，但是我竭尽全力踏踏实实地教他们。

在这些日子里，我与一个女人同居，她不是我合法的妻子，而是一个情妇，我之所以选择她，是因为我不安的欲望可以在她身上得到慰藉。但是她是我的唯一，而且我很忠实于她。与她同居的经验使我发现，婚姻盟约的约束与性伴侣间讨价还价的制约不同，前者是为生儿育女而缔结的，而在后者关系中，孩子的出生是双方最不情愿的，尽管当真的有了孩子时，他们不得不爱他们。

12

如果这个世界的事物令你愉悦，为着它们赞美上帝吧，但要从它们那里转移你的爱，而把爱献给创造者，好让沉浸于这些美好的事情中的你不会令他不快。如果你的快乐在于灵魂，在上帝里爱他们吧，因为灵魂太脆弱了，唯有当灵魂紧紧抓住上帝，才能坚定不移。他们如果不这样做，就只能走自己的路而最终迷路。爱他们吧，并且在上帝里努力引导他们归向上帝吧。告诉他们：“我们应该爱上帝，他创造了世界，并且上帝并不遥远。”他创造这个世界之后，并没有抛下这个世界不管。这个世界就是他创造的，而世界也是因他而存在的。哪里有真理，上帝就在哪里。他在我们内心的最深处，但是我们的心却远离他。仔细想想吧，叛逆的心灵，抓住这个创造你们的主。与他站在一起你就不会跌倒，在他里面安息，你就会感到平安。在你面前有什么样的障碍和陷阱？你的脚步把你引向何方？你所喜爱的美好事物都来自上帝，但是这些东西只有在你按照上帝的意愿来使用的时候才是美好的。如果抛开上帝而错误地去爱它们，它们就会理所当然地转为苦涩。你为什么选择游荡在这艰苦而辛劳的路上呢？在其上你找不到可安息的地方。在死亡的土地上你试图找到一份幸福的生活，可是幸福的生活不在那儿。没有生命的地方怎么让生活幸福呢？

我们的生命（Life）他自己来到这个世界，带走了我们的死亡。他用他丰盛的生命扭转了死亡，他发出雷鸣般的声音让我们从这个世界回到他的天国。他从天上来到我们中间，先是进入童贞女马利亚的子宫，在那里，我们凡人的肉体与他结合，就永远也不会死亡。然后他如新郎走出洞房一般，又如勇士欣然奔向前程。他不是在路上徘徊而是奔跑，呼唤我们回到他身边，用他的言语和行为呼唤我们，通过他的生命和死亡，通过他降到地狱又升入天堂，来呼唤我们。他离开我们的视线，好让我们转向内心并在那里找到他。他离开我们，但是他又与我们在一起。他也许没有与我们相伴，但他却从未离开我们。他回到他从来没有离开过的地方，因为通过他，这个世界得以被造，他存在于这个世界，他来到这世界是为了拯救罪人。我的灵魂向他忏悔，他是医治者，因为过犯是针对他的。人类的子孙啊，你们心灵还要愚顽多久？你的生命来自天国，你们还不愿意随他上升而活吗？然而，如果你们还站在高位并且争闹声上达天庭，你们如何上升呢？从这些高处下来，这个时候你才会攀到上帝那儿。如果你们上升却又对抗上帝，就会跌落下来。

[……]

13

那时我不明白这个道理。我爱上了低级的美丽，这种美丽使我沉沦。我经常问我的朋友：“我们会爱上任何不美丽的东西吗？到底什么是美，美是由什么组成的？到底是什么在吸引我们，并超过我们所爱的事物？除非在它们里面有美丽和优雅，否则它们没有能力赢得我们的心。”当我看一个东西时，我发现，事物本身整体的美和与其他事物搭配所形成的和谐之美有所不同，就好比身体的一部分相对于整个身体，或者是鞋子相对于穿鞋的脚。这一观念从我心中迸发，就像水从泉中涌出一样。我的大脑被这种观念填满，我写了一本书，名叫《美与适宜》，我记得大约有两三卷。主啊，你知道有多少卷，但是我已经忘记了，因为这书很快就弄丢了，我再也没有找到。

14

主啊，我的上帝，是什么原因促使我把书献给罗马伟大的雄辩家希埃利乌斯[8]呢？我从来没有见过他，但我敬佩他学识上的赫赫名气，并且深深地被他的演讲所打动。甚至除此以外，别人对他的崇拜都能给我留下深刻的印象。人们对他赞不绝口，因为他实在非同寻常。他生在叙利亚，最初训练用希腊语演讲，后来成为著名的拉丁语演说家，在哲学上也很有造诣。

如果我们听见人们赞美一个素未谋面的人，我们会敬佩他，但这并不意味着仅仅听到对他的赞美就使得我们敬佩他。然而，一个人的热情会点燃另一个人同样的热情之火。我们听到别人称赞一个人时，只有相信那些赞语是真心话，我们才会仰慕他，换句话说，就是真心称赞的人会仰慕他自己称赞的那个人。

[……]

但是希埃利乌斯是我仰慕其才华的那种人，我很希望拥有那样的才华。我的骄傲使我到处漂游，随风飘荡。你像一个舵手一样引导我，但是你驾驶的航线超出了我的理解。我现在知道，并且可以坦然承认，我仰慕希埃利乌斯，与其说是因为别人称赞他，不如说是因为他那些受到称赞的成就。我了解到这一点，是因为那同样的一群人不但不会称赞他，反而毁谤他。他们可能同样会说出他的一些才能，但又会吹毛求疵，鄙视那些才能。如果他们这样做，我的感情就不会被激发，我的仰慕之情也不会被点燃。然而，他的品质没有变化，他本人也没有什么不同。唯一不同的是他们对待他的态度。

我们可以从中看出灵魂是软弱无力的，除非它抓住了坚固的真理之石。人们表达自己的意见，但那只是他们自己的意见，像一阵阵风把灵魂吹向这里、吹到那里，晕头转向。光被遮蔽住了，使真理不被看见，尽管真理就在我们眼前。在我看来，带上我的书及我完成的工作，可以引起这位大人物的注意，这对我而言是非常重要的。如果他欣赏我的作品，我的热情会更加高涨。如果他发现了缺点，我那空虚又缺失上帝坚定真理的心，一定会遭受到严重的打击。然而，我在思考“美与适宜”的问题时深得其乐，我把这本书献给了他。尽管再没有别的人欣赏这本书，但我却引以为豪。

15

[……]

我挣扎着去接近你，但是你把我推了回来，让我品尝死亡的滋味。因为你拒斥骄傲的人。我居然在奇怪的疯狂中宣称，我就是来自你的本性，还有什么比这更狂妄的呢？我很善变，我自己知道。如果我想成为一个有学识的人，这只是意味着我想要精益求精。同样地，我宁愿认为你也是善变的，也不愿相信我与你不同。这就是你拒绝我并粉碎了我膨胀的骄傲的原因，那时，我的想象力继续停留在物质形式之上。尽管我谴责肉欲，我自己却是一个充满肉欲和血气的人。我像呼出的气息一样善变，无法再回到你身边。我四处漂泊，努力走向在你那儿并不存在的事物，或是在我自己或在我体内不存在的事物。这些事物不是通过你的真理而为我创造的，它们只是我愚蠢的想象力作用于具体物质的结果。尽管我不知道，我从上帝之城属于我的地盘中被驱逐出来，在上帝忠诚的孩子——我的同胞中流放。但是我只会空谈，并愚蠢地问他们：“如果像你们说的，上帝创造了灵魂，为什么灵魂会犯错？”主啊，于是过去我宁愿认为你不变的本质是被迫犯错，而不愿承认我自己是善变的，并且由于自由意志而犯错，那错误就是对我的惩罚。

[……]

16

我20岁的时候，拿到一本亚里士多德的《论十个范畴》。我迦太基的老师和被誉为著名学者的人提到这本书时，他们的脸上出现妄自尊大的表情，所以书名本身就足以让我目瞪口呆，就像我因一些奇妙的神秘而惊呆。那时我试图独自去阅读和理解这本书，虽然如今我问自己那样做我得到了什么益处。其他人告诉我，他们经历了重重困难才理解这本书，而且此前最博学的大师不仅给他们作了字面解释，还用大量图表来阐释。但是当我与他们讨论时，他们能够告诉我的不过是我通过自己的阅读已经发现了的东西。

[……]

我独立阅读和理解所有我能够找到的所谓自由学科的书籍，因为那时我一无是处，而且是一个有着肮脏野心的奴隶。我从中得到了什么呢？我阅读那些书时感到很愉悦，但却不知道书中确定无疑的事实的真正来源。我背对着光，我的脸朝向被它照亮的事物，于是我用来看光下的事物的眼睛却是黑暗的。不需要太多的努力和老师的指导，我就能理解所阅读的所有东西：辩论术、逻辑、地理、音乐及数学。哦，主啊，我的上帝，你是知道的，一个人理解迅速并且感知敏锐，是因为你给予他这些天赋。但是因为我没有把天赋奉献给你，我努力地将其大部分变成自己的能力，而不是为了你积蓄力量，我离开了你往远方去，挥霍你爱的赐予，并把它们换成了金钱。这么做坏处比益处大得多。如果不好好利用，能力对我有何益处呢？我拥有的能力，只有在我竭力教授给别人之后，我才意识到这些学科是很难掌握的，甚至对于勤奋、聪慧的学生也是一样，一个可以一贯地遵循我的教导的学生就可以被看作一名非常好的学者。

然而，如果我只是认为你，主，上帝，真理本身，是一个光明的、无限的身体，我只是其中掉出的一小块，那么我从阅读中能获得什么价值呢？这完全是歪曲真理！然而这曾经就是我的信仰。现在我可以毫不脸红地承认，主啊，你对我的怜悯，我不会命令你来帮助我，就像那些日子我大言不惭地去亵渎你，像一只狗一样对你狂吠。我聪慧的价值是什么？它可以带着这些学科大步向前，而且，所有的书，它们所缠绕的问题，我可以不用任何人类导师的帮助就可以解开，在你爱的教义中，我迷失在最丑陋的错误和邪恶的渎神行为中。你虔诚的孩子理解这些比我缓慢，可这是他们大的缺点吗？他们并没有抛弃你，而是在你教堂的安全巢穴中长大，将对你的信心作为食物来哺育他们仁慈的翅膀，这信心将拯救他们。

上帝，我们的主啊，让你翅膀的庇护给我们希望，保护我们并支持我们。你将支持我们，从儿时直到我们的头发变白都支持我们。当你是我们的力量时，我们强壮，但是当力量是我们自己的时候，我们便软弱，在你里面我们的善永远得到护佑，当我们偏离至善时，我们就转向了邪恶。主啊，让我们最终能回到你的家中，不要让我们迷路。我们的善在你那里得到护佑，不会出现问题，因为那就是你自己。我们也不担心没有我们可以返回的家园。我们曾经从中失落，但是我们的家园是你的永恒，它永远不会失落，因为我们已经离开罪恶。

第五卷

1

主啊，请接受我的忏悔。他们是通过我的唇舌献上的祭物，因为是你亲手造了它，是你的灵使它感动承认你的名。请医治我的百骨，并让它们说：主啊，谁能像你呢？

如果一个人向你忏悔，他不吐露内心最深处的想法，似乎以为你不知道那些想法。心灵也许会封闭，却不能遮蔽你的视线。人的心可能是坚硬的，却不能阻挡你双手的触摸。无论何时，只要你愿意，你的仁慈或惩罚都能使人的心变得柔软，就像没有人能躲避阳光一样，没有人能够躲避你燃烧的热量。让我的灵魂赞美你，彰显你的爱。让它公开承认你的慈爱，让它赞美你的仁慈。你所创造的都不停息地齐声赞美你。人们向你祈祷，他们的灵魂赞美你。动物、无生命的事物也一样，也都因着我们对它们的思考而通过我们的口舌来赞美你。因为我们的心灵从你创造的事物中获得供给，让我们可以克服弱点并提升到你的高度，同时利用它们来帮助我们回归你的身边，是你使这些事物变得妙不可言。我们因你而得到重塑，并找到真正的力量。

3

在我的上帝面前，我将描述我29岁的时光。

有一个叫作福斯图斯的摩尼教[9]主教，最近到了迦太基。他简直就是一个从魔鬼那儿来的诈骗者，很多人都被他演讲时迷人的姿态所吸引。这自然是我所仰慕的，但是我开始学会去区别这仅仅是雄辩还是我渴望学习的真理。摩尼教徒对这个叫福斯图斯的人谈论了很多，而我只想看看他要向我呈现什么学问，我并不关心他使用什么言辞来修辞。我已经听说他在所有高级学问中很擅长使用言辞，特别是在自由科学方面。

我曾读过许多科普书籍，现在对这些书依然记忆犹新。当我把这些知识与摩尼教单调的故事进行比较时，对我来说，二者之中的科学理论似乎更接近真理。因为他们的思想可延展至足够远，从而对他们周边的世界作出判断，虽然他们对世界之主一无所知。而你，主啊，你高高在上，以赞许的眼光观看卑微的众生，却从远处藐视骄傲的人。你只与那些内心谦卑的人亲近。而那些骄傲的人，虽然他们通过学习能够计算星星和海沙的数目，能够测量星座的位置和行星运行的轨迹，他们却找不到你。

[……]

6

大约有9年的时间，我的心摇摆不定。我是摩尼教的追随者，我极热切地期待着福斯图斯的到来。这个教派的教徒不能回答我提出的问题，但他们安慰我说，一旦福斯图斯到来，我就可以与他讨论，对于这些问题和我可能提出的更难的问题，他会毫不费力地给予一个明确的解答。

[……]

我对福斯图斯长久热切的期盼有了丰厚的回报，他确定了辩论题目并表现出好意。他很容易就能找到合适的词来展现他的思想，这让我惊喜。我不是唯一为此鼓掌的人，当然我鼓掌的次数可能比谁都多。但是我发现这很累人，当很多人聚在一起听他演讲时，我不能够接近他去请教我的问题，而且也不能在他的面前作友好的问答式交流。一旦有机会，我和朋友们就会吸引他的注意，尽管那并不是适宜私人交谈的场合。我提出了我的一些疑问，但是很快发现除了一些文学基础知识外，他没有什么学识。他仅读过一点西塞罗的演讲、一两本塞内加[10]的书、一些诗歌，以及他的教友用很美的拉丁文写成的书。除了日常的演讲训练外，这些读物是他雄辩的基础，也是他增加魅力，完善他那吸引人的人格和充分运用精神力量的基础。

[……]

7

当我发现福斯图斯对那些我以为他精通的领域一无所知时，便不再期待他能解决那些困扰我的问题。当然，尽管他在这些事情上是无知的，他依然是一个十分虔诚的人，只可惜他是一个摩尼教徒。摩尼教的书充满了对天空、星辰、太阳和月亮故事长篇累牍的编造。我十分希望福斯图斯能把这些与我在其他书中学到的算数对比一下，从而我可以判断摩尼教的理论是否更可能是真理，或者至少同样可能是真理，但是我开始意识到他不能给我一个详细的解释。当我建议应该考虑这些问题并可以一起讨论时，他非常谦虚，并且拒绝了。他知道他无法回答我的问题，并且不羞于承认这一点，不像其他我不得不容忍的健谈者，当他无话可说时，他不会试图给我上课。他有一颗心，尽管他寻找你的方式是错误的，但他并非不慎重。他没有完全意识到他的局限性，并且不想仓促地加入一场辩论，因为这种辩论可能迫使他处于他无法维持也无法轻易退出的局面。我反而因此更喜欢他了，因为对于心智而言，谦逊和坦诚是很好的装备，胜过我希望拥有的科学知识。我发现他对所有困难和深奥的问题的态度都是一样的。

[……]

于是，不经意间，这个吸引了许多人的福斯图斯如今开始将我从困境中解救出来。主啊，冥冥之中你指引的手没有丢弃我。我母亲日夜向你流泪，并为了我，将她的心血献上为祭，但是你引领我走在最奇妙的路上。主啊，是你引导了我，因为若一个人前进的步伐受到主的指引，他无疑会坚定不移。除了你的手之外，还有什么可以拯救我们，还有什么可以重新塑造你所创造的呢？

8

那时，在你的指引下，我被说服去罗马，在那儿教授我在迦太基所教的科目。

[……]

9

在罗马，我被疾病所击倒，几乎坠入地狱，背负着我对你犯下的罪，对自己犯下的罪，对其他人犯下的罪，一系列严重的罪行超过了原罪的总和，在罪里面我们和亚当都死了。那时你还没有在基督里宽恕我犯下的罪中的任何一条，在他的十字架上，你也还没有化解我因罪给你带来的敌意。如果你仅仅是我认为的一个幻象的话，那么你如何在十字架上化解这种敌意？到那时为止，我认为基督身体的死亡不是真的，而我自己灵魂的死亡却是真实的。因着对他死亡的怀疑，我的灵魂和生命是虚假的，而他身体的死亡却是真实的。

[……]

如果我死在那个国家，我母亲的心所受到的打击将永远也不会康复。言语无法表达她是多么爱我，她为我灵性的重生所承受的焦虑远远大于她生产我时的痛苦。如果我在那种情况下死去，无法想象她会怎样恢复过来，因我的死会刺透她那爱我的心。那么她经常做的恒久、迫切祷告的对象是谁呢？是你，除你以外没有别人。但是，你这位满有怜悯的主啊，你会鄙视这守贞寡妇从内心深处发出的悔恨、卑微的声音吗？她总是乐于施舍，积极为你的圣徒们效劳，每天都要到你的祭坛献祭，从不间断。她每天早晚去教堂两次，毫无例外。她并不是去听那些空洞的故事和老妇人的闲言碎语，而是去听你的教导，并且你也能听到她的祷告。在你的恩典中，她成就了自身，你能拒绝帮助她吗？或者，当她不要求金银或任何转瞬即逝的好处，而是请求你拯救她儿子的灵魂，你会鄙视她的眼泪吗？主啊，你绝不会这么做的。不，你在那儿听她的祷告，并按照你的时间做你决定做的事情。你一定不会在梦境和答复中欺骗她。在她虔敬的心中牢牢地记住这些我在上文中曾经提到的和没有提到的梦境和答复，好像得到你亲手书写的手谕一样，在祈祷时念念不忘，反复地对你提及。因为你的慈爱永远长存，在你的应许中，你屈尊为这些免除了所有债务的人做一个负债者。

10

所以，是你医好了我的疾病。你使你仆人的儿子的身体恢复健康，让他可以活着从你那里接受另一个更好、更确定的健康。

[……]

12

我开始积极地教授文法和雄辩术，这是我来罗马的目的。起初我在家里教，我招收了一些之前就听说过我的学生，通过他们我开始小有名气。但是我开始意识到在罗马有困难，而这困难在非洲是不会有的。千真万确的是，我发现这里没有小流氓闹事，但却听说，有一群学生会不断地搞集体阴谋以逃避支付他们导师的费用，或是投身到另外一个老师门下。他们是相当无耻的，与喜爱金钱相比，正义对于他们一文不值。我内心憎恨他们，而且不是没有私心的憎恨，我认为，我憎恨他们，更多是因为我对他们难以忍受，而不仅是他们对教师所犯的错误。……我依然憎恶这些偏执和思想扭曲的学生，但是我也爱他们，希望教导他们从而改变他们，让他们学会爱学习胜过爱金钱，并学会爱你，他们的上帝，因为你是真理、永不止息的善的源头和最圣洁的和平者。但是在这些日子里，我是因为害怕他们可能会给我带来伤害而讨厌他们，而不是因为你的缘故希望他们回归正路。

13

于是，当罗马的执政官收到一封来自米兰的信，要求为米兰找一位文法和雄辩老师，而且答应旅行的费用会由公共资金来负担的时候，我申请了这个职位，并且那些深陷在摩尼教的愚昧中的教友还推荐了我。尽管当时没有人知道，但这个旅行意味着我与他们的联系结束。最后执行官西马库斯安排了一场考试，他们认可了我的能力，并将我送去了米兰。

在米兰，我找到了你热心的仆人安波罗修主教，他因出众的品行而闻名于世。那时，他那极有天赋的唇舌不厌其烦地宣传你粮食的充裕、你圣油的喜乐和你让人清醒又沉醉的酒。我不知道，是你把我引向他，我以为是他引导我到了你那里。这位圣人作为主教，像父亲一样接待我，告诉我他是多么高兴我来了。我的心被他温暖，仅仅是这个人对我表示了友善，并非因为他是真理的教师，我已经对能在教会中找到这样的人感到绝望了。他向人们布道时，尽管带着不恰当的目的，我都仔细聆听。我当时的目的是凭自己去判断那些对他演讲能力的谈论是否正确，或是他的口才是否与我所听说的那样的好。于是，当我全神贯注地听他所使用的词时，我对主题就十分不感兴趣，甚至鄙视它。我对他迷人的演讲无比喜爱，虽然他是一位比福斯图斯更有学识的演讲者，但却没有那样流畅和风度翩翩。我仅仅说的是他的风格，但就内容来说，他却是举世无双的。福斯图斯在摩尼教的谬误中迷失了，而安波罗修则最确定无疑地教授关于拯救的教义。但你的仁慈不为罪人所知晓，正如当时的我，虽然正无意间一步一步地走向你。

14

虽然我不难明白安波罗修所讲的内容，但我仅仅关注他表达的方式，那是我当时的唯一兴趣，因为我已经不再相信人类能够找到通向你的道路。与我所欣赏的演讲方式不可分割的是演讲的主题，我视其无足轻重，可也无法将这二者分开。我全神贯注地学习他的演讲方式，并且开始意识到他所说的真理和事实。尽管这是一个渐近的过程。最初打动我的是，他所讲的东西还是有道理的。于是我开始相信基督宗教，我曾经认为基督宗教不可能驳斥摩尼教，可特别当我听完一段《旧约》的解释后，就改变了之前的看法。当我从字面上理解时，这些字句是死的，但一旦我听到它们的灵性意义，我就开始为我的绝望而责备自己，起码在那之前，这种绝望曾使我以为无法面对那些憎恨、嘲弄上帝律法和先知的人。但是我没有感觉到我只需走基督宗教的道路，因为它已经有了有学识的人，准备为它担保并不会在回答反对意见时失声。另外，我认为我自己的信念不应该受到谴责，因为两边的观点势均力敌。我认为基督宗教方面没有被打败，但也没有获胜。

下一步，我竭尽全力找到一些证明摩尼教谬误的证据。如果我能够构想出一种精神实体，那么他们的观点就会在瞬间被推翻，被我的思想拒绝。但是我做不到如此。不过，我对物质世界和整个自然思考得越多，尽可能通过我们的身体来感知，我愈加细查各种理论，越多地开始认为大多数哲学家的观点可能是正确的。于是，把所有的事情都当作疑问来对待，像学园派通常的做法那样，在教义与教义之间不作判断，我至少已经下决心要离开摩尼教，我在游移不定中徘徊，我认为继续留在摩尼教是不正确的，因为我发现一些哲学家的见解更有道理。然而，我完全拒绝相信这些哲学家可以医治我生病的灵魂，因为他们忽略了拯救人的基督之名。我决定在基督大公教会保留慕道友的身份，这是我父母所希望的，至少保留到我可以清晰地看见一束光引导我的脚步之前。

第六卷

1

主啊，我年轻时的希望，你这段时间在哪里？你为了躲避我而藏在哪里？难道不是你创造了我，使我与行走在大地上的野兽不同，也比天上的飞鸟更聪慧吗？然而，我在黑暗中走在危险的路上。我在自身之外的地方寻找你，在自己的心中也找不到你。我深入到海底。我丧失了所有信仰，并且对能够找到真理而感到绝望。

但是我母亲现在来到我这里，她的虔诚给了她力量，为追寻我而穿越陆地和海洋，用对你的坚定信仰来面对所有的危险。当船在危险中，是她安慰了全体船员的心，正是这些人在不习惯大海的乘客感到震惊时，转而安慰他们。她许诺他们将平安到达，因为你在异象中给了她应许。并且她发现我也处于严重的危险中，因为我对能寻找到真理感到绝望。我告诉她，我不是一个基督宗教徒，但是至少我不再是摩尼教徒了。可她没有高兴得跳起来，即便这个消息是出乎意料的。实际上，在这个程度上，她对我的担忧已经减轻了。在她向你的祷告中，她为我哭泣，好像我已经死了一样，但是她也知道你将唤醒我的生命。在她的心中，我被放在停尸架上，放到你的面前，等着你对这个寡妇的儿子说：“年轻人，我吩咐你起来。”然后，他便起来开始说话，接着你把他重新还给他母亲。于是当她听到她日复一日的祷告和眼泪，在最后，在很大程度上得到了回报时，她没有感觉到涌动的喜乐，她的心跳也没有加快。因我已经从错误中被解救出来，虽然我还没有抓住真理。可事实却相反，她确信，如果你已经应许她一切，你也会将剩余的应许给她。她心中充满了对你的信心，她很平静地告诉我，在基督里，她相信，在她离世之前一定会看到我成为虔诚的基督宗教徒。这是她告诉我的。但是对你，那所有怜悯之源泉，她流尽眼泪，更加热诚地祷告，只求你加快你的帮助并在黑暗中给我光明。她比以前更热切地去教堂，并全神贯注地听安波罗修讲道。对于她来说，安波罗修的话像她心里的活水，不断地涌流到永生。她将他看作上帝的天使般爱戴。因为她已经知道，通过他，我从原来的状态被引到目前这种不确定的摇摆状态。母亲确信我会走过这一状态，这种状态会把我从疾病引向健康，但是在我的前面还有更大的危险，这危险很像医生所说的危机。

5

从那时起，我开始相信基督宗教的教导。教会要求我们应该相信某些事物，即使它们未能得到证明，因为就算它们可以被证明，也不是所有人都能够理解，而且有些事物是根本无法被证明的。我想教会在这一事件上是完全诚实的，没有像摩尼教那样自负。摩尼教嘲笑那些通过信仰来认识事物的方式，轻率地对科学知识作出许诺，然后提出一个发明出来的荒谬体系，他们期望信徒们通过信任而相信，因为它们无法得到证明。主啊，于是，你把你最温柔、最仁慈的手放在我的心上，并使我的思想有条理，于是我开始意识到我相信无数看不见或不在场便看不到的事情——历史中的很多事情，许多关于某地某镇的事情我从未看见过，并相信许多朋友、医生或是他人的话。除非我相信这些事情，否则我们就要在人生中伴随绝对的虚无。最重要的是，这个信仰终于让我知道我的父母是谁，这信仰是如此确定和不可动摇，因为除非我相信被告知的内容，否则我绝不可能知道。通过这种方式，你使我认识到我不应该挑这些相信《圣经》的人的错误，你已经在地上的各民中建立了这样的伟大权威，而应该谴责那些不相信《圣经》的人们。而且我应该不在意这样一些人，他们问我为什么可以确信《圣经》是由一位从不说谎的真实的上帝通过圣灵赐给人们的。准确地说，我最需要相信这一点，因为在我读过的所有自相矛盾的哲学书中，误导人的假设无论引起怎样的争议，都没有一刻能够夺去我对你存在的信仰及你管理人类事务的权利。尽管那时我对你了解甚少。

我认为你是存在的，我们的福祉掌握在你的手中。这一信念有时强，有时弱，但是，即便我既不知道我应该如何思考你的存在，也不知道哪条道路将我引向你或引导我回到你身边，我却一直坚持这一信念。于是，由于我们太软弱了，无法仅靠理性来发现真理，基于这一原因，我们需要你圣书的权威。我开始相信，你绝不会在任何地方都赋予《圣经》这样显著的权威性，除非你已经打算让我们通过它寻找你并相信你。那些早先让我觉得荒谬的章节，现在听到了很多合理的解释，我视它们为深刻的奥秘。并且对我来说，更正确的做法应该是，《圣经》的权威应该通过纯正的信仰被尊重和接受，因为所有人都可以轻松地阅读它，但同时它又深藏着巨大的奥秘，拥有深刻的含义。它平实的语言和简约的风格使得任何人都容易理解，而且也能吸引有学问的人的关注。通过这种方式，《圣经》在它的大网下收罗了所有的人，有些人安全地通过了狭窄的网眼来到你那里。他们的人数并不多，如果不是《圣经》高高在上的权威，又神圣谦虚地将人们聚集在一起，人数还会更少。

[……]

13

我一直不断地被敦促结婚，而且他们已经为我选择了另一半，女方也接受了。我母亲竭尽所能帮助我，这是她的希望，一旦我结了婚，就会接受洗礼的救赎之水来洗净我的罪。她每天都很高兴，我变得更适合接受洗礼了，我对信仰的接受，使她看到她的祷告有了结果，你的应许得以实现。在我的要求和她自己的期望下，她每天用心灵祈求你在梦中能给她一些关于我未来婚姻的启示，但是你没有这样做。她有一些模糊和奇特的梦想，这是她被这些思想占据的结果，当她告诉我这些时，她把这些当作无关紧要的事情，说的时候也不像往常受到你启示时那样有信心。她经常说，有一些让她不能用语言形容的感觉使她能够区分你的启示和她自己的自然的梦。尽管如此，我婚礼的计划依然在进行，也征得了女孩的父母同意。她太年轻，离法定婚龄还有两年，但是我太喜欢她了，我愿意等待。

15

与此同时，我的罪恶越来越深重了。与我同居的女人被视为婚姻的障碍，被迫与我分开了，这一打击让我心如刀割，因为我仍深爱着她。她返回了非洲并发誓不再委身于任何其他男人，她留下了为我生的那个孩子。但是我太悲伤、太虚弱，我无法想象作为一个女人有此遭遇的情景。我需要等待那个已经答应与我结婚的女子两年，对此我有点不耐烦，因为我是情欲的奴隶，而不是真爱婚姻。我又找了一个情妇，没有结婚。这意味着我灵魂的疾病依然没有缓解，实际上是加重了，而且在无法解释的习惯的包庇下，会在婚姻的状态中延续下去。另外，当我第一个女人离开时，我受到的创伤没有愈合的迹象。最初，痛苦是尖刻而撕心裂肺的，然后伤口开始溃烂，而且痛苦变得更加迟钝，没有愈合的希望。

16

称赞和尊敬都是给你的，哦，怜悯之泉！当我的痛苦越来越深时，你越来越接近我。尽管我不知道，你的手已经作好了准备，要把我从泥潭中拉出来，并把我洗干净。除了对死亡和即将到来的末日审判的恐惧，没有什么可以阻止我在肉欲的泥潭中越陷越深。在我观念的转变中，这种惧怕从没有离开我的心。

[……]

我走过的路是多么的曲折啊！当我希望通过抛弃你而找到更好的东西时，我的灵魂将会遇到怎样的危险！无论我前后左右的路会通向哪里，我躺在艰难的床上，只有在你那里，灵魂才得以安息。你把我们从让我们迷失的错误的痛苦中解救出来，让我们走你的道路，并安慰我们：“继续奔跑吧，我会支持你，我会引导你并护送你到达终点。”

第七卷

1

到这时，我那充满罪恶的青春结束了。我逐渐步入成熟期，但是我年龄越大，就越是可耻地自欺欺人。除了这些通常肉眼所见之物外，我不能想象出任何实体。但是，主啊，我不能想象你人体的形状，我反对这一观点，因为我已经开始学习哲学，并且我很高兴地发现，我们的灵性母亲，你的大公教会，也反对这一信念。但是我不知道还能怎样想你。

我只是一个男人，一个软弱的男人，但是我试图把你看作最高的神，唯一的上帝，真正的神。在我心里，我相信你永远不会衰亡、受损或变化，尽管我不知道这是为什么，我确定无疑地懂得，会衰亡的事物较之不会衰亡的事物更为低级，于是我毫不犹豫地把不会受到伤害的放到会受到伤害的上面，而且我看见保持不变的事物比不断变化的事物更好。我的心里充满对我想象的创造的苦涩抗议，这唯一的真理是我仅有的武器，我可以努力用它清除云集于我心智之眼前的所有不洁的意象。但是我难以清除掉它们，每一次眨眼，它们又在我眼前聚集，成群地在我眼前出现，挡住了我的视线，尽管我不会想象你人体的形状，但我无法让自己摆脱这样一种思想，即你是某种身体物质在空间的伸展，要么渗透在世界之中，要么在世界之外的空间无限扩散。我认为这一物质是某种不会衰亡或受伤或变化的东西，因此比可能遭受腐败、损坏或变化的任何物质要更好。我用这种方式来推理，因为如果我试图想象某种没有空间方位的东西，对我来说它就什么也不是，绝对的虚无，连虚空都算不上。如果一个身体从被它占据的空间中移走，那个空间就空空如也，不管是在地上、水中、空气中或是天空中，那里依然将保持空无的状态。那儿什么也没有，就仅仅是一个空间而已。

[……]

于是我也想到你，我生命的生命，作为一个向四处延伸的多维的伟大存在，在无限的空间扩散，渗透整个的大千世界，并到达了世界之外没有界限的地方，于是地球和天空，以及所有创造物都被你填满，它们超不出你的范围，而你却没有极限。空气是覆盖大地的大气层，是一个物质的身体，但是却挡不住太阳光。阳光穿过它并穿透它，却没有破坏它或撕裂它，而是完全地填充它。用同样的方式，我想象你能够穿透物质的身体，不仅仅是空气和天空及大海，也包括地球，你可以穿透它们的所有部分，不论大小，故而它们因你的同在而被充满，你通过这种看不见的力量统管你创造的所有事物，内外统管。

这就是我坚持的理论，因为我不能用其他的方式想象你。但这个理论是错误的。如果它是正确的，就意味着地球的大部分将包含着你的大部分，而更小的部分则占更小的比例。任何事物都会因你的存在而充满，但是，通过这一方式，大象的身体比麻雀可以容纳更多的你，因为大象比麻雀大，而且会占据更多的空间。于是，你就被世界分成不同的部分，根据它的尺寸或大或小。这当然是很不正确的。但是那时你还没有照亮我的黑暗。

3

虽然我声称并坚定地相信，主啊，我的上帝，真正的上帝，你不仅创造了我们的灵魂，也创造了我们的身体，甚至创造了所有事物，无论是有生命的还是无生命的，尽管我相信你不会腐败、不会变异、也不会有任何程度的变化，我依然找不到对罪恶起源的明确的不繁复的解释。不管起源是什么，我找不到任何理论可以让我相信永恒不变的上帝是可变的。如果我相信这一点，我自己就会变成邪恶的成因，这正是我试图去寻找的事情。于是我继续从容地寻找，因为我很确信摩尼教的理论是错误的。我由衷地反驳这些人，因为我可以看见他们探寻罪恶的起源时，自己却满身罪恶，他们宁愿认为你的本体受罪恶影响，也不愿意承认他们自己会犯罪。

我被告知我们犯罪是基于我们的自由意志选择这样做，并且承受罪恶是因为你的正义恰好要求我们这样做。我竭尽全力理解这一道理，但还未能理解得很清楚。我试图在深渊中提高我被深渊吞没的精神感知，但是却再次陷入深渊。我不断地尝试，但总是重新陷进去。有一件事情让我能够进入你的光明。我知道我有一个意志，像我知道我有生命一样确信。当我选择做什么或不做什么时，我很确信是我自己，而不是其他什么人，实施了这一意志行为。因此，我即将认识到我的罪恶之源就在于此。如果我做任何违背意愿的事情，对我来说意味着发生某事，而不是我做了某事，我不把它看作错误，而是一个惩罚。并且，因为我认为你是公正的上帝，因此我承认你的惩罚也一定公正。

然而，接着我会再次问自己：“是谁造了我？当然是你，我的天父，你不仅是唯一的善，而且是善本身。那么，我怎样拥有一个可以选择做错事和拒绝做好事的意志，据此为我应该受到惩罚的原因提供一个合理的解释呢？是谁把这个意志给了我？当我的一切被上帝所创造，上帝本身是甜美的，是谁为我播下痛苦的种子？如果是魔鬼作祟，那么是谁创造了魔鬼？如果他曾经是一个好天使，由于自己的邪恶意志变成了魔鬼，他是怎样拥有让他成为魔鬼的邪恶意志的，难道不是由至善的造物主把他创造为天使的吗？”

[……]

12

我很清楚，即便会衰亡的事物也是善的。如果是最高的善，就不可能腐败。除非他们在某些方式上是善的，否则不可能腐败，如果他们是最高的善，就不可能朽坏。另外，如果他们完全没有善，就不存在朽坏的可能。腐败是有害的，但是除非他的善消失了，不然他就不会有害处。因此，要么一定是朽坏没有害处——这不可能；要么是任何东西都因善被剥夺而朽坏——这是毫无疑问的。但是如果他们被剥夺了所有的善，就根本不会存在了。如果他们依然存在，但是不会永久朽坏，他们就会比以前更好，因为他们现在继续在不可朽坏的状态中存在。如果说失去了所有的善，事物会更善，还有什么比这更荒谬呢？

于是我们必须得出如下结论：如果事物被剥夺了所有的善，他们将全体消失。并且这意味着只要他们存在，他们就是善。因此，无论是什么，都是善的。罪恶，我也试图发现它的起源，罪恶不是实体，因为如果是实体的话，就不会是善。要么是善的最高秩序的不可朽坏之实体，要么就是一个易朽坏的实体，这实体除非它是好的，否则就会朽坏。于是，对我来说，这就变得明朗了，你所创造的所有都是好的，没有实体不是你造的。因为你没有将他们造成一样，任何一个事物都是好的并且总体上都是好的，我们的上帝创造的所有被造物都是非常好的。

17

我很惊奇，尽管我现在爱你而不是你的某种幻影，但我没有一直为上帝感到快乐。你的美善吸引我靠近你，但很快我自身的重量就把我从你身边拽走，我沮丧地再次坠入世俗的迷乱之中。我背负的是肉体的习性。但我仍然保留着对你的记忆，而且我无可置疑的认为你是我唯一的依靠，但只是我还做不到。肉身永远是灵魂的负累，世俗的牢笼压迫着沉浸在万事中的思想。我也确信人类从世界的基本层面看见了你不可见的本质、你永恒的力量、你的神性，这些都通过你的受造物而为人所知。我想知道我要怎样才能欣赏地球或天国的物质中的美，是什么让我能够对变化的事物作出正确的决定，并规定某物应该这样，另一个应该那样。我想知道它是怎样的，我才能以这种方式判断事物，并且我意识到在我的思想之上，在变化的世界之上，存在着从不改变的真正永恒的真理。于是，我的思想逐渐从考虑物质转移到了灵魂，灵魂通过身体的感觉来感知事物，接着转移到灵魂内在的力量，身体的感觉将永恒的真实传递给灵魂。愚笨的动物是不会到达这个超越层面的。下一步是理性的力量，由肉体感觉交织而来的事实交由理性来判断。

这种理性的力量使我认识到自身也可能是变化的，它引导我思考它理解的来源。它将我的思想从常理中抽离，从加于其上的混乱意象中摆脱，所以，当它确信无疑地宣称永恒不变的事物比易变的事物更好时，它才发现照耀其全身的光究竟是什么，并明白如何才能认识到永恒不变之本体。除非由于某种原因，它认识到了永恒不变，否则它不可能确定永恒不变优于不喜欢易变。因此，在敬畏的瞬间，我的思想达到了洞见上帝本体的程度。于是，最后我确实看见了凭万物可感知的你不可见的本质。但是我没有力量凝视他们。在软弱中，我后退并回到自己的老路，除了那些我喜爱的和渴求的记忆之外，我什么也没有，就如同我闻到了美食的味道却尚未品尝一样。

18

我开始寻找获取足够力量的方式使我可以以你为乐，但是我找不到这一方式，直到我找到了上帝与人的中间人，耶稣基督，他是人，和人类一样，同时也作为上帝统治万物，受上帝永远的护佑，他向我发出召唤：“我就是道路、真理和生命。”是他与我们的肉体结合起来。这肉体是我们太软弱而无法获得的粮食，因为道成肉身，所以你的智慧是喂养婴儿期的我们的乳汁，我不够谦卑，没有将耶稣基督作为我的上帝，也没有领会到人性的弱点所造成的教训。这教训就是你的话语，永恒的真理，超越你创造物的最高层次，提拔那些服从于他的人到他身边。他用造我们的泥土为他自己在这世界上搭建了一座低矮简陋的小屋，通过小屋，他让那些服从他的人放下自己，来到他身边。他会治愈他们充满骄傲的心，并在这心里培育爱，让他们不再因为妄自尊大而误入歧途，但是当他们在脚下看到上帝本人时，那位以我们会死的肉身降卑来与享他的荣美的神，认识到他们自己的弱点。最后，他们在无力中匍匐在他的人性之前，然后随着神性的提升而提升。

第八卷

6

主啊，我的帮助者，我的救主，我现在要向你的圣名告知并忏悔，你是如何将我从紧紧束缚我的肉欲的禁锢和世俗事物的奴役中解放出来[……]

一天，由于某些原因，这些原因我记不起来了，内布利提乌斯没有和我们在一起，我和阿利比乌斯在我们的房子里接受一个来自非洲其他国家人的拜访，他叫蓬提齐亚努斯，在皇宫中担任要职。他向我们请教了一些事情，我们坐下谈了一会儿。碰巧他看见用来玩游戏的桌上放着一本书，就在我们的座位旁边。他拿起来，打开，并吃惊地发现书里面有使徒保罗的书信，他认为这是我当老师所用的一本书。于是他微笑地看着我，告诉我当他发现这本书，且在我眼前仅有这本书时，有多么的高兴，多么的惊喜。他是一个基督徒，是你忠实的仆人，我们的上帝。在教堂中，他跪在你的面前，日复一日地祷告，并牢记它们。当我告诉他我花了很大的精力学习保罗的书信时，他开始告诉我安东尼[11]的故事，安东尼是埃及的修士，他的名字在你的仆人中享有盛誉，但在这之前，我和阿利比乌斯从来没有听过他的名字。蓬提齐亚努斯认识到这一点后，更详细地给我们讲解，希望给我们这些无知的大脑注入一些知识，因为他很诧异我们没有听说过这个人。而我们则惊异于听到你最近做出的神奇事情，几乎就在我们的时代，在大公教会中，被那么多人所见证。实际上，我们三个人都很吃惊，我和阿利比乌斯因所听到的故事太奇妙而惊讶，而蓬提齐亚努斯吃惊是因为我们以前居然没有听说过。

从这以后，他继续告诉我们修道院里成群的修士的故事，他们的生活方式散发着你的馨香，是荒漠中的绿洲。所有这些对我来说都是新闻。米兰也有一座修道院，在城墙外面，在安波罗修的带领下有很多的兄弟团契生活，但我们对这也是一无所知。蓬提齐亚努斯继续说着，我们默默地听着。最后他告诉我们，他和三个同伴在特里尔城的事情。有一天下午，皇帝在竞技场看表演，他们在城墙边的花园里散步。他们分成了两组，蓬提齐亚努斯和另一同伴一直一起，另外两个则自己分开了。他们继续散步，第二组来到一座房子前，房子是你的一些仆人的，他俩精神贫乏，但天国属于他们。在房子里面他们发现了一本关于安东尼的书。其中一人开始阅读，并且非常着迷，为故事所激动，甚至在他读完故事之前，他就开始考虑自己如何也能过上同样的生活，抛弃世间的职业，专心服侍你。他们都是朝廷的官员，在为国家服务。突然之间，他心里充满圣洁的爱。他对自己很愤怒并充满了悔恨，他看着他的朋友说：“我们希望通过努力得到什么？我们期待什么？我们服务国家的目的是什么？我们在希望在宫廷里有比做国王的朋友更好的事情吗？尽管是这样，我们的位置一定岌岌可危并且暴露在危险之下？我们将会每次都遇到，仅仅达到另一个更大的危险。我们需要多久才能到达？但是只要我愿意，我可以在这个关键时刻成为上帝的朋友。”

他说了这些之后，又回到书里，遭受在他内心产生的新生命的痛苦煎熬。他继续阅读，在他心里，在那只有你可以看见的地方，正在发生变化。他的思想正在摆脱世俗，当时就表现了出来。因为他在阅读时，心潮澎湃，激动不已，最后哭了出来，因为他知道什么是正道并决定走正道。现在你的仆人对朋友说：“我已经同我的抱负决裂了，我决定侍奉上帝。从这一刻起，此时此地，我要开始服侍他。如果你不遵循我的引导，就别挡着我的路。”另一个人回答说，他会与同志站在一起，因为侍奉上帝是荣耀的，并且回报也是巨大的。于是这两位你现在的仆人，在付出必要的代价造塔，也就是说，他们以失去他们拥有的一切为代价来跟随你。

这时蓬提齐亚努斯和一直与他散步的同伴从花园的另一端走过来，他们来到房子跟前，看着他们的朋友。既然找到他们，他们说回家的时间到了，日光都开始消退了。但是另外两个人告诉他们自己已经作出的决定和计划做的事情。他们解释是什么原因促使他们决定走这样的路，他们是怎样达成一致的，并且要求朋友如果不加入，至少不要成为他们的绊脚石。蓬提齐亚努斯说，他和另一个人不会改变他们原来的道路，但是他们为自己的生活状态而感动地流泪。他们祝贺他们并要求他们代为祷告。于是，他们回到宫殿，被系在大地上的心所重负，但是其他人留在小房子里，心系天国。这两个人都已经订婚，但当那两个女人听到所发生的事情，她们也决定为你守独身。

7

这是蓬提齐亚努斯告诉我的。但是当他说的时候，主啊，你让我审视我自己。我已经背过身去，拒绝看到我自己。你让我正视自己，让我看见自己是多么肮脏，多么扭曲和卑鄙，怎样的遍体疮痍。我全部都看见了，站在那里，呆若木鸡，但是没有什么地方可以供我逃避自己。如果我试图移开目光，我会看着蓬提齐亚努斯，他依然在讲述他的故事，这样一来你就让我再一次与自己面对面，迫使我与自己的目光相接，让我可以看见我的邪恶并厌恶它。我已经知道了自己的罪孽，但是我经常假装那是不一样的东西。我视而不见，并忘记了它。

但是现在，当我听到那两个人是怎样作出选择，把自己完全托付给你，从而得到拯救时，我的心越是被他们所温暖，与他们相比，我更加恨我自己。我们的生命已经过去了很多年——12年，除非是我记错了——从我19岁那年读西塞罗的《荷尔顿西乌斯》起，它激发了我学习哲学的愿望。但是我依然迟迟不愿意放弃这个世界的快乐，这种放弃可以使我在这个世界自由地寻找其他幸福，这种寻找，不要说是发现，可以使我得到奖赏，它胜过人间的财宝和王国领土，胜过所有肉体的快乐，只要一点头就可以得到。作为一个年轻人，在犯错时我感到痛苦，特别是在青春期开始之时。我为了贞洁而向你祷告：“请你赐予我贞洁和节制，但不是现在。”我很担心你会马上答应我的祷告，并立刻治愈我肉欲的疾病，这种欲望是我想被满足的，而不是想去压制的。我徘徊在摩尼教渎神迷信的邪恶之路上，不是因为我认为那是正确的，而是因为我信仰它胜过基督教，我没有认真考究基督教，而是抱着恶意直接反对。

[……]

蓬提齐亚努斯一直地说，我的良心就是这样被啮蚀。我被燃烧的羞耻所战胜，当他结束他的故事并完成他此行的任务之后，他走了，我陷入沉思。我提出各种控诉来反对我自己。我拷问我的灵魂并用理性痛斥它，为什么现在应该追随我自己，既然我要努力地追随你。但它进行了反击。我的灵魂不愿听从，但也不能提供任何理由。所有过去的辩解已经用尽，并证明是错误的。它沉默不语，像害怕失去生命一样害怕除掉恶习，但是正是这恶习要了它的命。

8

内在的自我像一幢被一分为二的房子，两方对峙。在我内心激烈交锋中，激起了对我灵魂的反对。我找到了阿利比乌斯。我的表情暴露了我内心的不安，我惊呼：“我们到底怎么了？这个故事有什么意义？这些人没有接受像我们这样的教育，但他们站起身来直捣天国的大门，而我们这些饱学之士却匍匐在这个世界的血肉之下！这是因为他们走着我们引以为耻的那条道路吗？如果不跟上，会更糟糕吗？”

[……]

我们住的房子有一个小花园。我们可以自由地使用这个花园及其他房间，因为我们的东道主，也就是房主，不住在那里。我现在发现自己被我胸中的烦乱驱使，我不得不躲在花园里，在那里没有人会打断这激烈的挣扎，在那里我是自己的竞争者，直到我得出结论为止。结论是你知道的，主啊，但是我却不知道。与此同时，这种疯狂能使我清醒。我将死亡，这死亡会把我带向新生。我知道我内里的罪，但是没有意识到自己很快就会向善。于是我走进花园，阿利比乌斯跟着我。他的出现没有打乱我的独处，在这种情况下他怎能让我一人独处？我们在离房子尽可能远的地方坐下。我暴怒得像发了狂似的，但我自己没有接受你的意愿进入你的圣约。在我的骨子里，我知道这是我应该做的。在我内心深处，我向天上赞美。为达到这一目标，我不需要战马或战船，我甚至不需要从房子走到我们坐的地方那么远，因为要走过这一段旅程，并平安到达，没有什么比意愿的行动更为需要了。但是这必须是一个坚决又全心投入的意愿的行动，而不是那些不断地盘旋在我脑中的站不住脚的愿望，以致它必须与其自身角力，一部分努力向上，一部分坠落大地。

[……]

11

这是我疾病的本质，我被它折磨着，比过去更强烈地谴责自己，因为我被自己的锁链所捆绑。我希望锁链可以一次性全部打烂，因为现在对我来说，这只是一件捆着我的小事情。它一直捆着我。主啊，你从来没有停止关注我的内心。在你严厉的仁慈中，你用害怕和羞耻之鞭抽打我，以免我再次放弃使得破旧的残留锁链不被打破，而是重新获得力量，并更加快速地遮蔽我的眼睛。在心里我不停地说：“现在随它去吧，现在随它去吧！”仅仅说了这些，我就快要作出决定了。我即将作决定，但是我没有作成。尽管我没有退回到自己原来的状态。我站在决定的边缘，等着呼吸新鲜空气。我又试了一次，更接近我的目标了，那时依然又近了一点点，以至于我几乎可以伸手抓住它。但我还是没有达到。我不能伸手触及它或抓住它，因为我从自己应该死亡并获得新生的台阶上退了下来。我低级的本能牢牢地抓住了我，比高级的本能更强，那高级的本能却是我没有尝试过的。我越接近我要转变的时刻，我就越害怕地退缩了。但是这没有把我拉回去，也没有扭转我的目标——仅仅让我进退两难。

[……]

12

我探索自己隐藏的灵魂深处，并从中揪出可鄙的秘密，当我在心中把它们聚集在一起时，我的心里发生了强大的风暴，我的眼泪奔涌而出。我站起来，离开阿利比乌斯，好让我可以流泪并为我心灵的污秽而哭泣，对我而言眼泪更适合在独处中流淌。我走得很远以避免尴尬，甚至他在的时候也不例外。他一定察觉到我的感情，因为我已经说了一些，他已经从我的哽咽的声音中知道了。于是我站起来，让他充满困惑地坐在那儿。不知怎么的，我扑倒在一棵无花果树下，任凭我的泪水流淌，这是你应当接受的献祭。我的上帝啊，我有太多的话要对你说，我说了很多话，虽不是这些原话，但是这些意思：“主啊，你永远不会满意吗？我要一直接受你的惩罚吗？请忘记我长久以来的罪恶吧。”我仍然觉得自己被罪恶所捆绑。我继续在痛苦中哭求：“我不断地说‘明天，明天’，还要说多久？为什么不是现在？为什么不在现在就结束我的罪恶？”

我不断问自己这些问题，哭泣着，心中悲痛万分，这时我听见附近的房子里传来一个小孩子的歌声。我说不清是男孩还是女孩的声音，但是它一遍一遍重复着：“拿起来读，拿起来读。”我抬起头，仔细地想这是不是孩子们在游戏时常常念诵的歌谣，可是我记不起这样的歌谣。我止住了涌流的泪，站起身来，告诉自己这只可能是神圣的命令，要我打开《圣经》，去读那随之映入眼帘的第一段经文。我听过安东尼的故事，我记得他是怎样偶然去教会听到福音，并把它作为对自己的劝诫：“去变卖你的所有，分给穷人；你要积攒财富于天上，然后还要来跟随我。”经过这一神圣的宣召，他马上皈依了你。

于是我快速返回阿利比乌斯坐的地方，因为我离开时把使徒保罗的书信留在那里了。我抓起那本书，打开它，默默地阅读那映入眼帘的第一段：“不可荒宴醉酒，不可放荡纵欲，不可纷争嫉妒。总要披戴主耶稣基督，不要为肉体安排，去放纵私欲。”我不想再读下去，也不需要再读下去了。在那一瞬间，当我读完这句话时，好像一束信赖的光涌进我的内心，所有怀疑的黑暗被驱散了。

我用手指或其他的什么东西在书上作了标记，合上了书。当我告诉阿利比乌斯所发生的事情时，我的表情很平静。他也告诉我他的感受，当然那是我不知道的。他想看我所阅读的东西。我拿给他看，他接着读下去，我不知道接下来是什么，原来是：“你们要接纳信心软弱的人。”阿利比乌斯把这句话用在他身上并这样告诉我。这条忠告足以给他力量，没有经过任何犹豫的痛苦，他就下定决心并以此作为自己的目标。这很适合他的道德品质，在这方面他比我强很多。

然后我进去告诉我的母亲，她简直喜出望外。当我们讲述事情的经过时，她胜利地欢呼并赞美你，你满有大能，你的大能足以使你所行的超出所有我们所求所想的。因为她看见你应允她的远远超过了她曾经泪眼汪汪地祷告和悲伤哀求的。你使我皈依你自己，我不再渴求妻子或把任何希望放在这个世界上，而是牢牢地把握信仰的原则，那些原则你已经在多年以前在梦中向她展现了。是你把她的悲伤变成了欢乐，是比她曾经最想要的欢乐更多的欢乐，也是比她曾经想在我的孩子中找到的更甜美、更纯洁的欢乐。

第九卷

2

知道你在注视着我，我想自己最好从兜售口舌的市场中平静地退下来，而不是突然间轰动地离开。那些对你的律法与安宁没有思考的年轻人，他们在法庭上仅仅是撒谎和疯狂地争辩，我打算不让他们在我的口中买到任何武器以装备他们的疯狂。幸运的是，快到暑假了，我决定忍耐并推迟到一个合适的时候离开。既然我已经被你救赎，我就不想再次出卖自己。这个计划是你知道的，而除了我最亲密的朋友之外没有人知道。我们相互约定不让太多的人知道，虽然当我们自“流泪谷”上升时，唱着高升的歌，你已经给了我们锋利的箭和燃烧的火炭来抵御狡诈的舌头，这舌头可能以忠告的名义，用他们所谓的爱将我们吞下去，像人们吃自己喜爱的食物一样。

[……]

6

当提交我的名字去受洗的时间到来时，我们离开乡下回到米兰。阿利比乌斯也在那时决定在你那里获得新生。他已经具备举行圣礼所需的谦卑，他的身体已经经过严格的纪律的考验，他甚至会赤脚行走在意大利冰冻的土地上，这是很少有人敢做的。我们也带上了阿德奥达多斯，因我的罪而生的亲生儿子。你给了他所有的天赋。尽管他才15岁，但很多有学问和受人尊敬的人在智力上都不及他。我承认他的天赋是源于你，主啊，我的上帝，你是万物的创造者，你拥有巨大的力量来重塑我们的缺陷，我自己除了罪之外什么也没有给予他。是你，而不是别人，让我们按照你的期望把他培养长大。这都是你的馈赠，我都一一承认。

[……]

我们使他成为我们的同伴，在你的恩典之下没有人比我们自己更年轻。我们已经准备好以你的方式开始学习成长。我们都受洗了，昔日所有的忧虑一扫而光。这些日子太短了，我沉迷在惊奇和快乐之中，默想着你拯救人类的远大计划。当我听到赞美诗和颂歌的时候，不禁潸然泪下，来自你教堂的甜美歌声深深地打动了我。音乐在我耳边回荡，真理在我心中涌出，我献身的情感激烈涌动着，我泪如泉涌。但是这都是欢喜的眼泪。

8

哦，上帝啊，你让心意相同的人生活在一起，并把一个来自我家乡名叫艾弗第乌斯的年轻人带来，让他加入我们。他在我们之前皈依我主和受洗，并受雇为政府官员，但是他放弃了为政府服务而追随你。他留下与我们一起，打算过敬虔的生活。我们讨论着在哪里最能侍奉你，接着便一起动身返回非洲。当我们还在梯伯河口的奥斯蒂亚城[12]的时候，我母亲就去世了。

还有很多的事情我不能在这本书中记下来，因为我要节省时间。我的上帝啊，对于那些我还没有提到的事情，我祈求你接受我的忏悔和感激。但是我不会遗漏一件关于我母亲——你的仆人——的事情。在肉身上，她让我来到这个世界上；在她心里，她让我出生在你永恒的光中。我应该述说的不是她的能力，而是你给她的天赋。她既不是她自己的创造者也不是自己的老师。是你创造了她，即使是她的父母也不知道自己的孩子长大是什么样的。是基督的教导，是你独生儿子的指引，在一个基督教家庭中，她在成长中一直顺从并尊重你，这个家庭是你众多好的基督教家庭之一，属于你的教会[……]

10

在她去世前不久——你早已知道她的去世之日，主啊，但我们不知道——我和母亲两个人逗留在奥斯蒂亚城，透过一个窗户可以看见院子里的花园。我们经过长途跋涉之后待在那里，那地方远离尘嚣，我们在作远航之前的休整。我相信我要说的是你预先所做的秘密工作。我们在一起单独谈话，我们的交谈宁静而快乐。我们忘记过去，努力把握未来。在你的真理面前，真理就是你自己，我们在思考圣徒的永生是什么样子，这种生命是眼睛未曾见过，耳朵未曾听过，人心也未曾想过的。但是当我们张开心灵之口，接受从你天上的生命之源流出的泉水，只要是我们的力量所及，我们就会洒上圣水，并在一定程度上理解这一伟大的奥秘。

我们的谈话让我们得出结论，任何的肉体快乐，不论是多么伟大的快乐，不论世俗之光向它照射怎样的华彩，除了圣徒喜乐的生活之外，没有什么能够与之相媲美，甚至根本不值一提。当爱的火焰在我们体内燃烧得越旺，提升我们使我们越来越接近永恒的上帝时，我们的思想会从在不同程度上徘徊在物质事物的范围，到达天国，太阳和月亮及星宿从天国照耀着大地。我攀登得越高，就越惊奇地思考和诉说你所创造的一切。最终我们回到自己的心灵，然后又超越它们回到那个永恒富足的地方，在那里你让以色列人食用你真理的粮食。在那里生命是智慧，所有我们知道的事物都是由其创造，包括已经形成的事物，也包括尚未形成的事物。但是那智慧不是被创造的，它一直是那样的，而且永远是那样——或者，我不该说“一直是”和“将是”，可简单地说“它是”，因为永恒不是在过去也不是在将来。当我们谈论永恒的智慧时，我们用心中所有的力量来渴求它并极力追求它，刹那间我们达到并触摸到它。然后在叹息中，带着我们心灵里的收获，返回到自己说话的声音中，这声音里的每一个词是有开头有结尾的——这与你的话语相当的不同，我们的主啊，你持守自己到永远，不会衰老，并给所有事物以新生。

[……]

这是我们谈话的大意，尽管我们没有用这么精确的语言来说，也没有像对你说的这样准确。但是你知道，主啊，那天我们说话时，世界上所有的快乐与我们所谈论的相比显得没有任何价值。我母亲说：“儿子，对我来说在这个世界上我已经找不到任何更快乐的事情了。我仍可以做什么，或是我为什么在这个世界上，我都不知道，我在这世上已经没有其他的盼望了。我为什么希望在这个世界上活得长一点，只有一个原因，并且是唯一的原因，就是看见你在我死之前成为一个基督宗教徒。上帝应允了我的愿望，他的应许比这更多，因我现在看见你成为他的仆人，并轻视这世界所给你的幸福。我在这世界还有其他的祈求吗？”

11

我简直记不起我是怎样回答她的。从那天起大约过了5天，或是5天不到，母亲就发烧卧病在床了。一天，她在病中昏厥过去，并在短时间内失去了知觉。我们急忙赶到她身边，但是她很快就恢复了知觉，看着站在她身边的我和弟弟。她满脸疑惑地问：“我在哪里？”她近距离看着我们，满脸悲伤，沉默不语，她说：“你们要把母亲埋在这儿。”我什么也没有说，极力克制着眼泪，但是我弟弟说了一些话，大意是他希望母亲为了她的缘故死在自己的国家，而不是异国他乡。当她听到这些时，她面带忧色地看着弟弟，眼神中充满了对他这些世俗思想的责备。她转过来对我说：“听听他在说些什么！”然后她对我们俩说：“你们在什么地方埋葬母亲都没有关系。不要因为这事而让你们担忧！我所期望你们的是，不论在哪里，你应该在上帝的祭坛上想起我。”

[……]

母亲生病大约9天后，她56岁，我36岁时，她虔诚、全然献上的灵魂离开了肉体。

13

我的灵魂现在已经从那伤痛中康复了，也许我对这尘世的情感深感愧疚，我的眼中流出了另一种眼泪。主啊，那是我为你的使女所流的眼泪。那眼泪是从一颗惶恐的灵魂中流出的，这灵魂一想到每个与亚当同死的灵魂都要面对的种种危险就极度不安。尽管在她的灵魂离开肉体之前，她已经活在基督的里面，而且她的信仰和美好生活与你圣名的荣耀共鸣，但是，我不敢断言母亲从受洗得到新生的那时起，她口中没有说过一句与你诫命有抵触的话。你的儿子，就是真理本身，曾经说过：“凡是向弟兄发怒的、愚蠢的人，就必要遭受地狱之火的煎熬。”即使是值得颂赞的一生，如果抛开你的怜悯，当你审视他的时候，这也是有过失的。但是你不会无情地搜寻我们的缺点，因为我们希望并相信有一天我们会在你的身边找到一席之地。然而如果某人把他的功绩加以罗列，这功绩除了你的恩典之外还会有什么呢？但愿人能够明白他们只不过是人！他们所要夸耀的只是主！

为此，我的荣耀和我的生命，我心中的上帝，我要暂时抛开我母亲所做的所有善事。为那些，我感谢你，但是现在我为她的罪祷告。请你通过你那被钉十字架又坐在你的右边并为我们祈求的圣子来聆听，他是我们伤口的真正良药。我知道我的母亲总是表现出怜悯，并全心宽恕他人对她的冒犯。主啊，如果她在受洗之后这么长的时间里对你有所冒犯，请你宽恕她。我恳求你原谅她，不要追究她的责任。让你的仁慈隆重地欢迎你的判断吧。因你的话语是真实的，而且你已经答应怜悯那些值得怜悯的人。如果他们是值得怜悯的，这是你的馈赠。你要怜悯谁，就怜悯谁；你要恩待谁，就恩待谁。

[……]

让她与丈夫安息在一起。他是她的第一位丈夫，而且母亲没有再嫁。她服侍丈夫，把辛勤劳动得来的果实献给你，最后她为你赢得了他。主啊，我的上帝，启发你的仆人，我的弟兄——他们都是你的孩子。我的主人，我用心和声音，以及笔来服侍你——启发这些读你书的人来纪念莫妮卡，你的仆人，在你的祭坛上和巴特利西乌斯，早于她而去的丈夫。尽管我不知道，但是通过他们的身体你把我带进了这种生活。让读者虔诚地纪念他们，他们不仅是我的父母，而且是我的弟兄和姐妹，在教会我们大公教的母亲那里，我们同属于你，我们的天父，我们将是永恒耶路撒冷的居民，他们在向这圣城的朝圣途中一路叹息，从他们启程直到他们回到你身边为止，比起我一个人，如果更多的人通过阅读我的《忏悔录》来祈祷的话，我母亲对我最后的遗愿能够得到更大的满足。

第十卷

2

哦，主啊，人类良知的最深处在你眼前是赤露敞开的。就算我不向你忏悔，我有什么能逃得过你的双眼呢？我只能遮蔽自己眼睛不看你，而不能在你面前隐藏自己。但是，我现在的痛苦证明我对自己是多么不满意，你是我的光和喜乐。你是我的爱和渴求，我以自己为耻并把自己抛在一旁，只是追随你，而且只有在你里面，才能让你和我都满意。

因此，主啊，我的所有在你面前是赤露敞开的。我宣称向你忏悔使我获益良多。我不是仅用舌头的语言和声音来忏悔，而是用我灵魂的声音和我的思想大声向你哭泣来忏悔。你的耳朵能够听到，当我充满罪恶时，如果我对自己不满，这忏悔就是对你忏悔；当我做了善事时，如果我不认为是自己的美德，这也是对你的忏悔。主啊，你赐福正义之人，但是你首先使罪人成为正义人士。所以我的忏悔是在你——我的上帝——的注视下默默地进行，同时又是大声的忏悔，因为即使我的口舌完全无声，我的心也在向你哭泣。我向人诉说的一切美言，你已经提前在我心里听见了，而且不论你在我心里听见的美言是什么，都是你早先对我说过的。

4

人们在听我说的过程中希望得到什么益处呢？当他们听到借着你的恩典我与你这么地接近，他们会愿意与我一起感谢你吗？当他们听见我因自己的罪的重负而与你相隔绝时，他们会为我向你祷告吗？如果这是他们的心愿，我要告诉他们我是谁。主啊，我的上帝，如果很多人因为我向你表示感谢，很多人都因我而向你祷告，我就得不到什么好处。让那些我的真正的弟兄，按照你所教导的，爱我身上值得爱的品质，并让他们悲伤地在我身上发现那些按照你的教导而要责备的部分。这就是我希望自己真正的弟兄心里的感受。我不会对陌生人说话，也不会对“陌生的仇敌”说话，“他们做背信弃义的誓言，并举手发假誓。”我真正的弟兄是这样一些人，他们发现我的善就在心里高兴，而发现我的罪时就感到悲伤。他们是我真正的弟兄，因为不论他们看到的是我的善还是罪，他们都依然爱我。面对这样的人我才会敞露自己。让他们发现我身上的善而感到欣慰，发现罪时感到难过。那善是我在你里面借着你的恩典做的，而罪恶则是我自己的错误。这是你对我的惩罚。让我的弟兄为其中一个感到欣慰，为另一个感到难过。让感恩的旋律和悲伤的哭泣一起从他们的心中涌起，好像他们是在你面前燃烧的祭物的器皿。我向你祈求：“主啊，悦纳他们在你圣殿前献上的馨香，为了你名的缘故，请依照你丰盛的慈爱来怜爱我们。请不要放弃你已经开始的工作，而要让依然不完美的我变得完美。”

于是，如果我继续忏悔，我忏悔的不是我的过去，而是现在，这就是忏悔带来的善果。我向你忏悔时内心很快乐，但是也有忧惧。有悲伤，却也有希望。但是我不仅仅向你忏悔，而且也为向那些相信你的人忏悔，他们分享我的快乐并和我一样，命定是要死亡。在你的王国中，他们是我的同路人，并陪伴我同走天路，不论他们是先行，或是将要走，或是与我一起走过生命之路。他们是你的仆人，也是我的弟兄。你拣选他们做你的儿子。你让我视他们为主人，如果我希望与你同活并享受你的恩典，就必须服侍他们。这是你的吩咐，而如果这仅是只言片语，而没有基督的榜样作为行动的示范，那么这种命令对我来说就没有什么意义。我在话语和行为上都遵从你的吩咐。我在你的翅膀的庇护下如此行事，如果不是把灵魂交给你，寻求你翅膀的庇护，让你知道我的弱点，我就会处于危险之中。我不过是一个孩子，但是我的天父永远活着，我有一个足够强大的保护者来拯救我。那生养我、看顾我的是同一位，对我来说，除了你，全能的神，以外没有良善，你与我同在且甚至在我皈依你以前就与我同在了。于是我要按照你吩咐的去做，向我所侍奉的展示自己，不是曾经的自己，而是现在和将来的自己。但是，因为我不会检查我自己的行为，让我的言语按照它们的本意被理解。

30

你命令我要我继续让自己远离肉体的情欲，眼目的情欲和今生的骄傲；你命令我不要淫乱，虽然你并不禁止我结婚，但你建议我走一条更好的路。你给我恩典，我听从你的吩咐，甚至在圣礼之前我就开始禁欲。但是在我的记忆中，我说了很多，仍然还保留着以前习惯的印象。当我清醒时，这些习性对我有一些影响。但是当我进入睡梦中，它们不仅给我快乐，而且好像在行动上默认了。这种虚幻的想象强烈作用于我的灵魂和肉体，在睡梦中这幻想能够影响我，但是在现实中却不能。哦，主啊，我的上帝，我在睡觉时难道就不是我自己了吗，但是在我经历从醒到睡眠，或是从睡眠到醒时，我的情况是如此的不同。在睡眠中，我那可以抵制这种诱惑并保持坚定不动摇的理性哪里去了，在我闭上眼睛时被封闭起来了吗？它与身体的感觉一同入了睡吗？为什么我在梦中经常抵抗幻想的诱惑，因为我仍记得自己守贞洁的决定，并也遵守了，没有被这种东西诱惑？醒着与睡眠的差别如此之大，我睡觉时事情会以其他方式发生，当我醒着意识到的时候，我回到清晰的心智状态，因为这种不同，我就不用为此行为负责，尽管我对一些方式或是一些其他发生在我身上的事情感到遗憾。

哦，全能的上帝，你大能的双手有足够大的力量来治愈我灵魂的所有疾病。你给我更多的恩典就可以熄灭睡眠中挑逗我的火焰。哦，主啊，你会增加我的恩赐，让我的灵魂可以跟随我来到你身边，从被捆绑的阴谋中释放，并反对这种阴谋。通过你的恩典，我在睡梦中再也不会做出可耻的、不洁的行为，这行为被肉体的想象挑起，并导致身体被玷污。我不会再做，更不要说赞同它们了。对你来说，全能的主，“你有足够的力量来展开你的计划，这超越了我们所有的希望和梦想”，让我不再受这种诱惑，哪怕是意念上的微小试探，这些会激起我感官欢娱的试探，为我抵挡吧，让我在梦中也保持纯洁的心灵，这对你来说不是什么困难的事情。这是你可以在人生的任何时候为我做的，甚至在人生的黄金期。但是现在我对我良善的上帝作此忏悔，坦言我仍旧被这种罪恶所搅扰。我心中带着敬畏，因你的赐予而喜乐，但是我为自己的匮乏而悲伤，相信你会在我身上完善你的怜悯，直到我获得完全的安宁，那就是当死亡被吞没在凯旋之中时，我要全身心地与你共享的安宁。

35

我必须说出另一种诱惑，这种诱惑更加危险，因为它更加复杂。除了我们肉体的欲望，使我们渴望满足自己的感官和快乐，并引导我们走向毁灭，如果我们远离你而成为它们的奴隶，思想也会受到特定的倾向去使用肉体的感觉，不是为了某种身体的自我放纵，而是满足自己的好奇心。这种无用的好奇的伪装以科学和学习为名，因为它源于我们对知识的渴求，用眼看是获得知识的主要方式，在圣经里这被称为：“眼目的情欲”。尽管，准确地说，看是眼睛的适当功能，我们用其他感觉的词，我们使用它们来获得知识。我们不会说“听听这是多么闪光”“闻闻这是多么的亮”“尝一下这是怎么发光的”，或是“摸摸这是怎么发光的”，我们说这些事物是因为我们看得见。我们不仅会说“看看这是怎样发光的”，当某物只可以被我们的眼睛感知时，我们也会说“看看它有多响”“看看闻起来怎么样”“看看味道怎么样”“看看坚硬程度如何”。于是，我说，通常的感官体验被叫作眼目的情欲，原因是，虽然视觉的功能主要属于眼睛，当用于发现知识时，我们也一样使用其他的感觉器官，可以类推。

我们可以很容易地区分享乐的动机和好奇的动机。当感觉需要快乐时，他们就寻找视觉上美丽的事物、和谐的声音、芬芳的香味，以及尝起来美味且摸起来柔软的东西。但是，当他们的动机是好奇时，他们会寻找相反的事物，仅仅是为了证明，不是为了一种不快的体验，而是为了体验了解和发现的滋味。在看到一具破碎的尸体时，除了恐惧之外，还有什么愉悦感呢？然而人们会趋之若鹜地看那躺在地上的尸体，仅仅是为了体验其带给他们的悲伤和恐惧的感觉。他们甚至害怕那会给他们带来噩梦，好像当他们清醒时有某种东西迫使他们去看，又或者像是有什么东西像美丽的谣言一样吸引他们。对于其他的感觉也是一样，虽然再举例显得有点单调。在戏院里面怪异和奇特的表演满足人们不健康的好奇心，出于同样的原因，人们被引向探寻自然的秘密，这秘密与我们的生活没有关系。这种知识对他们没有价值，并且他们期望得到的仅仅是为了求知。这也是很奇怪的，这使得人们求助巫术，并出于为了让一些人走上邪路的目的而努力获取知识。这种情况甚至闯进了我们的信仰里，当我们要求从上帝那里看神迹奇事时，我们便把上帝放在了试探中，我们这么做不是为了得到拯救，而单单是喜欢一种体验。

[……]

我的人生充满了这种错误。我唯一的希望就是你无垠的慈爱。当我们的心变成储藏室，堆满这种没有价值的货物时，我的祈祷就因此经常被打断和分散。即使在你出现的时候，我们内心的声音也传到了你的耳朵，各种各样的琐碎思想闯进来，并打断祷告的伟大行动。

41

现在我开始思考自己的罪带来的可悲状态，根据诱惑的三种不同情况，我祈求你伸出援助之手拯救我。在我受伤的内心，我看见了你的光辉，这使我眩目。我问：谁可以接近这个荣耀？你的照管将我排除在外。你是掌管万物的真理。但是在我自私的渴望中，我不愿意失去你。与你在一起时，我想撒一个谎，就像当错误遮蔽一个人的双眼，使他看不到真理时，他不会承认自己明显的错误。这样一来，我失去了你，因为你不会与谎言同在。

42

谁可以让我重归于你，我应该向天使求助吗？但是如果我寻求到了帮助，我应该祷告什么呢？我该使用什么样的圣礼呢？我听说很多人没有力量通过自己回到你那里，就通过这种方式来试一下，但是他们都以渴望奇怪幻象而告终，他们唯一的收获只是妄想。他们试图在所有自负和傲慢的知识中找到你。当他们应该悲痛捶胸顿足时，内心却被骄傲所填满。因为他们在心中聚集，他们吸引堕落天使，低空中的王子，他们与骄傲为友并与之联合。但是这种联合捉弄了他们，使用魔幻的技巧，我们所找的是可以洗净他们罪恶的中保，实际上不是中保，而是化作光明天使的魔鬼。这魔鬼不是血肉的生物，而是对骄傲肉体的强有力的诱惑。他们都是终将要死亡的人和罪人，而你，主啊，你是不朽的和无罪的，他们想与你和解。但是在上帝与人之间的中保必须在某种程度上与神一样，又与人一样。如果在这二者之间，他像人，那么他就会离神太远；如果在二者之间像神，又会离人太远。这两种情况他都无法成为中保。但是因为你隐藏了正义的宣告，你给了魔鬼一个特权来嘲弄那些骄傲的人，他装作一个中保。一方面这个中保像人，他是有罪的；另一方面，他假装像上帝，因为他没有穿着会朽坏的血肉外衣，他试图把自己作为不朽的代表。但是因为罪的果报就是死，他与人一样出于这个原因而会被宣判死亡。

43

但是有一个真正的中保，在你隐秘的怜悯中，你已经把他展现给了人们。你派遣他，让人们通过他的榜样学习谦卑。他是神与人的中保，耶稣基督，他是一个人，他出现在人间，在有罪和必死的人与不朽和公义的上帝之间。他像人，所以会死；他像神，所以公义。因为他正义的回报是生命与和平，他的到来是通过他与上帝结合的公义，通过选择去分享他的死亡，使那些被他称义的罪人免于死亡。他被预示给古代的圣人们，让他们可以通过相信他即将来受难而得救。正如同我们因相信他在多年之前为我们受死而得救一样。因为作为人，他是我们的中保，但是作为上帝的圣言，他就不是上帝与人之间的中保，因为他与上帝平等，并与上帝同为上帝，与他一起同为一个上帝。

[……]

我的罪恶和被死亡加重的痛苦让我恐惧，我反复思考自己的问题，并几乎决定要去沙漠中寻求庇护。但是你阻止我这样做，并给我力量说：“他替众人死了，为的是要使活着的人不再为自己活着，却为那替他们死而复活的主而活。”主啊，我把我所有的烦恼都抛给你，从现在开始我要默想你律法的奥妙。你知道我是多么软弱，我的知识是多么匮乏，教导我并医治我的软弱吧。你的独生子拥有一切知识和智慧，用他的血拯救了我。把我从仇敌的嘲笑中解救出来，我知道救赎的代价。我吃他的肉，饮他的血，并与其他人分享。因为贫乏，我渴望充饥，成为吃饱喝足的人。谁追寻主，谁就会赞美主。

第十一卷

3

让我聆听并理解这些话：起初，你创造了天地。摩西[13]写下这些话。他写下以后就到你那儿去了，留下了这个你对他说话的世界。他从此不在这儿了，我不能与他面对面。但是如果他在这儿，我会缠住他，并以你的名义，我会苦苦地求他为我解释这些话。我会竖起耳朵全神贯注地聆听从他嘴里发出的所有声音。如果他用希伯来语说，他的话只会穿耳而过，我的大脑里什么也不会留下。如果他说拉丁语，我会知道他说什么。但是，我怎样才能知道他说的是真的呢？如果我也知道，那么我就不用通过他得到这些知识了。然而在我思想的最深处，真理既不是希伯来文，也不是希腊文、拉丁文，或任何外国语言，它仍然会向我说话，虽然不是通过嘴唇和舌头形成的音节来向我说话。它可能会是低语：“他说的是真理。”但是我马上就会确定。我会自信地对你的这个仆人说：“你告诉我的是真理。”

于是，我不再质问摩西，因为你赐予他的话是真的，因为你用你自己的真理充满他。我祈求你，我的上帝，宽恕我的罪，并像赐予你的仆人摩西以恩典说那样的话，来赐予我恩典以理解这些话。

9

他是起始，上帝啊，在那时你创造了天地。通过这种奇妙的方式，你说话，并在你的话语里、你的儿子——你的力量、你的智慧、你的真理创造了他们。

谁可以理解这个奥秘，或是可以把它解释给其他人呢？这是什么光？这柔和的光不时敲击着我的内心，促使我在敬畏中颤抖，然而也因它们的温暖燃烧我。我颤抖着感觉到我与它的不同，然而迄今为止我却与它相像，我因为它的火光而发亮。这是智慧之光，是智慧本身，时常地照耀着我，驱散笼罩我的阴云。但是当我软弱地远离这光时，这些云就重新在浓密黑暗的笼罩下包裹了我，这是我要承受的惩罚。我的力量因为痛苦而损耗，以致我不能持续被祝福。因此我将会活着，直到你宽恕了我的罪，并治愈我所有致命的疾病。你会把我从死亡的危险中解救出来，戴上你怜悯祝福的冠冕，满足我美好的愿望，像保存雄鹰的羽毛那样来保留我的青春。我们的拯救建立在某些东西的希望之上，在忍耐中我们等待你应许的实现。让这些能够听你话的人说出心声。我们相信你启示的话语，我要大声地说：“主啊，你创造的是多么五彩缤纷！你创造他们的智慧是多么奇妙！”你创造天地时开始的是智慧，智慧也是开始。

13

一个思想变化无常的人，其思想总会因过去时间的观念迷失，他可能会好奇：你，全能的上帝，万物的创造者和掌管者，天地的造物主，为什么会在你伟大创造工程最后完工之前，空闲着并让无数的时光流逝？我对这些人的忠告是摇醒他们的迷梦并仔细思考，因为他们的惊奇是基于错误的观念。

你是创造者，是所有时间的源头，在你创造时间以前怎么会有无数的时间流逝掉呢？一直存在着的时间不是你创造的吗？如果过去的时间不存在，又怎么能消失呢？

你是一切时间的创造者。如果，在你创造天地之前没有时间，那么怎么能说你在虚度光阴呢？你一定是创造了那个时间，因为时间在被你创造之前，是不会流逝的。

[……]

14

因此正确地说，如果你没有创造什么，就没有时间，因为时间是你所创造的。并且时间不会与你一起永存，因为你永恒不变。否则，如果时间永恒不变，就不是时间了。

[……]

19

你，所有造物的统治者，是用什么方式向人们的心灵揭示未来的呢？你曾启示先知们。这未来对我们来说是不存在的，那么现在你是怎样为我们启示未来的呢？还是你启示的只是未来事物在目前的征兆？把不存在的事物启示给我们这是完全不可能的。你做这事的方法超出了我们的理解。我没有能力来理解这个奥秘，通过我自己的能力绝不可能。但是在你的力量中，我可以理解，当你给予我恩典来看时，你是我灵魂之眼的甜美之光。

[……]

25

我向你忏悔，主啊，我依然不明白时间到底是什么。而且我忏悔自己不知道在时间中说的是什么，我已经谈论时间有好长时间了，如果实际上时间不是一直在流逝的话，那么这么长的时间就不算长的时间。如果我不知道时间的话，我怎样知道这一点的呢？是我确定知道时间是什么，只是不知道如何用言语来表达我所知道的吗？我处在一种难过的状态中，因为我甚至不知道我到底不知道什么！

[……]

31

哦，主啊，我的上帝，你的神秘是何等的深奥！我的罪恶使得自己被远远地抛开在你安全的天国之外！医治我的双眼并让我在你的光辉中欢呼雀跃。如果有一颗心灵被赋予这种强大的力量，知道并可以预知所有的过去和将来，就像我熟悉许多赞美诗一样，这颗心灵将会令人惊奇地超越信仰。我们要对此保持敬畏，过去的岁月和将来的时间都瞒不过这颗心灵。这就像我唱赞美诗，我知道自己已经唱了多少，还有多少没有唱，我离开头已经多远，离结束还有多久。但是，这是不可思议的，宇宙的创造者，灵魂与肉体的创造者，仅仅以这种方式就知道所有的过去和未来。你的知识远比这更奇妙、更神秘。不像人的知识，只唱一些他熟悉的赞美诗，或是听其他人唱一些他熟悉的赞美诗。当他这样做时，他的情感发生了变化，他的感觉被划分，因为他一边要想未唱的歌词，一边又还要记着他所唱过的。对于你来说绝非如此，你是永恒的不变，真正永恒的思想创造者。从一开始，你就知道天地，在你的知识中天地没有变化。以同样的方式，在起初你创造了天地，在你的行动中也没有改变。一些人明白这个道理，另一些人却不明白。让他们所有的人都赞美你吧！你超越于万物之上，但你又住在谦卑人的心中。因你安慰劳苦重担之人，抬眼仰望你高台的人不会跌倒。

第十二卷

2

我的唇舌向在最高处的你庄严谦卑地忏悔，是你创造了天地，我所看见的天和我脚所踏的地，这塑造了我们身体的大地。是你，创造了这一切。主啊，但是哪里是天外之天？诗篇中说：“天外之天属于上帝，他将大地赐予人的子孙？”我们看不见的天国在哪里？与之相比我们所看见的只是大地，可天国在哪里呢？

[……]

3

毫无疑问，为什么我们说大地是“看不见且没有形状的”，那是没有光线的深渊，原因是大地没有形状。为什么你要写“黑暗统治着深渊”，这唯一的原因就是那里完全没有光。如果有光，除了在其之上，又能在哪里抛洒光辉呢？但既然没有光，黑暗的在场不就是光的缺席吗？因此黑暗统治着一切，因为上面一点光都没有，就好像沉默统治着没有声音的地方。无声的沉默不就是声音的缺席吗？

[……]

4

除了用熟悉话语，还能用什么让即使愚笨的大脑也可以理解呢？在构成这个世界的事物中，能找到什么比“大地”和“深渊”更能描述这种空虚混沌呢？因为它们处于创造物的最底层，相对高级的事物，有底层事物的美丽形式，光芒四射。为什么我不能假定“大地是无形又没有形式的”这句话是要传达给人类的呢？而这恰是以一种他们可以理解的方式传达的。你创造不美丽的无形状的事物是为了让这个美丽的世界有形吗？

7

如果它开始就在那儿，为了做这些可见的、复杂形式的工具，那么它自己的起源是什么？只能把它的出现归结于你，所有的事物在你那里都有起源，不论它们存在的程度如何，虽然它们越不怎么像你，就离你越远——我这里不是说空间。这意味着，主啊，你不会像事物或环境一样改变，而是始终如一，恒久如一，并且一模一样，圣哉、圣哉、圣哉，主啊，全能的上帝，你在最初创造了事物，以你自己的方式，通过你的智慧，这智慧从你的本质而生，并且你从无中创造了有。

你创造了天地，但你并没有用你自己的本质来创造。如果你这样做，它们就会与你独生爱子平等了。对你来说，公义绝不会承认你本体以外的本体能与你平等。主啊，除你这位三位一体，一体三位的主，在你之外没有任何东西可以创造天地。因此，你必定是从无之中创造它们，一个是伟大的，一个是渺小的。没有什么是你不能做的。你是善的，所以你所造的都是善的，不管是伟大的天外之天，还是这个渺小的世界。你就是本身，除你以外什么也没有。于是，你从虚无中创造了天地，并将一个与另一个区分开来。一个与你接近，另一个与虚无接近。一个仅仅通过你来超越，另一个仅仅比虚无少一点。

13

主啊，这就是当我读到“起初，上帝创造了天地。地是不可见的，没有形状，黑暗统治着深渊”这些话时，解释你的《圣经》的方式。《圣经》上没有说你在哪一天创造了它们，但是我理解这个原因，“天”在这里意味着天外之天——那是智力的天国，在那里知识具有优先权，可以立刻知道所有，而不是部分，不像从一个镜子中看到的模糊的反射，而是作为一个整体，是清晰的，是面对面的，不是首先、其次……就像我刚刚说过的，而是一次认识全部，远远不是时间的起落——而“地”则意味着不可见、无形的，它也不像时间那样由此及彼地变化，因为没有形式就什么也没有。天与地，按我的理解，意味着当《圣经》说“起初，上帝创造天地”时，没有提到日子，天就是天外之天，这天从一开始就被赋予了形式，而地是不可见的，也没有秩序，完全没有形式。实际上《圣经》在下一节经文中解释的就是这个意思。因为它说第二天苍穹被创造，那就叫作天，这给我们理解第一句说的天是指没有提到日子的天。

27

摩西留下的论述，你选择将其传给我们，这论述像泉水一样，内容丰富，因为它在限定的空间里流动。泉水比那没有支流但长度更长的河流流量更大，有更多的支流，并浇灌更多的土地。同样，从摩西之口，发出极为简短但又命定的话，这些话为一大群讲道者所用，从我们每个人中涌出真理的清泉，通过更冗长又迂回的短句，推出一个尽可能像他一样的，真正的关于创造的解释，一些人会选择这种或那种解释。

[……]

31

因为这个原因，尽管我听见有人说：“摩西的意思是这样的”或“摩西的意思是那样的”，我想更虔诚的说法是：“如果两种观点都是对的，为什么摩西不采用两种呢？如果有人从同一句话中读出了第三种或是第四种，或是任何一种真正的意思，为什么我们不应该相信摩西读出了所有的意思呢？只有一位上帝使摩西用最适合大多数人的头脑的方式写《圣经》，这些人都可以在里面看见真理，虽然在每一个情形中不是同样的真理。”

就我而言，我坚决地声称并竭尽全力表示，如果要我写一本书，这书被最高权威认可，我宁愿用这种方式来写，一个读者可以在我的话中找到回应，不论他能够理解什么样的真理。我宁愿用这种方式来写，而不是明确地把一种简单的正确意见加在上面，尽管这些意见没有错误，但这会排斥其他意见。如果这是我为自己选择的，我的上帝，我不会这样轻率，好像假定一个像摩西一样伟大的人从你那里仅得到很少的恩赐。当他写这些话时，他完全意识到他们是默许的。他意识到了每个真理，那些我们可以从中推演出的真理，和那些我们尚不能推演但却可能发现的真理。

32

[……]

主啊，我的上帝，仅这些话我就写了这么多！如果我用这种篇幅来评论你的整部《圣经》，我需要多少耐心和时间啊！让我继续把自己的思想用于《圣经》，但是要简短一些。这样就可以让我满足于就给出一个解释，这个解释是被你点拨的，是正确的、确定的、好的，尽管我能知道还会有很多其他的解释。就让我在你面前带着坚定的信念作这样的忏悔，如果我给的解释与摩西的意思一致，那么我做的就是正确的、最好的。这就是我必须竭尽全力去做的。但是，如果我失败了，我至少要说，通过《圣经》的句子启示的你的真理，是与你愿意启示给摩西的是一样的。

第十三卷

1

我呼求你，上帝，我的怜悯，你创造了我，在我忘记你时，你没有忘记我。我请求你来到我的内心，激发我渴求你，准备我来接纳你。现在，当我呼求你，不要遗弃我，甚至在我呼求你之前你已经来帮助我。以各种各样的方式，一遍又一遍地，当我远离你时，你督促我来听你的声音，让我转向你，并一直亲自呼唤我，让我向你呼求帮助。你抹去我所有的罪恶行迹，为的是不要我遭受自己双手所做的应得的惩罚，这罪使得我远离你。甚至在我做之前，你已经考虑了我值得你赞赏的善行，以便回报你的手创造我之功劳。在我之前，你就存在了。我还未成型，你给了我存在。然而现在我存在了，这是出自你的美意，你提供了要创造怎样的我和创造我所需要的一切。你不需要我，我这个生物没有任何长处可以帮助你，我的主，我的上帝啊。我来服侍你不是由于这会减轻你的疲劳，也不是因为如果没有我的服侍你的能力就会减少。我不能像农民耕种土地那样地服侍你，因为即便我的耕作失败了，你的工作也会结出果实。我只能服侍你、敬拜你，以至能得到从你而来的善，若没有你，我就得不到善，因为我甚至不能再接受善。

3

在你创造之初，你说“要有光，就有了光”。

我想这些话可以被适宜地理解为关于灵魂的创造，因为它已经有了某种生命，可以获得你发出的光。但是，正像先前它由于自己的贫乏，不能向你说什么，于是没有这种生命来接受你的光，现在它既然存在了，它就不能说是因为自己的美德而接受了这一礼物。在这无形的世界状态中，除非它变成光，否则就无法取悦于你。当它变成光后，不仅是简单的存在，而是注视并依附你，你这照耀它的光。它也通过这种方式获得你的恩典，仅仅是你的恩典，所赐予它的存在和所赐予的生命就生活在幸福中了。通过经历一种向善的变化，它被转向那不变的，不论是变得更好还是更坏，这变化都是朝向你的。只有你可以不变化，因为只有你是绝对的简单，存在与幸福的存在是一样的，因为你是你自己的至福。

5

当我读到你的圣灵运行在水面上，我模糊地看见你是三位一体的，我的上帝。是你，天父，在最初借着我们的智慧创造天地，这智慧是你的智慧，源于你，与你平等，与你永存，这就是，在你的圣子体内。关于天外之天我有很多要说，地是不可见、没有形状的，而深渊显示出灵的创造时是多么黑暗，在其外形的空无中，没有连续性和稳定性。这只有归向你生命本身，才能获得你的荣耀光辉的反射而获得美丽和生命。通过这种方式，天外之天就出现了，天外之天分为水上和水下的。当我说这些事物时，我采用“上帝”一词，上帝创造了它们，即天父在这“起初”里面创造，亦即在圣子里创造。但是，我相信的上帝是三位一体的上帝，我在他的《圣经》神圣的字句中寻找这一真理，并发现《圣经》说你的灵运行在水面上。这里就提到三位一体，我的上帝，圣父、圣子和圣灵，万物的创造者。

11

谁可以理解三位一体的全能之神呢？我们都谈论他，虽然可能我们谈论的并不是真的三位一体，因为很少有人在谈论三一神的时候知道自己说什么。人们为之互相争辩，观点不一，但是除非他们处在平静中，否则就只能得到一个虚无的幻象。

我希望人们考虑三个问题。这三个问题都是与人相关的。这问题与三位一体不同，但是我建议他们可把它视作一项头脑训练，我们可以检验自己并认识到这种差异是多么大。这三个问题是：存在、知识和意志，我可以说我是、我知道、我要。我是知道和意志的存在。对于我是和我要我也知道，并且我要存在，也要知道。在这三者中——存在、知识和意志——有一个不可分割的生命，一个生命，一个思想，一个存在。因此，尽管他们各不相同，但这种区别并没有割裂它们。这对于那些有能力理解的人来说并不难。实际上，他需要的不是越过自己来看。让他近距离地审视自己，估量一下，然后告诉我他发现了什么。

但当他在这三者中发现了一个共同的原则，并告诉我他的发现，他不能认为自己发现了在这之上永恒不变的本体，这本体永恒不变的存在，永恒不变的知道，永恒不变的意志。因为我们中没有任何人可以轻易地认为上帝是三位一体。因为这所有的三者——永恒不变的存在、永恒不变的知道、永恒不变的意志——都在上帝的里面。不论三者是否在三位一体中的一个位格里面，每一个都是三者重合的；或者不论这些假定是否是真的，其单一性与复杂性以一种奇妙的方式合二为一，虽然上帝是无限的，然而他是自己的结束又是自己本身，因此三位一体在他自己里面，并为他自己所知，又满足自己。那最高的存在，唯一的不变者，存在于无限的统一体中。这是一种神秘，无人能解释，我们中谁又可以断言他可以解释呢？

28

“你看着你所创造的一切，哦上帝，并发现它们非常好。”我们也看见所有这些事物，并知道它们很好。在每一次的工作中，你首先命令它们被创造，当它们被创造出来之后，你依次看着每一个事物，并认为它们都是好的。我计算过并发现《圣经》告诉我们七次你看见你所创造的是好的，当你在第八次去看你所有的受造物时，我们被告知你发现它们不仅是好，而且是非常好，因为你立即把它们当作整体来看。每个分开的创造都是好的，但当他们被看为一个受造物时，他们不仅是好的，他们非常好。

这种说法可以用于所有美丽的事物。一个事物有若干部分，美丽蕴含在每一个部分中，整体的事物比单独的部分更漂亮，这都被恰当地组合并排列，组成一个整体，尽管每一部分就其作为单独的部分来说，本身就是一个美丽的事物。

35

哦，主啊，上帝，赐予我们平安吧，我们所有的一切都是你的馈赠。请赐予我们安宁，安息日的平安，永远没有夜晚的平安。因为这世界的秩序在其所有的美丽中都会消逝。当它们的存在达到极限时，所有美好的事物都将结束。它们已经被安排了有它们自己的早晨和夜晚。

37

在那永恒的安息日，你会在我们这里安息，就好像你现在在我们里面工作一样。我们要享受的安息是你的，就好像我们目前所做的工作是你的工作一样，只不过是通过我们来做。但是，主啊，你永远在工作，也永远在休息。你不是通过时间来看，也不是通过时间来运动，也不是在时间里休息，然而你创造了我们在时间中所看见的事物；你创造了时间本身，当时间停止时你就休息了。

38

我们能看见你创造的这些事物，因为它们存在。但是它们仅仅因为你看见它们而存在。在我们本身之外，我们看见它们存在，并且在我们自身里面，我们看见它们的美好。但是当你看到创造它们是正确的时候，你以同样的方式看见他们被创造。

我们只在瞬间之后，被激励做善事，即我们的心灵接受到圣灵的激发时，在这之前我们冲动地做坏事，因为那时我们已经离弃了你。但是你，唯一的神，良善的上帝，从来没有停止从善。通过你恩典的馈赠，我们做的一些工作是好的，但不是持久的。在那之后，当你把我们纳入你伟大的神圣存在时，我们希望可以找到安息。但是你是善本身，除了你自己不需要其他的善。你永远在安息中，因为你是自己的安息。

什么人可以教导其他人明白这个真理呢？什么天使可以教导其他的天使呢？什么天使可以教导人呢？我们必须问你，向你寻求答案。我们必须叩响你的门。只有这样我们才可以得到回答，并找到我们要寻求的结果。只有在那时，门才会向我们打开。

[1]在天主教中，盐是有特别的意义，盐加进水里制成圣水，很多仪式都会用到这种圣水。

[2]罗马诸神之一，朱庇特的妻子。

[3]即今阿尔及利亚的末达乌路赫（Mckourouch）。

[4]古希腊时期出现了民主制度，公共言论成为政治生活的一部分，因此演讲、辩论就很流行，于是出现了专门教授该技艺的老师，罗马也遗传了此风气。

[5]位于非洲北海岸，今突尼斯境内。

[6]西塞罗（公元前106—前43），古罗马著名政治家、演说家、雄辩家、法学家和哲学家。

[7]保罗（3—67），原名扫罗。保罗是亚伯拉罕的后裔，属于便雅悯支派的以色列人，早年参与迫害基督徒，据《圣经》记载，耶稣曾向他亲自显现。保罗是第一个去非犹太人中传播福音的基督徒，对于早期基督教会发展作出巨大贡献，可称为基督教的第一个神学家，《圣经》新约中很多书卷均是出自保罗之手。

[8]与奥古斯丁同时代的著名演说家。

[9]又称明教，是一个源自古代波斯宗教，为公元纪中叶波斯人摩尼（Mani）所创立。

[10]塞内加（公元4—65）是古罗马最重要的悲剧作家，他受斯多葛哲学影响，精于修辞和哲学，并曾担任过著名暴君尼禄的老师。他主张人们用内心的宁静来克服生活中的痛苦，宣传同情、仁爱。

[11]安东尼（公元250—约356），出生于埃及，长期在沙漠中修行，对后代的修道主义影响深远。

[12]梯伯河又称台伯河，位于意大利境内，奥斯蒂亚城位于梯伯河畔，是古罗马时期的著名商业和交通中心。

[13]摩西，公元前13世纪的犹太人先知，《圣经》旧约前五卷书的作者。

Book I

1

Can any praise be worthy of the Lord's majesty? How magnificent his strength! How inscrutable his wisdom! Man is one of your creatures, Lord, and his instinct is to praise you. He bears about him the mark of death, the sign of his own sin, to remind him that you thwart the proud. But still, since he is a part of your creation, he wishes to praise you. The thought of you stirs him so deeply that he cannot be content unless he praises you, because you made us for yourself and our hearts find no peace until they rest in you.

[...]

Those who look for the Lord will cry out in praise of him, because all who look for him shall find him, and when they find him they will praise him. I shall look for you, Lord, by praying to you and as I pray I shall believe in you, because we have had preachers to tell us about you. It is my faith that calls to you, Lord, the faith which you gave me and made to live in me through the merits of your Son, who became man, and through the ministry of your preacher.

6

But, dust and ashes though I am, let me appeal to your pity, since it is to you in your mercy that I speak, not to a man, who would simply laugh at me. Perhaps you too may laugh at me, but you will relent and have pity on me. For all I want to tell you, Lord, is that I do not know where I came from when I was born into this life which leads to death - or should I say, this death which leads to life? This much is hidden from me. But, although I do not remember it all myself, I know that when I came into the world all the comforts which your mercy provides were there ready for me. This I was told by my parents, the father who begat me and the mother who conceived me, the two from whose bodies you formed me in the limits of time. So it was that I was given the comfort of woman's milk.

[...]

I do acknowledge you, Lord of heaven and earth, and I praise you for my first beginnings, although I cannot remember them. But you have allowed men to discover these things about themselves by watching other babies, and also to learn much from what women have to tell. I know that I was a living person even at that age, and as I came towards the end of infancy I tried to find signs to convey my feelings to others. Where could such a living creature come from if not from you, O Lord? Can it be that any man has skill to fabricate himself? Or can there be some channel by which we derive our life and our very existence from some other source than you? Surely we can only derive them from our Maker, from you, Lord, to whom living and being are not different things, since infinite life and infinite being are one and the same. For you are infinite and never change. In you 'today' never comes to an end: and yet our 'today' does come to an end in you, because time, as well as everything else, exists in you. If it did not, it would have no means of passing. And since your years never come to an end, for you they are simply 'today'. The countless days of our lives and of our forefathers' lives have passed by within your 'today'. From it they have received their due measure of duration and their very existence. And so it will be with all the other days which are still to come. But you yourself are eternally the same. In your 'today' you will make all that is to exist tomorrow and thereafter, and in your 'today' you have made all that existed yesterday and for ever before.

Need it concern me if some people cannot understand this? Let them ask what it means, and be glad to ask: but they may content themselves with the question alone. For it is better for them to find you and leave the question unanswered than to find the answer without finding you.

7

Hear me, O God! How wicked are the sins of men! Men say this and you pity them, because you made man, but you did not make sin in him.

Who can recall to me the sins I committed as a baby? For in your sight no man is free from sin, not even a child who has lived only one day on earth. Who can show me what my sins were? Some small baby in whom I can see all that I do not remember about myself? What sins, then, did I commit when I was a baby myself? Was it a sin to cry when I wanted to feed at the breast? I am too old now to feed on mother's milk, but if I were to cry for the kind of food suited to my age, others would rightly laugh me to scorn and remonstrate with me. So then too I deserved a scolding for what I did; but since I could not have understood the scolding, it would have been unreasonable, and most unusual, to rebuke me. We root out these faults and discard them as we grow up, and this is proof enough that they are faults, because I have never seen a man purposely throw out the good when he clears away the bad. It can hardly be right for a child, even at that age, to cry for everything, including things which would harm him; to work himself into a tantrum against people older than himself and not required to obey him; and to try his best to strike and hurt others who know better than he does, including his own parents, when they do not give in to him and refuse to pander to whims which would only do him harm. This shows that, if babies are innocent, it is not for lack of will to do harm, but for lack of strength.

[...]

I do not remember that early part of my life, O Lord, but I believe what other people have told me about it and from watching other babies I can conclude that I also lived as they do. But, true though my conclusions may be, I do not like to think of that period as part of the same life I now lead, because it is dim and forgotten and, in this sense, it is no different from the time I spent in my mother's womb. But if I was born in sin and guilt was with me already when my mother conceived me, where, I ask you, Lord, where or when was I, your servant, ever innocent? But I will say no more about that time, for since no trace of it remains in my memory, it need no longer concern me.

9

But, O God my God, I now went through a period of suffering and humiliation. I was told that it was right and proper for me as a boy to pay attention to my teachers, so that I should do well at my study of grammar and get on in the world. This was the way to gain the respect of others and win for myself what passes for wealth in this world. So I was sent to school to learn to read. I was too small to understand what purpose it might serve and yet, if I was idle at my studies, I was beaten for it, because beating was favoured by tradition. Countless boys long since forgotten had built up this stony path for us to tread and we were made to pass along it, adding to the toil and sorrow of the sons of Adam.

But we found that some men prayed to you, Lord, and we learned from them to do the same, thinking of you in the only way that we could understand, as some great person who could listen to us and help us, even though we could not see you or hear you or touch you. I was still a boy when I first began to pray to you, my Help and Refuge. I used to prattle away to you, and though I was small, my devotion was great when I begged you not to let me be beaten at school. Sometimes, for my own good, you did not grant my prayer, and then my elders and even my parents, who certainly wished me no harm, would laugh at the beating I got - and in those days beatings were my one great bugbear.

[...]

11

While still a boy I had been told of the eternal life promised to us by Our Lord, who humbled himself and came down amongst us proud sinners. As a catechumen, I was blessed regularly from birth with the sign of the Cross and was seasoned with God's salt, for, O Lord, my mother placed great hope in you. Once as a child I was taken suddenly ill with a disorder of the stomach and was on the point of death. You, my God, were my guardian even then, and you saw the fervour and strength of my faith as I appealled to the piety of my own mother and to the mother of us all, your Church, to give me the baptism of Christ your Son, who is my God and my Master. My earthly mother was deeply anxious, because in the pure faith of her heart, she was in greater labour to ensure my eternal salvation than she had been at my birth. Had I not quickly recovered, she would have hastened to see that I was admitted to the sacraments of salvation and washed clean by acknowledging you, Lord Jesus, for the pardon of my sins. So my washing in the waters of baptism was postponed, in the surmise that, if I continued to live, I should defile myself again with sin and, after baptism, the guilt of pollution would be greater and more dangerous. Even at that age I already believed in you, and so did my mother and the whole household except for my father. But, in my heart, he did not gain the better of my mother's piety and prevent me from believing in Christ just because he still disbelieved himself. For she did all that she could to see that you, my God, should be a Father to me rather than he. In this you helped her to turn the scales against her husband, whom she always obeyed because by obeying him she obeyed your law, thereby showing greater virtue than he did.

I ask you, my God - for, if it is your will, I long to know - for what purpose was my baptism postponed at that time? Was it for my good that the reins which held me from sin were slackened? Or is it untrue that they were slackened? If not, why do we continually hear people say, even nowadays, 'Leave him alone and let him do it. He is not yet baptized'? Yet when the health of the body is at stake, no one says 'Let him get worse. He is not yet cured.' It would, then, have been much better if I had been healed at once and if all that I and my family could do had been done to make sure that once my soul had received its salvation, its safety should be left in your keeping, since its salvation had come from you. This would surely have been the better course. But my mother well knew how many great tides of temptation threatened me before I grew up, and she chose to let them beat upon the as yet unmoulded clay rather than upon the finished image which had received the stamp of baptism.

17

Let me tell you, my God, how I squandered the brains you gave me on foolish delusions. I was set a task which troubled me greatly, for if I were successful, I might win some praise: if not, I was afraid of disgrace or a beating. I had to recite the speech of Juno, who was pained and angry because she could not prevent Aeneas from sailing to Italy. I had been told that Juno had never really spoken the words, but we were compelled to make believe and follow the flight of the poet's fancy by repeating in prose what he had said in verse. The contest was to be won by the boy who found the best words to suit the meaning and best expressed feelings of sorrow and anger appropriate to the majesty of the character he impersonated.

What did all this matter to me, my God, my true Life? Why did my recitation win more praise than those of the many other boys in my class? Surely it was all so much smoke without fire? Was there no other subject on which I might have sharpened my wits and my tongue? I might have used them, O Lord, to praise you in the words of your Scriptures, which could have been a prop to support my heart, as if it were a young vine, so that it would not have produced this crop of worthless fruit, fit only for the birds to peck at. For offerings can be made to those birds of prey, the fallen angels, in more ways than one.

19

It was at the threshold of a world such as this that I stood in peril as a boy. I was already being prepared for its tournaments by a training which taught me to have a horror of faulty grammar instead of teaching me, when I committed these faults, not to envy others who avoided them. All this, my God, I admit and confess to you. By these means I won praise from the people whose favour I sought, for I thought that the right way to live was to do as they wished. I was blind to the whirlpool of debasement in which I had been plunged away from the sight of your eyes. For in your eyes nothing could be more debased than I was then, since I was even troublesome to the people whom I set out to please. Many and many a time I lied to my tutor, my masters, and my parents, and deceived them because I wanted to play games or watch some futile show or was impatient to imitate what I saw on the stage. I even stole from my parents' larder and from their table, either from greed or to get something to give to other boys in exchange for their favourite toys, which they were willing to barter with me. And in the games I played with them I often cheated in order to come off the better, simply because a vain desire to win had got the better of me. And yet there was nothing I could less easily endure, nothing that made me quarrel more bitterly, than to find others cheating me as I cheated them. All the same, if they found me out and blamed me for it, I would lose my temper rather than give in.

Can this be the innocence of childhood? Far from it, O Lord! But I beg you to forgive it. For commanders and kings may take the place of tutors and schoolmasters, nuts and balls and pet birds may give way to money and estates and servants, but these same passions remain with us while one stage of life follows upon another, just as more severe punishments follow upon the school-master's cane. It was, then, simply because they are small that you used children to symbolize humility when, as our King, you commended it by saying that the kingdom of heaven belongs to such as these.

20

And yet, Lord, even if you had willed that I should not survive my childhood, I should have owed you gratitude, because you are our God, the supreme Good, the Creator and Ruler of the universe. For even as a child I existed, I was alive, I had the power of feeling; I had an instinct to keep myself safe and sound, to preserve my own being, which was a trace of the single unseen Being from whom it was derived; I had an inner sense which watched over my bodily senses and kept them in full vigour; and even in the small things which occupied my thoughts I found pleasure in the truth. I disliked finding myself in the wrong; my memory was good; I was acquiring the command of words; I enjoyed the company of friends; and I shrank from pain, ignorance, and sorrow. Should I not be grateful that so small a creature possessed such wonderful qualities? But they were all gifts from God, for I did not give them to myself. His gifts are good and the sum of them all is my own self. Therefore, the God who made me must be good and all the good in me is his. I thank him and praise him for all the good in my life, even my life as a boy. But my sin was this, that I looked for pleasure, beauty, and truth not in him but in myself and his other creatures, and the search led me instead to pain, confusion, and error. My God, in whom is my delight, my glory, and my trust, I thank you for your gifts and beg you to preserve and keep them for me. Keep me, too, and so your gifts will grow and reach perfection and I shall be with you myself, for I should not even exist if it were not by your gift.

Book II

1

I must now carry my thoughts back to the abominable things I did in those days, the sins of the flesh which defiled my soul. I do this, my God, not because I love those sins, but so that I may love you. For love of your love I shall retrace my wicked ways. The memory is bitter, but it will help me to savour your sweetness, the sweetness that does not deceive but brings real joy and never fails. For love of your love I shall retrieve myself from the havoc of disruption which tore me to pieces when I turned away from you, whom alone I should have sought, and lost myself instead on many a different quest. For as I grew to manhood I was inflamed with desire for a surfeit of hell's pleasures. Foolhardy as I was, I ran wild with lust that was manifold and rank. In your eyes my beauty vanished and I was foul to the core, yet I was pleased with my own condition and anxious to be pleasing in the eyes of men.

2

I cared for nothing but to love and be loved. But my love went beyond the affection of one mind for another, beyond the arc of the bright beam of friendship. Bodily desire, like a morass, and adolescent sex welling up within me exuded mists which clouded over and obscured my heart, so that I could not distinguish the clear light of true love from the murk of lust. Love and lust together seethed within me. In my tender youth they swept me away over the precipice of my body's appetites and plunged me in the whirlpool of sin. More and more I angered you, unawares. For I had been deafened by the clank of my chains, the fetters of the death which was my due to punish the pride in my soul. I strayed still farther from you and you did not restrain me. I was tossed and spilled, floundering in the broiling sea of my fornication, and you said no word. How long it was before I learned that you were my true joy! You were silent then, and I went on my way, farther and farther from you, proud in my distress and restless in fatigue, sowing more and more seeds whose only crop was grief.

[...]

3

In the same year my studies were interrupted. I had already begun to go to the near-by town of Madaura to study literature and the art of public speaking, but I was brought back home while my father, a modest citizen of Thagaste whose determination was greater than his means, saved up the money to send me farther afield to Carthage. I need not tell all this to you, my God, but in your presence I tell it to my own kind, to those other men, however few, who may perhaps pick up this book. And I tell it so that I and all who read my words may realize the depths from which we are to cry to you. Your ears will surely listen to the cry of a penitent heart which lives the life of faith.

[...]

4

It is certain, O Lord, that theft is punished by your law, the law that is written in men's hearts and cannot be erased however sinful they are. For no thief can bear that another thief should steal from him, even if he is rich and the other is driven to it by want. Yet I was willing to steal, and steal I did, although I was not compelled by any lack, unless it were the lack of a sense of justice or a distaste for what was right and a greedy love of doing wrong. For of what I stole I already had plenty, and much better at that, and I had no wish to enjoy the things I coveted by stealing, but only to enjoy the theft itself and the sin. There was a pear-tree near our vineyard, loaded with fruit that was attractive neither to look at nor to taste. Late one night a band of ruffians, myself included, went off to shake down the fruit and carry it away, for we had continued our games out of doors until well after dark, as was our pernicious habit. We took away an enormous quantity of pears, not to eat them ourselves, but simply to throw them to the pigs. Perhaps we ate some of them, but our real pleasure consisted in doing something that was forbidden.

[...]

6

If the crime of theft which I committed that night as a boy of sixteen were a living thing, I could speak to it and ask what it was that, to my shame, I loved in it. I had no beauty because it was a robbery. It is true that the pears which we stole had beauty, because they were created by you, the good God, who are the most beautiful of all beings and the Creator of all things, the supreme Good and my own true Good. But it was not the pears that my unhappy soul desired. I had plenty of my own, better than those, and I only picked them so that I might steal. For no sooner had I picked them than I threw them away, and tasted nothing in them but my own sin, which I relished and enjoyed. If any part of one of those pears passed my lips, it was the sin that gave it flavour.

[...]

What was it, then, that pleased me in that act of theft? Which of my Lord's powers did I imitate in a perverse and wicked way? Since I had no real power to break his law, was it that I enjoyed at least the pretence of doing so, like a prisoner who creates for himself the illusion of liberty by doing something wrong, when he has no fear of punishment, under a feeble hallucination of power? Here was the slave who ran away from his master and chased a shadow instead! What an abomination! What a parody of life! What abysmal death! Could I enjoy doing wrong for no other reason than that it was wrong?

Book III

1

I went to Carthage, where I found myself in the midst of a hissing cauldron of lust. I had not yet fallen in love, but I was in love with the idea of it, and this feeling that something was missing made me despise myself for not being more anxious to satisfy the need. I began to look around for some object for my love, since I badly wanted to love something. I had no liking for the safe path without pitfalls, for although my real need was for you, my God, who are the food of the soul, I was not aware of this hunger. I felt no need for the food that does not perish, not because I had had my fill of it, but because the more I was starved of it the less palatable it seemed. Because of this my soul fell sick. It broke out in ulcers and looked about desperately for some material, worldly means of relieving the itch which they caused. But material things, which have no soul, could not be true objects for my love. To love and to have my love returned was my heart's desire, and it would be all the sweeter if I could also enjoy the body of the one who loved me.

[...]

3

Yet all the while, far above, your mercy hovered faithfully about me. I exhausted myself in depravity, in the pursuit of an unholy curiosity. I deserted you and sank to the bottom-most depths of scepticism and the mockery of devil-worship. My sins were a sacrifice to the devil, and for all of them you chastised me. I defied you even so far as to relish the thought of lust, and gratify it too, within the walls of your church during the celebration of your mysteries. For such a deed I deserved to pluck the fruit of death, and you punished me for it with a heavy lash. But, compared with my guilt, the penalty was nothing. How infinite is your mercy, my God! You are my Refuge from the terrible dangers amongst which I wandered, head on high, intent upon withdrawing still further from you. I loved my own way, not yours, but it was a truant's freedom that I loved.

Besides these pursuits I was also studying for the law. Such ambition was held to be honourable and I determined to succeed in it. The more unscrupulous I was, the greater my reputation was likely to be, for men are so blind that they even take pride in their blindness. By now I was at the top of the school of rhetoric. I was pleased with my superior status and swollen with conceit. All the same, as you well know, Lord, I behaved far more quietly than the 'Wreckers', a title of ferocious devilry which the fashionable set chose for themselves. I had nothing whatever to do with their outbursts of violence, but I lived amongst them, feeling a perverse sense of shame because I was not like them. I kept company with them and there were times when I found their friendship a pleasure, but I always had a horror of what they did when they lived up to their name. Without provocation they would set upon some timid newcomer, gratuitously affronting his sense of decency for their own amusement and using it as fodder for their spiteful jests. This was the devil's own behaviour or not far different. 'Wreckers' was a fit name for them, for they were already adrift and total wrecks themselves. The mockery and trickery which they loved to practise on others was a secret snare of the devil, by which they were mocked and tricked themselves.

4

These were the companions with whom I studied the art of eloquence at that impressionable age. It was my ambition to be a good speaker, for the unhallowed and inane purpose of gratifying human vanity. The prescribed course of study brought me to a work by an author named Cicero, whose writing nearly everyone admires, if not the spirit of it. The title of the book is Hortensius and it recommends the reader to study philosophy. It altered my outlook on life. It changed my prayers to you, O Lord, and provided me with new hopes and aspirations. All my empty dreams suddenly lost their charm and my heart began to throb with a bewildering passion for the wisdom of eternal truth. I began to climb out of the depths to which I had sunk, in order to return to you. For I did not use the book as a whetstone to sharpen my tongue. It was not the style of it but the contents which won me over, and yet the allowance which my mother paid me was supposed to be spent on putting an edge on my tongue. I was now in my nineteenth year and she supported me, because my father had died two years before.

[...]

But, O Light of my heart, you know that at that time, although Paul's words were not known to me, the only thing that pleased me in Cicero's book was his advice not simply to admire one or another of the schools of philosophy, but to love wisdom itself, whatever it might be, and to search for it, pursue it, hold it, and embrace it firmly. These were the words which excited me and set me burning with fire, and the only check to this blaze of enthusiasm was that they made no mention of the name of Christ. For by your mercy, Lord, from the time when my mother fed me at the breast my infant heart had been suckled dutifully on his name, the name of your Son, my Saviour. Deep inside my heart his name remained, and nothing could entirely captivate me, however learned, however neatly expressed, however true it might be, unless his name were in it.

5

So I made up my mind to examine the holy Scriptures and see what kind of books they were. I discovered something that was at once beyond the understanding of the proud and hidden from the eyes of children. Its gait was humble, but the heights it reached were sublime. It was enfolded in mysteries, and I was not the kind of man to enter into it or bow my head to follow where it led. But these were not the feelings I had when I first read the Scriptures. To me they seemed quite unworthy of comparison with the stately prose of Cicero, because I had too much conceit to accept their simplicity and not enough insight to penetrate their depths. It is surely true that as the child grows these books grow with him. But I was too proud to call myself a child. I was inflated with self-esteem, which made me think myself a great man.

11

But you sent down your help from above and rescued my soul from the depths of this darkness because my mother, your faithful servant, wept to you for me, shedding more tears for my spiritual death than other mothers shed for the bodily death of a son. For in her faith and in the spirit which she had from you she looked on me as dead. You heard her and did not despise the tears which streamed down and watered the earth in every place where she bowed her head in prayer. You heard her, for how else can I explain the dream with which you consoled her, so that she agreed to live with me and eat at the same table in our home? Lately she had refused to do this, because she loathed and shunned the blasphemy of my false beliefs.

She dreamed that she was standing on a wooden rule, and coming towards her in a halo of splendour she saw a young man who smiled at her in joy, although she herself was sad and quite consumed with grief. He asked her the reason for her sorrow and her daily tears, not because he did not know, but because he had something to tell her, for this is what happens in visions. When she replied that her tears were for the soul I had lost, he told her to take heart for, if she looked carefully, she would see that where she was, there also was I. And when she looked, she saw me standing beside her on the same rule.

Where could this dream have come from, unless it was that you listened to the prayer of her heart? For your goodness is almighty; you take good care of each of us as if you had no others in your care, and you look after all as you look after each. And surely it was for the same reason that, when she told me of the dream and I tried to interpret it as a message that she need not despair of being one day such as I was then, she said at once and without hesitation 'No! He did not say "Where he is, you are", but "Where you are, he is".'

[...]

12

I remember that in the meantime you gave her another answer to her prayers, though there is much besides this that escapes my memory and much too that I must omit, because I am in haste to pass on to other things, which I am more anxious to confess to you.

This other answer you gave her through the mouth of one of your priests, a bishop who had lived his life in the Church and was well versed in the Scriptures. My mother asked him, as a favour, to have a talk with me, so that he might refute my errors, drive the evil out of my mind, and replace it with good. He often did this when he found suitable pupils, but he refused to do it for me - a wise decision, as I afterwards realized. He told her that I was still unripe for instruction because, as she had told him, I was brimming over with the novelty of the heresy and had already upset a great many simple people with my casuistry. 'Leave him alone', he said. 'Just pray to God for him. From his own reading he will discover his mistakes and the depth of his profanity.'

At the same time he told her that when he was a child his misguided mother had handed him over to the Manichees. He had not only read almost all their books, but had also made copies of them, and even though no one argued the case with him or put him right, he had seen for himself that he ought to have nothing to do with the sect; and accordingly he had left it. Even after she had heard this my mother still would not be pacified, but persisted all the more with her tears and her entreaties that he should see me and discuss the matter. At last he grew impatient and said 'Leave me and go in peace. It cannot be that the son of these tears should be lost.'

In later years, as we talked together, she used to say that she accepted these words as a message from heaven.

Book IV

1

During the space of those nine years, from the nineteenth to the twenty-eighth year of my life, I was led astray myself and led others astray in my turn. We were alike deceivers and deceived in all our different aims and ambitions, both publicly when we expounded our so-called liberal ideas, and in private through our service to what we called religion. In public we were cocksure, in private superstitious, and everywhere void and empty. On the one hand we would hunt for worthless popular distinctions, the applause of an audience, prizes for poetry, or quickly fading wreaths won in competition. We loved the idle pastimes of the stage and in selfindulgence we were unrestrained. On the other hand we aspired to be purged of these lowly pleasures by taking food to the holy elect, as they were called, so that in their paunches it might pass through the process of being made into angels and gods who would set us free. These were the objects I pursued and the tasks I performed together with friends who, like myself and through my fault, were under the same delusion.

[...]

2

During those years I was a teacher of the art of public speaking. Love of money had gained the better of me and for it I sold to others the means of coming off the better in debate. But you know, Lord, that I preferred to have honest pupils, in so far as honesty has any meaning nowadays, and I had no evil intent when I taught the tricks of pleading, for I never meant them to be used to get the innocent condemned but, if the occasion arose, to save the lives of the guilty. From a distance, my God, you saw me losing my foothold on this treacherous ground, but through clouds of smoke you also saw a spark of good faith in me; for though, as I schooled my pupils, I was merely abetting their futile designs and their schemes of duplicity, nevertheless I did my best to teach them honestly.

In those days I lived with a woman, not my lawful wedded wife but a mistress whom I had chosen for no special reason but that my restless passions had alighted on her. But she was the only one and I was faithful to her. Living with her I found out by my own experience the difference between the restraint of the marriage alliance, contracted for the purpose of having children, and a bargain struck for lust, in which the birth of children is begrudged, though, if they come, we cannot help but love them.

[...]

12

If the things of this world delight you, praise God for them but turn your love away from them and give it to their Maker, so that in the things that please you you may not displease him. If your delight is in souls, love them in God, because they too are frail and stand firm only when they cling to him. If they do not, they go their own way and are lost. Love them, then, in him and draw as many with you to him as you can. Tell them 'He is the one we should love. He made the world and he stays close to it.' For when he made the world he did not go away and leave it. By him it was created and in him it exists. Wherever we taste the truth, God is there. He is in our very inmost hearts, but our hearts have strayed from him. Think well on it, unbelieving hearts and cling to him who made you. Stand with him and you shall not fall; rest in him and peace shall be yours. What snags and pitfalls lie before you? Where do your steps lead you? The good things which you love are all from God, but they are good and sweet only as long as they are used to do his will. They will rightly turn bitter if God is spurned and the things that come from him are wrongly loved. Why do you still choose to travel by this hard and arduous path? There is no rest to be found where you seek it. In the land of death you try to find a happy life: it is not there. How can life be happy where there is no life at all?

Our Life himself came down into this world and took away our death. He slew it with his own abounding life, and with thunder in his voice he called us from this world to return to him in heaven. From heaven he came down to us, entering first the Virgin's womb, where humanity, our mortal flesh, was wedded to him so that it might not be for ever mortal. Then as a bridegroom coming from his bed, he exulted like some great runner who sees the track before him. He did not linger on his way but ran, calling us to return to him, calling us by his words and deeds, by his life and death, by his descent into hell and his ascension into heaven. He departed from our sight, so that we should turn to our hearts and find him there. He departed, but he is here with us. He would not stay long with us, but he did not leave us. He went back to the place which he had never left, because he, through whom the world was made, was in the world and he came into the world to save sinners. To him my soul confesses and he is its Healer, because the wrong it did was against him. Great ones of the world, will your hearts always be hardened? Your Life has come down from heaven: will you not now at last rise with him and live? But how can you rise if you are in high places and your clamour reaches heaven? Come down from those heights, for then you may climb and, this time, climb to God. To climb against him was your fall.

[...]

13

I did not know this then. I was in love with beauty of a lower order and it was dragging me down. I used to ask my friends 'Do we love anything unless it is beautiful? What, then, is beauty and in what does it consist? What is it that attracts us and wins us over to the things we love? Unless there were beauty and grace in them, they would be powerless to win our hearts.' When I looked at things, it struck me that there was a difference between the beauty of an object considered by itself as one whole and the beauty to be found in a proper proportion between separate things, such as the due balance between the whole of the body and any of its limbs, or between the foot and the shoe with which it is shod, and so on. This idea burst from my heart like water from a spring. My mind was full of it and I wrote a book called Beauty and Proportion, in two or three volumes as far as I remember. You know how many there were, O Lord. I have forgotten, because by some chance the book was lost and I no longer have it.

14

O Lord, my God, what induced me to dedicate my book to Hierius, the great public speaker at Rome? I had never even seen him, but I admired his brilliant reputation for learning and had been greatly struck by what I had heard of his speeches. Even more than this I was impressed by the admiration which other people had for him. They overwhelmed him with praise, because it seemed extraordinary that a man born in Syria and originally trained to speak in Greek had later become so remarkable a speaker in Latin, and had also such a wealth of knowledge of the subjects studied by philosophers.

We can admire persons whom we have never seen, if we hear them praised, though this does not mean that simply to hear their praises will make us admire them. But enthusiasm in one man will kindle the same fire in another, for we admire the person whose praises we hear only if we believe that they are sincerely uttered - in other words that the person who utters them genuinely admires the man whom he praises.

[...]

But Hierius was the kind of man in whom I admired qualities that I would have been glad to possess. In my pride I was running adrift, at the mercy of every wind. You were guiding me as a helmsman steers a ship, but the course you steered was beyond my understanding. I know now, and confess it as the truth, that I admired Hierius more because others praised him than for the accomplishments for which they praised him. I know this because those same people, instead of praising him, might have abused him. They might have spoken of the same talents in him but found fault with them and despised them. If they had done this, my feelings would not have been aroused nor my admiration kindled. Yet his qualities would have been the same and he himself would have been no different. The only difference would have been in their attitude towards him.

We can see from this that the soul is weak and helpless unless it clings to the firm rock of truth. Men give voice to their opinions, but they are only opinions, like so many puffs of wind that waft the soul hither and thither and make it veer and turn. The light is clouded over and the truth cannot be seen, although it is there before our eyes. I thought it a matter of much importance to myself to bring my book and the work I had done to the notice of this great man. If he had approved of them, my fervour would have been all the more ardent. If he had found fault, my heart, which was empty and bereft of God's firm truth, would have suffered a cruel blow. Yet I found pleasure in giving my mind to the problem of beauty and proportion, the work which I had dedicated to him. Although I found no others to admire it, I was proud of it myself.

15

[...]

I was struggling to reach you, but you thrust me back so that I knew the taste of death. For you thwart the proud. And what greater pride could there be than to assert, as I did in my strange madness, that by nature I was what you are? I was changeable, and I knew it; for if I wanted to be a learned man, it could only mean that I wanted to be better than I was. All the same I preferred to think that you too were changeable rather than suppose that I was not what you are. This was why you thrust me back and crushed my rearing pride, while my imagination continued to play on material forms. Myself a man of flesh and blood I blamed the flesh. I was as fickle as a breath of wind, unable to return to you. I drifted on, making my way towards things that had no existence in you or in myself or in the body. They were not created for me by your truth but were the inventions of my own foolish imagination working on material things. Though I did not know it, I was in exile from my place in God's city among his faithful children, my fellow citizens. But I was all words, and stupidly I used to ask them, 'If, as you say, God made the soul, why does it err?' Yet I did not like them to ask me in return, 'If what you say is true, why does God err?' So I used to argue that your unchangeable substance, my God, was forced to err, rather than admit that my own was changeable and erred of its own free will, and that its errors were my punishment.

[...]

16

When I was only about twenty years of age Aristotle's book on the 'Ten Categories' came into my hands. Whenever my teacher at Carthage and others who were reputed to be scholars mentioned this book, their cheeks would swell with self-importance, so that the title alone was enough to make me stand agape, as though I were poised over some wonderful divine mystery. I managed to read it and understand it without help, though I now ask myself what advantage I gained from doing so. Other people told me that they had understood it only with difficulty, after the most learned masters had not only explained it to them but also illustrated it with a wealth of diagrams. But when I discussed it with them, I found that they could tell me no more about it than I had already discovered by reading it on my own.

[...]

I read and understood by myself all the books that I could find on the so-called liberal arts, for in those days I was a good-for-nothing and a slave to sordid ambitions. But what advantage did I gain from them? I read them with pleasure, but I did not know the real source of such true and certain facts as they contained. I had my back to the light and my face was turned towards the things which it illumined, so that my eyes, by which I saw the things which stood in the light, were themselves in darkness. Without great difficulty and without need of a teacher I understood all that I read on the arts of rhetoric and logic, on geometry, music, and mathematics. You know this, O Lord my God, because if a man is quick to understand and his perception is keen, he has these gifts from you. But since I made no offering of them to you, it did me more harm than good to struggle to keep in my own power so large a part of what you had given to me and, instead of preserving my strength for you, to leave you and go to a far country to squander your gifts on loves that sold themselves for money. For what good to me was my ability, if I did not use it well? And ability I had, for until I tried to instruct others I did not realize that these subjects are very difficult to master, even for pupils who are studious and intelligent, and a student who could follow my instruction without faltering was reckoned a very fine scholar.

But what value did I gain from my reading as long as I thought that you, Lord God who are the Truth, were a bright, unbounded body and I a small piece broken from it? What utter distortion of the truth! Yet this was my belief; and I do not now blush to acknowledge, my God, the mercies you have shown to me, nor to call you to my aid, just as in those days I did not blush to declare my blasphemies aloud and snarl at you like a dog. What, then, was the value to me of my intelligence, which could take these subjects in its stride, and all those books, with their tangled problems, which I unravelled without the help of any human tutor, when in the doctrine of your love I was lost in the most hideous error and the vilest sacrilege? And was it so great a drawback to your faithful children that they were slower than I to understand such things? For they did not forsake you, but grew like fledglings in the safe nest of your Church, nourishing the wings of charity on the food of the faith that would save them.

O Lord our God, let the shelter of your wings give us hope. Protect us and uphold us. You will be the Support that upholds us from childhood till the hair on our heads is grey. When you are our strength we are strong, but when our strength is our own we are weak. In you our good abides for ever, and when we turn away from it we turn to evil. Let us come home at last to you, O Lord, for fear that we be lost. For in you our good abides and it has no blemish, since it is yourself. Nor do we fear that there is no home to which we can return. We fell from it; but our home is your eternity and it does not fall because we are away.

Book V

1

Accept my confessions, O Lord. They are a sacrifice offered by my tongue, for yours was the hand that fashioned it and yours the spirit that moved it to acknowledge you. Heal all my bones and let them say Lord, there is none like you.

If a man confesses to you, he does not reveal his inmost thoughts to you as though you did not know them. For the heart may shut itself away, but it cannot hide from your sight. Man's heart may be hard, but it cannot resist the touch of your hand. Whenever you will, your mercy or your punishment can make it relent, and just as none can hide away from the sun, none can escape your burning heat.

Let my soul praise you, so that it may show its love; and let it make avowal of your mercies, so that for these it may praise you. No part of your creation ever ceases to resound in praise of you. Man turns his lips to you in prayer and his spirit praises you. Animals too and lifeless things as well praise you through the lips of all who give them thought. For our souls lean for support upon the things which you have created, so that we may be lifted up to you from our weakness and use them to help us on our way to you who made them all so wonderfully. And in you we are remade and find true strength.

3

In the sight of my God I will describe the twenty-ninth year of my age.

A Manichean bishop named Faustus had recently arrived at Carthage. He was a great decoy of the devil and many people were trapped by his charming manner of speech. This I certainly admired, but I was beginning to distinguish between mere eloquence and the real truth, which I was so eager to learn. The Manichees talked so much about this man Faustus that I wanted to see what scholarly fare he would lay before me, and I did not care what words he used to garnish the dish. I had already heard that he was very well versed in all the higher forms of learning and particularly in the liberal sciences.

I had read a great many scientific books which were still alive in my memory. When I compared them with the tedious tales of the Manichees, it seemed to me that, of the two, the theories of the scientists were the more likely to be true. For their thoughts could reach far enough to form a judgement about the world around them, though they found no trace of him who is Master of it. You, Lord, who are so high above us, yet look with favour on the humble, look on the proud too, but from far off. You come close only to men who are humble at heart. The proud cannot find you, even though by dint of study they have skill to number stars and grains of sand, to measure the tracts of constellations and trace the paths of planets.

[...]

6

For almost the whole of those nine years during which my mind was unsettled and I was an aspirant of the Manichees, I awaited the coming of this man Faustus with the keenest expectation. Other members of the sect whom I happened to meet were unable to answer the questions I raised upon these subjects, but they assured me that once Faustus had arrived I had only to discuss them with him and he would have no difficulty in giving me a clear explanation of my queries and any other more difficult problems which I might put forward.

[...]

My long and eager expectation of Faustus's arrival was amply rewarded by the way in which he set about the task of disputation and the goodwill that he showed. The ease with which he found the right words to clothe his thoughts delighted me, and I was not the only one to applaud it, though perhaps I did so more than most. But I found it tiresome, when so many people assembled to hear him, not to be allowed to approach him with my difficulties and lay them before him in the friendly give-and-take of conversation. As soon as the opportunity arose I and some of my friends claimed his attention at a time when a private discussion would not be inappropriate. I mentioned some of my doubts, but soon discovered that except for a rudimentary knowledge of literature he had no claims to scholarship. He had read some of Cicero's speeches, one or two books of Seneca, some poetry, and such books as had been written in good Latin by members of his sect. Besides his daily practice as a speaker, this reading was the basis of his eloquence, which derived extra charm and plausibility from his attractive personality and his ability to make good use of his mental powers.

[...]

7

As soon as it became clear to me that Faustus was quite uninformed about the subjects in which I had expected him to be an expert, I began to lose hope that he could lift the veil and resolve the problems which perplexed me. Of course, despite his ignorance of these matters he might still have been a truly pious man, provided he were not a Manichee. The Manichean books are full of the most tedious fictions about the sky and the stars, the sun and the moon. I badly wanted Faustus to compare these with the mathematical calculations which I had studied in other books, so that I might judge whether the Manichean theories were more likely to be true or, at least, equally probable, but I now began to realize that he could not give me a detailed explanation. When I suggested that we should consider these problems and discuss them together, he was certainly modest enough not to undertake the task. He knew that he did not know the answers to my questions and was not ashamed to admit it, for unlike many other talkative people whom I have had to endure, he would not try to teach me a lesson when he had nothing to say. He had a heart, and though his approach to you was mistaken, he was not without discretion. He was not entirely unaware of his limitations and did not want to enter rashly into an argument which might force him into a position which he could not possibly maintain and from which he could not easily withdraw. I liked him all the better for this, because modesty and candour are finer equipment for the mind than scientific knowledge of the kind that I wished to possess. I found that his attitude towards all the more difficult and abstruse questions was the same.

[...]

So it was that, unwittingly and without intent, Faustus who had been a deadly snare to many now began to release me from the trap in which I had been caught. For in the mystery of your providence, my God, your guiding hand did not desert me. Night and day my mother poured out her tears to you and offered her heart-blood in sacrifice for me, and in the most wonderful way you guided me. It was you who guided me, my God, for man's feet stand firm, if the Lord is with him to prosper his journey. What else can save us but your hand, remaking what you have made?

8

It was, then, by your guidance that I was persuaded to go to Rome and teach there the subjects which I taught at Carthage.

[...]

9

At Rome I was at once struck down by illness, which all but carried me off to hell loaded with all the evil that I had committed against you, against myself, and against other men, a host of grave offences over and above the bond of original sin, by which we all have died with Adam. You had not yet forgiven me any of these sins in Christ nor, on his cross, had he dissolved the enmity which my sins had earned me in your sight. How could he dissolve it on the cross if he were a mere phantom, as I believed? In so far, then, as I thought the death of his body unreal, the death of my own soul was real; and the life of my soul, because it doubted his death, was as false as the death of his flesh was true.

[...]

If I had died in that state, my mother's heart would never have recovered from the blow. Words cannot describe how dearly she loved me or how much greater was the anxiety she suffered for my spiritual birth than the physical pain she had endured in bringing me into the world. I cannot see how she could ever have recovered if I had died in that condition, for my death would have pierced the very heart of her love. And what would have become of all the fervent prayers which she offered so often and without fail? They would have come to you, nowhere but to you. But would you, O God of mercy, have despised the contrite and humble heart of that chaste and gentle widow, so ready to give alms, so full of humble reverence for your saints, who never let a day go by unless she had brought an offering to your altar, and never failed to come to your church twice every day, each morning and night, not to listen to empty tales and old wives' gossip, but so that she might hear the preaching of your word and you might listen to her prayers? Could you deny your help to her, when it was by your grace that she was what she was, or despise her tears, when she asked not for gold or silver or any fleeting, short-lived favour, but that the soul of her son might be saved? Never would you have done this, O Lord. No, you were there to hear her prayer and do all, in due order, as you had determined it was to be done. It could not be that you would have deceived her in the visions you sent her and the answers you gave to her prayers, both those that I have recorded and the others which I have not set down. All these signs she cherished in her faithful heart, and in her ceaseless prayers she laid them before you as though they were pledges signed by your hand. For, since your mercy endures for ever, by your promises you deign to become a debtor to those whom you release from every debt.

10

So it was that you healed my sickness. To the son of your servant you restored the health of his body, so that he might live to receive from you another far better and more certain kind of health.

[...]

12

I began actively to set about the business of teaching literature and public speaking, which was the purpose for which I had come to Rome. At first I taught in my house, where I collected a number of pupils who had heard of me, and through them my reputation began to grow. But I now realized that there were difficulties in Rome with which I had not had to contend in Africa. True enough, I found that there was no rioting by young hooligans, but I was told that at any moment a number of students would plot together to avoid paying their master his fees and would transfer in a body to another. They were quite unscrupulous, and justice meant nothing to them compared with the love of money. There was hatred for them in my heart, and it was not unselfish hatred, for I suppose that I hated them more for what I should have to suffer from them than for the wrong they might do to any teacher ... For their warped and crooked minds I still hate students like these, but I love them too, hoping to teach them to mend their ways, so that they may learn to love their studies more than money and love you, their God, still more, for you are the Truth, the Source of good that does not fail, and the Peace of purest innocence. But in those days I was readier to dislike them for fear of the harm they might cause me than to hope that they would become good for your sake.

13

So, when the Prefect of Rome received a request from Milan to find a teacher of literature and elocution for the city, with a promise that travelling expenses would be charged to public funds, I applied for the appointment, armed with recommendations from my friends who were so fuddled with the Manichean rigmarole. This journey was to mean the end of my association with them, though none of us knew it at the time. Eventually Symmachus, who was then Prefect, set me a test to satisfy himself of my abilities and sent me to Milan.

In Milan I found your devoted servant the bishop Ambrose, who was known throughout the world as a man whom there were few to equal in goodness. At that time his gifted tongue never tired of dispensing the richness of your corn, the joy of your oil, and the sober intoxication of your wine. Unknown to me, it was you who led me to him, so that I might knowingly be led by him to you. This man of God received me like a father and, as bishop, told me how glad he was that I had come. My heart warmed to him, not at first as a teacher of the truth, which I had quite despaired of finding in your Church, but simply as a man who showed me kindness. I listened attentively when he preached to the people, though not with the proper intention; for my purpose was to judge for myself whether the reports of his powers as a speaker were accurate, or whether eloquence flowed from him more, or less, readily than I had been told. So while I paid the closest attention to the words he used, I was quite uninterested in the subject-matter and was even contemptuous of it. I was delighted with his charming delivery, but although he was a more learned speaker than Faustus, he had not the same soothing and gratifying manner. I am speaking only of his style for, as to content, there could be no comparison between the two. Faustus had lost his way among the fallacies of Manicheism, while Ambrose most surely taught the doctrine of salvation. But your mercy is unknown to sinners such as I was then, though step by step, unwittingly, I was coming closer to it.

14

For although I did not trouble to take what Ambrose said to heart, but only to listen to the manner in which he said it - this being the only paltry interest that remained to me now that I had lost hope that man could find the path that led to you - nevertheless his meaning, which I tried to ignore, found its way into my mind together with his words, which I admired so much. I could not keep the two apart, and while I was all ears to seize upon his eloquence, I also began to sense the truth of what he said, though only gradually. First of all it struck me that it was, after all, possible to vindicate his arguments. I began to believe that the Catholic faith, which I had thought impossible to defend against the objections of the Manichees, might fairly be maintained, especially since I had heard one passage after another in the Old Testament figuratively explained. These passages had been death to me when I took them literally, but once I had heard them explained in their spiritual meaning I began to blame myself for my despair, at least in so far as it had led me to suppose that it was quite impossible to counter people who hated and derided the law and the prophets. But I did not feel that I ought to follow the Catholic path simply because it too had its learned men, ready to vouch for it and never at a loss for sound arguments in answer to objections. On the other hand I did not think that my own beliefs should be condemned simply because an equally good case could be made out for either side. For I thought the Catholic side unbeaten but still not victorious.

Next I tried my utmost to find some certain proof which would convict the Manichees of falsehood. If I had been able to conceive of a spiritual substance, all their inventions would at once have been disproved and rejected from my mind. But this I could not do. However, the more I thought about the material world and the whole of nature, as far as we can be aware of it through our bodily senses, and the more I took stock of the various theories, the more I began to think that the opinions of the majority of the philosophers were most likely to be true. So, treating everything as a matter of doubt, as the Academics are generally supposed to do, and hovering between one doctrine and another, I made up my mind at least to leave the Manichees, for while I was in this state of indecision I did not think it right to remain in the sect now that I found the theories of some of the philosophers preferable. Nevertheless I utterly refused to entrust the healing of the maladies of my soul to these philosophers, because they ignored the saving name of Christ. I therefore decided to remain a catechumen in the Catholic Church, which was what my parents wanted, at least until I could clearly see a light to guide my steps.

Book VI

1

O God, Hope of my youth, where were you all this time? Where were you hiding from me? Were you not my Creator and was it not you who made me different from the beasts that walk on the earth and wiser than the birds that fly in the air? Yet I was walking on a treacherous path, in darkness. I was looking for you outside myself and I did not find the God of my own heart. I had reached the depths of the ocean. I had lost all faith and was in despair of finding the truth.

By now my mother had come to me, for her piety had given her strength to follow me over land and sea, facing all perils in the sure faith she had in you. When the ship was in danger, it was she who put heart into the crew, the very men to whom passengers unused to the sea turn for reassurance when they are alarmed. She promised them that they would make the land in safety, because you had given her this promise in a vision. And she found that I too was in grave danger because of my despair of discovering the truth. I told her that I was not a Catholic Christian, but at least I was no longer a Manichee. Yet she did not leap for joy as though this news were unexpected. In fact, to this extent, her anxiety for me had already been allayed. For in her prayers to you she wept for me as though I were dead, but she also knew that you would recall me to life. In her heart she offered me to you as though I were laid out on a bier, waiting for you to say to the widow's son, 'Young man, I say to you, stand up.' And he would get up and begin to speak, and you would give him back to his mother. So she felt no great surge of joy and her heart beat none the faster when she heard that the tears and the prayers which she had offered you day after day had at last, in great part, been rewarded. For I had been rescued from falsehood, even if I had not yet grasped the truth. Instead, because she was sure that if you had promised her all, you would also give her what remained to be given, she told me quite serenely, with her heart full of faith, that in Christ she believed that before she left this life she would see me a faithful Catholic. This was what she said to me. But to you, from whom all mercies spring, she poured out her tears and her prayers all the more fervently, begging you to speed your help and give me light in my darkness. She hurried all the more eagerly to church, where she listened with rapt attention to all that Ambrose said. For her his words were like a spring of water within her, that flows continually to bring her everlasting life. She loved him as God's angel, because she had learnt that it was through him that I had been led, for the time being, into a state of wavering uncertainty. She had no doubt that I must pass through this condition, which would lead me from sickness to health, but not before I had surmounted a still graver danger, much like that which doctors call the crisis.

5

From now on I began to prefer the Catholic teaching. The Church demanded that certain things should be believed even though they could not be proved, for if they could be proved, not all men could understand the proof, and some could not be proved at all. I thought that the Church was entirely honest in this and far less pretentious than the Manichees, who laughed at people who took things on faith, made rash promises of scientific knowledge, and then put forward a whole system of preposterous inventions which they expected their followers to believe on trust because they could not be proved. Then, O Lord, you laid your most gentle, most merciful finger on my heart and set my thoughts in order, for I began to realize that I believed countless things which I had never seen or which had taken place when I was not there to see - so many events in the history of the world, so many facts about places and towns which I had never seen, and so much that I believed on the word of friends or doctors or various other people. Unless we took these things on trust, we should accomplish absolutely nothing in this life. Most of all it came home to me how firm and unshakeable was the faith which told me who my parents were, because I could never have known this unless I believed what I was told. In this way you made me understand that I ought not to find fault with those who believed your Bible, which you have established with such great authority amongst almost all the nations of the earth, but with those who did not believe it; and that I ought to pay no attention to people who asked me how I could be sure that the Scriptures were delivered to mankind by the Spirit of the one true God who can tell no lie. It was precisely this that I most needed to believe, because in all the conflicting books of philosophy which I had read no misleading proposition, however contentious, had been able, even for one moment, to wrest from me my belief in your existence and in your right to govern human affairs; and this despite the fact that I had no knowledge of what you are.

My belief that you existed and that our well-being was in your hands was sometimes strong, sometimes weak, but I always held to it even though I knew neither what I ought to think about your substance nor which way would lead me to you or lead me back to you. And so, since we are too weak to discover the truth by reason alone and for this reason need the authority of sacred books, I began to believe that you would never have invested the Bible with such conspicuous authority in every land unless you had intended it to be the means by which we should look for you and believe in you. As for the passages which had previously struck me as absurd, now that I had heard reasonable explanations of many of them I regarded them as of the nature of profound mysteries; and it seemed to me all the more right that the authority of Scripture should be respected and accepted with the purest faith, because while all can read it with ease, it also has a deeper meaning in which its great secrets are locked away. Its plain language and simple style make it accessible to everyone, and yet it absorbs the attention of the learned. By this means it gathers all men in the wide sweep of its net, and some pass safely through the narrow mesh and come to you. They are not many, but they would be fewer still if it were not that this book stands out alone on so high a peak of authority and yet draws so great a throng in the embrace of its holy humility.

[...]

13

I was being urged incessantly to marry, and had already made my proposal and been accepted. My mother had done all she could to help, for it was her hope that, once I was married, I should be washed clean of my sins by the saving waters of baptism. She was delighted that, day by day, I was becoming more fitted for baptism, and in my acceptance of the faith she saw the answer to her prayers and the fulfilment of your promises. At my request and by her own desire she daily beseeched you with heartfelt prayers to send her some revelation in a vision about my future marriage, but this you would not do. She had some vague and fanciful dreams, which were the result of her preoccupation with these thoughts, and when she told me about them, she treated them as of no importance and did not speak with the assurance that she always had when you sent her visions. She always said that by some sense, which she could not describe in words, she was able to distinguish between your revelations and her own natural dreams. All the same, the plans for my marriage were pushed ahead and the girl's parents were asked for their consent. She was nearly two years too young for marriage, but I liked her well enough and was content to wait.

15

Meanwhile I was sinning more and more. The woman with whom I had been living was torn from my side as an obstacle to my marriage and this was a blow which crushed my heart to bleeding, because I loved her dearly. She went back to Africa, vowing never to give herself to any other man, and left with me the son whom she had borne me. But I was too unhappy and too weak to imitate this example set me by a woman. I was impatient at the delay of two years which had to pass before the girl whom I had asked to marry became my wife, and because I was more a slave of lust than a true lover of marriage, I took another mistress, without the sanction of wedlock. This meant that the disease of my soul would continue unabated, in fact it would be aggravated, and under the watch and ward of uninterrupted habit it would persist into the state of marriage. Furthermore the wound that I had received when my first mistress was wrenched away showed no signs of healing. At first the pain was sharp and searing, but then the wound began to fester, and though the pain was duller there was all the less hope of a cure.

16

Praise and honour be yours, O Fountain of mercy! As my misery grew worse and worse, you came the closer to me. Though I did not know it, your hand was poised ready to lift me from the mire and wash me clean. Nothing prevented me from plunging still deeper into the gulf of carnal pleasure except the fear of death and your judgement to come. Through all my changing opinions this fear never left my heart.

[...]

What crooked paths I trod! What dangers threatened my soul when it rashly hoped that by abandoning you it would find something better! Whichever way it turned, on front or back or sides, it lay on a bed that was hard, for in you alone the soul can rest. You are there to free us from the misery of error which leads us astray, to set us on your own path and to comfort us by saying, 'Run on, for I shall hold you up. I shall lead you and carry you on to the end.'

Book VII

1

By now my adolescence, with all its shameful sins, was dead. I was approaching mature manhood, but the older I grew, the more disgraceful was my self-delusion. I could imagine no kind of substance except such as is normally seen by the eye. But I did not think of you, my God, in the shape of a human body, for I had rejected this idea ever since I had first begun to study philosophy, and I was glad to find that our spiritual mother, your Catholic Church, also rejected such beliefs. But I did not know how else to think of you.

I was only a man, and a weak man at that, but I tried to think of you as the supreme God, the only God, the true God. With all my heart I believed that you could never suffer decay or hurt or change, for although I did not know how or why this should be, I understood with complete certainty that what is subject to decay is inferior to that which is not, and without hesitation I placed that which cannot be harmed above that which can, and I saw that what remains constant is better than that which is changeable. My heart was full of bitter protests against the creations of my imagination, and this single truth was the only weapon with which I could try to drive from my mind's eye all the unclean images which swarmed before it. But hardly had I brushed them aside than, in the flicker of an eyelid, they crowded upon me again, forcing themselves upon my sight and clouding my vision, so that although I did not imagine you in the shape of a human body, I could not free myself from the thought that you were some kind of bodily substance extended in space, either permeating the world or diffused in infinity beyond it. This substance I thought of as something not subject to decay or harm or variation and therefore better than any that might suffer corruption or damage or change. I reasoned in this way because, if I tried to imagine something without dimensions of space, it seemed to me that nothing, absolutely nothing, remained, not even a void. For if a body were removed from the space which it occupied, and that space remained empty of any body whatsoever, whether of earth, water, air, or sky, there would still remain an empty space. Nothing would be there, but it would still be a space.

[...]

So I thought of you too, O Life of my life, as a great being with dimensions extending everywhere, throughout infinite space, permeating the whole mass of the world and reaching in all directions beyond it without limit, so that the earth and the sky and all creation were full of you and their limits were within you, while you had no limits at all. For the air, that is, the atmosphere which covers the earth, is a material body, but it does not block out the light of the sun. The light passes through it and penetrates it, not by breaking it or splitting it, but by filling it completely. In the same way I imagined that you were able to pass through material bodies, not only the air and the sky and the sea, but also the earth, and that you could penetrate to all their parts, the greatest and the smallest alike, so that they were filled with your presence, and by this unseen force you ruled over all that you had created, from within and from without.

This was the theory to which I held, because I could imagine you in no other way. But it was a false theory. For if it were true, it would mean that a greater part of the earth would contain a greater part of you, and a smaller part less in proportion. Everything would be filled with your presence, but in such a way that the body of an elephant would contain more of you than the body of a sparrow, because the one is larger than the other and occupies more space. So you would distribute your parts piecemeal among the parts of the world, to each more or less according to its size. This, of course, is quite untrue. But at that time you had not yet given me light in my darkness.

3

But although I declared and firmly believed that you, our Lord God, the true God who made not only our souls but also our bodies and not only our souls and bodies but all things, living and inanimate, as well, although I believed that you were free from corruption or mutation or any degree of change, I still could not find a clear explanation, without complications, of the cause of evil. Whatever the cause might be, I saw that it was not to be found in any theory that would oblige me to believe that the immutable God was mutable. If I believed this, I should myself become a cause of evil, the very thing which I was trying to discover. So I continued the search with some sense of relief, because I was quite sure that the theories of the Manichees were wrong. I repudiated these people with all my heart, because I could see that while they were inquiring into the origin of evil they were full of evil themselves, since they preferred to think that yours was a substance that could suffer evil rather than that theirs was capable of committing it.

I was told that we do evil because we choose to do so of our own free will, and suffer it because your justice rightly demands that we should. I did my best to understand this, but I could not see it clearly. I tried to raise my mental perceptions out of the abyss which engulfed them, but I sank back into it once more. Again and again I tried, but always I sank back. One thing lifted me up into the light of your day. It was that I knew that I had a will, as surely as I knew that there was life in me. When I chose to do something or not to do it, I was quite certain that it was my own self, and not some other person, who made this act of will, so that I was on the point of understanding that herein lay the cause of my sin. If I did anything against my will, it seemed to me to be something which happened to me rather than something which I did, and I looked upon it not as a fault, but as a punishment. And because I thought of you as a just God, I admitted at once that your punishments were not unjust.

But then I would ask myself once more: 'Who made me? Surely it was my God, who is not only good but Goodness itself. How, then, do I come to possess a will that can choose to do wrong and refuse to do good, thereby providing a just reason why I should be punished? Who put this will into me? Who sowed this seed of bitterness in me, when all that I am was made by my God, who is Sweetness itself? If it was the devil who put it there, who made the devil? If he was a good angel who became a devil because of his own wicked will, how did he come to possess the wicked will which made him a devil, when the Creator, who is entirely good, made him a good angel and nothing else?'

[...]

12

It was made clear to me also that even those things which are subject to decay are good. If they were of the supreme order of goodness, they could not become corrupt; but neither could they become corrupt unless they were in some way good. For if they were supremely good, it would not be possible for them to be corrupted. On the other hand, if they were entirely without good, there would be nothing in them that could become corrupt. For corruption is harmful, but unless it diminished what is good, it could do no harm. The conclusion then must be either that corruption does no harm - which is not possible; or that everything which is corrupted is deprived of good - which is beyond doubt. But if they are deprived of all good, they will not exist at all. For if they still exist but can no longer be corrupted, they will be better than they were before, because they now continue their existence in an incorruptible state. But could anything be more preposterous than to say that things are made better by being deprived of all good?

So we must conclude that if things are deprived of all good, they cease altogether to be; and this means that as long as they are, they are good. Therefore, whatever is, is good; and evil, the origin of which I was trying to find, is not a substance, because if it were a substance, it would be good. For either it would be an incorruptible substance of the supreme order of goodness, or it would be a corruptible substance which would not be corruptible unless it were good. So it became obvious to me that all that you have made is good, and that there are no substances whatsoever that were not made by you. And because you did not make them all equal, each single thing is good and collectively they are very good, for our God made his whole creation very good.

17

I was astonished that although I now loved you and not some phantom in your place, I did not persist in enjoyment of my God. Your beauty drew me to you, but soon I was dragged away from you by my own weight and in dismay I plunged again into the things of this world. The weight I carried was the habit of the flesh. But your memory remained with me and I had no doubt at all that you were the one to whom I should cling, only I was not yet able to cling to you. For ever the soul is weighed down by a mortal body, earth-bound cell that clogs the manifold activity of its thought. I was most certain, too, that from the foundations of the world men have caught sight of your invisible nature, your eternal power, and your divineness, as they are known through your creatures. For I wondered how it was that I could appreciate beauty in material things on earth or in the heavens, and what it was that enabled me to make correct decisions about things that are subject to change and to rule that one thing ought to be like this, another like that. I wondered how it was that I was able to judge them in this way, and I realized that above my own mind, which was liable to change, there was the never changing, true eternity of truth. So, step by step, my thoughts moved on from the consideration of material things to the soul, which perceives things through the senses of the body, and then to the soul's inner power, to which the bodily senses communicate external facts. Beyond this dumb animals cannot go. The next stage is the power of reason, to which the facts communicated by the bodily senses are submitted for judgement.

This power of reason, realizing that in me it too was liable to change, led me on to consider the source of its own understanding. It withdrew my thoughts from their normal course and drew back from the confusion of images which pressed upon it, so that it might discover what light it was that had been shed upon it when it proclaimed for certain that what was immutable was better than that which was not, and how it had come to know the immutable itself. For unless, by some means, it had known the immutable, it could not possibly have been certain that it was preferable to the mutable. And so, in an instant of awe, my mind attained to the sight of the God who IS. Then, at last, I caught sight of your invisible nature, as it is known through your creatures. But I had no strength to fix my gaze upon them. In my weakness I recoiled and fell back into my old ways, carrying with me nothing but the memory of something that I loved and longed for, as though I had sensed the fragrance of the fare but was not yet able to eat it.

18

I began to search for a means of gaining the strength I needed to enjoy you, but I could not find this means until I embraced the mediator between God and men, Jesus Christ, who is a man, like them, and also rules as God over all things, blessed for ever. He was calling to me and saying I am the way; I am truth and life. He it was who united with our flesh that food which I was too weak to take; for the Word was made flesh so that your Wisdom, by which you created all things, might be milk to suckle us in infancy. For I was not humble enough to conceive of the humble Jesus Christ as my God, nor had I learnt what lesson his human weakness was meant to teach. The lesson is that your Word, the eternal Truth, which far surpasses even the higher parts of your creation, raises up to himself all who subject themselves to him. From the clay of which we are made he built for himself a lowly house in this world below, so that by this means he might cause those who were to be made subject to him to abandon themselves and come over to his side. He would cure them of the pride that swelled up in their hearts and would nurture love in its place, so that they should no longer stride ahead confident in themselves, but might realize their own weakness when at their feet they saw God himself, enfeebled by sharing this garment of our mortality. And at last, from weariness, they would cast themselves down upon his humanity, and when it rose they too would rise.

Book VIII

6

O Lord, my Helper and my Redeemer, I shall now tell and confess to the glory of your name how you released me from the fetters of lust which held me so tightly shackled and from my slavery to the things of this world [...]

One day when for some reason that I cannot recall Nebridius was not with us, Alypius and I were visited at our house by a fellow-countryman of ours from Africa, a man named Ponticianus, who held a high position in the Emperor's household. He had some request to make of us and we sat down to talk. He happened to notice a book lying on a table used for games, which was near where we were sitting. He picked it up and opened it and was greatly surprised to find that it contained Paul's epistles, for he had supposed that it was one of the books which used to tax all my strength as a teacher. Then he smiled and looked at me and said how glad he was, and how surprised, to find this book, and no others, there before my eyes. He of course was a Christian and a faithful servant to you, our God. Time and again he knelt before you in church repeating his prayers and lingering over them. When I told him that I studied Paul's writings with the greatest attention, he began to tell us the story of Antony, the Egyptian monk, whose name was held in high honour by your servants, although Alypius and I had never heard it until then. When Ponticianus realized this, he went into greater detail, wishing to instil some knowledge of this great man into our ignorant minds, for he was very surprised that we had not heard of him. For our part, we too were astonished to hear of the wonders you had worked so recently, almost in our own times, and witnessed by so many, in the true faith and in the Catholic Church. In fact all three of us were amazed, Alypius and I because the story we heard was so remarkable, and Ponticianus because we had not heard it before.

After this he went on to tell us of the groups of monks in the monasteries, of their way of life that savours of your sweetness, and of the fruitful wastes of the desert. All of this was new to us. There was a monastery at Milan also, outside the walls, full of good brethren under the care of Ambrose, but we knew nothing of this either. Ponticianus continued to talk and we listened in silence. Eventually he told us of the time when he and three of his companions were at Trêves. One afternoon, while the Emperor was watching the games in the circus, they went out to stroll in the gardens near the city walls. They became separated into two groups, Ponticianus and one of the others remaining together while the other two went off by themselves. As they wandered on, the second pair came to a house which was the home of some servants of yours, men poor in spirit, to whom the kingdom of heaven belongs. In the house they found a book containing the life of Antony. One of them began to read it and was so fascinated and thrilled by the story that even before he had finished reading he conceived the idea of taking upon himself the same kind of life and abandoning his career in the world - both he and his friend were officials in the service of the State - in order to become your servant. All at once he was filled with the love of holiness. Angry with himself and full of remorse, he looked at his friend and said, 'What do we hope to gain by all the efforts we make? What are we looking for? What is our purpose in serving the State? Can we hope for anything better at Court than to be the Emperor's friends? Even so, surely our position would be precarious and exposed to much danger? We shall meet it at every turn, only to reach another danger which is greater still. And how long is it to be before we reach it? But if I wish, I can become the friend of God at this very moment.'

After saying this he turned back to the book, labouring under the pain of the new life that was taking birth in him. He read on and in his heart, where you alone could see, a change was taking place. His mind was being divested of the world, as could presently be seen. For while he was reading, his heart leaping and turning in his breast, a cry broke from him as he saw the better course and determined to take it. Your servant now, he said to his friend, 'I have torn myself free from all our ambitions and have decided to serve God. From this very moment, here and now, I shall start to serve him. If you will not follow my lead, do not stand in my way.' The other answered that he would stand by his comrade, for such service was glorious and the reward was great. So these two, now your servants, built their tower at the cost which had to be paid, that is, at the cost of giving up all they possessed and following you.

At this moment Ponticianus and the man who had been walking with him in another part of the garden arrived at the house, looking for their friends. Now that they had found them they said that it was time to go home, as the daylight was beginning to fade. But the other two told them of the decision they had made and what they proposed to do. They explained what had made them decide to take this course and how they had agreed upon it, and they asked their friends, if they would not join them, at least not to put obstacles in their way. Ponticianus said that he and the other man did not change their old ways, but they were moved to tears for their own state of life. In all reverence they congratulated the others and commended themselves to their prayers. Then they went back to the palace, burdened with hearts that were bound to this earth; but the others remained in the house and their hearts were fixed upon heaven. Both these men were under a promise of marriage, but once the two women heard what had happened, they too dedicated their virginity to you.

7

This was what Ponticianus told us. But while he was speaking, O Lord, you were turning me around to look at myself. For I had placed myself behind my own back, refusing to see myself. You were setting me before my own eyes so that I could see how sordid I was, how deformed and squalid, how tainted with ulcers and sores. I saw it all and stood aghast, but there was no place where I could escape from myself. If I tried to turn my eyes away they fell on Ponticianus, still telling his tale, and in this way you brought me face to face with myself once more, forcing me upon my own sight so that I should see my wickedness and loathe it. I had known it all along, but I had always pretended that it was something different. I had turned a blind eye and forgotten it.

But now, the more my heart warmed to those two men as I heard how they had made the choice that was to save them by giving themselves up entirely to your care, the more bitterly I hated myself in comparison with them. Many years of my life had passed - twelve, unless I am wrong - since I had read Cicero's Hortensius at the age of nineteen and it had inspired me to study philosophy. But I still postponed my renunciation of this world's joys, which would have left me free to look for that other happiness, the very search for which, let alone its discovery, I ought to have prized above the discovery of all human treasures and kingdoms or the ability to enjoy all the pleasures of the body at a mere nod of the head. As a youth I had been woefully at fault, particularly in early adolesence. I had prayed to you for chastity and said 'Give me chastity and continence, but not yet.' For I was afraid that you would answer my prayer at once and cure me too soon of the disease of lust, which I wanted satisfied, not quelled. I had wandered on along the road of vice in the sacrilegious superstition of the Manichees, not because I thought that it was right, but because I preferred it to the Christian belief, which I did not explore as I ought but opposed out of malice.

[...]

All the time that Ponticianus was speaking my conscience gnawed away at me like this. I was overcome by burning shame, and when he had finished his tale and completed the business for which he had come, he went away and I was left to my own thoughts. I made all sorts of accusations against myself. I cudgelled my soul and belaboured it with reasons why it should follow me now that I was trying so hard to follow you. But it fought back. It would not obey and yet could offer no excuse. All its old arguments were exhausted and had been shown to be false. It remained silent and afraid, for as much as the loss of life itself it feared the stanching of the flow of habit, by which it was wasting away to death.

8

My inner self was a house divided against itself. In the heat of the fierce conflict which I had stirred up against my soul in our common abode, my heart, I turned upon Alypius. My looks betrayed the commotion in my mind as I exclaimed, 'What is the matter with us? What is the meaning of this story? These men have not had our schooling, yet they stand up and storm the gates of heaven while we, for all our learning, lie here grovelling in this world of flesh and blood! Is it because they have led the way that we are ashamed to follow? Is it not worse to hold back?'

[...]

There was a small garden attached to the house where we lodged. We were free to make use of it as well as the rest of the house because our host, the owner of the house, did not live there. I now found myself driven by the tumult in my breast to take refuge in this garden, where no one could interrupt that fierce struggle, in which I was my own contestant, until it came to its conclusion. What the conclusion was to be you knew, O Lord, but I did not. Meanwhile I was beside myself with madness that would bring me sanity. I was dying a death that would bring me life. I knew the evil that was in me, but the good that was soon to be born in me I did not know. So I went out into the garden and Alypius followed at my heels. His presence was no intrusion on my solitude, and how could he leave me in that state? We sat down as far as possible from the house. I was frantic, overcome by violent anger with myself for not accepting your will and entering into your covenant. Yet in my bones I knew that this was what I ought to do. In my heart of hearts I praised it to the skies. And to reach this goal I needed no chariot or ship. I need not even walk as far as I had come from the house to the place where we sat, for to make the journey, and to arrive safely, no more was required than an act of will. But it must be a resolute and whole-hearted act of the will, not some lame wish which I kept turning over and over in my mind, so that it had to wrestle with itself, part of it trying to rise, part falling to the ground.

[...]

11

This was the nature of my sickness. I was in torment, reproaching myself more bitterly than ever as I twisted and turned in my chain. I hoped that my chain might be broken once and for all, because it was only a small thing that held me now. All the same it held me. And you, O Lord, never ceased to watch over my secret heart. In your stern mercy you lashed me with the twin scourge of fear and shame in case I should give way once more and the worn and slender remnant of my chain should not be broken but gain new strength and bind me all the faster. In my heart I kept saying 'Let it be now, let it be now!', and merely by saying this I was on the point of making the resolution. I was on the point of making it, but I did not succeed. Yet I did not fall back into my old state. I stood on the brink of resolution, waiting to take fresh breath. I tried again and came a little nearer to my goal, and then a little nearer still, so that I could almost reach out and grasp it. But I did not reach it. I could not reach out to it or grasp it, because I held back from the step by which I should die to death and become alive to life. My lower instincts, which had taken firm hold of me, were stronger than the higher, which were untried. And the closer I came to the moment which was to mark the great change in me, the more I shrank from it in horror. But it did not drive me back or turn me from my purpose: it merely left me hanging in suspense.

[...]

12

I probed the hidden depths of my soul and wrung its pitiful secrets from it, and when I mustered them all before the eyes of my heart, a great storm broke within me, bringing with it a great deluge of tears. I stood up and left Alypius so that I might weep and cry to my heart's content, for it occurred to me that tears were best shed in solitude. I moved away far enough to avoid being embarrassed even by his presence. He must have realized what my feelings were, for I suppose I had said something and he had known from the sound of my voice that I was ready to burst into tears. So I stood up and left him where we had been sitting, utterly bewildered. Somehow I flung myself down beneath a fig tree and gave way to the tears which now streamed from my eyes, the sacrifice that is acceptable to you. I had much to say to you, my God, not in these very words but in this strain: Lord, will you never be content? Must we always taste your vengeance? Forget the long record of our sins. For I felt that I was still the captive of my sins, and in my misery I kept crying "How long shall I go on saying 'tomorrow, tomorrow'? Why not now? Why not make an end of my ugly sins at this moment?"

I was asking myself these questions, weeping all the while with the most bitter sorrow in my heart, when all at once I heard the sing-song voice of a child in a nearby house. Whether it was the voice of a boy or a girl I cannot say, but again and again it repeated the refrain 'Take it and read, take it and read'. At this I looked up, thinking hard whether there was any kind of game in which children used to chant words like these, but I could not remember ever hearing them before. I stemmed my flood of tears and stood up, telling myself that this could only be a divine command to open my book of Scripture and read the first passage on which my eyes should fall. For I had heard the story of Antony, and I remembered how he had happened to go into a church while the Gospel was being read and had taken it as a counsel addressed to himself when he heard the words Go home and sell all that belongs to you. Give it to the poor, and so the treasure you have shall be in heaven; then come back and follow me. By this divine pronouncement he had at once been converted to you.

So I hurried back to the place where Alypius was sitting, for when I stood up to move away I had put down the book containing Paul's Epistles. I seized it and opened it, and in silence I read the first passage on which my eyes fell: Not in revelling and drunkenness, not in lust and wantonness, not in quarrels and rivalries. Rather, arm yourselves with the Lord Jesus Christ; spend no more thought on nature and nature's appetites. I had no wish to read more and no need to do so. For in an instant, as I came to the end of the sentence, it was as though the light of confidence flooded into my heart and all the darkness of doubt was dispelled.

I marked the place with my finger or by some other sign and closed the book. My looks now were quite calm as I told Alypius what had happened to me. He too told me what he had been feeling, which of course I did not know. He asked to see what I had read. I showed it to him and he read on beyond the text which I had read. I did not know what followed, but it was this: Find room among you for a man of over-delicate conscience. Alypius applied this to himself and told me so. This admonition was enough to give him strength, and without suffering the distress of hesitation he made his resolution and took this good purpose to himself. And it very well suited his moral character, which had long been far, far better than my own.

Then we went in and told my mother, who was overjoyed. And when we went on to describe how it had all happened, she was jubilant with triumph and glorified you, who are powerful enough, and more than powerful enough, to carry out your purpose beyond all our hopes and dreams. For she saw that you had granted her far more than she used to ask in her tearful prayers and plaintive lamentations. You converted me to yourself, so that I no longer desired a wife or placed any hope in this world but stood firmly upon the rule of faith, where you had shown me to her in a dream so many years before. And you turned her sadness into rejoicing, into joy far fuller than her dearest wish, far sweeter and more chaste than any she had hoped to find in children begotten of my flesh.

Book IX

2

Knowing that you were watching me I thought it best to retire quietly from the market where I sold the services of my tongue rather than make an abrupt and sensational departure. I intended that young pupils who gave no thought to your law or your peace, but only to lies and the insane warfare of the courts, should no longer buy from my lips any weapon to arm their madness. Luckily there were now only a few days left before the autumn holidays, and I decided to bear with this delay and withdraw at the proper time. Now that I had been redeemed by you I had no intention of offering myself for sale again. This plan was known to you, but no man knew of it except our closest friends. We had agreed that it should not be made generally known, although, as we climbed up from the valley of tears, singing the song of ascent, you had given us sharp arrows and burning coals to use against any cunning tongues that might speak against us under the pretence of giving good advice and devour us with their love, just as men devour food for which they have a liking.

[...]

6

When the time came for me to hand in my name for baptism, we left the country and went back to Milan. It was Alypius's wish to be reborn in you at the same time. He was already endued with the humility which fits a man for your sacraments, and he had subjected his body to such stern discipline that he would even walk barefoot on the icy soil of Italy, a thing which few would venture to do. With us we took the boy Adeodatus, my natural son born of my sin. You had given him every gift. Although he was barely fifteen, there were many learned and respected men who were not his equals in intelligence. I acknowledge that he had his gifts from you, O Lord my God, who are the Creator of all and have great power to reshape our deformities, for there was nothing of mine in that boy except my sin. It was you too, and none other, who had inspired us to bring him up as you would have him. These were your gifts and I acknowledge them.

[...]

We made him our companion, in your grace no younger than ourselves. Together we were ready to begin our schooling in your ways. We were baptized, and all anxiety over the past melted away from us. The days were all too short, for I was lost in wonder and joy, meditating upon your far-reaching providence for the salvation of the human race. The tears flowed from me when I heard your hymns and canticles, for the sweet singing of your Church moved me deeply. The music surged in my ears, truth seeped into my heart, and my feelings of devotion overflowed, so that the tears streamed down. But they were tears of gladness.

8

You, O God, who bring men of one mind to live together, brought a young man from our own town, named Evodius, to join our company. He had been converted and baptized before us, while he was employed as a government officer, but he had given up the service of the State and entered upon yours. He remained with us and we intended to live together in the devout life which we proposed to lead. We discussed where we could most usefully serve you and together we set out to return to Africa. While we were at Ostia, at the mouth of the Tiber, my mother died.

There are many things which I do not set down in this book, since I am pressed for time. My God, I pray you to accept my confessions and also the gratitude I bear you for all the many things which I pass over in silence. But I will omit not a word that my mind can bring to birth concerning your servant, my mother. In the flesh she brought me to birth in this world: in her heart she brought me to birth in your eternal light. It is not of her gifts that I shall speak, but of the gifts you gave to her. For she was neither her own maker nor her own teacher. It was you who made her, and neither her father nor her mother knew what kind of woman their daughter would grow up to be. It was by Christ's teaching, by the guidance of your only Son, that she was brought up to honour and obey you in one of those good Christian families which form the body of your Church [...]

10

Not long before the day on which she was to leave this life - you knew which day it was to be, O Lord, though we did not - my mother and I were alone, leaning from a window which overlooked the garden in the courtyard of the house where we were staying at Ostia. We were waiting there after our long and tiring journey, away from the crowd, to refresh ourselves before our sea-voyage. I believe that what I am going to tell happened through the secret working of your providence. For we were talking alone together and our conversation was serene and joyful. We had forgotten what we had left behind and were intent on what lay before us. In the presence of Truth, which is yourself, we were wondering what the eternal life of the saints would be like, that life which no eye has seen, no ear has heard, no human heart conceived. But we laid the lips of our hearts to the heavenly stream that flows from your fountain, the source of all life which is in you, so that as far as it was in our power to do so we might be sprinkled with its waters and in some sense reach an understanding of this great mystery.

Our conversation led us to the conclusion that no bodily pleasure, however great it might be and whatever earthly light might shed lustre upon it, was worthy of comparison, or even of mention, beside the happiness of the life of the saints. As the flame of love burned stronger in us and raised us higher towards the eternal God, our thoughts ranged over the whole compass of material things in their various degrees, up to the heavens themselves, from which the sun and the moon and the stars shine down upon the earth. Higher still we climbed, thinking and speaking all the while in wonder at all that you have made. At length we came to our own souls and passed beyond them to that place of everlasting plenty, where you feed Israel for ever with the food of truth. There life is that Wisdom by which all these things that we know are made, all things that ever have been and all that are yet to be. But that Wisdom is not made: it is as it has always been and as it will be for ever - or, rather, I should not say that it has been or will be, for it simply is, because eternity is not in the past or in the future. And while we spoke of the eternal Wisdom, longing for it and straining for it with all the strength of our hearts, for one fleeting instant we reached out and touched it. Then with a sigh, leaving our spiritual harvest bound to it, we returned to the sound of our own speech, in which each word has a beginning and an ending - far, far different from your Word, our Lord, who abides in himself for ever, yet never grows old and gives new life to all things.

[...]

This was the purport of our talk, though we did not speak in these precise words or exactly as I have reported them. Yet you know, O Lord, that as we talked that day, the world, for all its pleasures, seemed a paltry place compared with the life that we spoke of. And then my mother said, 'My son, for my part I find no further pleasure in this life. What I am still to do or why I am here in the world, I do not know, for I have no more to hope for on this earth. There was one reason, and one alone, why I wished to remain a little longer in this life, and that was to see you a Catholic Christian before I died. God has granted my wish and more besides, for I now see you as his servant, spurning such happiness as the world can give. What is left for me to do in this world?'

11

I scarcely remember what answer I gave her. It was about five days after this, or not much more, that she took to her bed with a fever. One day during her illness she had a fainting fit and lost consciousness for a short time. We hurried to her bedside, but she soon regained consciousness and looked up at my brother and me as we stood beside her. With a puzzled look she asked 'Where was I?' Then watching us closely as we stood there speechless with grief, she said 'You will bury your mother here.' I said nothing, trying hard to hold back my tears, but my brother said something to the effect that he wished for her sake that she would die in her own country, not abroad. When she heard this, she looked at him anxiously and her eyes reproached him for his worldly thoughts. She turned to me and said, 'See how he talks!' and then, speaking to both of us, she went on, 'It does not matter where you bury my body. Do not let that worry you! All I ask of you is that, wherever you may be, you should remember me at the altar of the Lord.'

[...]

And so on the ninth day of her illness, when she was fifty-six and I was thirty-three, her pious and devoted soul was set free from the body.

13

Now that my soul has recovered from that wound, in which perhaps I was guilty of too much worldly affection, tears of another sort stream from my eyes. They are tears which I offer to you, my God, for your handmaid. They flow from a spirit which trembles at the thought of the dangers which await every soul that has died with Adam. For although she was alive in Christ even before her soul was parted from the body, and her faith and the good life she led resounded to the glory of your name, yet I cannot presume to say that from the time when she was reborn in baptism no word contrary to your commandments ever fell from her lips. Your Son, the Truth, has said: Any man who says to his brother, You fool, must answer for it in hell fire, and however praiseworthy a man's life may be, it will go hard with him if you lay aside your mercy when you come to examine it. But you do not search out our faults ruthlessly, and because of this we hope and believe that one day we shall find a place with you. Yet if any man makes a list of his deserts, what would it be but a list of your gifts? If only men would know themselves for what they are! If only they who boast would make their boast in the Lord!

And so, my Glory and my Life, God of my heart, I will lay aside for a while all the good deeds which my mother did. For them I thank you, but now I pray to you for her sins. Hear me through your Son, who hung on the cross and now sits at your right hand and pleads for us, for he is the true medicine of our wounds. I know that my mother always acted with mercy and that she forgave others with all her heart when they trespassed against her. Forgive her too, O Lord, if ever she trespassed against you in all the long years of her life after baptism. Forgive her, I beseech you; do not call her to account. Let your mercy give your judgement an honourable welcome, for your words are true and you have promised mercy to the merciful. If they are merciful, it is by your gift; and you will show pity on those whom you pity; you will show mercy where you are merciful.

[...]

Let her rest in peace with her husband. He was her first husband and she married no other after him. She served him, yielding you a harvest, so that in the end she also won him for you. O my Lord, my God, inspire your servants my brothers - they are your sons and my masters, whom I serve with heart and voice and pen - inspire those of them who read this book to remember Monica, your servant, at your altar and with her Patricius, her husband, who died before her, by whose bodies you brought me into this life, though how it was I do not know. With pious hearts let them remember those who were not only my parents in this light that fails, but were also my brother and sister, subject to you, our Father, in our Catholic mother the Church, and will be my fellow citizens in the eternal Jerusalem for which your people sigh throughout their pilgrimage, from the time when they set out until the time when they return to you. So it shall be that the last request that my mother made to me shall be granted in the prayers of the many who read my confessions more fully than in mine alone.

Book X

2

O Lord, the depths of man's conscience lie bare before your eyes. Could anything of mine remain hidden from you, even if I refused to confess it? I should only be shielding my eyes from seeing you, not hiding myself from you. But now that I have the evidence of my own misery to prove to me how displeasing I am to myself, you are my light and my joy. It is you whom I love and desire, so that I am ashamed of myself and cast myself aside and choose you instead, and I please neither you nor myself except in you.

So, O Lord, all that I am is laid bare before you. I have declared how it profits me to confess to you. And I make my confession, not in words and sounds made by the tongue alone, but with the voice of my soul and in my thoughts which cry aloud to you. Your ear can hear them. For when I am sinful, if I am displeased with myself, this is a confession that I make to you; and when I am good, if I do not claim the merit for myself, this too is confession. For you, O Lord, give your benediction to the just, but first you make a just man of the sinner. And so my confession is made both silently in your sight, my God, and aloud as well, because even though my tongue utters no sound, my heart cries to you. For whatever good I may speak to men you have heard it before in my heart, and whatever good you hear in my heart, you have first spoken to me yourself.

4

But what good do they hope will be done if they listen to what I say? Is it that they wish to join with me in thanking you, when they hear how close I have come to you by your grace, and to pray for me, when they hear how far I am set apart from you by the burden of my sins? If this is what they wish, I shall tell them what I am. For no small good is gained, O Lord my God, if many offer you thanks for me and many pray to you for me. Let all who are truly my brothers love in me what they know from your teaching to be worthy of their love, and let them sorrow to find in me what they know from your teaching to be occasion for remorse. This is what I wish my true brothers to feel in their hearts. I do not speak of strangers or of alien foes, who make treacherous promises, and lift their hands in perjury. But my true brothers are those who rejoice for me in their hearts when they find good in me, and grieve for me when they find sin. They are my true brothers, because whether they see good in me or evil, they love me still. To such as these I shall reveal what I am. Let them breathe a sigh of joy for what is good in me and a sigh of grief for what is bad. The good I do is done by you in me and by your grace: the evil is my fault; it is the punishment you send me. Let my brothers draw their breath in joy for the one and sigh with grief for the other. Let hymns of thanksgiving and cries of sorrow rise together from their hearts, as though they were vessels burning with incense before you. And I pray you, O Lord, to be pleased with the incense that rises in your holy temple and, for your name's sake, to have mercy on me, as you are ever rich in mercy. Do not relinquish what you have begun, but make perfect what is still imperfect in me.

So, if I go on to confess, not what I was, but what I am, the good that comes of it is this. There is joy in my heart when I confess to you, yet there is fear as well; there is sorrow, and yet hope. But I confess not only to you but also to the believers among men, all who share my joy and all who, like me, are doomed to die; all who are my fellows in your kingdom and all who accompany me on this pilgrimage, whether they have gone before or are still to come or are with me as I make my way through life. They are your servants and my brothers. You have chosen them to be your sons. You have named them as the masters whom I am to serve if I wish to live with you and in your grace. This is your bidding, but it would hold less meaning for me if it were made known to me in words alone and I had not the example of Christ, who has shown me the way by his deeds as well. I do your bidding in word and deed alike. I do it beneath the protection of your wings, for the peril would be too great if it were not that my soul has submitted to you and sought the shelter of your wings and that my weakness is known to you. I am no more than a child, but my Father lives for ever and I have a Protector great enough to save me. For he who begot me and he who watches over me are one and the same, and for me there is no good but you, the Almighty, who are with me even before I am with you. So to such as you command me to serve I will reveal, not what I have been, but what I have become and what I am. But, since I do not scrutinize my own conduct, let my words be understood as they are meant.

30

It is truly your command that I should be continent and restrain myself from gratification of corrupt nature, gratification of the eye, the empty pomp of living. You commanded me not to commit fornication, and though you did not forbid me to marry, you counselled me to take a better course. You gave me the grace and I did your bidding, even before I became a minister of your sacrament. But in my memory, of which I have said much, the images of things imprinted upon it by my former habits still linger on. When I am awake they obtrude themselves upon me, though with little strength. But when I dream, they not only give me pleasure but are very much like acquiescence in the act. The power which these illusory images have over my soul and my body is so great that what is no more than a vision can influence me in sleep in a way that the reality cannot do when I am awake. Surely it cannot be that when I am asleep I am not myself, O Lord my God? And yet the moment when I pass from wakefulness to sleep, or return again from sleep to wakefulness, marks a great difference in me. During sleep where is my reason which, when I am awake, resists such suggestions and remains firm and undismayed even in face of the realities themselves? Is it sealed off when I close my eyes? Does it fall asleep with the senses of the body? And why is it that even in sleep I often resist the attractions of these images, for I remember my chaste resolutions and abide by them and give no consent to temptations of this sort? Yet the difference between waking and sleeping is so great that even when, during sleep, it happens otherwise, I return to a clear conscience when I wake and realize that, because of this difference, I was not responsible for the act, although I am sorry that by some means or other it happened to me.

The power of your hand, O God Almighty, is indeed great enough to cure all the diseases of my soul. By granting me more abundant grace you can even quench the fire of sensuality which provokes me in my sleep. More and more, O Lord, you will increase your gifts in me, so that my soul may follow me to you, freed from the concupiscence which binds it, and rebel no more against itself. By your grace it will no longer commit in sleep these shameful, unclean acts inspired by sensual images, which lead to the pollution of the body: it will not so much as consent to them. For to you, the Almighty, who are powerful enough to carry out your purpose beyond all our hopes and dreams, it is no great task to prescribe that no temptations of this kind, even such slight temptations as can be checked by the least act of will, should arouse pleasure in me, even in sleep, prowhich we say that we see. Yet we not only say 'See how it shines' when we are speaking of something which only the eyes can perceive, but we also say 'See how loud it is', 'See how it smells', 'See how it tastes', and 'See how hard it is'. So, as I said, sense-experience in general is called the lust of the eyes because, although the function of sight belongs primarily to the eyes, we apply it to the other organs of sense as well, by analogy, when they are used to discover any item of knowledge.

We can easily distinguish between the motives of pleasure and curiosity. When the senses demand pleasure, they look for objects of visual beauty, harmonious sounds, fragrant perfumes, and things that are pleasant to the taste or soft to the touch. But when their motive is curiosity, they may look for just the reverse of these things, simply to put it to the proof, not for the sake of an unpleasant experience, but from a relish for investigation and discovery. What pleasure can there be in the sight of a mangled corpse, which can only horrify? Yet people will flock to see one lying on the ground, simply for the sensation of sorrow and horror that it gives them. They are even afraid that it may bring them nightmares, as though it were something that they had been forced to look at while they were awake or something to which they had been attracted by rumours of its beauty. The same is true of the other senses, although it would be tedious to give further examples. It is to satisfy this unhealthy curiosity that freaks and prodigies are put on show in the theatre, and for the same reason men are led to investigate the secrets of nature, which are irrelevant to our lives, although such knowledge is of no value to them and they wish to gain it merely for the sake of knowing. It is curiosity, too, which causes men to turn to sorcery in the effort to obtain knowledge for the same perverted purpose. And it even invades our religion, for we put God to the test when we demand signs and wonders from him, not in the hope of salvation, but simply for the love of the experience.

[...]

My life is full of such faults, and my only hope is in your boundless mercy. For when our hearts become repositories piled high with such worthless stock as this, it is the cause of interruption and distraction from our prayers. And although, in your presence, the voices of our hearts are raised to your ear, all kinds of trivial thoughts break in and cut us off from the great act of prayer.

41

I have now considered the sorry state to which my sins have brought me, according to the three different forms which temptation may take, and I have invoked your helping hand to save me. For in my wounded heart I saw your splendour and it dazzled me. I asked: Who can come close to such glory? Your watchful care has lost sight of me. You are the Truth which presides over all things. But in my selfish longing I did not wish to lose you. Together with you I wanted to possess a lie, much as a man will not utter so glaring a falsehood that it blinds his own eyes to the truth. And in this way I lost you, because you do not deign to be possessed together with a lie.

42

Whom could I find to reconcile me to you? Ought I to have sought the help of the angels? But if I had sought their help, what prayers should I have uttered? What rites should I have used? Many men, so I have heard, for lack of strength to return to you by themselves, have tried to do so by this means, but they ended by craving for strange visions, and their only reward was delusion. For they tried to find you in all the conceit and arrogance of their learning. They thrust out their chests in pride, when they should have beaten their breasts in mourning. And because they resembled them at heart, they attracted to their side the fallen angels, the princes of the lower air, their companions and associates in pride. But these allies tricked them, using magic craft, for while they sought a mediator who would cleanse them of their impurities, it was no mediator that they found. It was the devil, passing for an angel of light, and it was a potent lure for their proud flesh that he was not a creature of flesh and blood. For they were mortal men and sinners; but you, O Lord, to whom they wanted to be reconciled, are immortal and without sin. But a mediator between God and man must have something in common with God and something in common with man. For if in both these points he were like men, he would be far from God; and if in both of them he were like God, he would be far from men. In neither case could he be a mediator. But since, by the hidden pronouncements of your justice, you have given the devil licence to make a mockery of pride, he poses as a mediator. For in one point he is like man: he is sinful. And in the other he pretends to be like God: because he is not clothed with a mortal body of flesh and blood, he tries to represent himself as immortal. But since sin offers death for wages, in common with men he has this reason to be condemned to die.

43

But there is a true Mediator, whom in your secret mercy you have shown to men. You sent him so that by his example they too might learn humility. He is the Mediator between God and men, Jesus Christ, who is a man, and he appeared on earth between men, who are sinful and mortal, and God, who is immortal and just. Like men he was mortal: like God, he was just. And because the reward of the just is life and peace, he came so that by his own justness, which is his in union with God, he might make null the death of the wicked whom he justified, by choosing to share their death. He was made known to holy men in ancient times, so that they might be saved through faith in his passion to come, just as we are saved through faith in the passion he suffered long ago. For as man, he is our Mediator; but as the Word of God, he is not an intermediary between God and man because he is equal with God, and God with God, and together with him one God.

[...]

Terrified by my sins and the dead weight of my misery, I had turned my problems over in my mind and was half determined to seek refuge in the desert. But you forbade me to do this and gave me strength by saying: Christ died for us all, so that being alive should no longer mean living with our own life, but with his life who died for us. Lord, I cast all my troubles on you and from now on I shall contemplate the wonders of your law. You know how weak I am and how inadequate is my knowledge: teach me and heal my frailty. Your only Son, in whom the whole treasury of wisdom and knowledge is stored up, has redeemed me with his blood. Save me from the scorn of my enemies, for the price of my redemption is always in my thoughts. I eat it and drink it and minister it to others; and as one of the poor I long to be filled with it, to be one of those who eat and have their fill. And those who look for the Lord will cry out in praise of him.

Book XI

3

Let me hear and understand the meaning of the words: In the Beginning you made heaven and earth. Moses wrote these words. He wrote them and passed on into your presence, leaving this world where you spoke to him. He is no longer here and I cannot see him face to face. But if he were here, I would lay hold of him and in your name I would beg and beseech him to explain those words to me. I would be all ears to catch the sounds that fell from his lips. If he spoke in Hebrew, his words would strike my ear in vain and none of their meaning would reach my mind. If he spoke in Latin, I should know what he said. But how should I know whether what he said was true? If I knew this too, it could not be from him that I got such knowledge. But deep inside me, in my most intimate thought, Truth, which is neither Hebrew nor Greek nor Latin nor any foreign speech, would speak to me, though not in syllables formed by lips and tongue. It would whisper, 'He speaks the truth.' And at once I should be assured. In all confidence I would say to this man, your servant, 'What you tell me is true.'

Since, then, I cannot question Moses, whose words were true because you, the Truth, filled him with yourself, I beseech you, my God, to forgive my sins and grant me the grace to understand those words, as you granted him, your servant, the grace to speak them.

9

He is the Beginning, O God, in which you made heaven and earth. In this wonderful way you spoke and created them in your Word, in your Son, who is your Strength, your Wisdom, and your Truth.

Who can understand this mystery or explain it to others? What is that light whose gentle beams now and again strike through to my heart, causing me to shudder in awe yet firing me with their warmth? I shudder to feel how different I am from it: yet in so far as I am like it, I am aglow with its fire. It is the light of Wisdom, Wisdom itself, which at times shines upon me, parting my clouds. But when I weakly fall away from its light, those clouds envelop me again in the dense mantle of darkness which I bear for my punishment. For my strength ebbs away for very misery, so that I cannot sustain my blessings. And so I shall remain until you, O Lord, who have pardoned all my sins, also heal all my mortal ills. For you will rescue my life from deadly peril, crown me with the blessings of your mercy, content all my desire for good, restore my youth as the eagle's plumage is restored. Our salvation is founded upon the hope of something, and in endurance we await the fulfilment of your promises. Let those who are able listen to your voice speaking to their hearts. Trusting in your inspired words, I shall cry out: What diversity, Lord, in your creatures! What wisdom has designed them all! The Beginning is Wisdom and Wisdom is the Beginning in which you made heaven and earth.

13

A fickle-minded man, whose thoughts were all astray because of his conception of time past, might wonder why you, who are God almighty, Creator of all, Sustainer of all, and Maker of heaven and earth, should have been idle and allowed countless ages to elapse before you finally undertook the vast work of creation. My advice to such people is to shake off their dreams and think carefully, because their wonder is based on a misconception.

How could those countless ages have elapsed when you, the Creator, in whom all ages have their origin, had not yet created them? What time could there have been that was not created by you? How could time elapse if it never was?

You are the Maker of all time. If, then, there was any time before you made heaven and earth, how can anyone say that you were idle? You must have made that time, for time could not elapse before you made it.

[...]

14

It is therefore true to say that when you had not made anything, there was no time, because time itself was of your making. And no time is co-eternal with you, because you never change; whereas, if time never changed, it would not be time.

[...]

19

In what way, then, do you, Ruler of all that you have created, reveal the future to the souls of men? You have revealed it to your prophets. But how do you reveal the future to us when, for us, the future does not exist? Is it that you only reveal present signs of things that are to come? For it is utterly impossible that things which do not exist should be revealed. The means by which you do this is far beyond our understanding. I have not the strength to comprehend this mystery, and by my own power I never shall. But in your strength I shall understand it, when you grant me the grace to see, sweet Light of the eyes of my soul.

[...]

25

I confess to you, Lord, that I still do not know what time is. Yet I confess too that I do know that I am saying this in time, that I have been talking about time for a long time, and that this long time would not be a long time if it were not for the fact that time has been passing all the while. How can I know this, when I do not know what time is? Is it that I do know what time is, but do not know how to put what I know into words? I am in a sorry state, for I do not even know what I do not know!

[...]

31

O Lord my God, how deep are your mysteries! How far from your safe haven have I been cast away by the consequences of my sins! Heal my eyes and let me rejoice in your light. If there were a mind endowed with such great power of knowing and foreknowing that all the past and all the future were known to it as clearly as I know a familiar psalm, that mind would be wonderful beyond belief. We should hold back from it in awe at the thought that nothing in all the history of the past and nothing in all the ages yet to come was hidden from it. It would know all this as surely as, when I sing the psalm, I know what I have already sung and what I have still to sing, how far I am from the beginning and how far from the end. But it is unthinkable that you, Creator of the universe, Creator of souls and bodies, should know all the past and all the future merely in this way. Your knowledge is far more wonderful, far more mysterious than this. It is not like the knowledge of a man who sings words well known to him or listens to another singing a familiar psalm. While he does this, his feelings vary and his senses are divided, because he is partly anticipating words still to come and partly remembering words already sung. It is far otherwise with you, for you are eternally without change, the truly eternal Creator of minds. In the Beginning you knew heaven and earth, and there was no change in your knowledge. In just the same way, in the Beginning you created heaven and earth, and there was no change in your action. Some understand this and some do not: let all alike praise you. You are supreme above all, yet your dwelling is in the humble of heart. For you comfort the burdened, and none fall who lift their eyes to your high place.

Book XII

2

Humbly my tongue confesses to you in the height of your majesty that it was you who made heaven and earth, the heaven I see and the earth I tread, from which, too, came this earthly body that I bear. It was you who made them. But where, O Lord, is the Heaven of Heavens, of which we hear in the words of the psalm: To the Lord belongs the Heaven of Heavens, the earth he gives to the children of men? Where is that other heaven which we cannot see and compared with which all that we see is merely earth?

[...]

3

Undoubtedly the reason why we are told that this earth was 'invisible and without form', a kind of deep abyss over which there was no light, is that it had no form whatsoever; and the reason why you commanded it to be written that 'darkness reigned over the deep' could only be that there was total absence of light. For if there had been light, where else would it have been but high above, shedding brilliance over all? But since as yet there was no light, what else was the presence of darkness but the absence of light? Darkness, then, reigned over all, because there was no light above, just as silence reigns where there is no sound. For what else is the presence of silence but the absence of sound?

[...]

4

How, then, could it be described in such a way that even dull minds could grasp it, except by means of some familiar word? And of all that goes to make up this world what can be found nearer to utter formlessness than 'earth' and 'the deep'? Since they are the lowest in the scale of created things, they have beauty of form in a lower degree than the other, higher things, which are radiant in their splendour. Why, then, should I not assume that the words 'earth, invisible and without form' are meant to convey to men, in a way that they can understand, that formless matter which you created without beauty in order to make from it this beautiful world?

7

If it was to be there first, in order to be the vehicle for all these visible, composite forms, what can have been its own origin? It can only have derived its being from you, for all things have their origin in you, whatever the degree of their being, although the less they are like you, the farther they are from you - and here I am not speaking in terms of space. This means, then, that you, O Lord, whose being does not alter as times change but is ever and always one and the same, the very same, holy, holy, holy, Lord God Almighty, made something in the Beginning, which is of yourself, in your Wisdom, which is born of your own substance, and you created this thing out of nothing.

You created heaven and earth but you did not make them of your own substance. If you had done so, they would have been equal to your only-begotten Son, and therefore to yourself, and justice could in no way admit that what was not of your own substance should be equal to you. But besides yourself, O God, who are Trinity in Unity, Unity in Trinity, there was nothing from which you could make heaven and earth. Therefore you must have created them from nothing, the one great, the other small. For there is nothing that you cannot do. You are good and all that you make must be good, both the great Heaven of Heavens and this little earth. You were, and besides you nothing was. From nothing, then, you created heaven and earth, distinct from one another; the one close to yourself, the other close to being nothing; the one surpassed only by yourself, the other little more than nothing.

13

This then, my God, is how I interpret your Scripture when I read the words: 'In the Beginning God made heaven and earth. The earth was invisible and without form, and darkness reigned over the deep.' Scripture does not say on which day you made them, and I understand the reason for this to be that 'heaven' here means the Heaven of Heavens - that is, the intellectual heaven, where the intellect is privileged to know all at once, not in part only, not as if it were looking at a confused reflection in a mirror, but as a whole, clearly, face to face; not first one thing and then another but, as I have said, all at once, quite apart from the ebb and flow of time - and 'earth' means the invisible, formless earth, also unaffected by the ebb and flow of time which always marks the change from this to that, since where there is no form there can be no this and no that. These, then, are the heaven and earth that are meant, as I understand it, when the Scripture says 'In the Beginning God made heaven and earth' without mention of day - heaven, that is, the Heaven of Heavens which was given form from the very beginning, and earth, that is, earth invisible and without order, which was utterly formless. In fact the Scripture explains in the very next sentence what earth is meant by this. And since it says that on the second day the firmament was made and that it was called heaven, it gives us to understand which heaven was meant by the first sentence, which makes no mention of days.

27

The account left by Moses, whom you chose to pass it on to us, is like a spring which is all the more copious because it flows in a confined space. Its waters are carried by a maze of channels over a wider area than could be reached by any single stream drawing its water from the same source and flowing through many different places. In the same way, from the words of Moses, uttered in all brevity but destined to serve a host of preachers, there gush clear streams of truth from which each of us, though in more prolix and roundabout phrases, may derive a true explanation of the creation as best he is able, some choosing one and some another interpretation.

[...]

31

For this reason, although I hear people say 'Moses meant this' or 'Moses meant that', I think it more truly religious to say 'Why should he not have had both meanings in mind, if both are true? And if others see in the same words a third, or a fourth, or any number of true meanings, why should we not believe that Moses saw them all? There is only one God, who caused Moses to write the Holy Scriptures in the way best suited to the minds of great numbers of men who would all see truths in them, though not the same truths in each case.'

For my part I declare resolutely and with all my heart that if I were called upon to write a book which was to be vested with the highest authority, I should prefer to write it in such a way that a reader could find re-echoed in my words whatever truths he was able to apprehend. I would rather write in this way than impose a single true meaning so explicitly that it would exclude all others, even though they contained no falsehood that could give me offence. And if this is what I would choose for myself, I will not be so rash, my God, as to suppose that so great a man as Moses deserved a lesser gift from you. As he wrote those words, he was aware of all that they implied. He was conscious of every truth that we can deduce from them and of others besides that we cannot, or cannot yet, find in them but are nevertheless there to be found.

32

[...]

O Lord my God, how much I have written on so few words! What endurance I should need and how much time, if I were to comment upon the whole of your Scriptures at such length! Let me, then, continue to lay before you my thoughts upon the Scriptures, but more briefly; and in so doing let me be content to give one explanation only, the one which I see by your inspiration to be true and certain and good, even though many may occur to me in places where more than one is possible. Let me lay this confession before you in the firm belief that if the explanation I give accords with the meaning which Moses had in mind, I shall have done what is right and best. This is what I must try my utmost to do. But if I fail, let me at least say what your Truth wills to reveal to me by the words of Scripture, just as he revealed what he willed to Moses.

Book XIII

1

I call upon you, O God, my Mercy, who made me and did not forget me when I forgot you. I call you to come into my soul, for by inspiring it to long for you you prepare it to receive you. Now, as I call upon you, do not desert me, for you came to my aid even before I called upon you. In all sorts of ways, over and over again, when I was far from you, you coaxed me to listen to your voice, to turn my back on you no more, and to call upon you for aid when, all the time, you were calling to me yourself. You blotted out all my evil deeds, in order not to repay me with the punishment I deserved for the work of my hands, which had led me away from you; and even before I did them, you took into account all the good deeds by which I should deserve well of you, in order to recompense yourself for the work of your hands which made me. For before I was, you were: I was nothing, that you should give me being. Yet now I am; and this is because out of your goodness you provided for all that you have made me and all from which you have made me. You had no need of me, nor am I a creature good in such a way as to be helpful to you, my Lord and my God. It is not as though you could grow tired by working and I could serve you by preventing your fatigue, nor would your power be any the less if my service were lacking. I cannot serve you as a peasant tills the land, for your works bear fruit even if I fail to serve you with my husbandry. I can only serve you and worship you so that good may come to me from you, and but for you no good could come to me, for I should not even exist to receive it.

3

At the beginning of creation you said Let there be light; and the light began. I think these words are properly to be understood to refer to the spiritual creation, because it was already life of a certain kind, able to be given light by you. But just as, previously, it could make no claim on you, by its own deserts, to be the kind of life which could receive your light, so, now that it existed, it could not claim to receive this gift by its own merits. In its formless state it would not have been pleasing to you unless it became light. And it became light, not simply by existing, but by fixing its gaze upon you and clinging to you, the Light which shone upon it. In this way it owes to your grace, and to your grace alone, both the gift of its very existence and the gift of a life that is lived in happiness. For, by undergoing a change, which bettered it, it was turned towards that which cannot change, either for better or for worse, that is, towards you. Only you can never change, because you alone are absolute simplicity, for whom to live is the same as to live in blessed happiness, since you are your own beatitude.

5

When I read that your Spirit moved over the waters, I catch a faint glimpse of the Trinity which you are, my God. For it was you, the Father, who created heaven and earth in the Beginning of our Wisdom - which is your Wisdom, born of you, equal to you, and co-eternal with you - that is, in your Son. I have had much to say of the Heaven of Heavens, of the earth invisible and without form, and of the deep, showing how its darkness was in keeping with the spiritual creation, which, in its formlessness, had no cohesion or stability. Such it would have remained unless, by being turned to God, from whom it already drew such life as it had, it had received beauty as well as life by the reflection of his glory. In this way the Heaven of Heavens came into being, that is, the heaven of the heaven which was later created between the waters above and the waters below. When I spoke of these things, I took the word 'God', who made them, to mean the Father and the 'Beginning', in which he made them, to mean the Son. But, believing that my God is a Trinity, I searched for this truth in the sacred words of his Scripture and found it where it says that your Spirit moved over the waters. Here, then, is the Trinity, my God, Father, Son, and Holy Ghost, the Creator of all creation.

11

Who can understand the omnipotent Trinity? We all speak of it, though we may not speak of it as it truly is, for rarely does a soul know what it is saying when it speaks of the Trinity. Men wrangle and dispute about it, but it is a vision that is given to none unless they are at peace.

There are three things, all found in man himself, which I should like men to consider. They are far different from the Trinity, but I suggest them as a subject for mental exercise by which we can test ourselves and realize how great this difference is. The three things are existence, knowledge, and will, for I can say that I am, I know, and I will. I am a being which knows and wills; I know both that I am and that I will; and I will both to be and to know. In these three - being, knowledge, and will - there is one inseparable life, one life, one mind, one essence; and therefore, although they are distinct from one another, the distinction does not separate them. This must be plain to anyone who has the ability to understand it. In fact he need not look beyond himself. Let him examine himself closely, take stock, and tell me what he finds.

But when he has found a common principle in these three and has told me what he finds, he must not think that he has discovered that which is above them all and is unchangeable, that which immutably is, immutably knows, and immutably wills. For none of us can easily conceive whether God is a Trinity because all these three - immutable being, immutable knowledge, and immutable will - are together in him; whether all three are together in each person of the Trinity, so that each is threefold; or whether both these suppositions are true and in some wonderful way, in which the simple and the multiple are one, though God is infinite he is yet an end to himself and in himself, so that the Trinity is in itself, and is known to itself, and suffices to itself, the supreme Being, one alone immutably, in the vastness of its unity. This is a mystery that none can explain, and which of us would presume to assert that he can?

28

And you saw all that you had made, O God, and found it very good. We, too, see all these things and know that they are very good. In the case of each of your works you first commanded them to be made, and when they had been made you looked at each in turn and saw that it was good. I have counted and found that Scripture tells us seven times that you saw that what you had made was good, and when you looked for the eighth time and saw the whole of your creation, we are told that you found it not only good but very good, for you saw all at once as one whole. Each separate work was good, but when they were all seen as one, they were not merely good: they were very good.

The same can be said of every material thing which has beauty. For a thing which consists of several parts, each beautiful in itself, is far more beautiful than the individual parts which, properly combined and arranged, compose the whole, even though each part, taken separately, is itself a thing of beauty.

35

O Lord God, grant us peace, for all that we have is your gift. Grant us the peace of repose, the peace of the Sabbath, the peace which has no evening. For this worldly order in all its beauty will pass away. All these things that are very good will come to an end when the limit of their existence is reached. They have been allotted their morning and their evening.

37

In that eternal Sabbath you will rest in us, just as now you work in us. The rest that we shall enjoy will be yours, just as the work that we now do is your work done through us. But you, O Lord, are eternally at work and eternally at rest. It is not in time that you see or in time that you move or in time that you rest: yet you make what we see in time; you make time itself and the repose which comes when time ceases.

38

We see the things which you have made, because they exist. But they only exist because you see them. Outside ourselves we see that they exist, and in our inner selves we see that they are good. But when you saw that it was right that they should be made, in the same act you saw them made.

It was only after a lapse of time that we were impelled to do good, that is, after our hearts had received the inspiration of the Holy Spirit. Before then our impulse was to do wrong, because we had deserted you. But you, who are the one God, the good God, have never ceased to do good. By the gift of your grace some of the works that we do are good, but they are not everlasting. After them we hope that we shall find rest, when you admit us to the great holiness of your presence. But you are Goodness itself and need no good besides yourself. You are for ever at rest, because you are your own repose.

What man can teach another to understand this truth? What angel can teach it to an angel? What angel can teach it to a man? We must ask it of you, seek it in you; we must knock at your door. Only then shall we receive what we ask and find what we seek; only then will the door be opened to us.

导读

米歇尔·德·蒙田（1533—1592），文艺复兴时期法国作家、思想家、哲学家，出生于法国波尔多附近佩里戈尔的贵族家庭，早年学习拉丁文，成年后曾在波尔多法院任职十余年，当过国王的侍从，游历欧洲各地，还两次当选波尔多市市长。在法国陷入宗教战争的大背景下，蒙田辞去在法院的工作后回到乡下隐居。蒙田的隐居不是消极避世，而是闭门读书、写作，于1572年开始撰写《随笔录》（Essais）。此后20年蒙田对这部作品不断扩充、修改、再版，终其一生成就一部著作，留名后世。

蒙田以博学著称，三卷随笔用古法文写就，以对人类感情的冷峻观察和对西方文化的冷静研究，旁征博引许多古希腊、古罗马作家的论述，其中大量引用拉丁语等多种语言，主题繁杂，包括日常生活、传统习俗、人生哲理、宗教战争、教育问题等。他对自己的行为与思想进行描写和剖析，观察自我、观察内在。书中有多处前后不一致的观点，反应了蒙田不断变化的想法，他本人亦对此作了说明。

1580年，《随笔录》初版上市，大获成功；17世纪，蒙田的名声就已远播海外。但是《随笔录》的文章结构松散，洋洋洒洒，并不怎么符合17世纪上半叶的人们的口味，直到18世纪才重获欣赏，经历四百余年考验，最终证明了这是一部不朽的杰作。这部著作融汇了16世纪各种知识和百家思想，开创了随笔文学形式的先河，闪耀着人文思想的光。在《随笔录》的百篇作品中，《论友谊》撷取7篇，供读者品读。

“论友谊”阐释了什么是真正的友谊。蒙田在在波尔多法院任职期间与拉博埃希结为莫逆。但几年后挚友不幸离世，令蒙田大受打击。蒙田对完美、神圣的友谊进行了赞颂，认为自古以来的四种爱——自然之爱、社会之爱、好客之爱和性欲之爱，都达不到这样的友谊。至于为何如此爱自己的挚友，蒙田的回答是：“因为这是他，因为这是我。”

“依靠我们自己的能力来判断是非那简直是疯了”认为要深刻认识我们自己的无知与软弱，轻易相信与轻易不信一样都是愚蠢的行径。对于大自然的力量和教廷教规必须怀有敬意，虚荣心和好奇心都对思想有害。

“论谈话艺术”指出比起范例，从反例中能学到更多东西，“每天我都会从某人愚笨的行为举止中得到告诫和建议”；同理，谈话中的反对意见应正视，勇于接受别人的指正。谈话要有条理，如果做不到恰如其分地说话，就不要愚蠢的强辩。

“论闲散”简要描述了思想不能专注而带来的危害。思想并不是处在闲散状态就能令人带来轻松自在，恰恰相反，会令人颓唐，心境沉重，“当灵魂没有一个明确的目标，那么心灵便迷失方向”。

“论父亲对孩子的感情”提出父亲应以美德、能力、善行、谦和赢得孩子的尊敬，为培养孩子明智地使用财富，作出奉献，而不是一毛不拔，令孩子不得不有求于他。蒙田认为创作者对作品一样作出了奉献，其关系好比父子，甚至认为智慧的产物比肉体孕育的产物更为高尚。

“论适度”认为做任何事都要适度，好事做过分了就不再是好事了。然而为了达到适度的目的，人过分压抑精神和肉体合理的需求，“用来减损自己快乐的数量和质量时，人类的智慧真是一种愚昧的聪明”，正所谓过犹不及。

“直到死才能断定是不是幸福”给出了最终判定是否幸福的时限——一生。世事变幻无常，命运的力量顷刻间翻覆天地，在生命中的哪个时刻都无法下定论，除了死亡时刻。“当评价人的一生时，我始终看其生命是如何结束的”，是否死得其所决定了一个人身后名声好坏。

蒙田随笔在西方文学史上占有重要地位，影响了弗朗西斯·培根、莎士比亚、卢梭等诸多作家和思想家。尼采谈到蒙田时这样说道：“世人对生活的热情，由于这样一个人的写作而大大提高了。”蒙田的随笔思想内涵丰富，富有哲理，平实易懂，不加雕饰，至今仍为世人所喜爱，源源不断地为现代人输送精神给养。

秦瑞宇

论友谊

1.我注视着我属下的一位画家在作画，突然觉得有一种超越他的欲望。他挑选了墙中央最好的一块地方，想充分施展一下自己的才华；然后，他用怪异图案填满了画周围的空白，这些怪异图案都是些荒诞不经的绘画，它们的诱人之处只在于千姿百态、新颖独特。事实上，这些散文若不是变形和怪异图案一起对各色各样奇形怪状的肢体做修修补补，配以纯粹偶然连贯的次序和比例，那么又算什么呢？

一个长着鱼尾巴的美丽姑娘。[1]

2.我可以设法达到那个画家第二阶段的水平，不过尚未达到他第一阶段较高的水平：我的绘画本领长进甚微，要不我就敢于着手画一幅色彩浓厚的装饰画，然后按照艺术的规则打磨润色、装饰美化。于是，我决定从埃蒂安·德·拉博埃西那儿借一幅“画”，它将给我其余的作品带来荣誉：我意思是这幅画就是他那篇题名为“论甘愿受奴役”的论文，而不是别人在不甚了解的情况下又给起名“反独裁”题目的那篇论文。还在很年轻的时候，他就写了这么一篇评论文以抨击专制并向自由致敬。这篇论文在具有评价能力的读者中长期传阅——颇受赞誉，备受推崇，因为它确实是一篇上乘之作，正如它看上去那样出色。然而，这远不是他所撰写的最佳之作。当他到了更加成熟的年龄，我认识了他，如果那时，他就已构思出像我这样的计划，写下自己所思所想的话，我们现在肯定会看到许多文学精品，以让我们近距离领略古典作品的壮丽；因为特别就天赋而言，我知道没有人能与他比肩。然而，除了这一篇之外，他就没有什么传世之作了——甚至那也是出于偶然：我认为当他完成后就再也没有看过它——以及给我们的内战弄得臭名昭著的关于《一月敕令》的《思考文集》：或许这部集子在其他地方还有一定的市场。这些就是在他留给后人的文学作品中我所能重新看到的一切了，我是他的继承人，在他弥留之际，他非常钟情地将书籍和手稿——除了我出版过的他那部小册子之外——遗赠给我。

3.我对那篇论文尤为感激，因为它让我们初次结识彼此：在认识他之前我早就见过他，同时也第一次知道他的大名；因此，为了我们之间那可爱的友谊如上帝所乐见的那般长久，我们将之培养得那么完美无缺，可以肯定这种友谊在作品中几乎看不到，在当代人之间也根本无迹可寻。要建立这样的友谊需要许多偶然的条件，只有靠运气才能在三百年里实现一次。我们之间的伙伴关系胜过一切，这似乎是我们的本性使然——亚里士多德说过，好的立法者对友谊比对正义表现得更为关切。伙伴关系之间尽善尽美的极致在于友谊；因为以快乐或利益、以大众需要或个人需要铸就或培养起来的一切友谊，不太美好、也不太崇高——因而也就不太像“友谊”——因为除了友谊本身之外，它们还带有某种意图、目的和结果。它们也不符合自古以来的四种爱：自然之爱、社会之爱、好客之爱和性欲之爱。

4.子女对父亲，更多的是关于尊敬的问题；友谊是通过相互信赖培养起来的，而由于他们过分不平等，所以友谊就不存在；友谊还可能妨碍他们自然的义务：因为父亲所有私密的想法，由于担心招致不适当的亲近而无法与他们的子女分享，而且孩子们无法向父亲提出劝告乃至警告——这是构成友谊的重要义务之一。过去在一些民族中，孩子按风俗杀死父亲，而在另一些民族中，父亲按习惯杀死孩子，他们之所以这样做，都是为了避免一方给另一方构成障碍：自然而然，一方的生存取决于另一方的灭亡。

5.过去，有些哲学家对如此自然的亲情关系持藐视态度——那就亲眼目睹一下阿里斯底波吧：自从孩子们从他身上降生以来，他一直亏欠他们感情，正当受到这种感情压抑时，他开始倾诉说：就算我们怀上虱子和虫子，那也得把他们生下来。还有一位哲学家，普罗塔戈试图劝他与他的兄弟言归于好，可是遭到反驳：“我们虽同母所生，可他不再与我有什么瓜葛。”

6.兄弟这个称呼真的是一个美丽的称呼，并且充满爱意：这就是我和拉博埃西结成兄弟情谊的原因所在。但是，随着分享财产或分割财产而来的是，一个人变富裕导致另一个人变贫穷，它会大大损害和削弱兄弟之情。兄弟们必须同舟共济，沿着同一航向奋力前行：他们势必常常相互冲撞和争抢。此外，为什么在他们之间一定存在真正完美、密不可分的关系呢？父子可能截然不同：兄弟也可能如此。“他是我的儿子，他是我同胞，可他很野蛮、很邪恶、很愚蠢！”到了他们因为法律和天然关系要保持亲情关系时，那就更少有自己的选择了，也更少有“甘心情愿的自由”了。我们甘心情愿的自由本身才能够恰当地产生感情和充满爱意的友谊，而非其他。这并不是说我无法分析别的因素所带来的影响，只是由于我有过最好的父亲，直至辞世前他依然是最宽容的父亲，他出身名门望族，这个家族就和睦而论堪为世代相传的楷模：

众所周知我对兄弟如父亲般的关爱。[2]

7.你不能把友谊与男女的爱情相提并论，即使这种爱情出于我们自己的选择，你也不能将它们归入同一个范畴。我必须承认爱情的火焰——

因为我不是不认识那位将甜蜜的辛酸与情

人的呵护糅合在一起的女神。[3]

更旺盛、更炽烈、也更热切。可它是一缕匆匆忙忙、变幻无常的火焰，上下起伏、飘忽不定；它是一缕狂热的火焰，易于遭到扑灭，只能照亮我们生活的一角。而对朋友的爱则是一股人间普遍的热情，温和平静，又是一股永恒而稳定的热情，一切都那么轻柔坦荡，既不尖锐也不强烈。而且，性爱不过是一种我们对难以得到的东西的狂热渴望：

就像猎人追野兔，

度过严寒与酷暑，

越过崇山与峡谷，

猎物逃跑他追捕，

一旦抓住不珍护。[4]

8.爱情一进入友谊的领地（即各种念想同时起作用的地方），就变得衰弱无力。享受爱情就等于失去爱情：爱情的目标在于人的身体，因而受到满足的支配。相反，友谊的获得和我们的意愿是成正比的：因为友谊是关于思想的问题，随着我们的灵魂在实践友谊中被净化，友谊只有在我们享受它的时候才能喷涌而出，得到滋养并茁壮成长。在如此完美的友谊深处，那些变幻无常的爱情曾经在我的心中寻找到一席之地——更不必说在拉博埃西的心中了，他在他的诗篇中向大家坦白了太多太多。于是，友谊和爱情这两种情感进入我的内心，它们都意识到彼此的存在却从来不能相比，前者在高空自豪的翱翔中保持自己的航向，轻蔑地看着后者沿着下面的道路奔跑。

9.至于婚姻，作为一项交易除了准入是自由的之外（婚姻期限受到约束，绝非我们的意志所能支配），受其他意图束缚；在婚姻之内，人们不得不很快解开无数纠结缠蔓的死结，这些死结足以切断活生生的爱情之线，扰乱它的进程；而在友谊之中，除了友谊本身之外，既没有买卖也没有交易。再者，女人的确通常难以对支撑起神圣友谊的亲昵和相互信赖作出回报，她们的心灵似乎也没有坚定到足以承受得住这般长久紧绷的死结。实际上，如果不是因为如此，如果有可能使这样自愿又自由的关系得到实现，在这种关系中不仅心灵充满乐趣，肉体也在其中得到愉悦——整个人全身心地投入其中——可以肯定地说这可爱的友谊将会更加充实也更加丰富。但是，尚无先例显示女性能达到如此的境界，并且参照古代哲学流派达成的共识，女性从不在此列。

10.希腊人的同性恋应该为我们的习俗所不容；因为当他们进行同性恋时，要求爱人间要有悬殊的年龄和有差异的偏好，所以这既不是完美的结合，也不是我们现在追求的和谐。“这种友谊的爱情算什么呢？为何没有人会爱上一个丑陋的年轻人或是一个英俊的老头子呢？”[5]因为在我提及它时，我想即使柏拉图学院描绘的肖像亦不能不与我的相符：维纳斯儿子在情人心中激起对青春美少年的最初迷恋（此时他们允许一切无度的热情可能产生的过分打情骂俏）只是建立在身体美的基础上，这是身体产生的假象（因为它不能建立在精神的基础上，因为精神尚未呈现出来，甚至正在孕育中，因太幼稚而难以萌芽）；假如有人疯狂地迷恋上一个青春少年，那么追求爱情的手段就是财富、礼物、加官晋爵和其他，这是为学院派所指责的低劣手段。假如爱情之火在更高尚者心中点燃，那么爱情的手段同样也是更高尚的：给对方哲学方面的指导，教对方学习尊敬宗教，教对方遵守法律并为国家利益而献身，宣扬英勇无畏、智慧和正义方面的榜样，有了这些榜样，求爱者要努力使自己因为优雅和美丽的心灵而值得被接受（他身体的美早已消逝），并希望通过这种精神上的交流促成更稳定更持久的结合。当这种搭配产生结果时——在适当的时期（他们不要求求爱者费工夫考虑许诺，却严格要求被爱者这样做，因为他必须从观察中对那种内心的，难以辨别和发现的美进行判断）——然后在被爱者的心中便产生一种以心灵美为媒介而构想出来的精神上的欲望。在他看来，这种美是卓越的：外表的美是次要的也是偶然的——这与求爱者的看法恰恰相反。由于这种原因，学院派哲学家们对被爱者持更加尊重的态度，并且表明上帝也是这么做的；他们严厉训斥诗人埃斯库罗斯在阿喀琉斯和帕特洛克罗斯的爱情中，赋予阿喀琉斯以求爱者的角色，让这个尚无胡须的青涩少年成了全希腊最美的人。

11.一旦这种普遍的交流得以确立，就利用爱情更有价值的一面来履行义务，支配爱情。学院派哲学家们说：爱情会为个人生活和大众生活结出有用之果；爱情是国家的力量，在那些国家，爱情既是可以接受的风俗，也是对正义举动与自由的重要维护——哈莫迪和阿里斯托格同的爱情故事可以为证。这就是他们称爱情为神圣原因之所在。他们认为，只有暴君的暴行和人们的卑鄙行为才与爱情势不两立。然而，在说的都说了，做的都做了之后，我们可以向学院派哲学家们作出的唯一让步是，爱情原本就是以友谊为结果的恋爱——这一点完全符合斯多葛学派哲学家的爱情定义：“爱情就是要努力将友谊建立在美的外表上。”[6]

12.我现在回到更加稳定也更加公平的友谊话题上：“随着岁月的流逝，友谊中的人物变得坚强起来，如此的友谊才能被称之为友谊。”[7]

13.此外，我们通常所称的朋友和友谊，不过是由于某种机会或某种相配而结识的熟人和熟悉的关系，通过这种关系，我们的心灵相互支持。在我所谈论的友谊中，各种心灵在如此普遍的交流中融为一体，从而抹去了将它们结合在一起的接缝，连接得天衣无缝，无迹可觅。如果有人逼我说为什么我爱他，我觉得无法用言语来表达，只能回答说：“因为那是他，因为这是我。”引发这种结合的媒介超出我所有的推理，也超出了我能够专门谈论的一切——大概是某种难以解释的命运之力量吧。

14.在我们彼此看到对方前，我们都在寻找对方——这是因为我们两个人已经从别人那里听到种种议论（这些议论给我们的情感带来了超乎寻常的冲击），而且，我相信，还因为上帝的某种天命：我们借由名声知晓彼此。初次见面碰巧是在一个拥挤不堪的城市节日场合，我们发现两人如此互相吸引，如此相互了解，如此联系在一起，从此我们再不会跟别人像跟我们之间那么亲密无间了。他用拉丁文写过一部优秀的《讽刺文学》，该作品已出版，他通过这部作品为自己作了辩解，并且解释了我们之间的关系为何迅速发展到了完美境界。生命短暂，我们相识又晚（因为我们两个都长大成人——他比我大几岁）——没时间可以浪费在遵循松散而普通的友谊模式中，而这种模式需要经过长期的交往后进行深思熟虑。这种友谊除了自身之外别无法则可循；除了自身之外，也别无他物可比较。这样就不存在特别的顾虑——也不存在一而再再而三三而四的顾虑，更不存在没完没了的顾虑了——不过，倒是有一些难以理解的可贵之处：它们全都混淆在一起，这些东西捕获我的意志，促使我的意志钻进他的意志，然后在他的意志中消失；这些也捕获他的意志，促使他的意志钻进我的意志，而后在我的意志中消失，彼此都带着同样的渴望和仿效的心态。我说消失，是真心实意在说“消失”；我们都对自己毫无保留：不分彼此。

15.在罗马执政官（对底波里斯·格拉居斯定罪，迫害了他的那些亲信）面前，拉里乌斯最终问格拉居斯的最亲密朋友凯厄斯·布莱修斯：他到底为他都做了多少事。他回答道：“无所不为。”——“什么！无所不为？”拉里乌斯继续道，“如果他命令你放火燃掉我们的神殿，你会怎么办？”——布莱修斯反驳道：“他从来没叫我做这事呀。”拉里乌斯补充道：“但是，假使他已经命令你了。”他回答道：“那我就遵命。”[8]历史上人们断言，如果他真的是格拉居斯那么亲密无间的朋友，那么他就没有理由用最后那句鲁莽的话激怒执政官，而且绝不该放弃对格拉居斯希望他所做之事的信任。但是，指责他的回答像在煽风点火的那些人，并不完全明白友谊的奥妙，也无法接受凭他的影响以及学识，他可以对格拉居斯的想法了如指掌的前提。他们不是因为是同胞而成了朋友，不是为了做朋友而做朋友，不是因为都与国家敌对，都野心勃勃、勾心斗角而成了朋友。彼此完全将自己托付给对方之后，他们各自完全支配彼此的欲望，由品德来指引并由理智来引导（没有理智就不可能将他们维系在一起），布莱修斯的回答很恰当。如果他们的行为出现裂痕，那么依我看，他们既不是彼此的朋友，也不是他们自己的朋友。再者，如果有人这样质问我：“假设你的意志命令你去杀死你女儿的话，你会杀死她吗？”那么我的回答听起来肯定跟他们的并无二致，我说我会。那并不证明我同意这么做了，因为我对我的意志并不存疑，也不怀疑朋友的意志。世上的一切争论都无法左右我对我的朋友的意图和决定的信任。没有一次他当我的面作出行动的决定——不论看起来是什么行动决定——而我不能即刻发现其动机的。我们就是如此地心有灵犀，以如此强烈的感情相互关注，抱相同的感情各自向对方赤诚袒露心扉，这样不仅我能像了解自己的思想一样了解他的思想，而且对把自己托付给他比托付给自己更为信任。

16.别让任何人将普通的友谊与这种友谊相提并论。我了解这些友谊——甚至其中最完美的——也了解其他的，可我得奉劝你们不要混淆它们的规定：你会自欺欺人。在其他友谊中你必须小心翼翼明智前进，将主动权掌握在手中：这种关系并非如此牢靠，所以没有理由怀疑这一点。“爱一个朋友，”奇洛说过，“就想着有一天你必然要憎恨他；恨他，想着你必然要爱他。”[9]这条训诫在那种至高无上的友谊中是如此令人厌恶，可相比你们会用到的亚里士多德经常重复的：“啊！我的朋友，没有一个是朋友！”[10]这句格言，这条训诫在践行司空见惯的友谊中倒是健康有益的。

17.各种付出和帮忙可以培养其他的友谊，可这些在这段崇高的友谊关系中简直不值一提：这是由于我们的意志已经浑然一体。我感觉到的友谊之爱并没有增加——无论斯多葛学派哲学家会怎么说——我也不会为得到了帮助而感到庆幸，正如我不会对我为自己做了好事儿欣喜一样：所以这样的朋友关系真的太完美了，让他们失去了付出的意识，憎恶和剔除他们之间各种形式的隔阂，诸如帮忙、义务、感恩、请求、感激等东西。他们的意志、财产、妻子、孩子、荣誉和生命，这一切都是共有的；根据亚里士多德最恰当的定义，他们之间的联系在于两个分身共有一个灵魂，[11]所以他们既不需借让也不需给予对方任何东西。这就是为什么那些立法者禁止夫妻互赠礼物，以此把婚姻颂扬成想像中神圣的关系，期望能借此表明所有一切都必须属于他们俩，因此在两人之间没什么能够分开或割裂的。在我所谈论的这种友谊中，如果一方能给予另一方东西，其实是受惠的一方给他的朋友施以了恩惠。重要的是，他们各自都想给对方好处，结果是提供途径和机会的那一方其实更为慷慨大方，因为他给了朋友去帮他实现最大愿望的快乐。当哲学家戴奥真尼斯手头拮据时，他不说叫朋友给他一点钱，而说叫朋友还给他一点钱！[12]为了说明现实生活中这样的事如何发生，我只想引用古代的一个例子。

18.柯林斯人欧达米达斯有两个朋友：卡里色努斯和阿里休斯，前者是西西奥尼亚人，后者也是柯林斯人。当欧达米达斯在穷困潦倒中即将去世时，由于他的两个朋友很富有，所以他就立了如下遗嘱：“我遗赠给阿里休斯：由他照顾我母亲并给她养老送终；我遗赠卡里色努斯：由他照看我女儿直到她结婚，并尽可能给她提供一套最齐备的嫁妆。假如他们当中有一个碰巧去世，那么我指定在世者替他履行我的遗嘱。”最初看到遗嘱的那些人嘲笑这份遗嘱；可是，当那两个继承人得知此遗嘱时，他们欣然地接受了该遗嘱。其中的卡里色努斯5天之后真的去世了；继承遗嘱的希望因而就落在了阿里休斯身上，他精心照料朋友托付的母亲；然后从五英担银子的财产中，他拿出两英担半给自己的独生女办婚礼，又拿出另两英担半给欧达米达斯的女儿，并在同一天为她们举办婚礼。[13]

19.这算是最完美的例子，除了一个条件：里面不止一个朋友。我刚才所谈论的完美友谊是不可分割的：每个人都将自己如此彻底地交给自己的朋友，再无剩余的东西去跟另外一个人分享：相反，他感到伤心的是自己分身乏术，不能一分为二，一分为三，甚至一分为四；他没有几个灵魂，也没有几个意志，否则也就能将它们全都送给他所爱的那个人。

20.普通的友谊是可以共同分享的。你可以爱一个朋友的英俊潇洒；爱另一个朋友的和蔼可亲；爱第三个朋友的宽宏大量；爱第四个朋友的慈父般深情厚谊；爱第五个朋友的兄弟般手足之情，等等。但是，在这段友谊中，爱占据灵魂并用至高无上的统治主导它：这种事情是无法复制的。如果两个朋友同时叫你帮助他们，那么你马上赶去帮哪一个呢？如果他们的请求发生冲突，那么谁又会先得到你优先的帮助呢？如果一个人叫你避而不谈对另一个人有益的事情，那么你如何摆脱这种尴尬的局面呢？唯有最高尚的友谊能够摆脱所有其他的束缚。我已发誓不对任何人透露的秘密，我可以不惧对誓言的违背去告诉他而不是别人：他就是我。两个人能拥有最高尚的友谊已经是一大奇迹，有人说三个人有最高尚的友谊，这是不知道这种友谊高不可攀。东西有可以相比的就不是最好的。如果有人提议说我在两个朋友中能像爱一个那样爱另一个，还提议说他们能够彼此相爱，并且就像我爱他们那样爱我，那么他就变成一个多面人，甚至变成一个同盟，这样的同盟是最多“个体”的同盟，也是最团结一致的同盟。这样的例子哪怕是一个在这世上也难以找到。

21.这个故事的其他部分与我刚才所说的如出一辙：当欧达米达斯因自己的需要而利用朋友们时，他就是将恩泽和实惠赠予了他们。他将继承人们的慷慨留给了他们自己，这份慷慨借由他们帮助他而送到他们自己的手里。毋庸置疑，相比起阿里休斯，友爱的力量在他的行为中表现得更为淋漓尽致。概而言之，这些行为超越了任何未曾尝试过的人的想象力。尤其令我肃然起敬的是一位年轻士兵的回答，赛勒斯问那个士兵愿出多少钱卖掉那匹为他在比赛中获奖的马：“为了一个王国，你愿意把马卖掉吗？”——“不卖，真的，陛下；可如果我能找到一个值得结交的人，那么为了得到一位朋友，我还是愿意将马送出。”[14]好一个“如果我能找到”的假设；因为你能轻而易举地找到泛泛之交。可对于我们这种友谊，这种可以让我们在其中毫无保留地交流最深最隐秘思想的友谊，毫无疑问我们的一切动机都必须是纯洁到极点的。

22.在那些只依靠目标来维系的关系中，我们只需提防出现特别影响目标实现的那些瑕疵。我的医生或律师信什么教与我无关：这种顾虑与他们对我的友好的服务毫不相干。在这种交易中，我与仆人们交流以相同方式来对待：我几乎不去调查我的男仆近不近女色，我想知道他是否勤奋工作；我对赶骡夫的关注不在于赌不赌钱，而在于赶不赶得好骡子，我对厨子的关注也不在于爱不爱骂人，而在于称不称职。告诉世人该怎么做（相当多的人那样做）并非我所关切的事，而我在这世上该怎么做就跟我不无关系了：

这就是我要做的事：做你该做的事。[15]

为了坐在桌旁能谈得融洽，我挑易相处的人而不挑聪明的人；上床睡觉，我先挑美女，后挑贞女；在社交谈话中，我挑有本领的人——即使是不诚实的人。诸如此类。

23.就像那位骑在木马上与自己的小孩玩耍的哲学家[16]被人看到此景，对那很吃惊的人所说的一样，在他自己有孩子之前不要作出评论，等他有相同的感受，会对此番举止作出恰当的评判：所以我多么希望我对着说话的那些人能明白我在说什么；不过，意识到这份友谊离一般的现实有多远——同时也意识到这份友谊有多稀罕——我不指望可以找到对此公正的评价，因为古人留给我们的这个主题的作品，与我所说的感情相比似乎微不足道。在这个例子中，这些结果胜过哲学上的那些至理名言。

当我的理智处于正常时，我不会用任何东西与一位令人快乐的朋友相比拟。[17]

24.在古代，米南德断言，哪怕一个人仅仅遇到过朋友的影子，他也是幸福的。[18]他这么说肯定是对的，尤其是如果他实际上品尝过友谊的滋味。事实上，如果我比较一下我的余生——尽管靠上帝的恩惠我甜蜜舒适地生活，平静的心灵免受哀伤的打扰（除了这位朋友的死亡），自满自足于与生倶来的自然恩赐也再别无他求——要是把这种生活与我被赠予的跟那样一个男人成为朋友和伙伴的四年时光相比，这种生活不过是过眼烟云，也不过是一个漆黑沉闷的夜晚。

25.从我失去他的那一天起：

那是永远残酷却也永远值得纪念的一天。

（既然上帝这么明示），[19]

我只不过疲倦地苟且偷生。我得到的那些快乐并没给我带来慰藉：反而因为他的故去令我倍感伤心。每样东西我们都是各分一半：我感觉我正从他那儿窃取他的那一份：

曾与我分享一切的他离我而去时，

我想，我在享受快乐也是不对的。[20]

我已经如此习惯于在一切事物中成为二分之一

个，以至于我现在感觉我只不过是半个人。

既然不合时宜的打击

夺走了我灵魂的一部分，

我为何依旧徘徊在乐趣渐少，

残缺不全的生存中？

那一天就是我俩一起倒下的时间。[21]

26.无论做什么，想什么，我都怀念他——就像他肯定也会怀念我一样；因为正如他在能力和品德上远远超过我，他为友谊所做的努力也已胜过了我：

为如此亲爱的人忧伤

会有什么羞耻或限度？……

我是多么不幸的人啊！

失去这样一位好兄弟。

一切的欢乐随你消逝，

活着时你的爱呵护它；

你啊，我亲密的兄弟，

你的死毁灭我的快乐；

我的灵魂和你埋葬在一起。

因为失去了你，我已追溯

心中曾有过的思想和灵魂所体验过的快乐；

是否我再也不能和你说话，

再不也能听你说你做了些什么？

是否我再也看不到你，

兄弟，比生命更贵重的你？

但是无论如何，我一定永远爱你。[22]

27.让我们听听这个16岁的男孩说什么吧！

28.我已经发现，这部作品的出版已造成了不良的后果，因为出版它的人试图扰乱和改变国家政治局面，不在乎是否对其有利；而且他们已将这部作品列为他们自己的重要核心著作之一，因此我将收回将其放在这里的决定。为了在那些无法知道作者的观点或行为的人中，他的名誉就不受到损害，我告诉他们，他纯粹把这部作品当作年轻时撰写的习作；这只不过是一个稀松平常的主题，在成百上千本书中都提及过。我并不怀疑他相信自己所写的东西，因为他太讲良心了，即使是在一部轻松的作品中，他也不会说假话。此外我还知道，如果他有选择机会的话，他宁愿生在威尼斯，而不愿生在萨拉特。这种想法是对的。可是，他还有一条铭刻在心中的最高准则：服从并且最审慎地遵从与生倶来的法则。从来就没有一个公民比他更好，更希望自己国家安宁，更反对所处时代出现骚乱和异端。他只会用自己的力量将动乱扼杀，而不是提供资源去把他们鼓动起来。他的思想气质是按照前几个世纪的模子浇铸出来的，与我们的截然不同。

29.所以，我将用另一部作品取代那篇严肃的论文，那部作品与《甘愿受奴役》写于同一个时期，不过写得更加华丽，也更加幽默。

依靠我们自己的能力来判断是非那简直是疯了

1.我们把轻易相信任何事归因于头脑简单，把轻易被人说服归因于无知，这或许不无道理，因为我想曾经有人教过我，信任就像戳在我们灵魂上的印记：灵魂越柔软越少抵抗，就越容易将任何事印上：“正如放在天平的砝码必然要把天平压低一样，思想必然要屈服于确凿的证据。”[23]灵魂越空虚越少给它提供平衡物，那么在最初深信的压力下，其天平就越容易变得摇摆不定。这就是为什么小孩子、普通人、女人和病人更容易被牵着鼻子走。

2.另一方面，不断轻视某事并且指责它像是假的，就因为在我们看来它似乎并不像是真的，在这种情况下，就存在着一种愚蠢的自大。这在那些自认为能力在普通人之上的人当中算是小毛病了。

3.我从前常做这样的事。如果我听人讲鬼走路、预言、妖术、魔术以及我没法相信的某种传说——

梦、不可思议的恐怖、奇迹、巫婆、

塞萨利死者或符咒的夜间拜访[24]

——我常常为受如此愚蠢行为欺骗的人感到悲哀。现在我发现，我过去至少也一样令人同情。这并不是说经历随后向我展现了任何超越我原本相信的事（在我看来也不是因为缺乏什么好奇心），但是，理智已经教会我们，无论你这样指责什么东西是绝对错的和绝不可能的，那么你就是宣称了解新领域、上帝的意志和作为我们母亲的大自然的力量；理智还教会我们，世上没有什么比依赖我们自己的能力和潜力去给事情下结论的举动更愚蠢的事了。

4.如果我们不把这些法则运用到超越我们理解的事情中，那么在生活中，不知有多少怪异或令人惊讶的事！如果考虑到我们不得不穿过一团迷雾，只是为了弄明白我们已掌握的东西，我们肯定会发现，不是知识而是习惯令事物不再怪异；

因为生活已使人满足并令人感到厌倦，

现在已没有人再注视天堂闪光的神殿；

如果这样的东西新近呈现在我们面前，那么它们似乎跟其他东西一样令人难以置信；

假使现在第一次将它们

突然间呈现给凡人的话：

没什么称得上更为非凡；

国人不敢相信这些东西。[25]

从未真正见过河的人第一次遇到一条河，会误认为是海洋，因为我们认为，我们所知的最大东西是自然中同类物中最大的。

河流并不都是那么大，

可对没见过更大河流的人而言它是巨大的；

最大的树最大的人也由此而来；

各类我们所知的最大是我们自认为的最大。

“当我们习惯于看某事时，我们就会习以为常、见怪不怪；我们从不会查找与此相同的事的种种原因。”[26]使我们查找任何事物原因的不在于其规模，而在于其新奇。

5.我们应更深入了解自己的无知和弱点，以更尊敬的态度评价大自然的无穷力量。有多少不可能的事被值得我们信赖的人证实：如果我们无法确信，那么我们至少应该保持怀疑。判定它们不可能无异于轻率地自以为是，自吹自擂我们知道极限在哪里。如果我们明白不可能与不寻常之间的差异，或者违背大自然进化的规则与违背人类共识之间的差异，那么就会遵守奇洛在《没有什么东西可超越》中所确定的规则，不要轻率地相信，不要轻率地不相信。

6.我们在佛罗莎特著作中看到，贝恩的富瓦伯爵次日清晨得知朱比洛思的加斯提约翰国王战败，他获取信息的手段让人嘲笑。据历史记载，霍诺留斯教皇在菲力普·奥古斯都国王在蒙特驾崩的当天，就为他举行公众安灵弥撒，并且命令意大利举国上下举行同样的安灵弥撒，因为见证人的权威并未高到足以令我们信服，所以当听到这件事时，我们也会发出嘲笑。

7.可是且慢。当普鲁塔克（且不管许多他声称引自古代的例子）说他本人相当肯定地知道，在图密善时代，安东尼历经七天行程在德国吃败仗的消息，并在罗马公然宣布该消息，战报当天就不胫而走；当恺撒坚持认为事件的消息实际上预见了事件本身时，这是很经常发生的事：如果我们假设他们是单纯的人，那么他们只不过是跟着聚众闹事，自己上当受骗，因为他们看事情不比我们清晰！[27]

8.当普利尼期望运用评价的手段时，有什么能比他的评价来得更仔细、更明确、更真切更不掺杂质的呢？（我并不在此讨论他卓尔不群的博学；我不大看重这方面：可就这两种品质而言，我们哪里能胜过他？）然而，任何一个小学生都能证实他在撒谎，并给他上一节自然课。

9.在布谢的作品中读到与圣西拉里的遗迹有关的奇迹时，我们会耸耸肩表示对此不屑一顾：他的权威并非大到足以剥夺我们向他挑战的自由。不过，对我来说，从此谴责所有类似的故事看起来十分鲁莽。像奥古斯丁这样一个大圣人发誓他见到了：[28]在米兰，一个盲童靠圣日尔韦和圣普罗塔修斯的遗物恢复了视力；在迦太基，一位新受洗的妇女在另一位妇女胸前画个十字，治好了她的癌症；他的好朋友赫斯珀洛斯从君主坟墓取来一小把土，驱走了骚扰他家的恶魔，并且用从教堂取来的土同样治好一个瘫痪病人；一个妇女在列队行进时接触过圣斯狄芬装有花束的遗物箱，之后她用箱里的花卉擦眼睛，结果恢复了不久前失去的视力——还有其他几个就发生在他眼前的奇迹。要是他和他称为目击者的两个神圣主教奥勒留和马克西姆斯在一起，那么我们还能责备他什么呢？责备他无知、头脑简单、轻信、故意欺骗、冒名顶替吗？在我们这个时代，还有什么人会如此鲁莽到认为自己可在美德、虔诚、学识、评价以及能力方面与他们相提并论呢？嗨！即使他们拿不出理由，他们也可以以其真正的威信令我信服呀。[29]

10.除了必然相随的荒谬鲁莽之外，在我们蔑视我们所不能理解的种种事物时所产生的严重后果里还存在着一种危险。因为只要你自以为是地设置了真理和谬误的界定，紧接着发现有必要相信一些比你所拒绝相信的更为古怪的东西，你就得被迫放弃这些界定。

11.现在依我看，在我们的良心上，在现今的宗教冲突中，带来数不胜数的混乱的，正是天主教徒可以随时将他们的一些教规牺牲掉的那种做法。当他们在一些有争议的教规上屈从于敌人时，他们相信他们这样做是恰当而且明智的。可是，他们看不到放弃和投降给敌方带来了什么好处，或者多大程度上能激励他继续进攻，除此之外，他们所选的那些似乎无足轻重的教规有时候却是极为重要的。

12.我们要么完全屈服于教会的权威，要么完全把自己从中解脱出来。而不是我们自己来决定对信仰的皈依要到什么程度。

13.此外，我可能讲过这一点，因为我曾经分析过它；在过去，我使用过这种自由进行选择和挑选，以期忽略我们教规中的某些细节，因为它们似乎相当奇怪或空洞；然后，当我将这件事告诉一些读书人时，我发现，那些教规是建立在厚实而且绝对坚实的基础上，正是我们的无知和动物式的愚蠢，才使我们不敬畏它们。

14.为何我们无法记住在自己的判断中感觉到的所有矛盾呢？有多少东西昨天对我们来说是信条，而今天在我们看来却成了无稽之谈呢？

15.虚荣心和好奇心是我们灵魂的孪生灾难。好奇心使我们什么都想探听；而虚荣心又使我们对尚未解决或尚未确定的事妄下结论。

论谈话艺术

1.把惩罚一些人作为对其他人的警告，这是我们维护正义的一贯做法。因为就像柏拉图所说的那样，为已做错的事而惩罚人总是愚蠢之举：做过的事不可能更改。其意图是不让他们重蹈覆辙或者使其他人避免犯他们犯过的错误。[30]我们不想改变我们将要绞死的人；而想通过他改变其他人。我也是这样做的。我身上的毛病习惯成自然，而且无药可医，可因为好绅士就得成为公众仿效的楷模，所以我可能起到的是切勿仿效的模范带头作用：

你可知道阿不思儿子过得多悲惨

巴鲁斯又多可怜，这难道你不知？

这是一次珍惜遗产的极好教训呀。[31]

2.惩罚和指责我自己的不足之处可能教某人担心自己犯错误。（我自己最难能可贵的才能，与其说是来自于自我夸耀，倒不如说是源于自我批评）这就是我常常回顾这一点并且乐此不疲的原因之所在。然而，在漫无边际的交谈中，你在谈论自己时并非没有失误：指责自己将使你始终为人所相信；赞扬自己则令你永远不为人所相信。

3.可能有一些跟我性格一样的人，他们通过避免反面例子而不是学习正面榜样而变得更好。这是大加图说到下一句话时正思考的教训，他曾说智者从愚人那学到的东西比愚人从智者那学到的东西来得多；[32]也正如帕乌撒尼亚斯所说，古代七弦琴表演家常要学生去听一些生活在马路边的表演者演奏，以便学会厌恶不和谐的乐音和错误的节奏。[33]比起曾经吸引过我的仁慈的事例，我对残忍行为的憎恶更深切地激励我做人要仁慈。要让我在马鞍上笔直地坐着，优秀的侍从武官可能力不胜任；可是看到一个律师或一个威尼斯人在户外骑马时，我就会坐得笔直。错误的说法比正确的说法能更好地纠正自己。每天我都会从某人愚笨的行为举止中得到告诫和建议。打击你的东西比取悦你的东西更多地影响到你，并且让你清醒。我们只能通过诸如倒退和冲突而不是和谐，通过变成不一样的而不是成为相同的来提升自己。在从正面实例中几乎学不到什么后，我使用日常生活中的反面实例，我看到别人令人生厌，就力求自己易于相处；看到别人软弱，让自己坚强；看到别人强硬，让自己温和。我还给自己设定了不做到就不罢休的目标。

4.在我看来，谈话是我们的思想最富成效也最为自然的运用。我发现练习谈话是生活中最妙趣横生的活动。这就是为什么，如果我现在被迫作出选择，我想我宁可失明也不可丧失说话能力或者听力。在他们的学院里，雅典人，甚至更多的罗马人，以极大的热情坚持这项练习。在我们现在这个时代，意大利人保留着这项练习的某些活动——这对他们颇有益处，这一点从他们与我们的智慧的比较中就能看出。研究书本是一项缺乏活力的迟缓的活动，而谈话则既提供学问又提供练习。如果我正与一个功底扎实的强手辩论，那么他一定会从侧面抨击我，左右开攻展开话锋；他的思想将大大提升我的思想。对抗、竞争和荣耀将推动我更上一层楼。在谈话中，最令人痛苦的地方就在于意见完美的和谐一致。

5.正如我们的思想通过与充满朝气、条理清晰的思想接触得以加强那样，无论如何夸大与卑贱而糟糕的思想不断交流和接触会给我们的思想造成的损失和危害都不为过。没有传染病像它那样具有传染性。经历让我懂得其价值究竟几何。我喜欢争论和讨论，不过只与几个人争论和讨论，并且是为了个人的目的：因为我认为，把争论和讨论当作一场大型的公开展示，炫耀你的智慧和措词，这对令人敬仰的人而言是一种有失身份的交易。

6.愚昧是一种不良的品性：而不能容忍愚昧还被闹得气急败坏（就像发生在我身上一样），这就成了另一种几乎更为粗鄙的愚昧了。而这就是现在我想自责的地方。

7.我轻松自在地开展讨论和争论。既然意见并未在我内心找到准备生根发芽的土壤，那就没有什么令我感到可怕的建议，也没有什么使我受伤的信条，无论这些意见与我的想法有多大差异。人类大脑适时产生的如此轻佻的奇思怪想无不发生在我身上。那些剥夺了我们对话语权判断的人，对奇怪的观点看上去很温和；我们也许不能把我们的赞许借给他们，可是我们确实可以把我们的耳朵借给他们。当天平上的一边小盘空空如也时，我将让另一边小盘由一个老太婆的梦来摇摆：如果我宁愿挑奇数而不挑偶数，或者挑星期四而不挑星期五；如果我宁愿桌位是十二号或十四号，而不愿是十三号；如果我宁愿在旅游中看到野兔绕开我走的路，而不愿看到它们横穿过去，并且让我的左脚先穿靴子，然后才是右脚，我认为这些都是可以原谅的。所有这些古怪的行为（在我们当中确有其例）至少值得一听。对我来说，它们只比一边空盘重，可它们确实也只比一边空盘重。同样，流行的无根无据的意见自然存在一定的分量，它总比没有意见要来得有分量。一个不愿意做更多思考的人或许会为了避开迷信的沼泽而跌入顽固的泥潭。

8.那么，相互矛盾的评价既不冒犯我，也不激怒我：它们只不过让我清醒，并给我提供锻炼的机会。我们通常回避别人的指正，可我们应该自告奋勇地接受别人的指正，尤其是当这种指正来自谈话而非来自演讲的时候。每当我们遇上对立面，我们期待的不是想了解这种对立，而是不论对错怎样才能摆脱这种对立面。对于对立面，我们不是伸出欢迎的双臂，而是指指点点。我能容忍朋友粗暴地对待我：“你是白痴！你在胡言乱语！”在绅士当中，我喜欢人们真诚表达自己的意见，言为心声。我们切不该觉得忠言逆耳。我喜欢一种强韧的、亲密的、大丈夫之间的伙伴关系，这种友谊因为尖锐的充满活力的交流而感到喜悦，就好比因为爱而导致流血的啃咬和抓挠而感到欢欣一样。如果谈话一味讲究礼貌和艺术，不具有争论性，那么这种谈话既不够激烈，也不够宽宏大量；“不可能存在没有辩驳的争论”。[34]

9.当我处于矛盾之中时，矛盾引发我的注意力而不激起我的愤怒。我会接近跟我闹矛盾的人：他马上就会指正我。因为真理的目标对我们二者来讲都是共同的。——他的回答会是什么呢？愤怒的感情已经影响了他的判断。紊乱的思绪已经赶在理智之前夺取了他的判断。——如果我们不得不在解决争论的问题上打赌，那么谈话肯定是个好主意；如果我们的失败有一种物质作标记让我们能在上面留个记录，我的仆人就能说：“去年您的无知和顽固20次就让您支付了100克朗。”

10.我迎接真理，抚弄真理，不论真理在谁的手上，我都会找到它；我雀跃地向真理投降，只要我一看到真理从遥远处向我靠近时，我就伸出被征服的双臂迎接它。假如人们不是用专横跋扈的态度并迂腐地皱起眉头去抨击它，我将用我的肩膀顶住车轮去帮助人们一起对我的作品开展批评：对我的作品，我经常更多出于礼貌的缘故作修改，而不是为了达到合理修改的目的，我宁愿通过我随时的让步来鼓励人们自由地批评我——是的，即使是在让我付出某种代价的时候。然而，在我们这个时代，要诱导人这样做可是一件难事。他们没有肚量去纠正别人，正是由于他们没有肚量容忍别人的纠正，彼此面对面谈话时总是遮遮掩掩。

11.我是如此乐于由别人来评价自己并认识自己，所以不论采取两种形式中的哪一种，对我而言都是道德中立的。我的想法经常如此自相矛盾并且自我指摘，因此如果有人驳斥我的思想，我只会乐于给予他们驳斥我的权力，对我来说那些驳斥就跟自我驳斥没什么两样。但是，我会与任何太专横的人争吵，如同我认识的一个人，如果你不接受他的意见，他就不高兴；如果你羞于遵从他的意见，他就会将之当作一种侮辱。

12.苏格拉底始终对他的论点所引发的争议笑脸相迎。可以说，因为他的论点比较坚实，所以占优的一方总是他，他把他们作为新的胜利来欢迎：可恰恰相反，我们发现，没有什么会比下列事实让我们更容易受影响：确信自己的卓然不凡，确信我们对对手的轻蔑，确信弱者理所当然应该心甘情愿地接受修正他们错误的驳斥。

13.我常常诚挚地向那些粗暴待我的人而不是怕我的人求教。不得不应付钦佩我们和服从我们的人是一种无聊且有害的乐趣。安提斯泰尼命令他的儿子们决不要向任何赞扬他们的人表达谢意或表示感激。[35]在白热化的争论中，当我在对手强大的理性能力面前作出让步时，我为超越自己而感到非常骄傲，这种骄傲胜过我通过他的弱点取胜而得到过的满足。简而言之，我接受和认可任何攻击，不管它们多么微弱，只要它们来得坦荡直接，可我向来对以不当方式进行的攻击很不耐烦。我很少担心我们正讨论的内容；所有的意见对我来说都是相同的，而哪个提议获胜对我而言无关紧要。如果辩论以得当方式进行的话，我可以整天平静地进行争辩。我并不希望那么强有力和微妙的辩论成为我们的秩序——那种每天在牧羊人和营业员当中辩论都能找到的秩序从未在我们当中出现。如果他们误入歧途，则是由于这种辩论缺乏谦恭。我们同样也会误入歧途。不过，他们强烈的偏狭并没有使他们迷失方向，离题万里：他们的争论继续进行，彼此插嘴，互相攻击，但是切中要点。依我看，答中要点就算回答得很好。可当讨论变得一片混乱并且缺乏秩序时，我就会放弃论题，暴躁而浅薄地坚持形式，顽固、扭曲、专横地辩论——为此我事后不能不感到害臊。

14.带着善意去与傻瓜辩论是不可能的。这样，不只是我的判断会毁在这样一位粗暴的主人手里，一同受损的还有我明辨是非的能力。我们的争论应该被禁止，并且像其他文字罪一样受到处罚。因为争论总是受到愤怒的支配和控制，还有什么恶行不是他们在相互之间唤醒并层层堆积起来的吗？首先，我们感觉到针对争论的敌意；然后，我们感觉到针对人的敌意。在辩论之中，我们如果只被教会如何驳斥论点，我们一方反驳另一方的辩论，结果就是消灭真理，废除真理。这就是为什么柏拉图在他的《论共和国》中禁止不适宜参与辩论的愚钝之人进行这项练习。[36]

15.你在探索什么？你究竟为什么准备与既无步调又无风格的人走这条路呢？如果我们撇开论题以便检验处理论题的方式，我们并没有做错——我不是指一种学院派装模作样的方式，而是一种以健全智力为基础的自然方式。可最后发生了什么呢？一个向东一个向西；他们在一大堆细枝末节的混乱中遗失了基本要点。混乱时刻过去之后，他们再也不明白自己在寻找什么。一个人差一点说到要害，另一个高谈阔论得太离谱，而再一个人则低调得太离谱。一个人紧扣一个词或一个对比不放；而另一个人则再也听不到对手的论点，却过多受到自己思路的限制：他想跟进的是自己的论点，而不是你的论点。另一个人意识到自己腰杆子太软了，害怕一切，否认一切，并且从一开始就混淆论点，或者就在辩论达到高潮时，他一反常态变得完全沉默、装模作样，这些都出于一种郁闷的无知、一种傲慢的蔑视，或是一种想要避免冲突的荒谬的谦虚。还有一个人并不在乎他要卸下多少防卫，只要他能击中你论说的要害。还有人字字必较，并且相信每个字都像理智那样有分量。这种人只不过是在发挥自己嗓音和肺部的超凡力量。然后，有人违心地总结经验；而有人则以毫无用处的介绍和离题的方式让你不愿听下去。还有人用纯粹的辱骂武装自己，选择一种毫无根据的“德国式争论”，以便让自己从带给他重压的与有识之士的交往和谈话中解脱出来。

16.最后还有一个人，除在辩证结论与逻辑公式的樊篱中使你受围攻外，他没有理智。当人们反思我们所利用的专业技能的用处时，谁不开始怀疑这些专业技能，并且怀疑我们是否能从中得到什么生活中实实在在看得见的好处呢？“这样的博学无药可救。”[37]曾有人以逻辑获得智慧吗？逻辑的美丽诺言实现在哪儿？逻辑既不教人如何更好地过日子，也不教人怎样恰如其分地辩论。嘴臭女人的咯咯声比逻辑教授的公开辩论更聒噪。我宁愿我的儿子在小酒馆而不是大学这个聒噪的地方里学习说话。

17.带一个艺术教师来，并与他交谈吧。为何他没能使我们感觉到他“艺术”的高超呢？为何他也没能使妇女以及我们这些愚人为其坚实可靠的论点及其编排有序的修辞而心醉神迷呢？为何他无法以其意志征服并影响我们呢？为何一个出色掌握着知识和风格的人会将其尖锐的不加选择的论点与种种侮辱，以及愤怒混为一谈呢？让他脱掉他的学术头巾、他的长袍，也别讲拉丁语了！让他停止生硬地滥用亚里士多德的理论撞击我们的耳朵吧！嗨！更糟的是，你总把他误认为我们当中的一员。语言上造成混淆不清的绕弯子使我想起变戏法的种种伎俩：他们那巧妙的花招冲击了我们的感官，可决不能动摇我们的信仰。除了表演这样的杂耍之外，除了得到某种低劣平庸的东西之外，他们一无所获。他们也许更为人所知，可他们的荒谬可笑却丝毫没有减弱。

18.我像博学的人那样喜欢和尊敬学问。当学识利用得恰如其分时，它就会变成人类最高尚、最丰硕的收获。但是，有一类人（并且他们多得不计其数）使博学成了他们体现价值与成就的资本，他们为了记忆而放弃理解，“躲藏在别人的影子后面”，[38]离开了书本他们就一事无成。与其说我对愚昧厌恶，倒不如说我对这类人的博学（我敢说博学吗？）更厌恶。

19.在我的国家，在我有生之年，学校的知识已给人带来滚滚的财源，却难得改变人们的灵魂。如果知识遇上的灵魂都已变得愚钝，那么它就像一大块未加工、未消化的硬块，并使灵魂窒息；如果灵魂未受到束缚的话，知识趋于净化灵魂，剔除并荡涤灵魂的杂质。博学是一样东西，其特性几乎不好也不坏：它对极有天赋的人来说是一件非常有用的附属品；而对其余的人而言却极其有害；更准确地说，博学这样东西，在使用时有很大的价值，可它容不得自身被廉价获取：一方面博学是一根高贵的权杖；另一方面博学又是愚人的装饰品。

20.继续我们的话题：除开让敌人知道根本不能与你匹敌之外，你还想要取得什么更大的胜利吗？用你的论点去引他进步吧，真理才是胜利者；以你的秩序和风格去这样做，你就会成为胜利者！

21.我相信，在柏拉图和色诺芬的眼里，苏格拉底与其说为了辩论而辩论，倒不如说是为了辩论家而辩论；与其说是为了教育欧西德莫斯和普罗泰戈拉他们辩术的不当，倒不如说是为了教育他们自身的不当。苏格拉底把握住手中的第一个主题，就树立一个实用的目标，不是把内容讲明白；即启迪他打算训练和培养的才智之士的思想。我们所捕捉的猎物只不过是狩猎的乐趣：如果我们的追捕拙劣又愚笨，我们就是不可原谅的：但如果我们只是没能杀死猎物，这又是另一回事了。因为我们生来就是要去追求真理：占有真理就是拥有更大的力量。真理并非（如德谟克利特所说）隐藏在万丈深渊：更准确地说，真理是在认识上帝的过程中不断升华。

22.这个世界只不过是一所调查研究的学校。问题并不是谁来敲钟，而是谁向校钟发起最精彩的冲锋。说什么是真理的人如同说什么不是真理的人一样都表现得很愚蠢：我们所在意的是你怎么说，而不是你说什么。我对形式和内容并重，给什么样的案子找什么样的律师，就像亚尔西巴德跟我们说过的那样。每天我都花时间阅读作家的作品，我不是关心他们的学问，也不是寻找他们的论题，而是看看他们如何处理论题，就像我力求与著名才智之士进行讨论一样，不是为了从论题中学到什么，而是为了达到明白论题的意图。

23.任何人都会说真心话：可极少人会把话说得有条理，说得很明智，说得很恰当。因此出于无知的错误并不会得罪我：谬论才会得罪我。由于与我打交道者的无理要求，我时常中断讨论买卖的事，即便是有利于我的买卖。那些对我毕恭毕敬的人，就算他们有过失，我一年到头对他们也发不了一次的脾气，可当他们的观点成了愚昧的论述，或成了固执己见的荒谬借口和粗鄙自辩时，我们每天都会唇枪舌剑。尽管他们既不明白为什么也不理解他们所听到的，可是他们还是照答不误。这足以使你感到绝望。只有当我的脑袋猛撞在另一个人的脑袋上时，我才觉得头上撞出一块大肿块：比起我仆人们的轻率、无礼和直率的愚蠢，我会更容易原谅他们的疏忽大意。哪怕他们能做某事，还是让他们少做点！你满怀希望他们能热情高涨地投入工作：可在一个笨蛋身上一无所获，也没什么好指望的。

24.说是这样说，可如果我换一种态度对待这事，那又怎样呢？这或许很好：首先，这说明为什么我责备自己无法容忍这件事，认为它在对与错的人身上同样是缺点，因为在无法容忍有别自己的个性中，总有粗暴的坏脾气。其次，被世上的愚蠢所挑拨和激怒，是最愚蠢和最忍无可忍的事——并且不存在什么更稀奇古怪的事。因为这大概使你从原则上令自己懊恼，所以如果先哲专注于自己的话，他从来就不乏给自己流泪的机会。[39]七圣之一的迈森原来幽默得就跟提蒙和德谟克利特一样：当有人问到他自己一个人正在笑什么时，他回答说：“我在嘲笑自己一个人在笑这件事。”

25.每天我都要作不知多少的说明和答复，这些以我的标准来判断是愚蠢的——要是以他人的标准，一定是更经常这样做！如果我闭口不谈这些，那么别人又该怎么做呢？！总而言之，我们不得不在生活中过日子，那就让河水在桥下流淌而别为之担心吧！或者至少我们不要为此感到难受！的确，为何我们遇到驼背的残疾人能不发怒，却因不能容忍神经错乱的人而勃然大怒呢？[40]这样的冷酷是有害的，因为它出于吹毛求疵的心态，而不出于那人过错。让我们始终牢牢记住柏拉图的格言：“如果我觉得什么事出了毛病，那会不会因为我自己出了毛病呢？难道错的不会是我吗？我自己的批评难道不会反而指责的是自己？”智者和受鼓励者都会制止处罚人类最普遍常见的错误。处罚不仅是我们彼此的指责，它常常会变成针对我们自己的指责，而且在存有争议的事件中也成为我们的理由和论点：我们用自己的剑刺穿自己。正如第一个说这句话的人独到明智地写下的那样：“每个人觉得自己的大便闻起来气味都很香。”[41]

26.我们的眼睛看不到我们背后的任何东西。当我们一天百次嘲弄我们的邻居时，我们实际上在嘲弄自己；我们时常憎恨别人身上的毛病，可那些毛病在自己身上最为明显，而且由于令人难以置信地缺乏羞耻感和敏锐力，我们被身上这些毛病吓了一大跳。在昨天我就亲眼目睹了一个聪明的贵族在开玩笑，实际上那些笑话很中肯，是关于另一个贵族以愚蠢的方式向每个人大肆宣扬他的家庭结构和家族联盟，那些家族联盟一半以上是假的，当自己的出身越令人存疑的时候，这种人越倾向于编造这类蠢话：他也是，可如果他退后一步看看自己，那么他也许已经发现，他在乱传消息时没少放肆的言行，在着重炫耀妻子家族地位时没少令人讨厌。看到妻子被自己这样的丈夫捧得傲慢起来，如此傲慢多么危险啊！如果他们懂得拉丁文的话，我们应该对这样的人说：

这就是！如果她自己不够疯狂，那就怂恿她！[42]

27.我的意思不是说人就不该提出批评，除非人完美无缺；如果事情果真如此，那就没人提出批评。我的意思是，当我们对某件后来存疑的事情的评价而使某人遭到指控时，我们就不该免于内部法庭的质询。一个人无法克服自身的缺点，然而他自己却仍然试图除去长在别人身上的也许没那么恶毒和顽固的小嫩芽，对他来说这就是一件仁慈的善事。如果有人提醒我有某个缺点，我却回答说他也有同样的缺点，这个回答在我看来绝不恰当。那样做会带来什么不同呢？警告仍然是真实的、有益的。如果我们有健康的鼻孔，那么我们的排泄物应该更是臭气冲天。苏格拉底相信，如果有一个人发现儿子及陌生人在一起犯暴力罪或伤害罪，那么这个人首先应该去投案自首，由法官判决后到刽子手那儿请求赎罪；其次应该把儿子供出；最后再把那个陌生人供出。[43]如果这条训诫要求太高的话，至少儿子的父亲应该在自己良心上谴责自己。

28.我们最初的评价严格地说就是我们的种种感觉，这些感觉只通过外部偶然感知东西。怪不得在一切有助于我们社会的要素中，表面现象和外表礼节就这么持久普遍地增加，其结果是，管理制度最完好最有效的部分就在于此。我们始终在与人打交道，人的本性又有惊人的物质特性。近年来，有些人希望为我们发起一场沉思的非物质崇拜运动，那些人不该感到惊讶，如果有人认为，要是非物质崇拜在我们当中不是作为一种门派或派系的标记和手段加以保留，而只是留存它自身，那么它肯定已从他们手中溜走，化为乌有。

29.这在讨论中也是一样的：发言人的庄重、学术礼服和级别，这些常常给空虚无聊的论点增添可信度。谁会相信有如此众多随行人员、如此不怒自威的君主其内在没有某种超凡脱俗的才能呢！谁又会相信一个肩负国家如此重大使命和职责的人，一个如此轻蔑如此自大的人，并不比一个从老远处就向他鞠躬、没有官衔的人来得聪明呢！这种人说出的话及其扭曲的嘴脸都受到人们的注视和揣摩，每个人力求赋予他们某种永恒美好的意义。如果他屈尊参加一般讨论，并且你向他表现出除赞同和敬畏之外的什么东西，那么他就会以经验的权威使你一败涂地：他听过这样的事；见过这样的事；也做过这样的事：他用种种事例让你彻底被打败。我想告诉这种人，外科医生的经验之果不在于详述其各种手术，也不在于提醒我们他治过4个瘟疫患者、3个痛风病人，除非他懂得如何从中提取素材以形成自己的判断，除非他懂得如何让我们相信其医学技能的实践已使其变得更聪明。所以在各种乐器的交响中，我们听不到诗琴、小竖琴和笛子的乐音，而听到整体的和声——这种和声效果是整个乐团不同乐器齐奏产生的。

30.如果他们的使命和旅行已使他们得到提高，那么这应当体现在他们理解的结果中。讲述我们的种种经验是不够的：我们必须掂量经验，将经验归类；我们肯定还消化了经验并提取了经验，以便吸取它们所蕴含的道理并加以总结。从来就没有如此之多的书本经验！听一听经验之谈总是好处多多，收益多多，因为来自他们记忆宝库的经验为我们提供充分的指导，这种指导妙不可言，值得称赞：这必然在帮助我们生活方面具有极大的价值。可那不是此时此刻我们正寻求的：史料叙述者与搜集者并不值得称赞。

31.我厌恶言语和行动上的一切专制，我喜欢防范那些通过我们的各种感官欺骗我们的判断的微小事情；通过对特别社会阶层的人保持警惕的眼光，我已发现他们大多数人就像我们中的其他人一样：

在这高台上普通的感官绝非够用。[44]

32.或许我们尊重他们，并且对他们的认知比他们实际的情况要少，因为他们着手做得越多，暴露得也越多。搬运工的力量必须比其搬运的重担更大。尚未用尽浑身力量的人让你猜想是否他有所保留，还是已经达到了极限：屈服于重担之下的人暴露其局限性以及肩膀的虚弱。这就是为什么许多有学问的人比别人更能被看出缺乏足够的灵魂。他们可以当好农夫、好商人、好工匠：他们也就生而具有适合此类工作的力量。知识是一件很有分量的东西：他们埋头钻研知识。他们的精神器官既没有足够的能量也没有足够的技巧来展示这种高贵的物质，分配其力量，使用其力量，并使其力量有助于他们。知识只能驻扎在强大的天赋中：这种天赋十分罕见。苏格拉底说：当软弱无力的才智之士们处理哲学问题时，他们会有损哲学的尊严；当哲学覆盖在一张破罩子上时，似乎变得毫无价值，颇有瑕疵。[45]

33.这就是他们如何变得腐烂、迷糊：

戴上猩猩脸的假面具，

穿真丝袍男孩真逗趣，

留下裸露出的光屁股，

逗得桌上宾客乐呵呵。

34.那些人统治我们，发号施令，将世界握在自己手中，而对那些人来说一样的是：它不足以让他们拥有普通的智慧，也不足以能获得我们所能获得的东西。如果他们不是远在我们之上，那么他们就远在我们之下。因为他们许诺得越多，也就亏欠得越多；这就是为何在他们这种情况下保持沉默不仅是一种彬彬有礼、严肃庄重的举止，而且常常还是一种有益的举动。当美伽巴佐斯去阿贝勒斯的工作室看他时，他长时间保持沉默。可当他开始谈论艺术作品时，却受到粗鲁无礼的非难：“当你保持沉默时，由于你办公室的锁链和你的随行人员，你似乎是一个伟大人物，可现在一听你说话，连学徒也看不起你。”[46]那些华丽的装饰和显赫的财产既无法容忍他平民百姓般的无知，也无法容忍他对绘画不得体的评论：他应当一直保持这种表面上所具有的鉴赏力，因为在我所处的时代，多少人以冷酷少语的姿态令他们愚蠢的灵魂看上去像是充满智慧和能力。

35.尊严和职责必然更多是依靠运气而非才干来获得，人们常常为此错误地责备君主们。相反，他们有如此的好运气是一个奇迹，实际上他们很难得有各种方式去享受这份运气。

对君主而言，其主要功绩就在于了解其臣民，[47]因为大自然并没赋予他们一双能够纵观天下芸芸众生的眼睛，这双眼睛既能明辨是非，又能洞察我们的内心，我们的内心是我们认识意志和良好品质的栖息地。他们挑选我们时，不得不借助于摸索猜测：按我们的家族、财富、学问以及人们的意见——最无力的论据。要是有人能发现人们能运用公正评价与合理选择的手段，这样的人总能一举确立共和国的完美形式。

36.“是的。可他使这一大事得以圆满完成。”——这意味深长，可还是不够充分，因为我们正确地接受这样一条准则，准则写道：计划不必通过结果来评价。甚至在首领中腐败的辩护律师已令人高兴地改邪归正时，迦太基人还是惩罚了他们。古罗马人往往拒绝记载战绩辉煌的胜利，因为胜利不是靠指挥官的优秀品质，而是靠其好运。我们时常注意到，在这世上的活动中运气和品德相匹敌：运气向我们展示出其所具有的压倒一切的力量；因为无法使不称职者聪明起来，所以运气乐于用让他们走运的方式推翻我们的自以为是。运气喜欢来捣乱，同时支持那些进程完全与其步调一致的工作。这就是为什么我们每天都能看到我们当中最普通的人给最伟大的公共事业和个人事业带来胜利的果实。

37.波斯人西拉马尼斯回答了那些惊愕于他的事业如此糟糕、同时明白他的计划又是如此英明的人，其回答是，他只是其计划的主人，而运气才是成就事业的女主人：这话也能对相反情形的解释作出同样的回答。[48]

38.这世上大多数事都是本身偶然发生：

运气找到出路。[49]

39.这样的结果常常给大多数无能的领袖增加威信。我们的干涉其实不过是一种习惯，是传统和范例的结果，而不是理性的结果。曾经有一次大冒险让我十分震惊；然后，我从那些冒险的成功者身上懂得他们的动机是什么以及他们所使用的方法：除一般观念外，我什么也没找到。

40.实际上，如果不是为了炫耀的话，大多数的一般观念在实践中恐怕也是最可靠也最适合。如果大多数谦逊的理性都建立在坚实的基础上，那会如何呢？如果最卑贱的、最松懈的、最守旧的做法最适合我们所关切的事，那又会如何呢？如果我们要捍卫枢密院权威的话，我们就无须俗人参与枢密院，也不想高瞻远瞩以逾越最初的障碍。如果我们想维护枢密院的声誉，那么就得把它当作一个整体来看待。

41.我想暂时概述这件事，稍微讲述其最初的方面，然后我通常把主要细节的任务留给上帝。

将其余的事托付给上帝。

在我看来，好运与歹运是两种至高无上的力量。智慧在命运的角色扮演游戏中没有出场的机会。如果一个人认为能够把握原因与结果，并且自作主张亲自引导行动的进展，那么他所从事的事业必将徒劳无功，在战争的部署中尤为如此。从来就没有比我有时看到的实际情况更加谨慎的军事状况：或许因为我们惧怕会在途中迷失方向，所以为了迎接决战行动的高潮将自己留在预备队中！

42.我还想说，我们真正的智慧和成熟的反思多半是偶然发生的。我的意志和推理是以这样那样的方式激发的。他们的许多运动控制他们自己，而不受我控制。我的理性天天都屈从于机遇的刺激和鼓动：

他们心中的思想永远转动，

他们胸中的感情四处流动，

它们就像风前面的云一样。[50]

43.你看来会明白在我们的城市谁掌握最多的权力，谁把工作做得最好。你会发现他们通常并不聪明过人。妇女、儿童、疯子跟才华横溢的君主一样统治过国家，这样的例子不是没有。修昔底德说过：粗放的人更常在这类事务中取得成功，比精细的人做得更好。[51]我们常常把他们走好运的行为归因于他们的智慧。

每个出类拔萃的人由其好运得以升迁；

然后我们就说他聪明。

44.这就是为何我坚决主张，我们一切活动的结果为我们的价值和能力所提供的证据少之又少。

45.现在我要说，这只够我们看出一个人青云直上，身居要职；即使在他离官卸职前三天我们才认识他，可他高尚和天才的观点不知不觉融入了我们的评价，并且我们让自己相信，通过气势与声誉的渐长，他在才能方面有所加强。我们对他的评价并不是以其价值为基础，而是（就像有一把算盘有多个计数器的情况一样）以其等级标志为基础。让他再碰一碰霉运，再摔一摔跤，并且再次淹没在人群中，然后我们大家感到惊奇：究竟什么使得他一飞冲天！我们便会问：“这个人还是原来的那个人吗？当他高高在上时，他不知道更多这方面的问题吗？君主会对这一点点东西感到满意吗？”我们得到命运很好的眷顾，的确如此！

46.这就是我在我自己的时代多次见到的一些事。

47.什么！甚至是在戏剧中大人物的面具也有点影响了我们，蒙蔽了我们。我对君主最钦佩的就是那群崇拜者。一切都要卑躬屈从于我们的君主——除了我们的智慧。我的理智不是为卑躬屈从而造，虽然我的膝盖是。

48.当美兰提欧斯被问到他是如何看待狄阿尼索斯的悲剧时，他回答：“我从来就不明白这件事，因为人们把它说得面目全非了！”那么，这也太过分了吧！在那些评价伟人言语的人中，大多数都会回答：“我从未听过他说的话：他的形象被尊严、伟大和崇高给模糊了。”[52]

49.有一天，当安提斯泰尼鼓动雅典人下令要像用马一样用驴犁田时，他被告知驴生来就不是干犁田这样的活。他反驳道：“这有什么关系。这件事完全取决于你们发布的命令：你们大多数人在指挥作战时所投入的无知无能者，无不突然变得百依百顺，被指挥得服服贴贴，因为正是你们才雇佣了他们呀！”[53]

50.与此相关的习惯是，如此众多的人尊崇他们当中选出来的君主。他们并不满足于尊敬他们：他们需要崇拜他们。一旦墨西哥人完成了国王登基大典，他们就不敢看国王的脸一眼，可虽然他们已将国王奉为王国的神明，但他们要国王发誓不仅得保留他们的宗教、他们的法律和他们的自由，得勇敢、公正以及和蔼，而且还得让太阳明亮地转动并且发出人们习惯的光芒，让云团在适当的季节消散，让河流在河道中流动，让土地长出人们所需的一切东西。[54]

51.我反对这种广为流传的风尚。当我看到一个人的能力伴随高官厚禄受公众喝彩时，我就非常怀疑这种能力。我们应该记住能力对一个人意味着：当他要说时就能说；能相机行事；能以主人的权力中断讨论或转换主题；能在毕恭毕敬、战战兢兢的朝臣面前，以摇头、微笑或以沉默的方式捍卫自己，挡回反对意见。

52.当某件琐事在餐桌上成为轻松讨论的话题时，一个富豪参与讨论，他以这样的一句话开场：“任何另有说法的人不是无知者就是说谎者。”还说了些诸如此类的话。你最好握紧你手中的匕首对该话题的哲学要点追根究底！

53.另有一条我感觉十分受用的告诫：在辩论和讨论中，我们觉得正确的话不一定立即被人接受。大多数人靠拾人牙慧致富。或许事情正是这样：某某人作了一番好评论，或给了一个好回答，或发表了一次简明扼要的言论，把话说出来了却没有意识到它的力量。（我们抓不住我们所借用的东西，毫无疑问，这在我自己身上可以得到证实。）我们不应该一味地让步，不管它可能蕴涵什么美好的东西或真理。我们应该不是严厉地攻击它，就是在假装不了解它的情况下做点让步，以便彻底弄清，并发现它是如何在其作者身上栖息落脚的。我们可能正在帮他的利剑刺向其不可及之处，同时我们迎头撞上。有好几回，在唇枪舌剑的必然压力下，我已经作出了反击，这种反击意外切中目标。我以数量体现分量，让他们接受了。

54.在与一个能言善辩者辩论时，我喜欢抢先说出他的结论，省去他进行自我辩解的麻烦；当他的想法尚未成熟或正在形成时，我就先发制人对它们进行分析（他一旦思维形成条理就告诫我，并且威胁到我）。同样我还讲，我和我先前提过的那些人的做法截然不同：除他们所解释的之外，我们必须不作任何假设，也不理解任何东西。如果他们的判断是得当的但却是以一种放之四海而皆准的方式表述出来——“这是好的，那是坏的”——那么就找出它的正确是否是因为运气。给他们的定论一些条件限制：“它为什么好？它怎么好？”那些普遍的论断（我感觉很普通）一点名堂也没有。他们就像那些称赞一堆人或一群人的人；那些真正认识他们的人直呼其名，一个个评价他们。然而，这只是偶一为之的事。这解释了为什么：平均一天一次以上，我见过脑子愚钝的人试着通过指出他们正在阅读的书里某个绝妙的细节来扮聪明，可他们选错了重点，这是他们所心仪的地方，可是这没有表现出作家的出色，而是揭示了他们自己的无知。

55.当刚听了一整页关于维吉尔的内容时，你确实会拍案叫绝：“刚才这页写得真美啊！”狡猾的人就用这种方式。但是，为了保证能着手回顾优秀作家的细节描写，为了尝试准确地指出精选例子显示其自身的高超，通过接二连三的词汇斟酌、独特措辞、素材的选择以说明他情绪激昂之处，并不是很多人试着那样做。“我们不仅应该检验每个人说什么，而且还应该检验他的观点，以及他为什么这么说”。[55]我天天都听到愚蠢的人口中蹦出并不愚蠢的话。他们甚至说出一些动听的话；让我们看一看他们是如何深刻理解这些话的吧！也让我们看一看他们从何处掌握这些话的吧！

56.此刻，如果你来为他们阐明并强化格言，那么他们立刻就会利用你的解释，并从你的身上抢走它：“这就是我所要说的，”或“这就是我对它的理解，恰如其分，”或“之所以我不这样说出格言，是因为我无法找到恰当的词汇。”——继续狂吹吧！我们甚至应该利用狡猾来惩罚这种狂妄自大的愚蠢。

57.赫格西亚斯的原则是我们既不该憎恨也不该非难而应该指引，这在其他地方是对的，可在这儿却不然。[56]要是一个人不知如何利用别人的帮助，根本不值得你的帮助，那么在帮助这种人的过程中既没有正义也没有善意可言。我喜欢让这种人在泥潭里陷得更深，甚至动弹不得——让他们陷得如此之深，以致有可能的话最终让他们意识到需要别人的帮助！

58.你不能靠一次警告治愈愚蠢和不理性的病症。关于这种治疗法，我们可适当提及赛勒斯对那个敦促他作战时给部队鼓舞士气的人所回答的话：一次精彩的长篇大论不可能使人在战场上变成英勇无畏的战士，这跟靠听一首优美的歌曲你就能成为一个好音乐家一样不可能。[57]学徒生涯必须经历，在出师独当一面之前，定要经过长期坚持不懈的学习。

59.只是对我们自己的亲人我们才有义务认真地纠正和指导；但是，给第一个过路人说教，或对我们遇上的第一个人宣读关于愚昧无知的演讲稿，这可是我厌恶的做法。在我参与的讨论中我很少这样做；我宁愿放弃这一切做法，而不愿借助如此冷淡又装模作样的演讲。在演讲和写作中，我的性情并不合适那些正在初学原理的人。但是，不管我在交往中或当着第三者的面把事情评价成多么错误或荒唐，我从不暴跳如雷地用话语或手势来打断他们。

60.同时，讲理的人对自己感到满意可以说是合乎情理，要是愚蠢的人不讲理的人来得更为洋洋自得，那么没有哪种愚蠢更让我气愤了。要是智慧不准你自满自足，并且总是以不满和害怕为由把你撵走，而固执和鲁莽却让它们的主人充满快乐和自信，那可是一大灾难啊。就是人们当中最不聪明的人才看不起比他们强的人，总是从充满荣耀和快乐的争吵中凯旋。往往他们傲慢的话语和欢乐的神情为他们从旁观者眼中赢得胜利，那些路人通常不知如何判断也不能识别真正的优胜。动物般愚蠢最确凿的依据就是蛮横的固执己见。还有什么会比一头驴更肯定、更果断、更轻蔑、更深沉、更庄重、更严肃呢？

61.也许我们可以把那些短暂的有针对性的交流列入谈话和讨论这一类，在那当中朋友们之间洋溢着快乐和亲密，他们时而愉快地一起开玩笑，时而尖锐地彼此嘲讽。这是我乐观天性决定的相当适合我的一项运动；如果这项运动不像我刚描述的其他运动那样紧张严肃，那么它依旧热烈而巧妙，在莱库格斯看来也依旧有用。在我关注的地方，我贡献出更多的是自由氛围，而不是智慧，因而我在这里比在寻找素材的过程中来得更加幸福；可我是一个追求完美的人，因为不仅在激烈尖锐的时候，而且甚至在粗鲁无礼的时候，我都能容忍反击而不生气。当我突然受到攻击时，如果我无法立刻找到一个巧妙的应答，我不是浪费时间近于顽固地用含糊不清的无聊争论对攻击穷追不舍，而是随它去，愉快地掩住两耳，等待更好的反击机会。要知道，没有一个小贩能在每次讨价还价中都占到便宜。

62.当辩论失败时，大多数人会改变声音和措辞，他们不是在为自己挽回颓势，而是气急败坏地暴露自己的缺点和脆弱。在玩笑的刺激下，我们有时会掐断那些拴着对方缺点的秘密之弦，我们冷静时如果没人招惹，我们绝不会去拨弄这一根根弦；我们彼此提醒对方失误不是没有益处的。有些别的身体运动，如法国式鲁莽野蛮的运动，我恨之入骨。对这样的运动我很敏感：在我一生中，我见过两个王室血统的王储就因为这些运动而命丧黄泉。它是一项为乐趣而战的丑陋运动。[58]

63.此外，当我要评价一个人时，我会问他到什么程度他自己会感到满意；对自己所说或所写的东西他会满意到什么程度。我请他不要找那些美妙的借口：例如“我原来说话写作只是玩玩而已”——

它只是半成品就从铁砧上拿掉。[59]

“在它身上我只花了一个小时；从那以后我再也没看它”——我说：“好吧，把这些东西都搁一边儿去。给我展示一下确实完全代表你的某种东西，就是某种你高兴拿来给人评价的东西。”然后我说：“你认为你作品最美的地方在哪里？是这种特征还是那种特征呢？是其优雅的风格、论题、你对素材的发现、你的评价、还是你的博学呢？”

64.我通常发现，之所以一些人在评价自己的作品跟评价别人的作品时同样有误，不仅是因为他们的感情使然，还因为他们对作品缺乏理解能力和分析能力。作品本身借由它的要素和运气，能以超出作者自己的理解和研究的范围的程度使作者受惠；作品能跑在作者之前。没有什么比起让我评价自己作品令我更无法拿捏：我给论文排名次——十分犹豫不决，几乎没有信心——时而信心全无，时而信心十足。

65.许多书由于论题而成为有用的书，书的作者并不引以为荣。就好作品而言，有些好书对其作者来说是一种耻辱。我可以写关于我们的宴请方式，关于我们的服装——而且我还能把它们写得非常优美；我能出版当朝执政君主的敕令和御函；我能出一本好书的节本（而且每部好书的节本都是一部愚蠢的节本），书籍本身可以偶然丢失。事情都像这样。子孙后代从这样的著述中得到的奇特帮助。可除了感到幸运，我还能从这样的作品中获得什么荣誉呢？一大批名著就属于此类。

66.几年前，在拜读菲利普·德·康明斯——他肯定是一个非常优秀的作家——的著作时，我注意到如下这条不同寻常的格言：“我们应该小心翼翼地为主人提供殷勤的服务，免得他无法公正地赏你。”我该赞扬的不是他，而是他这句话的主题。不久前，我在塔西佗的作品中偶然看到这句话：“帮助只有在它们似乎可报答时才使人愉快。而太多帮忙让我们只能报以憎恶而非感激。”塞内加更激烈：“对无法报答感到耻辱的人会要他的恩人去死。”奎因图斯·西塞罗用一个更为轻松婉转的短语写道：“无法偿还欠你债务的人绝不可能爱你。”[60]

67.作家的主题适当的时候能显示出他是有学问的人还是记性好的人，可如果你想评价其内在什么品质最真实地体现他，什么品质最可敬（我的意思是他的内在力量和心灵美），那么你就必须知道什么真正是他的，什么肯定不是他的；在不属于他的这种特质中，在他作出的贡献中有多少我们得归因于他的选择、处理、修饰及其文学才能。假使他已经用了别人的东西，那么他将破坏自己的文风，这样的事太常发生了！当我们从一位现代诗人那儿偶然发现某个精彩绝伦的例子，或从一位布道者那儿碰巧遇上某次激烈的辩论时，像我们这样几乎没怎么看过书的人就会感到困难重重。在我们从一个学者那儿得知这个东西是他们原创的还是他们从别人那儿信手拈来的之前，我们不敢对他们妄加赞扬。可就算我知道了，我还是心存疑虑。

68.我刚刚一口气读完塔西佗的《历史》（这对我来说可是件稀罕事：我一次花一整个小时读一本书已经是20年前的事了。我这样做，只是出于一个贵族的推荐，这个贵族在法国因其自身德行、长久以来的才气以及被认为与其许多兄弟同甘共苦的善心而德高望重）。我不知道有什么作家，能把公众事件的记述与如此多对个人道德偏见的反思结合起来。并且在我看来（与他的看法恰恰相反）因为他有特别任务：关注当代君主（那些人性格各异却都相当古怪且极端）的生涯，及其在臣民中主要因其残酷而引人瞩目的功绩，所以比起他报道战役和世界革命，他就有一个更引人关注、更妙趣横生的演说话题。因此，当他下笔仓促刻画那些干净的、高贵的死亡，好像害怕冗长啰嗦的报道会让我们厌倦时，我发现他无利可图。

69.这种历史态度颇有益处。公共事件的展开更多取决于命运的舵手，而个人事件的展开则取决于我们自己。塔西佗的作品与其说是对历史事件的陈述，不如说是对历史事件的评价；与其说其中包含报道，不如说其中蕴涵告诫。它不是一本用来阅读的书，而是一本用来研究和学习的书。该书富含大量箴言，以至于无论对与错它们都无处不在。它是伦理和政论的温床，用以供给在这个世界中身居统治高位的那些人，并对他们加以粉饰。他用实在而有力的道理为自己申辩，在警句般精巧的文体中，遵循他那个年代做作的文风。（他们十分喜欢一种高级文体，结果是当发现论题中缺乏机警或巧妙的成分时，他们便求助于富于机智、精细微妙的语句。）他与塞内加大同小异，可塞内加更尖锐，而塔西佗身上似乎更多人情味。塔西佗适合服务于一个病态不安的国家，像我们现在自己的国家一样：你往往会相信我们原来是他叙述和痛骂的主题。那些对他的善良和真诚抱怀疑的人，无疑暴露出对他的怨恨出自偏见。在处理罗马事务中，他颇有见地，并倾向于站在公正的立场上。我的确感到遗憾，除了更神秘之外，塔西佗把庞培写得同马略和斯库拉一样不好，但比起与他生活并对付他的人在其裁定中所提到的，塔西佗对他的评价更为冷酷。[61]真的，为力求控制局势，庞培既抱有野心，也希望复仇：甚至他的朋友担心胜利可能使他冲昏头脑，可他还不至于到了另外那两个人那种精神错乱的极端程度。他人生中没有什么东西向我们暗示专制和残酷的恐怖行径确实存在。此外，我们决不应该无端怀疑，而应该更重证据。所以，在这一点上我并不相信塔西佗。

70.他所写的那些确实是简单朴实、直截了当的报道，这些报道或许可能因为它们与他最终的评价并不完全相符这一事实引起争辩，因为这种种评价是他所采取的不公平态度所导致；那些报道常常是他所无法加以证实的——他几乎拿不出有独到见解的证据。依据赋予他这样做的法律，他无须对清规戒律唯命是从，而且也无须为不了解宗教而辩解。这是他的不幸，而不是他的过错。

71.我一直在着重研究对他的评价：并不完全都清楚。例如，从寄给老迈体弱的底波里斯人组成的参议院那封信，我摘出这几句话：“阁下，怎么啦？我应该写信给您，此刻我不应该写些什么给您吗？我知道，我每天都在接近死亡；假如我懂得写些什么的话，诸位男神和女神或许会让我的下场更可悲。”我无法明白为什么他把这些话如此确定运用于折磨底波里斯人良心的悔恨上。至少我看到这里时，我没发现是怎么回事。[62]

72.依我看，他似乎还有点委屈，当他被迫提及他曾经在罗马当过荣耀的地方官吏这件事时，他继续解释说，他没有提及地方官吏是不想为此自吹自擂。在我看来，这做法对一个像他那样的人来说似乎相当不真实：不敢全面谈论你自己就暴露出思想的一个缺陷。一个有正直而睿智的头脑能够作出肯定的和真实的评价，在各种情况下既引用别人身上的例子也引用自身的例子，直率地引用第三方也引用自己做见证人。为了支持真理和自由，我们应该逾越那些陈规陋习。我不仅敢于谈论自己，而且还敢于谈论自己以外的任何东西。当我写到别的什么东西时，我就会离题，让我的主题逃脱我。我不喜欢自己如此缺乏专注，我也不如此作茧自缚，以至于我无法剥离自己，像思考一个邻居或一棵树那样分隔开来思考自己。如果你无法看到自己的价值局限所在，或者如果你说的比看到的东西多，其中的错误是一样的。我们欠上帝的爱比欠自己更多。我们对他知之甚少，却不停讨论他，还要多谈。

73.如果塔西佗的作品将他个性的一切向我们和盘托出，那么他就是一个非常伟大、正直、勇敢的人，他的德行就不具有迷信的色彩，而具有哲学的味道和宽宏大量的品质。你会发现他的一些证言相当轻率；例如他坚持认为当一个士兵的双手在搬一堆木头过程中由于寒冷而变得僵硬时，脱离其手臂，然后插在那儿麻木了。[63]在类似的例子中，我习惯对如此伟大见证人的威信心悦诚服。他还说，塞拉皮斯神赐下神力，维斯西巴安在亚历山大治愈一个双目失明的妇女，他用他的唾液涂在她的双眼上，同时施加其他魔法，他遵照记载重大事件的著名史学家的忠实榜样这样写，流行的谣传和看法都存在于民事之中。其任务在于对大众的信仰作复述，而不作解释。阐释它们的角色由作为良心导师的神学家和哲学家来担当。这就是为什么他的史学家同仁，作为当时的伟人，极其明智地说：“我传递给别人的东西比我自己相信的多。我无法为我所怀疑的东西担保，我也无法忽略传统所告诉我的东西。”而另一个说：“这些东西既不可确认也不可否认：我们必须坚持传统。”[64]塔西佗在对神迹的信仰逐渐衰落期间写道，他希望自己能给那些神迹提供一个立足点，所以在他的《编年史》中包罗许多如此尊古怀旧的体面人士所能接受的古老的内容。

74.这话说得多好。让他们将他们的历史传递给我们，是根据他们搜罗到的东西，而不是根据他们自己的估计。我是主题的主宰者，我处理主题，可我不为主题对任何人负责，也不对那些相信我所说的一切的人负责。有时我的思想表示出怀疑似是而非的论点，文字上的细微差别令我摇头叹息；但是，我写出来让他们碰碰运气。我知道一些人做这事获得好名声。我并不能一人评价他们。我全方位地描写自己，从起床到睡觉，从正面到反面，从右边到左边，包括我所有与生倶来的复杂性。甚至一直很强大的思想在它们工作运转和甄别分辨时也不总是管用。

75.这是通过我的记忆含含糊糊地呈现的塔西佗。对他的所有评价既不严密又有缺陷。

论闲散

1.正如人们看到荒芜的土地，要是富饶肥沃，便长满成千上万种无用的杂草，其结果是，如果我们要让土地发挥作用的话，我们就必须征服土地，忙于耕种，尤其播上为我所用的种子；就像人们有时可能看到留守的孤独妇女生下一大堆不成样子的孩子；除了接受精子，没有什么能让她们自己需要忙忙碌碌，以便生下优秀的后代：思想也是如此。如果我们不让思想忙碌于某种特别的耕作——用一条缰绳将其束缚，那么它便肆忌横行，在幻象的荒地上漫游：

就像当青铜盆里波动的水

反射阳光和月亮的笑脸时，

回照的微光高高地飞上空，

光线射在嵌镶的天花板上。[65]

2.那么，骚乱就带来疯狂和语无伦次的失常：

他们像在病人的梦中

构筑空虚的幻影。[66]

当灵魂没有一个明确的目标，那么心灵便迷失方向；正如人们所说，如果你无处不在，那么你就哪儿也不在。

无论谁哪儿都想住，那就哪儿也住不了。[67]

3.最近我到庄园隐居起来，决心尽我所能专心致志地独自一个静静度过所剩无几的余生；在我看来，对我的思想所能起到的最大帮助就是让思想处在全然闲散的状态，照管好它自己，只关注它自己，平静地思考它自己。我希望我的思想从那以后能做起这些事情更为容易，然而随着时光的流逝，我的思想已变得成熟，并且已变得沉重。

4.我感觉到——

闲散总是带来思想的无常变化。[68]

相反的是，闲散像一匹脱缰的野马逃跑了，给自己带来的烦恼；远比过去要多；闲散使得思想接二连三混乱不堪地产生出众多假想的异兽和神奇的怪物，因此，为了方便我思索这些千奇百怪的东西，我开始将它们记录下来，以期及时让我的思想自感羞愧。

论父亲对孩子的感情

致埃斯狄萨克夫人，

1.夫人：除非奇特或新奇（这两个特性赋予任何事物以价值）吸引我，我决不轻易放下这部拙作的创作工作；可这部作品又是如此的奇异，并且与惯常作品迥然不同。

2.该作品起源于一种悲伤的幽默（这对我的自然天性来说又是一种极不相符的情绪），这种幽默出自几年前我自己陷入孤独的隐居生活所引起的懊恼，它最初进入我的脑海，这才使我疯狂地关注起写作。发现自己相当空虚，没有什么东西可写之后，我自告奋勇地将自己作为主题和论题。这本书是世上这类书中绝无仅有的一本，其观念充满野性且荒诞古怪。我这部作品因这古怪的特性值得关注，因为世上最好的工匠也不知如何用如此不着边际和琐碎的材料制作超群的作品。

3.此时此刻，夫人，我已决定画一幅自己的生活画，如果描绘不出我长期以来对您高尚的美德的敬意，那我肯定忽略了一个重要特征。在本章的开头，我尤其想这么做，因为在你所有的优秀品质中，最突出的是您对您孩子的爱。

4.人人都知道，当您的丈夫埃斯狄萨克撒手人寰，而您成了寡妇时，您正值青春年华；有多少相当值得尊敬的绅士向您求婚，对像您这样地位的法国贵妇人自然会这样；而您有着坚定不移的意志，多年来您历尽千辛万苦，承担起负责照顾孩子的事务（这些事务一直让您奔忙于法国的许多边远地区，至今脱不开身）的重担；您的智慧或好运使那些事务都很顺利。知道您的人都会立刻同意我的看法：我们找不到哪怕一个当今的例子能够比您的母爱更为令人动容。

5.夫人，我赞美上帝。您的爱有了如此美妙的结果，您的儿子埃斯狄萨克显现出光明的前途：当一个优秀儿子长大成人，他的责任和感恩将是对您的回报。可他现在还是个孩子，无法对从您身上得到的难以计算的母爱表示感激。所以我希望，如果这本书有一天会捧在他的手中，到我甚至无法开口说话的时候，他也会从我的书中学到一些东西——我可以诚实地为其中的内容作保，倘能如愿，这些东西将会成为有力的见证，使他能因此而认识到：在法国没有哪位绅士比他从母亲那里得到的教诲来得多，而且我还可以保证，将来他会承认你的这些美德，除此之外，没有别的行为可以确实有力地证明他的善良和高尚。

6.如果真有一种自然法则——换句话说，如果真有一种可以视为普遍永久印记在动物和人类身上的本能（尚存争议）——那么我敢说，在致力于自我保护和避免任何有害的事情之后，就是对自己后代的爱。这仿佛是大自然对万物繁衍所做的托付。若反过来看，孩子对父母的爱没有那么深就并不令人感到惊讶了。在此基础上，我们还可以加上从亚里士多德那儿得到的思考，[69]即任何对别人行善的人爱别人胜过他被别人爱；给予者比接受者感觉到更大的爱；创造者爱创造物比创造物——如果创造物真有感情的话——爱他来得更多。这一点显得尤为真实，因为每个人都把自己的存在看得很珍贵：而存在则在于运动和活动；因此，从某种意义上说，每个人，在某种程度上，都存在于其所做所为中：捐助者的行为既美好又高贵；另一方面，受助者的行为仅仅是实用的，高贵的行为比纯粹实用的行为更为可爱。高贵是持续不变的，常常给每个高贵行为的施予者以满足。然而，实用性会容易消失或减少，而且对实用性的记忆既不令人感到很舒心也不那么甜蜜。让我们付出最大代价的东西对我们来说最为亲切可爱——给予比接受让我们付出的代价更大。

7.因为上帝很乐于赋予我们某种无序推理的小聪明，所以我们不应该像动物那样奴隶般地屈从自然法则，而应该以我们的自由意志和判断遵从自然法则，所以我们确实应该对自然法则的普遍权威作出某种让步，但不应该听任自己被自然法则残暴地摆布：唯有理性才能必然决定我们的前途。

8.对我来说，那些不依靠理性和判断而产生的偏好平淡得出奇。在讨论的主题中，当新生儿尚无心理活动，也没有让他们变得惹人喜爱的明显特征时，我无法为引发人们拥抱新生儿的那种情感找到合理的解释。而我从不乐意人们当我的面给新生儿喂奶。真切的合理的爱应该是天生的，然后随着我们对孩子的了解，这种爱不断加深；如果他们表现出他们应该得到这种爱，那么我们就应该用真正的父爱去呵护他们，因为我们的天性到那时就会与理性并行向前；如果他们不值得爱——我们就作出相同的回应——不管自然天性如何强大，我们都应该始终遵从理性。

9.实际上，相反的情况常常发生；我们自己都会感觉到，孩子的蹦蹦跳跳及其幼稚的恶作剧比他们成人后的活动更让我们触动，好像我们不是把他们当人来爱，而是把他们当玩具或宠物猴来爱。有些父亲会给还是孩童的子女大量玩具，可也会对他们一长大就要小钱花的行为表示不满。这甚至看上去，事实上，仿佛我们嫉妒地看着他们在这世上享受——他们能享受我们却要失去，这使我们变得吝啬，对孩子拳脚相向。让我们愤怒的是，他们会紧跟在我们后面，仿佛命令我们靠边站。因为事实清楚明白地摆在眼前，孩子们只能通过损耗我们的存在和生活来实现他们自己的。如果这会使我们感到恐惧的话，我们就不该当父亲。

10.我认为不让他们分享家庭的财产和成员利益既冷酷又不公正——当他们能承担起家务时，就将家务的全部知识传授给作为生活伙伴的他们——这并不减少我们的利益，同时我们无须在其身上节省以便为他将来的利益作准备，因为我们就是为了这一目的生孩子。看到一位老父亲，身体虚弱得只剩下半条命，把自己拥有绝对所有权的大笔财富塞入烟囱角落，却不用来帮助和培养几个子女，让孩子们浪费最美好的时光，在公共事务上不追求进取和出人头地，这也是不公平的。绝望驱使他们寻找一些方法，哪怕是不正当的，以满足自我需要：在我这个年代，我见过几个出身名门的年轻人，深深沉溺于盗窃，以至于没有什么处罚可以让他们改邪归正。我认识一个年轻人，跟他关系很好，在他的兄弟，一位勇敢的非常值得尊敬的贵族的恳请下，我与他就这件事有过一次交谈。在回答中，这位年轻人相当直率地承认，父亲不折不扣的吝啬促使他作出如此卑鄙的行径。他还补充说，他现在已是深陷其中而不能自拔。他与其他几个人在早晨拜访一位女士，偷窃这位女士的戒指时被逮了个正着。这使我想起了我听说的有关另一个贵族的故事：这个贵族早已过惯了从事这一理想行当的生活，并且对其有了迫切的需要，结果是当他真的成为遗产的继承人，并决定金盆洗手时，他还是无法改邪归正，只要路过一个货摊，凡是他需要的东西照偷不误，宁可稍后要让人去付账。我认识几个人就是如此积习难改并行窃成性，以至于他们经常从自己的亲密伙伴那里偷东西，然后将偷来的东西返还。

11.我可能是一个爱吹牛的人，不过没有什么我不懂的恶习。我的性格比理性更令我对偷窃深恶痛绝：我从没有想过从什么人那儿偷什么东西。诚然，我所生活的那个社区与法国其余地区相比更斥责偷窃行为，可在我们这个年代，我们时有机会见过其他省的贵族被判诸多可怕的抢劫罪。恐怕我们必须把这样的堕落行为部分归因于他们父亲的过错。

12.如果无论谁再告诉我——像一个十分理智的贵族曾经告诉过我的那样——他想从他所有的存款中得到唯一实在的好处，就是他孩子的尊敬和奉承（因为现在这把年纪已使他丧失力量，那就成了他剩下的以防被每个人轻视怠慢的唯一良方，用以维护其在家中的威信——确实，根据亚里士多德的理论，不仅老年人，各种各样的弱者都对吝啬推崇备至）[70]——钱确实能带来些什么。可这种药用于医治的病的产生是应该可以预防的。如果父亲只能通过让子女依赖于他的帮助来抓住他们的爱——如果这可以被称之为爱的话，那么他的确是个不幸的人。

13.我们应该让自己以美德和能力而受人尊敬，也以善行和谦和而受人爱戴。稀有木材的灰烬也有其价值，而我们也习惯于毕恭毕敬地保存伟人的遗骸及遗物。在体面过日子的情形下，也不会真正朽化，依然受到尊敬——尤其是对孩子们来说，他们的灵魂必须得到指引，不受需要和欲望的指使，也不受严苛和权力的命令，而需要理智的引导。

若你问我的看法，有赖权力的威信

比与爱结合的威信来得更坚固或更稳定，

那么我的回答是这种情况很不真实。[71]

14.我指责在培育温和思想中的所有暴行，因为温和的思想是为荣誉与自由而培养的。在严格和强制之下总是有某种卑屈的东西，而我认为你永远不能以武力得到你无法以理性、智慧和技能所得到的东西。

15.那就是我成长的方式。父母告诉我，我在童年时期只有两次尝过棍棒的滋味，而且只是轻轻的。我用同样的方式对待自己的亲生子女，尽管他们在断奶前都去世了。可是，唯一逃过厄运的女儿蕾奥娜已经6岁多（她母亲的温和就这样轻易感染了她），而我们没有用过话语——而且是和蔼可亲的话语——之外的任何东西教育她以及惩罚她幼稚的过错。即使我有时失望，那也有许多其他应该被责备的因素，而不用挑我教育方法的毛病，我知道这是正确又合乎天性的。

16.我还是对天生不易屈从别人、生存更自由的男孩更加谨慎：我很希望他们胸襟宽阔，真诚坦率。除了能让人的灵魂更为怯懦或更顽固，我从未见过鞭子能实现任何事情。

17.我们不是想得到子女的爱戴吗？我们不是不想他们希望我们死掉吗？——尽管无论何时这种可怕的想法都不可能是对的或可宽恕的：“犯罪没有正当的理由”——那么，让我们理智地用我们所拥有并支配的任何东西来丰富他们的生活吧！我们不该这么年轻就结婚，以至于我们成年人的年纪几乎与孩子的年纪混淆起来。如此的不体面会使我们陷入重重困难——我特别指在贵族的家庭中，孩子们过的是一种休闲式的生活，而且正如我们所说，他们可以靠自己的收入生活。在其他情况下，即在生活等同于为金钱而奋斗的家庭中，众多孩子成为整个家庭的帮手；他们成了帮助家庭富裕的新方式、新手段。

18.我33岁结婚；而我赞成35岁结婚——这是亚里士多德的主张。柏拉图不赞成男人30岁前结婚；不过他嘲笑55岁之后才同床睡觉的配偶，并断定他们的后代不值得养育。[72]

19.正是泰勒士给定结婚的正确年龄；他的母亲在他年轻时就催促他结婚。但他说：“太早了。”可在他年纪较大时，他又说：“太迟了！”任何不凑巧的事都找不到凑巧的时间，那就相机行事吧！

20.古代高卢人认为，男人20岁前与女人结婚应受责备，特别建议那些想为战争而受训的人直到成年都得保持贞洁，因为跟女人睡觉会使人变得温顺柔弱，萎靡不振。

可现在与年轻的姑娘结婚，

幸福地生儿育女，

为人夫为人父，

付出的爱却使他虚弱。[73]

21.据希腊历史记载，塔伦图姆·德·依克斯、克里索、艾斯狄鲁斯、迪奥庞普斯以及其他人，在整个奥林匹克运动会为赛跑、摔跤和其他比赛的身体调整期，不让自己有任何的性行为。[74]

22.突尼斯总督穆雷·哈桑（查理五世皇帝助其恢复王位的人）责怪父亲，因为他老是跟妻子在一起，并且称他父亲是一个阴气十足的产卵鱼，产下一堆孩子。

23.在西班牙印第安人居住的某一省份，男人只允许在40岁以后结婚，而姑娘却可以10岁就结婚。[75]

24.要是一个贵族只有35岁，就给一个20岁的儿子让路，这也未免太操之过急了吧：他还能在军队远征中或在其君主的宫廷里赢得声望。他需要有自己的钱；他可以让他儿子分上一份但不能忘了他自己。这种人可准确无误地说出父亲们常挂在嘴边的话：“我不希望在我离开人世之前被剥得精光。”可是，父亲随着岁数的增加，疾病缠身使他身体变垮，体弱多病使其不再参加社交，如果他念念不忘一大堆的财产，他就是与自己和家人都过不去。要是他精明狡猾的话，他不想有被剥得精光后离开人世的那一天——不要剥到衬衫，留下既漂亮又暖和的浴袍。他对剩下的辉煌已经没有更多作用了：他应该将一切财富作为礼物送给那些按自然法则应该归属的人。

25.正确的做法是，按照自然法则，他应该让子女使用他被自然剥夺的东西：否则他的态度必然就有一种恶意与妒忌的成分。查理五世皇帝摆出的最好姿态就是，在模仿某些古代与他同级别的当政者中他认识到：理性清楚地命令我们，当衣服加重负担而妨碍到我们时，那就把它们脱掉；当我们的双腿无力支撑我们行走时，那就去死。一旦他开始感觉体力不支，体能不足，无法继续进行与他挣来的荣誉相关的事情时，他就得将财产、头衔和权力移交给儿子：

聪明足以为那匹疲倦的老马解下马具，

以免气喘吁吁地而马失前蹄让人取笑。[76]

26.这种无法及时意识到人有缺陷，也无法意识到老年自然使身体和精力极度衰落的缺陷——依我看，身体和精力一样衰落，除非精力事实上占有较大的份额——毁了世上多少伟人的一世英名。我一生见过并且熟知当朝执政的伟人，他们明显从原来的身强力壮到后来的惊人衰退，我知道这种情形是从他们在鼎盛时期声名显赫开始的。为了他们的荣誉，我总是衷心希望他们隐退，卸下公务与军务的担子，这种担子再也不是他们所要肩负的了。

27.曾经有一个贵族，我过去常常去他家，他是个鳏夫，年事已高，可仍旧精力充沛。他有几个女儿都出嫁了，一个儿子已经到了一定年纪可以参与社会活动，因此他的房子负担起了大量的支出，还要接待相当多的来客；这让他一点也高兴不起来，不仅是由于担心经济问题，更多是这把年纪的他，还得接受一种与我们迥然不同的生活方式。有一天，我自以为斗胆地跟他说，如果他能为年轻人腾出空间，把他的主要住宅交给儿子（因为它是唯一家具设备齐全的住宅），然后回到邻近自家的庄园，在那儿没人打扰他的休息，因为，鉴于孩子们的情况，没有其他办法能让他避免我们年轻人不适宜的陪伴。他采纳了我的建议，也很喜欢这样的生活。

28.这并不是说，我们应该把我们财产权当作一件具有约束力的礼物，而不能反悔。我现在够老了，足以扮演这样的角色，可以让年轻人使用我的房子和财产，不过如果他们给我惹麻烦的话我可以随时收回我的承诺。之所以我得让他们拥有房子和财产的使用权，是因为它们不再给予我快乐，可我得保留我所希望拥有的对家庭事务的权威，因为我总认为，对一位老父亲而言，培养他的子女管理家务事准是一份极大的幸福；那么他可以在他一生中看他们如何做事，并针对这些事情以他的亲身经历给予他们建议和指导，为把过往的荣誉和房子的安排交到继承人手中亲自作准备，对他们未来的作为寄予希望。

29.为了这件事，我不想回避与他们交往；我希望尽可能在我年纪允许的情况下，亲近他们，以便观察他们，多分享他们的欢乐和喜悦。即使我并不参与他们的生活（因为我无法做到和他们一起生活却又不令我们的交往受阻，由于我那令人沮丧的年龄和压垮我的病痛——同时也不被迫改变我自己的原则和习惯），我希望至少生活在我房子的附近以接近他们——不必太讲究，而是最舒适地接近。（正如几年前我所看到的那样）并不是每任圣伊莱尔德普瓦捷的院长，在他悲伤烦心的影响下都落到这种孤独的地步，以至于当我走进他的房间时，他已经22年从未迈出房间一步；然而，除他胃部风湿病痛发作之外，他仍旧可以自由自在、舒适悠闲地走动。他甚至几乎不让任何人进去看他，哪怕一周一次；除给他送食品的贴身男仆每天只进出一次外，他始终都是一个人闭门待在那个房间里。他唯一的工作就是室内走动，读一本书（因为他有点偏好文学），固执地决定就要在这样的环境中告老——不久之后，他就是这样去世的。

30.我总试图与子女建立种种温和的关系，以此在他们内心激起一种对我主动的爱和真实的感情——某种在天性善良的子女身上容易得到的东西；当然，如果他们最终成了野蛮的畜牲（我们这个年代盛产这样的畜牲），那么你必然要恨他们，就像这样躲开他们。

31.我反对禁止子女叫“父亲”，却让他们使用别的更为恭敬的称呼的风俗，好像大自然没有给我们的威信提供足够的证明。我们将万能之神称为父亲，却蔑视让自己的孩子用此称呼我们。

32.不公平，甚至疯狂的是，以成天皱着眉头来表现严苛、蔑视的方式剥夺成年子女与他们父亲的亲密关系，并以此希望让他们害怕父亲并顺从父亲。这简直是一种徒劳无功的闹剧，使父亲令子女生厌作呕；更糟的是，还使父亲变得荒谬可笑。因为他们的子女充满着青春活力，享受世上欢乐；他们以嘲笑的态度面对一个男人凶猛残暴的表情，不难想象，在这种男人的血管或心脏里没留下一滴父子之情的血液——子女们只是把父亲当作亚麻田里的稻草人看待！纵然我能让自己令人敬畏，我也宁愿让自己受人爱戴。

33.人到老年毛病多多，体弱无力；年老体迈遭到轻视，获得的最大恩赐却是家人的爱，老年的双臂不再令人害怕，再也指挥不动家人了。

34.我认识一个人，他年轻时飞扬跋扈。现在他年事渐高，尽管试图努力接受年老的事实，可他还是扇人巴掌，咬伤别人，发誓诅咒——简直法国脾气最火爆的大老爷；他小心翼翼、谨慎防范，可这都是他家人串通欺瞒的闹剧；家里人随意取用他最好的谷仓、地窖、甚至钱包里的东西：尽管他把钥匙都放在小袋子里，这袋子对他来说比眼珠子还亲。他乐于保持节俭，餐饭简单，而在他住宅里不同的秘密地方，都在挥霍、赌博，把他的怒气和小气当笑话讲。每个人都用警戒的眼神看他。如果某个不幸的仆人碰巧忠实于他，他会立刻向这个下人投去怀疑的目光——这是老年人常有的毛病。这人不知多少次对我夸口说他牢牢掌管着家庭，清楚地关注着他的家务事，家人对他服服帖帖，毕恭毕敬。

只是很多事他不知道！[77]

在我的熟人当中，没人比他拥有更多天赋和才能，还有律己品质，他却像失败地回到了孩提时代。这就是我把他从几个我所知道的例子中挑选出来的原因所在。

35.这个例子可能会引起一场学术辩论：像他现在这种状况是好是坏。在他面前，一切东西都得服从他；他在家里耍威风岂不是白耍：因为不曾有家人跟他作对；他们相信他所说的，可对他是既害怕又尊重，正如他期望的那样！要是他辞退一个仆人，仆人得立刻卷铺盖走人——只是不出现在他的眼前而已。老人家就是这么步履蹒跚，思维混乱，以至于这个贴身男仆一整年生活在房子里，履行其职责，甚至都没有引起他的注意。在适当的时候，从远方寄来一封信，这是一封令人同情的信，一封表示顺从的信，信中充满着种种允诺：将来一定要做得更好；这个贴身男仆那时那刻发现老人家回心转意，又开始表现出赞赏的态度。

36.这个贵族要寄信，不合家里人心意就被扣下。他们隐瞒起这封信，之后有时编造理由以解释没有回音或回信。因为外来的信不会先到他的手里，所以他只看到他适合知道的信。如果他碰巧手里拿着信的话，他总要人把信念给他听，这样家人就当场编造一些谎言：有人写信骂他，也假装某人请求他原谅。简而言之，他看到的关于自己的事都是制造出来的假象，他们之所以会这样做，是因为不想让他发脾气恼火。

37.虽以不同的借口，可都为达到同样的目的，我见过相当多家庭以这种方式长期稳定地运转。

38.妻子总是跟丈夫意见不合。前者为了跟后者闹矛盾抓住任何的托词；而任何的借口都被当作充足的正当理由。我认识一个人，她过去常常窃取丈夫的批发货物——她跟她的忏悔神父说：“这都是为了能给予更多的施舍。”（能信任这么个信教的挥霍者么！）不管她们丈夫同意给予什么，都不称心，必须或以诡计或以暴力僭取，这么做总不光明正大。就像我所想起的情况一样，当她们代表子女行动起来反对某个可怜的老头子时，她们就抓住这个借口，得意洋洋地发泄一通情感，好像她们都是奴隶，准备随时共同密谋反对丈夫的家政大权。如果子女是朝气蓬勃的男孩和成年人，那么母亲就会联合起他们，威逼利诱笼络管家、会计和其他人。

39.没妻子又没孩子的老头儿较不容易遭此种不幸，一旦遭遇就会更为残酷和辱没尊严。卡托老人在他那个时代早已说过：“有那么多的贴身男仆，就有那么多的敌人。”假如他那个年代的纯真与我们这个年代相比中间已经有一道难以填平的沟壑，我们就得考虑一下他岂不是在告诫我们：妻子、儿子和贴身男仆都是“那么多的敌人”。

40.衰老提供给我们一份份甜蜜的礼物，包括漫不经心、无知和不知上当受骗，这倒是一件好事。如果我们真要抵抗的话，尤其是现在当解决我们争端的法官通常都站在子女——以及被收买的人——那一边时，在我们身上又会发生什么呢？

41.欺骗行为可能逃得过我的视线，但是我极易上当受骗的德行却逃不过我自己的视线。能够将自己可怜的晚年托付给朋友的人真是三生有幸。我们会一直念叨朋友的好处，这种益处跟以契约为基础的亲情关系有着天壤之别！即使是我在畜牲之间所看到的朋友的对手，我也会向这种对手表示多么心悦诚服的尊敬啊！曾经体会过朋友的好处对我而言是好还是坏呢？肯定是好的。我对他的哀悼使我感到安慰和荣耀。能为他举行葬礼不是生命中一件无比虔诚、令人愉快的事吗？有任何得到的快乐可以与这失去的快乐相媲美吗？我已经决定让自己的思想变得专注而僵化，紧抱这种观念不放。

42.别人可能会骗我，可至少我不会自欺欺人地认为我能保护自己而不受别人欺骗；我也不会为想方设法使自己能这样做而绞尽脑汁。我只有在内心——不是在令人不安的、喧嚣的好奇中，而是在娱乐和坚持中——才能找到这类不忠行为的对策。每当我听说某些人处在这种状况时，我不关心他，而立马将目光转向自己以看一看我是怎么做的。触动他的每件事也都会触动我。发生在他身上的事是一次告诫，一次警报。每一天，每一时刻，我们说起别人的事，那些事情本应更可能发生在我们身上，如果我们学会扩展思路和反省自己的话。同样，许多作家为还击进攻者猛冲出来，将矛掷向敌人，这些矛可能正好被掷回，投中他们。作家们就是以这种方式来捍卫自己，然而自己却受到了伤害。

43.当元帅德·蒙吕克先生生前跟我说起他儿子（一个真正勇敢的、前途极有希望的绅士，死在马德拉群岛上）的失利时，除了深深的后悔，他所感到的忧伤和心碎源自他觉得从未对儿子流露过自己的心思，也觉得失去了认识和品味儿子心意的机会，所有这些都因为他想要显露出一个父亲的威严；他从未告诉过儿子，他对儿子那无尽的爱，也从未告诉儿子，他对儿子的品德有着多么高的评价。他说过：“可怜的儿子从我身上看到的一切，就是一张皱着眉头、满不在乎的脸；他死了，执信我不会爱他也不会给他应得的评价。为了他而存在我心里那份特殊的爱，我怀着这份爱的存在又为了谁！他是不是还没有能够从这份爱中体味到乐趣，也感觉不到所有充满感恩的亲情？我强迫自己，折磨自己，一直戴着这副愚蠢的假面具，从而失去了与儿子相依为命的天伦之乐——也失去了儿子的情谊，这种情谊对我必然变得冷淡：除了粗暴外，他从未从我这儿得到过什么东西；除了一张残暴的面孔外，他也从未从我这里了解到什么。”

44.我感觉这种悲伤是合情合理的、应该珍藏的：因为我从经验中充分认识到，当我们失去我们的所爱时，没有什么安慰比认识到记得告诉他们一切、享受与他们最完美最纯粹的沟通来得更加甜蜜。

45.我尽可能多地对我的家人敞开心扉，我充分准备好告诉他们或任何其他人，我打算对他们做什么，以及我对他们的评价是什么。我要赶紧展现自我，让别人认识自己，因为我不想他们因我而受任何方式的误导。

46.据恺撒说，在我们古代高卢人的特别习俗中有以下这么一条：儿子不出现在他们父亲面前，也从不敢跟父亲一起出现在大庭广众，直到他们开始携带武器为止，仿佛表明那时才是父亲与儿子的关系亲密无间的时候。[78]

47.然而，对这个时代我所见过对父亲式的谨慎的另一诟病是，当父亲的不但不满足于在他们的漫长一生中剥夺了子女们财产的自然份额，还在他们死后，将管理一切财产的权力留给寡妇，随他们高兴任意处置这些财产。我所认识的一个封建领主（王国最高级别的官员中），他每年可有望合法得到价值500英担的财产：然而50岁时在债务缠身的打击下，在还应该活着的时候他却死了，而他母亲尽管年事已高，可按他80岁寿终的父亲的遗嘱，她仍然享有全部财产的权利。

48.对我来说，这决不合乎情理。

49.尽管如此，我还是无法明白，一个事业兴旺发达的人去追求一个以大办嫁妆为由而增加其负担的女子对他有多大的好处：没有比受外债约束对一个家庭来说更具毁灭性。我的先辈都遵循这条极其适合他们的训诫；我也如此。

50.然而，那些警告我不要娶富婆的人，是由于恐惧她们可能对我们来说承担更少的义务却又更难搞定，但那些人因为他们无聊猜测反而错失了好事一桩。如果女人不讲道理，那么第一次强词夺理同第二次强词夺理一样让她不用付出代价。这样的女人大错特错时，她们会对自己格外满意；而对好女人来说，她们越富有就越和蔼可亲，就像美丽的女人更甘心情愿保持贞节一样。

51.让母亲掌管家务直到儿子达到足以承担家庭责任的法定年龄为止，这是合情合理的；可如果（考虑到女性的一般弱点）儿子们一旦达到法定承担家庭责任的年龄就比自己的妻子更聪明能干，那么父亲就没把他们教育好。不过，让母亲依赖儿子的意愿，这总是更别扭。儿子应该慷慨地赡养母亲，根据她们的家庭和年龄条件来维持她们的生活状况，特别是由于需求或贫困使得她们比男性更难以忍受：这副沉重的担子应该由儿子承担，而不应该由母亲。

52.总的来说，当我们去世时，分享我们财产最佳的办法是（我相信）遵循一般地方法规。法律比我们想得更为周全，所以让法律作出错误的选择比我们自己鲁莽冒险地这样做要来得好。财产并不真正属于我们个人，因为我们离开人世时，民法有权指定继承人。即使我们也有某种考虑，我认为，要证明我们剥夺任何人天生拥有的财产权，以及普通法律规定他可以拥有的东西，这要拿出十分明确的理由；使财产的归属变得反复无常，随心所欲，这肯定是对自由不合理的滥用。

53.命运是友好的，给我种种可能引导我因普法的规定而改变偏好的机会。我认识一些人，要是忠贞不渝地为他们效劳，那肯定是浪费时光：一言不慎可能抹杀十年功名。在他们离世之际，任何会对他们阿谀奉承的人确实侥幸！俗话说最后一勺舀得多：那并不是最经常最善意的关心，而是新近、眼前正做着的服务。

54.有些人把意志当作鞭子和胡萝卜来利用，以奖惩可能声称对遗产感兴趣的那些人的每一举动。但是，这是一个长期的问题；这一问题极为重大，不能时时加以改变：聪明的人能一劳永逸地解决这一问题——并且尊重公众合理的风俗习惯。

55.我们太偏爱男性的继承权；想到姓氏荒谬的亘古不变，也太过妄测小男孩的未来。有人可能轻易对我做过不公平的事，叫我靠一边去，因为不论人家教我做智力训练还是身体训练，我比我任何兄弟（实际上比我这个地方的所有小孩）都更不管用、更迟钝、更不愿学习。占卜常常欺取我们的信任而妨碍我们的继承，在此基础上的选择无不是一种疯狂的举动。如果我们能永远打破这种陈规陋习，并且纠正靠命运去选择继承人，那就可能不用考虑某些明显的身体残疾——终身残疾和不可医治的那类残疾——这一点在我们当中那些对美推崇备至的人看来是极其有害的。

56.柏拉图的立法者和公民之间有过一次愉快的对话，这样的对话可能令我这几页熠熠生辉：“什么！”感觉他们的末日即将来临后，他们便说：“我们就不能随意把自己的财产遗赠给什么人？多么残酷啊！上帝，我们高兴给得较多还是给得较少，都取决于继承人在我们的家务中、在我们生病中、在我们年老时如何赡养我们，这难道不合法！”立法者作出这样的回答：“我尊敬的朋友，你们肯定很快就会去世，所以你们中的任何人都难以‘了解自己’（根据特尔斐的神谕）而且也难以了解什么是你的。我制定法律，并且坚持认为你并不属于你自己，你所享有的东西其实也不属于你自己。你和你的财产属于你的家庭，过去是这样，将来也是这样。我还想说的是，你的家庭和你的财产都属于共和国。因而，如果在你生病中或在老年时，某个奉承者试图说服你立不公正的遗嘱（或者如果你一发脾气而为之），我会阻止。出于对我们城市和你的家庭的普遍关心的尊重，我会制定法律，以便将个人利益必须合理服从大众利益的事公之于众。去吧，静静地、甘心情愿地到人类需要召唤你去的地方吧。我对所有的东西一视同仁，而且我通常保护所有的人，我也会保护你去世后所遗留下的财产。”[79]

57.还是言归正传吧。然而，女人无论如何不应该控制男人，而只应该自然掌握为母之道——除了对脾气暴躁而屈从女人的人的惩处，这在我看来是对的；可这并不适用于老太太，这是我们现在讨论的主题。正是这一事实的明确思考才使我们制订和维护继承法——但是没人曾见过这条法律——这种法律剥夺女性继承王位；尽管命运给予某些地方的权威胜过其他地方，可世界上几乎不存在像在这里一样法律条文不被引用的司法判断，也没得到理性的批准。

58.将我们对继承权的监管交由妻子们判断，并由她们在我们的儿子中作出选择是件危险的事情。这无论怎么说都是不合理的、怪诞荒谬的，因为她们经历怀孕时那些痛苦的滋味和身体的渴望都永远存在于她们心灵中。她们常常关注最柔弱的，或者倾注心力在那些（如果她们有的话）还环抱着她们脖子的那些小东西。因为女性没有足够的推理能力，能根据事物优点对其选择和采纳，所以她们任由自己被引向唯有自然印象在起作用的地方——就像动物一样，只认还在吃奶的幼崽。

59.顺便说一下，经验清楚地向我们表明，我们如此重视的自然之爱根基很浅。为了一小笔钱，我们每天从女人的怀里拽出她们的孩子，让她们来看管我们的孩子。我们让她们把她们的婴儿托给某个恶劣的奶妈，而我们却不愿把自己的孩子托给这种奶妈，也不愿把自己的孩子托给雌山羊；那么，无论这样做对她们可能有什么伤害，我们不但禁止她们给她们的孩子喂奶，而且还不准她们照顾她们的孩子；她们必须全力以赴为我们的孩子服务。到那时我们便明白，在大多数情况下，习俗产生一种比自然的爱更令人困惑的私爱；她们对那些养子的生存比对她们亲生子女的生存更加忧心忡忡。

60.我之所以提到雌山羊，是因为当我的居住地的农妇无法给自己的婴儿喂奶时，就召唤山羊来帮忙；我现在有两个男仆，他们吃母奶决不超过一周。这些雌山羊从一开始就被饲养用来哺育人类的孩子；它们识别得出孩子开始哭泣的声音然后马上跑过来。它们拒绝给其他小孩喂奶，只喂正在喂养的那个。这个小孩对另一只雌山羊也同样拒绝。有一天，我看见一个失去自己的雌山羊的婴儿，父亲只能从邻居那儿借了一只：这孩子拒绝吃奶，然后就死了，当然是死于饥饿。

61.牲畜就跟我们一样轻易贬低母爱，并使母爱变得不纯洁。

62.希罗多德讲述过利比亚的某一地区，那里的男人不加选择地跟女人躺在一起，可一旦小孩会蹒跚学步，他就能在人群中认出自己的父亲，自然的本能引导他迈出第一串脚步。[80]但我相信常常会出差错。

63.现在，一旦我们考虑这一事实：爱自己的孩子只是因为我们生了他们，并把他们称为第二自我，我们便会明白，我们还从自己身上孕育出某些丝毫不逊色的东西。我们在自己灵魂中所产生的东西——我们思想的产物以及我们才智的产物——是比身体更加高贵，也是比我们自己更加纯洁的产物。在其生长过程中，我们既当爹又当娘；这些“孩子们”让我们付出昂贵的代价，而如果它们有什么好处的话，就是给我们带来更多的荣誉。就其他孩子而言，他们的优良品质更多地属于他们自己，而不属于我们：我们的作用只占极少的分量；但是，至于这些孩子，他们的高雅、价值和美丽都属于我们。由于这种原因，他们跟我们更像是从同一个模子出来，与我们心心相印。柏拉图补充说，这样的孩子是不朽的，并使其父亲永生——正如在吕库尔戈斯、梭伦和米诺斯这些例子中，他们的孩子甚至将他们变成了神。[81]

64.由于我们的历史书籍充满了一般父爱的范例，所以在我看来，再去引用些别的什么例子就不合适了。

65.特里卡的好主教赫利奥多洛斯，宁愿放弃如此可敬的、收入不菲的、庄严尊贵的主教职位，而不愿毁掉他的“女儿”，她现在依然还活着——她是一个漂亮的姑娘，不过在着装方面，比神父的女儿可能更讲究更艳丽了点——并且很妖治。

66.在古罗马，有一个骁勇善战的达官显人，名叫拉宾努斯；在他所有的能力中，他擅长每一类文学；我想，他是那个老拉宾努斯的儿子。老拉宾努斯是高卢战争中最重要的一位将领，先是为恺撒效劳，随后全力投靠庞培大帝，并为庞培大帝英勇奋战，直到恺撒在西班牙击败他为止。有些人嫉妒我现在所提到的小拉宾努斯；他大概在朝臣中也有仇敌，并且由于自己的直率和继承父亲对暴政的天生敌意，他特别受到当代君主的喜爱，这些我相信给他的书籍和写作增添了色彩。他的敌人在古罗马行政官面前告发了他，并且还给他定了罪名，同时命令将他已经出版的几本书焚毁。这就是书籍和博学引发死刑的先例；这种死刑随后被运用在罗马其他几个案例中。我们没有足够的手段和理由去实施酷刑，除非我们能让酷刑本身关注那些已经被大自然豁免了任何形式痛感的东西，例如我们的声誉和我们思想的产物；除非我们把对身体的体罚折磨放在缪斯女神的教义和法典上进行。

67.拉宾努斯无法忍受如此的失落，也无法忍受比他所深爱的孩子们活得更长；他把自己活活监禁在家中地窖，躺在垃圾上；在那儿他为自己的死亡和埋葬作好准备。人们难以发现还有什么父爱会比这样的父爱更加动人。当他那位能言善辩的朋友凯西欧斯·西弗勒斯看到那些书被焚烧时，他大声喊道，他也应该跟那些书籍一起被活烧，因为在他的记忆中，他深深珍藏着书中的内容。

68.类似的不幸也发生在杰龙提斯·克得斯身上，他因在其书中称赞布鲁特斯和凯西欧斯遭到指控。那个专横、恶劣、腐败的上议院（堪比底波里斯更坏的主人）指责他的作品是火葬用的柴堆：这使得他十分高兴有自己的书籍相伴，因为书籍焚毁时，他也绝食身亡了。

69.卢坎是个好人，却遭到那个无赖尼禄的谴责；在卢坎生命的最后一刻，当大量的血从他血管里喷涌而出时（他鞭打医生命令他们将他杀死），当他的手脚已经冰凉、心脏开始渐渐变冷时，他记起的最后一件事就是他《内战记》里的诗句；他背诵这几句诗，当他念到最后几个词时，他与诗句一道离开人间。这不是在向他的孩子们作父亲般深情的告别吗？这岂不等于当我们去世时我们为孩子所留下的悼别和亲切的拥抱吗？这岂不是我们生命结束前回想起那些我们生前拥有过的、最亲切的往事的自然本能结果吗？

70.听说伊壁鸠鲁被严重的疝气发作折磨得卧床等死时，他只是在他传授给世人的哲学之美中找到安慰；[82]我们是否应该相信，他曾在那些出身名门、受过良好教育的孩子们身上（如果他曾经有过）找到等同于他在自己所创作的丰富作品中找到的快乐呢？如果他已经有过选择，在死后不是留下畸形的残疾小孩，就是一本愚蠢不得体的书——并非指他一个而是所有和他类似的贤人——那么他宁愿承受第一种悲剧，不选择第二种。

71.如果某人强迫圣奥古斯都不是杀死自己的孩子（假使他有孩子），就是毁掉自己的作品（我们的宗教从中受益匪浅），那么他宁愿杀死孩子。可能这个例子对圣奥古斯都有些不敬。

72.我根本不能肯定，比起跟我妻子，我是否更愿意与缪斯女神生下一个健康完整的儿子。至于我头脑中浮现的这个孩子，我会像对待自己亲骨肉所做的那样，给他的东西我会无条件地给他，决不反悔；虽然我已做了这么一点好事，可是他不再由我处置；他可能知道许多我不再知道的事，他也可能记得连我自己都忘了的事；如有求于他的帮助，那好像向一个陌生人求助。我比他聪明，但他比我现在富有。

73.热爱诗歌的人，比起做罗马第一美少年的父亲，更满足于做《埃涅阿斯记》的父亲，很难说失去其中一个比失去另一个更可容忍。因为据亚里士多德说，在所有艺术家中最钟情于他的作品的就是诗人。[83]

74.难以置信的是，伊巴密浓达（他自夸他的诗歌是由两个“女儿”构成，这两个女儿总有一天会给她们父亲带来荣誉——他意指他两次战胜斯巴达人的伟大胜利）同意用两次胜利来交换两个全希腊最美丽的女儿；亚历山大和恺撒曾经希望他们能放弃他们在战争中立下的丰功伟绩，以拥有儿子和继承人的快乐作为回报，无论那些功绩多完美多伟大；实际上，我真的很怀疑，菲迪亚斯或其他杰出的雕刻家，喜欢跟亲生子女相处，胜过按照艺术法则长期精心制作的雕塑杰作。

75.至于那些极端疯狂的感情，有时激怒了对女儿充满爱的父亲们，有时也激怒了对儿子充满爱的母亲，类似的感情在其他父母身上也能找到：皮革马力翁的传说可以佐证，他雕刻了那座盖世无双的美女塑像，绝望地沉迷于对自己作品的疯狂爱恋中，神将美女复活：

他抚摸象牙塑像；

它开始变软；

它的坚硬消失了，

它在他的手中就范。[84]

论适度

1.好像我们触摸什么都会传染破坏：本身漂亮的好东西一经我们处理就变得腐烂恶化。我们甚至以这样的方式——如果我们太紧太用力地把美德紧抱在怀里，我们的行为就会使美德变得邪恶——握住美德。那些说美德不会过度（倘若美德过度，那么美德就不再是美德了）的人只不过是在玩弄文字游戏罢了。

疯狂之名出自圣人，而不公正之名出自公正，

若在美德本身后面努力过了头，他们连现在都不如。[85]

这是从哲学的角度所进行的一种仔细观察：人们可以既十分喜爱美德，又过度公正。上帝的话非常切中这种偏见：“别聪明过度，可你们要清醒明智。”[86]

2.我在大贵族中见过一位，为表现出虔诚向教，其做法超过了所有相同社会等级的人，从而伤害了自己的宗教名誉。[87]

3.我喜欢温和适度的性情。甚至当对做好事表现出一种不适度的热情时，即使不冒犯我，还是令我感到震惊，不知说什么好。帕乌撒尼亚斯的母亲（她是第一个控告，也是第一个用筑墙石砸死自己儿子的人）和卜斯杜缪斯（这个独裁者因为儿子年轻气盛，擅自冲在部队前面，成功打入敌人，却杀了儿子）似乎对我而言都不正常；他们好像很古怪。[88]我既不喜欢劝告也不喜欢仿效如此野蛮代价昂贵的美德：把箭射偏的弓箭手跟脱靶的弓箭手都一样没有射中目标；猛地陷入一片漆黑的地方和突然走近一股强光都让我的眼睛不适。

4在柏拉图的著作中，[89]卡里克利斯说过，哲学在其两个极端都是有害的；他劝我们不要超过有益的限度去钻研哲学：适度接受哲学才会既愉快又有益，不然最终可能导致一个人变得邪恶野蛮，变得蔑视宗教和公认的律法，成为社交的敌人，成为我们人类快乐的敌人，在治理城市、帮助别人和自己上变得毫无价值——成了一个你可以随意打其两耳光的人。他说的话不假，因为哲学过度就束缚了我们与生倶来的自由，并且用不合时宜的细微差别使我们偏离了那条大自然为我们探索出的美丽舒适的大道。

5.我们对妻子怀有的感情是完全合法的：然而，神学却约束这种感情，并对它加以抑制。在圣托马斯·阿奎那[90]指责近亲结婚时所引用的理由中，我想我曾经读过以下的内容：危险的是，对这样的妻子的爱情可能并非适度的，因为如果他们之间这种婚姻感情是充实且完整的话（这种婚姻感情应该如此），你就会继续给它添加更多亲情。毫无疑问，这样一种过度行为会使丈夫的爱超出理智范围。

6.那些诸如神学和哲学主导人类道德的学科，把万事万物都纳入它们的关注范围：没有什么活动是私人的或神秘到可以逃离这些学科的关注或评判。只有初学者才会批评这些学科的自由倾向。它们就好比那种女人，在交欢时什么都可以让人看，却又因为太害羞而不敢给医生看。因此，站在这些学科的立场，我想把以下的东西教给丈夫们——换句话说，要是有什么人还过于热情，甚至他们所享受的和妻子躺在一起的快乐也会被指责，如果那些快乐没有保持在适度范围内的话；这样你会放纵过头，就好比犯了法。在房事中，最初的热情怂恿我们所做的那些无耻爱抚，不仅对我们的妻子不合适，而且施加在她们身上也有害于她们。至少她们从其他方面学来了无耻！当我们需要她们时，她们总是能满足的。就这点而言，我顺其自然，简单行事。

7.婚姻既是宗教又是虔诚的结合：这就是为什么我们得自婚姻的快乐必须是严肃的、节制的，并且与某种吸引力相结合；婚姻的感官刺激应该是既有几分明智又有几分责任。其主要目的是生育，所以就有一些人怀疑，当女人怀孕或变得老态龙钟时，当我们无望怀孕时，还追求性交是否妥当。在柏拉图看来，这就构成一种杀人罪。包括穆罕默德在内的所有人憎恨与怀孕的女人性交，也憎恨与仍然在月经期的女人性交。泽诺比雅为了怀孕接纳了丈夫；一旦怀上了，在她整个怀孕期她就让他在外自由行动；只是怀孕一结束，她才允许他再次性交。原有一场美好的、心灵高尚的婚姻等着你！[91]

8.原来就是从某位好色的诗人那儿，柏拉图听到了关于朱庇特有一天对他妻子如此用心接近的故事：朱庇特等不及她躺在床上，就把她按倒在地板上，却忘了他刚刚与其他神在天庭里刚刚作出的重大决定，还吹嘘他如此地享受这次性交，就像他初次背着她的父母夺去她的第一次一样。[92]

9.波斯国王们确实把他们的妻子作为宾客邀请到他们的欢庆宴会上，可是一旦他们喝得酒气冲天，情欲高涨，就把妻子送回宫邸，以便不让她们与自己有鱼水之欢以满足他们无度的胃口，反而派人去叫他们不需要尊重的其他女人。[93]

10.并不是每个人都能充分享受各种快乐和愉悦。伊巴密浓达有一个放荡不羁的男孩被关进监狱，佩洛披达斯为了达到自己的目的，恳求释放他；伊巴密浓达拒绝了他的要求，不过却应允一个同样请求释放他的妓女，还说释放他是帮情人的忙而不是给首领面子。当执政官索福克勒斯和伯里克利在一起时，索福克勒斯偶然看见一个英俊的青年走过，他对伯里克利说：“一个多么英俊的男孩啊！”伯里克利说：“对别人来说是很好，但对执政官来说不是，他必须手眼干净。”[94]

11.当王后埃略斯·维纳斯抱怨国王与其他女人干苟且之事时，他回答道：他是出于良心而为之，婚姻只是名誉和尊严的字眼，而不是放纵和淫乱色欲的代名词。我们教会的老作家们都体面地提到一个拒绝丈夫的妻子，因为她不希望成为他淫乱的对象。[95]

12.简而言之，快乐不管怎么合乎体统，当这种快乐变得过分放纵时，就难以不被诟病。

13.尽管严重，可难道人不是一种悲惨的动物？由于人的自然属性，人几乎无法感受到纯粹且彻底的单一的快乐，甚至还得通过辩论来减少那种快乐；人还嫌自己不够悲惨，非得使用艺术手段和各种努力以使自己的悲惨程度加深。

我们以艺术手段使命运的悲惨之路变得更惨。[96]

14.用来减损自己快乐的数量和质量时，人类的智慧真是一种愚昧的聪明——就像女人用勤勉和得体来塑造自己的艺术气质，可因为她们的梳子和化妆品让我们心烦，所以我们也很难去感受她们的勤勉和得体。如果我能创立起一种哲学学派，我肯定会另辟蹊径——更加自然的路，真正平坦方便的路。我可能已使自己强大到足以知道何时止步停下。

15.让我们思考一下这样的事实：那些治疗我们心灵与身体的医生，好像在一起密谋，找不到治疗我们的其他方案，也找不到医治疾病的良药，而只能让我们忍受折磨、疼痛和苦难。还要忍受警戒、斋戒、穿上毛衬衫和到远方孤寂的地方充军、终身监禁、灾祸以及其他苦难，不一而足。不过，只是如果苦难真的存在并造成苦涩的疼痛，如果发生在流放勒斯玻斯岛上的伽利奥身上那样的事不会降临：罗马人听说，他正在那里享受乐趣，惩罚打击的手段竟然变成一种快乐，就在享受快乐之际，他奉命回到家中与妻子团圆，而且只准待在家里，以便让他真切地从情感上体验到这样的惩罚。[97]因为如果一个人的健康和幸福都被斋戒搞得一团糟，或者如果他发现鱼比肉更美味可口，那么斋戒就不再是有益健康的良方，就像另一类医生开的药对喜欢服药的人没有什么药效一样。良药之所以起作用，就在于其苦口的滋味。通常习惯用大黄的体质会有损其药效；要治胃，良方就必须是某种能作用于胃的药物：在此“以毒攻毒”的常理不管用，因为在这种情况下只能以药治病。

16.这种观念有几分像所有宗教所普遍采纳的另一种老观念，这种老观念使我们以为我们可以通过谋杀和屠杀愉悦上帝和大自然。

17.甚至在我们的始祖时代，当阿姆拉斯征服伊斯特摩斯时，他为了父亲的魂灵让600个希腊青年献祭，让他们的血起到安抚的作用，为死者赎罪。[98]并且在我们现在新发现的土地上——跟我们的土地比起来那些是纯洁的处女地——处处都接受这种观念：他们的一切偶像都用人类的血来祭奠，并不缺乏令人恐惧的残酷例子。男人被活烧；当烧到一半时，他们被从火焰中拖出来，以便心脏和内脏可以挖出来；甚至包括妇女在内的其他人被活活剥皮：她们的皮肤，血淋淋的，被当作外套穿在其他人身上。还有不少关于坚贞的例子。为了那些即将牺牲做祭品的不幸者，老人、妇女和小孩提前好几天乞求施舍，以作为他们牺牲时的献金，并且亲自出现在大屠杀现场，与在场的所有人一起唱歌跳舞。墨西哥国王的特使们，为了让费尔南多·科特斯意识到他们主人的伟大，首先告诉科特斯：国号令有30个诸侯君主，每个君主都可以征召10万战士；他居住在天底下最坚固最美丽的城市。然后他们补充说：他每年都让5万男人为诸神献身。还真的听说国王与相邻的几大民族交战，不仅以此培养本国的年轻人，而且主要抓获战俘作为他的祭品。在另一个地方有个城市，在那儿他们以同时杀50个男人欢迎科特斯。我打算多说件事：科特斯征服了这些民族中的若干民族后，他们四处派信使找到他，并且寻求与其和解。他们以明智的方式给他提供以下三种礼物：“阁下，这里有5个奴隶；如果您是一个以血肉为食的残暴的神，那就把他们吃掉吧，我们将给您带更多的奴隶；如果您是一个善良的神，这里有羽毛和熏香；如果您是人，那就请您接受这些鸟和水果吧。”[99]

直到死才能断定是不是幸福

1.你必须始终等待一个人末日到来：

在他死亡和最后葬礼仪式前，

没有什么人能说他是不是幸福。[100]

孩子们都知道这样一个故事：克洛伊索斯国王被赛勒斯篡夺了王位，并被判处死刑，在等待执行时他大声呼喊：“梭伦啊，梭伦！”这事被报告到赛勒斯那儿，赛勒斯问他这喊的是什么意思。克洛伊索斯向他解释说，梭伦曾给过他一个警告：无论命运对人们可能怎么微笑，直到你看到他们经历生命的最后一天为止，他们才能称得上幸福，因为世事千变万化、各不相同，稍有变幻都难以料定。而现在他正以自己的生命为代价对其加以应验。这就是为什么阿格西劳斯给一个人——这人说波斯王是幸福的，因为波斯王年纪轻轻就继承这么一大笔财产——这样的回答：“是的，可当普里阿姆到了那把年纪时，他也没有不幸福。”[101]亚历山大大帝的后代，马其顿国王，在罗马却成了细木匠和代笔人；西西里岛的专制君主在科林斯却成了教书匠。庞培，大半个世界的征服者，一个统领三军的皇帝，却向埃及国王手下的一个小官员哀求，多活了五六个月的时间。在我们父辈的那个年代，米兰的第十个公爵路德维柯·斯福扎在意大利长期以来一直处于霸主地位，可人们却在罗锡城堡看着他作为囚犯死去——（最糟糕的是）他在那儿生活了十年之久。基督教帝国最伟大的国王遗孀，最美丽的皇后不也死在刽子手的刀下吗？[102]这样的例子不计其数。正是因为暴风骤雨似乎对着我们桀傲不驯的大楼的高顶勃然狂怒，也有天神妒忌凡间的大人物。

某种隐藏的力量显然推翻人们所做所为，

似要践踏辉煌的霸权和扈从坚韧的斧头，

与此同时，轻蔑嘲笑地将它们统揽手中。[103]

命运有时似乎正好埋伏在人生的最后一天，以展示其力量，这种力量将顷刻间推翻命运在数年间所建立的积累，让我们跟随拉贝里乌斯，并且大声喊出：“我活到这一天，是不该比我该有的寿命多活的一天。”[104]

2.梭伦的善意劝告可以用这种方式加以接受。可他是一个哲学家：至于这种情况，命运的眷顾和惩处谈不上幸福或不幸，显赫名声与高官重权实际上都是无关紧要的东西。所以，或许在我看来，他的期待超出这一点，他想告诉我们，人生的幸福（就像现在所做的一样，取决于天生高贵精神的安宁和满足，也取决于有规矩的人的决心和信心）决不可归因于任何人，直到我们已看到他在人生戏剧中的谢幕表演，这一表演无疑是最难的。在其余的演出中，他可能戴着演员的面具：那些精彩的哲学辩论可能只是做一做姿态；无论什么降临在我们头上，不可能马上就考验我们，还能让我们面不改色心不跳。可是，在死亡与毫无伪装的自我之间所表演的这最后一幕中，我们必须直截了当地说实话；我们必须在展示出心底真实的一面：

只有那时肺腑之言才真实。

撕掉那假面具：留下真实。[105]

这就是为何人生所有其他行为都必须在最后行动的试金石上磨砺。这块试金石就是主日，一切的审判日；它就是（一位古人说过）[106]评价我现在和过去一切岁月的一天。我的研究成果只有到盖棺才可定论。到那时，人们便会明白我的论点是否言由衷而发。

3.我注意到几个人，他们的死决定给他们的一生带来或好或坏的名声。庞培的岳父西比奥死得磊落，为他挽回人们一直以来对他很差的评价。当被问到在夏比利亚、伊菲克拉底和伊巴密浓达他自己三人中，哪一个最值得尊敬时，伊巴密浓达回答道：

“在作出这种评价之前，你必须看到我们都去世。”（的确，如果任何人想掂量伊巴密浓达的价值，而又不知道他生命结束时的荣誉和伟大，那么对他的评价肯定会大打折扣。）

4.在我所处的时代，在我所知道的最可恶、最声名狼藉的人当中，有那么三个人，他们虽各有各的令人厌恶的一面，可他们的死却规规矩矩，无处挑剔：上帝最大的快乐莫过如此。

5.有些人死得其所，死得幸运。我认识一个人[107]，他的生命线是朝着飞黄腾达的方向发展，可这条生命线突然断了；他死得如此灿烂辉煌，以至于在我看来，他崇高的目标因为没有实现而更加伟大，他提出了目标，壮志未酬，人们对他的景仰超过他的期望。当他倒下时，他超越了他的人生历程所渴求的权力和声誉。

6.当评价人的一生时，我始终看其生命是如何结束的：我对我自己生命的结束最为关心的一点是，生命应该有一个美好的结局——换句话说，以一种悄然平静的方式告别人世。

1
On friendship

1. I was watching an artist on my staff working on a painting when I felt a desire to emulate him. The finest place in the middle of a wall he selects for a picture to be executed to the best of his ability; then he fills up the empty spaces all round it with grotesques, which are fantastical paintings whose attractiveness consists merely in variety and novelty. And in truth what are these Essays if not monstrosities and grotesques botched together from a variety of limbs having no defined shape, with an order sequence and proportion which are purely fortuitous?

Desinit in piscem mulier formosa superne.

[A fair woman terminating in the tail of a fish.][〔1〕]

2. I can manage to reach the second stage of that painter but I fall short of the first and better one: my abilities cannot stretch so far as to venture to undertake a richly ornate picture, polished and fashioned according to the rules of art. So I decided to borrow a 'painting' from Etienne de La Boëtie, which will bring honour to the rest of the job: I mean the treatise to which he gave the title On Willing Slavery but which others, not knowing this, very appropriately baptised afresh as Against One. He wrote it, while still very young, as a kind of essay against tyrants in honour of freedom. It has long circulated among men of discretion-not without great and well-merited esteem, for it is a noble work, as solid as may be. Yet it is far from being the best he was capable of. If, at the age when I knew him when he was more mature, he had conceived a design such as mine and written down his thoughts, we would now see many choice works bringing us close to the glory of the Ancients; for, particularly where natural endowments are concerned, I know nobody who can compare with him. Yet nothing of his survives apart from this treatise-and even that is due to accident: I do not think he ever saw it again once he let go of it-and some Considerations on that Edict of January which our civil wars have made notorious: I may perhaps still find a place for it elsewhere. That is all I have been able to recover of his literary remains, I the heir to whom, with death on his lips, he so lovingly willed his books and his papers-apart from the slim volume of his works which I have had published already.

3. Yet I am particularly indebted to that treatise, because it first brought us together: it was shown to me long before I met him and first made me acquainted with his name; thus preparing for that loving-friendship between us which as long as it pleased God we fostered so perfect and so entire that it is certain that few such can even be read about, and no trace at all of it can be found among men of today. So many fortuitous circumstances are needed to make it, that it is already something if Fortune can achieve it once in three centuries. There seems to be nothing for which Nature has better prepared us than for fellowship-and Aristotle says that good lawgivers have shown more concern for friendship than for justice. Within a fellowship the peak of perfection consists in friendship; for all forms of it which are forged or fostered by pleasure or profit or by public or private necessity are so much the less beautiful and noble-and therefore so much the less 'friendship'-in that they bring in some purpose, end or fruition other than the friendship itself. Nor do those four ancient species of love conform to it: the natural, the social, the hospitable and the erotic.

4. From children to fathers it is more a matter of respect; friendship, being fostered by mutual confidences, cannot exist between them because of their excessive inequality; it might also interfere with their natural obligations: for all the secret thoughts of fathers cannot be shared with their children for fear of begetting an unbecoming intimacy; neither can those counsels and admonitions which constitute one of the principal obligations of friendship be offered by children to their fathers. There have been peoples where it was the custom for children to kill their fathers and others for fathers to kill their children to avoid the impediment which each can constitute for the other: one depends naturally on the downfall of the other.

5. There have been philosophers who held such natural bonds in contempt-witness Aristippus: when he was being pressed about the affection which he owed to his children since they had sprung from him, he began to spit, saying that that sprang from him too, and that we also engender lice and worms. And there was that other one whom Plutarch sought to reconcile with his brother but who retorted: 'He matters no more to me for coming out of the same hole.'

6. The name of brother is truly a fair one and full of love: that is why La Boëtie and I made a brotherhood of our alliance. But sharing out property or dividing it up, with the wealth of one becoming the poverty of the other, can wondrously melt and weaken the solder binding brothers together. Brothers have to progress and advance by driving along the same path in the same convoy: they needs must frequently bump and jostle against each other. Moreover, why should there be found between them that congruity and affinity which engender true and perfect friendship? Father and son can be of totally different complexions: so can brothers. 'He is my son, he is my kinsman, but he is wild, wicked or daft!' And to the extent that they are loving relationships commanded by the law and the bonds of nature, there is less of our own choice, less 'willing freedom'. Our 'willing freedom' produces nothing more properly its own than affection and loving-friendship. It is not that I have failed to assay all that the other kind can afford, having had the best father who ever was, and the most indulgent even into extreme old age, and coming as I do from a family renowned and exemplary from generation to generation in the matter of brotherly harmony:

et ipse

Notus in fratres animi paterni.

[And myself known for my fatherly concern for my brothers.][〔2〕]

7. You cannot compare with friendship the passion men feel for women, even though it is born of our own choice, nor can you put them in the same category. I must admit that the flames of passion-

neque enim est dea nescia nostri

Que dulcem curis miscet amaritiem

[for I am not unacquainted with that goddess who mingles sweet bitterness with love's cares][〔3〕]-

are more active, sharp and keen. But that fire is a rash one, fickle, fluctuating and variable; it is a feverish fire, subject to attacks and relapses, which only gets hold of a corner of us. The love of friends is a general universal warmth, temperate moreover and smooth, a warmth which is constant and at rest, all gentleness and evenness, having nothing sharp nor keen. What is more, sexual love is but a mad craving for something which escapes us:

Come segue la lepre il cacciatore

Al freddo, al caldo, alla montagna, al lito;

Ne piu l'estima poi che presa vede,

Et sol dietro a chi fugge affretta il piede.

[Like the hunter who chases the hare through heat and cold, o'er hill and dale, yet, once he has bagged it, he thinks nothing of it; only while it flees away does he pound after it.][〔4〕]

8. As soon as it enters the territory of friendship (where wills work together, that is) it languishes and grows faint. To enjoy it is to lose it: its end is in the body and therefore subject to satiety. Friendship on the contrary is enjoyed in proportion to our desire: since it is a matter of the mind, with our souls being purified by practising it, it can spring forth, be nourished and grow only when enjoyed. Far below such perfect friendship those fickle passions also once found a place in me-not to mention in La Boëtie, who confesses to all too many in his verses. And so those two emotions came into me, each one aware of the other but never to be compared, the first maintaining its course in a proud and lofty flight, scornfully watching the other racing along way down below.

9. As for marriage, apart from being a bargain where only the entrance is free (its duration being fettered and constrained, depending on things outside our will), it is a bargain struck for other purposes; within it you soon have to unsnarl hundreds of extraneous tangled ends, which are enough to break the thread of a living passion and to trouble its course, whereas in friendship there is no traffic or commerce but with itself. In addition, women are in truth not normally capable of responding to such familiarity and mutual confidence as sustain that holy bond of friendship, nor do their souls seem firm enough to withstand the clasp of a knot so lasting and so tightly drawn. And indeed if it were not for that, if it were possible to fashion such a relationship, willing and free, in which not only the souls had this full enjoyment but in which the bodies too shared in the union-where the whole human being was involved-it is certain that the loving-friendship would be more full and more abundant. But there is no example yet of woman attaining to it and by the common agreement of the Ancient schools of philosophy she is excluded from it.

10. And that alternative licence of the Greeks is rightly abhorrent to our manners; moreover since as they practised it it required a great disparity of age and divergence of favours between the lovers, it did not correspond either to that perfect union and congruity which we are seeking here. 'Quis est enim iste amor amicitiae? Cur neque deformem adolescentem quisquam amat, neque formosum senem?' [What is this 'friendship-love'? Why does nobody ever fall in love with a youth who is ugly or with a beautiful old man?][〔5〕] For even the portrayal of it by the Academy will not I think belie me when I say this about it: that the original frenzy inspired by Venus' son in the heart of the Lover towards the bloom of a tender youth (in which they allow all the excessive and passionate assaults which an immoderate ardour can produce) was simply based on physical beauty, a false image of generation in the body (for it could not have been based on the mind, which had yet to show itself, which was even then being born, too young to sprout); that if so mad a passion took hold of a base mind the means of pursuing it were riches, presents, favouritism in advancement to high office and such other base traffickings which the Academy condemned; if it lighted on a more noble mind its inducements were likewise more noble: instruction in philosophy; lessons teaching reverence for religion, obedience to the law and dying for the good of one's country; examples of valour, wisdom, justice, with the Lover striving to make himself worthy of acceptance by the graciousness and beauty of his soul (that of his body having long since faded) and hoping by this mental alliance to strike a more firm and durable match. When this suit produced its results-in due season (for while they did not require the Lover to devote time and discretion to this undertaking they strictly required it of the Beloved, since he had to reach a judgement about a kind of beauty which is internal, difficult to recognize and concealed from discovery)-there was then born in that Beloved the desire mentally to conceive through the medium of the beauty of the mind. For him this beauty was pre-eminent: that of the body, secondary and contingent-quite the opposite from the Lover. For this reason they held the Beloved in higher esteem and proved that the gods do so too; they severely rebuked the poet Aeschylus for having given, in the love of Achilles and Patroclus, the role of the Lover to Achilles, who was the fairest of all the Greeks, in the first verdure of unbearded youth.

11. Once this general communion had been established, with the more worthy aspect of it fulfilling its duties and predominating, they said that it produced fruits useful for private and public life; that it was the strength of those countries where it was the accepted custom and the main defence of right conduct and freedom-witness the loves of Hermodius and Aristogiton. That is why they call it sacred and divine. By their reckoning only the violence of tyrants and the baseness of the people are opposed to it. Yet when all is said and done the only point we can concede to the Academy is that it was a love-affair which ended in friendship-which conforms well enough to the Stoic definition of love: 'Amorem conatum esse amicitiae faciendae ex pulchritudinis specie.' [Love is the striving to establish friendship on the external signs of beauty.][〔6〕]

12. I now return to a kind of love more equable and more equitable: 'Omnino amicitiae, corroboratis jam confirmatisque ingeniis et aetatibus, judicandae sunt.' [Such only are to be considered friendships in which characters have been confirmed and strengthened with age.][〔7〕]

13. Moreover what we normally call friends and friendships are no more than acquaintances and familiar relationships bound by some chance or some suitability, by means of which our souls support each other. In the friendship which I am talking about, souls are mingled and confounded in so universal a blending that they efface the seam which joins them together so that it cannot be found. If you press me to say why I loved him, I feel that it cannot be expressed except by replying: 'Because it was him: because it was me.' Mediating this union there was, beyond all my reasoning, beyond all that I can say specifically about it, some inexplicable force of destiny.

14. We were seeking each other before we set eyes on each other-both because of the reports we each had heard (which made a more violent assault on our emotions than was reasonable from what they had said, and, I believe, because of some decree of Heaven: we embraced each other by repute, and, at our first meeting, which chanced to be at a great crowded town-festival, we discovered ourselves to be so seized by each other, so known to each other and so bound together that from then on none was so close as each was to the other. He wrote an excellent Latin Satire, which has been published, by which he defends and explains the suddenness of our relationship which so quickly reached perfection. Having so short a period to last, having begun so late (for we were both grown men-he more than a few years older than I)-it had no time to waste on following the pattern of those slacker ordinary friendships which require so much prudent foresight in long preliminary acquaintance. This friendship has had no ideal to follow other than itself; no comparison but with itself. There is no one particular consideration-nor two nor three nor four nor a thousand of them-but rather some inexplicable quintessence of them all mixed up together which, having captured my will, brought it to plunge into his and lose itself and which, having captured his will, brought it to plunge and lose itself in mine with an equal hunger and emulation. I say 'lose itself' in very truth; we kept nothing back for ourselves: nothing was his or mine.

15. In the presence of the Roman Consuls (who, after the condemnation of Tiberius Gracchus were prosecuting those who had been in his confidence) Laelius eventually asked Caius Blosius, the closest friend of Gracchus, how much he would have done for him. He replied: 'Anything.'-'What, anything?' Laelius continued: 'And what if he had ordered you to set fire to our temples?'-'He would never have asked me to,' retorted Blosius. 'But supposing he had,' Laelius added. 'Then I would have obeyed,' he replied.[〔8〕] Now if he really were so perfect a friend of Gracchus as history asserts, he had no business provoking the Consuls with that last rash assertion and ought never to have abandoned the certainty he had of the wishes of Gracchus. But those who condemn his reply as seditious do not fully understand the mystery of friendship and fail to accept the premiss that he had Gracchus' intentions in the pocket of his sleeve, both by his influence and by his knowledge. They were more friends than citizens; friends, more than friends or foes of their country or friends of ambition and civil strife. Having completely committed themselves to each other, they each completely held the reins of each other's desires; grant that this pair were guided by virtue and led by reason (without which it is impossible to harness them together) Blosius' reply is what it should have been. If their actions broke the traces, then they were, by my measure, neither friends of each other nor friends of themselves. Moreover that reply sounds no different than mine would be, if I were interrogated thus: 'If your will commanded you to kill your daughter would you kill her?' and I said that I would. For that is no witness that I would consent to do so, because I do not doubt what my will is, any more than I doubt the will of such a friend. All the arguments in the world have no power to dislodge me from the certainty which I have of the intentions and decisions of my friend. Not one of his actions could be set before me-no matter what it looked like-without my immediately discovering its motive. Our souls were yoked together in such unity, and contemplated each other with so ardent an affection, and with the same affection revealed each to each other right down to the very entrails, that not only did I know his mind as well as I knew my own but I would have entrusted myself to him with greater assurance than to myself.

16. Let nobody place those other common friendships in the same rank as this. I know about them-the most perfect of their kind-as well as anyone else, but I would advise you not to confound their rules: you would deceive yourself. In those other friendships you must proceed with wisdom and caution, keeping the reins in your hand: the bond is not so well tied that there is no reason to doubt it. 'Love a friend,' said Chilo, 'as though some day you must hate him: hate him, as though you must love him'.[〔9〕] That precept which is so detestable in that sovereign master-friendship is salutary in the practice of friendships which are common and customary, in relation to which you must employ that saying which Aristotle often repeated: 'O my friends, there is no friend!'[〔10〕]

17. In this noble relationship, the services and good turns which foster those other friendships do not even merit being taken into account: that is because of the total interfusion of our wills. For just as the friendly love I feel for myself is not increased-no matter what the Stoics may say-by any help I give myself in my need, and just as I feel no gratitude for any good turn I do to myself: so too the union of such friends, being truly perfect, leads them to lose any awareness of such services, to hate and to drive out from between them all terms of division and difference, such as good turn, duty, gratitude, request, thanks and the like. Everything is genuinely common to them both: their wills, goods, wives, children, honour and lives; their correspondence is that of one soul in bodies twain, according to that most apt definition of Aristotle's,[〔11〕] so they can neither lend nor give anything to each other. That is why those who make laws forbid gifts between husband and wife, so as to honour marriage with some imagined resemblance to that holy bond, wishing to infer by it that everything must belong to them both, so that there is nothing to divide or to split up between them. In the kind of friendship I am talking about, if it were possible for one to give to the other it is the one who received the benefaction who would lay an obligation on his companion. For each of them, more than anything else, is seeking the good of the other, so that the one who furnishes the means and the occasion is in fact the more generous, since he gives his friend the joy of performing for him what he most desires. When Diogenes the philosopher was short of money he did not say that he would ask his friends to give him some but to give him some back![〔12〕] And to show how this happens in practice I will cite an example-a unique one-from Antiquity.

18. Eudamidas, a Corinthian, had two friends: Charixenus, a Sicyonian, and Aretheus, also a Corinthian. As he happened to die in poverty, his two friends being rich, he made the following testament: 'To Aretheus I bequeath that he look after my mother and maintain her in her old age; to Charixenus, that he see that my daughter be married, providing her with the largest dowry he can; and if one of them should chance to die I appoint the survivor to substitute for him.' Those who first saw his will laughed at it; but, when those heirs learned of it, they accepted it with a unique joy. One of them, Charixenus, did die five days later; the possibility of substitution was thus opened in favour of Aretheus, and he looked after the mother with much care; then, of five hundred weight of silver in his possession, he gave two and a half for the marriage of his only daughter and two and a half for the daughter of Eudamidas, celebrating their weddings on the same day.[〔13〕]

19. This example is a most full one, save for one circumstance: there was more than one friend. For the perfect friendship which I am talking about is indivisible: each gives himself so entirely to his friend that he has nothing left to share with another: on the contrary, he grieves that he is not two-fold, three-fold or four-fold and that he does not have several souls, several wills, so that he could give them all to the one he loves.

20. Common friendships can be shared. In one friend one can love beauty; in another, affability; in another, generosity; in another, a fatherly affection; in another, a brotherly one; and so on. But in this friendship love takes possession of the soul and reigns there with full sovereign sway: that cannot possibly be duplicated. If two friends asked you to help them at the same time, which of them would you dash to? If they asked for conflicting favours, who would have the priority? If one entrusted to your silence something which it was useful for the other to know, how would you get out of that? The unique, highest friendship loosens all other bonds. That secret which I have sworn to reveal to no other, I can reveal without perjury to him who is not another: he is me. It is a great enough miracle for oneself to be redoubled: they do not realize how high a one it is when they talk of its being tripled. The uttermost cannot be matched. If anyone suggests that I can love each of two friends as much as the other, and that they can love each other and love me as much as I love them, he is turning into a plural, into a confraternity, that which is the most 'one', the most bound into one. One single example of it is moreover the rarest thing to find in the world.

21. The rest of that story conforms well what I was saying: for Eudamidas bestows a grace and favour on his friends when he makes use of them in his necessity. He left them heirs to his own generosity, which consists in putting into their hands the means of doing him good. And there is no doubt that the force of loving-friendship is more richly displayed in what he did than in what Aretheus did. To sum up, these are deeds which surpass the imagination of anyone who has not tasted them; they make me wondrously honour the reply of that young soldier when Cyrus inquired of him how much he would take for a horse which had enabled him to win the prize in the races: 'Would he sell it for a kingdom?'-'No, indeed, Sire; but I would willingly give it away to gain a friend, if I could find a man worthy of such an alliance.'[〔14〕] Not badly put, that, 'If I could find'; for you can easily find men fit for a superficial acquaintanceship. But for our kind, in which we are dealing with the innermost recesses of our minds with no reservations, it is certain that all of our motives must be pure and sure to perfection.

22. In those alliances which only get hold of us by one end, we need simply to provide against such flaws as specifically affect that end. It cannot matter to me what the religion of my doctor or my lawyer is: that consideration has nothing in common with the friendly services which they owe to me. And in such commerce as arises at home with my servants I act the same way: I make few inquiries about the chastity of my footman: I want to know if he is hard-working; I am less concerned by a mule-driver who gambles than by one who is an idiot, or by a cook who swears than by one who is incompetent. It is not my concern to tell the world how to behave (plenty of others do that) but how I behave in it:

Mihi sic usus est; tibi, ut opus est facto, face.

[This is what I do: do what serves you.][〔15〕]

For the intimate companionship of my table I choose the agreeable not the wise; in my bed, beauty comes before virtue; in social conversation, ability-even without integrity. And so on.

23. Just as that philosopher[〔16〕] playing with his children and riding astride a hobby-horse told the man who surprised him at it not to make comments before he had children of his own, judging that the emotions which would then arise in his soul would make him a good judge of such behaviour: so too I could wish that I were speaking to people who had assayed what I am talking about; but realizing how far removed from common practice is such a friendship-and how rare it is-I do not expect to find one good judge of it. For the very writings which Antiquity have left us on this subject seem weak to me compared to what I feel. In this case the very precepts of philosophy are surpassed by the results:

Nil ego contulerim jucundo sanus amico.

[Whilst I am in my right mind, there is nothing I will compare with a delightful friend.][〔17〕]

24. In Antiquity Menander pronounced a man to be happy if he had merely encountered the shadow of a friend.[〔18〕] He was certainly right to say so, especially if he had actually tasted friendship. For in truth if I compare all the rest of my life-although by the grace of God I have lived it sweetly and easily, exempt (save for the death of such a friend) from grievous affliction in full tranquillity of mind, contenting myself with the natural endowments which I was born with and not going about looking for others-if I compare it, I say, to those four years which it was vouchsafed to me to enjoy in the sweet companionship and fellowship of a man like that, it is but smoke and ashes, a night dark and dreary.

25. Since that day when I lost him,

quem semper acerbum,

Semper honoratum (sic, Dii, voluistis) habebo,

[which I shall ever hold bitter to me, though always honour (since the gods ordained it so),][〔19〕]

I merely drag wearily on. The very pleasures which are proffered me do not console me: they redouble my sorrow at his loss. In everything we were halves: I feel I am stealing his share from him:

Nec fas esse ulla me voluptate hic frui

Decrevi, tantisper dum ille abest meus particeps.

[Nor is it right for me to enjoy pleasures, I decided, while he who shared things with me is absent from me.][〔20〕]

I was already so used and accustomed to being, in everything, one of two, that I now feel I am no more than a half:

Illam meae si partem animae tulit

Maturior vis, quid moror altera,

Nec charus aeque, nec superstes

Integer? Ille dies utramque

Duxit ruinam.

[Since an untimely blow has borne away a part of my soul, why do I still linger on less dear, only partly surviving? That day was the downfall of us both.][〔21〕]

26. There is no deed nor thought in which I do not miss him-as he would have missed me; for just as he infinitely surpassed me in ability and virtue so did he do so in the offices of friendship:

Quis desiderio sit pudor aut modus

Tam chari capitis?...

O misero frater adempte mihi!

Omnia tecum una perierunt gaudia nostra,

Quae tuus in vita dulcis alebat amor.

Tu mea, tu moriens fregisti commoda, frater;

Tecum una tota est nostra sepulta anima,

Cujus ego interitu tota de mente fugavi

Haec studia atque omnes delicias animi.

Alloquar? audiero nunquam tua verba loquentem?

Nunquam ego te, vita frater amabilior,

Aspiciam posthac? At certe semper amabo.

[What shame or limit should there be to grief for one so dear? ...How wretched I am, having lost such a brother! With you died all our joys, which your sweet love fostered when you were alive. You, brother, have destroyed my happiness by your death: all my soul is buried with you. Because of your loss I have chased all thoughts from my mind and all pleasures from my soul...Shall I never speak to you, never hear you talking of what you have done? Shall I never see you again, my brother, dearer than life itself? But certainly I shall love you always.][〔22〕]

27. Let us hear a while this sixteen-year-old boy.

28. Having discovered that this work of his has since been published to an evil end by those who seek to disturb and change the state of our national polity without worrying whether they will make it better, and that they have set it among works of their own kidney, I have gone back on my decision to place it here. And so that the author's reputation should not be harmed among those who cannot know his opinions or his actions, I tell them that this subject was treated by him in his childhood purely as an exercise; it is a commonplace theme, pawed over in hundreds and hundreds of books. I have no doubt that he believed what he wrote, for he was too conscientious to tell untruths even in a light-hearted work. And I know, moreover, that if he had had the choice he would rather have been born in Venice than in Sarlat. Rightly so. But he had another maxim supremely imprinted upon his soul: to obey, and most scrupulously submit to, the laws under which he was born. There never was a better citizen, one more devoted to his country's peace or more opposed to the disturbances and novelties of his time. He would have used his abilities to snuff them out, not to provide materials to stir them up. The mould of his mind was cast on the model of centuries different from ours.

29. So instead of that serious work I will substitute another one, more gallant and more playful, which he wrote in the same season of his life.

NOTE

〔1〕　Horace, Ars poetica 4. (Poets can create monsters at will; say a fair maid with the tail of a fish, that is, a mermaid.)

〔2〕　Horace, Odes, II, ii, 6-7 (adapted to apply to Montaigne).

〔3〕　Catullus, Epigrams, LXVI, 17-18.

〔4〕　Ariosto, Orlando furioso, X, vii.

〔5〕　Cicero, Tusc. disput., IV, xxxiii, 70. (In Greek philosophical homosexuality the older man was the Lover; the younger, the Beloved, showed admiration, or gratitude for instruction.)

〔6〕　Cicero, Tusc. disput., IV, xxiv, 71.

〔7〕　Cicero, De amicitia, XX, 74.

〔8〕　Cicero, De amicitia, XI, 33-9.

〔9〕　Chilo's chilling judgement was normally attributed to Bias, one of the Seven Sages of Greece.

〔10〕　Erasmus, Apophthegmata, VII, Aristoteles Stagirites, XXVIII.

〔11〕　Erasmus, ibid., VII, Aristoteles Stagirites, XIX.

〔12〕　Erasmus, ibid., III, Diogenes Cynicus, LXXXII.

〔13〕　From Lucian of Samosata, Toxaris, or, On friendship, XXII.

〔14〕　Xenophon, Cyropaedia, VIII, iii, 270.

〔15〕　Terence, Heautontimorumenos, I, i, 28.

〔16〕　Agesilaus (Cf. Erasmus, Apophthegmata, I. Agesilaus, LXVIII).

〔17〕　Horace, Satires, I, v, 44.

〔18〕　Plutarch (tr. Amyot), De l'amitié fraternelle, 82C-D.

〔19〕　Virgil, Aeneid, V, 49-50.

〔20〕　Terence, Heautontimorumenos, I, I, 97-8.

〔21〕　Horace, Odes, II, xvii, 5-9.

〔22〕　Catullus, LXVIII, 20f.; LXV, 9f. (adapted).

2
That it is madness to judge the true and
the false from our own capacities

1. It is not perhaps without good reason that we attribute to simple-mindedness a readiness to believe anything and to ignorance the readiness to be convinced, for I think I was once taught that a belief is like an impression stamped on our soul: the softer and less resisting the soul, the easier it is to print anything on it: 'Ut necesse est lancem in libra ponderibus impositis deprimi, sic animum perspicuis cedere.' ['For just as a weight placed on a balance must weigh it down, so the mind must yield to clear evidence.'][〔1〕] The more empty a soul is and the less furnished with counterweights, the more easily its balance will be swayed under the force of its first convictions. That is why children, the common people, women and the sick are more readily led by the nose.

2. On the other hand there is a silly arrogance in continuing to disdain something and to condemn it as false just because it seems unlikely to us. That is a common vice among those who think their capacities are above the ordinary.

3. I used to do that once: if I heard tell of ghosts walking or of prophecies, enchantments, sorcery, or some other tale which I could not get my teeth into-

Somnia, terrores magicos, miracula, sagas,

Nocturnos lemures portentaque Thessala

[Dreams, magic terrors, miracles, witches, nocturnal visits from the dead or spells from Thessaly][〔2〕]

-I used to feel sorry for the wretched folk who were taken in by such madness. Now I find that I was at least as much to be pitied as they were. It is not that experience has subsequently shown me anything going beyond my original beliefs (nor is it from any lack of curiosity on my part), but reason has taught me that, if you condemn in this way anything whatever as definitely false and quite impossible, you are claiming to know the frontiers and bounds of the will of God and the power of Nature our Mother; it taught me also that there is nothing in the whole world madder than bringing matters down to the measure of our own capacities and potentialities.

4. How many of the things which constantly come into our purview must be deemed monstrous or miraculous if we apply such terms to anything which outstrips our reason! If we consider that we have to grope through a fog even to understand the very things we hold in our hands, then we will certainly find that it is not knowledge but habit which takes away their strangeness;

jam nemo, fessus satiate vivendi,

Suspicere in coeli dignatur lucida templa;

[Already now, tired and satiated with life, nobody bothers to gaze up at the shining temples of the heavens:]

such things, if they were newly presented to us, would seem as unbelievable as any others;

si nunc primum mortalibus adsint

Ex improviso, ceu sint objecta repente,

Nil magis his rebus poterat mirabile dici,

Aut minus ante quod auderent fore credere gentes.

[supposing that now, for the first time, they were suddenly shown to mortal men: nothing could be called more miraculous; such things the nations would not have dared to believe.][〔3〕]

He who had never actually seen a river, the first time he did so took it for the ocean, since we think that the biggest things that we know represent the limits of what Nature can produce in that species.

Scilicet et fluvius, qui non est maximus, eii est

Qui non ante aliquem majorem vidit, et ingens

Arbor homoque videtur; et omnia de genere omni

Maxima quae vidit quisque, haec ingentia fingit.

[Just as a river may not be all that big, but seems huge to a man who has never seen a bigger one, so, too, for the biggest tree or biggest man; and the biggest thing of any kind which we know is considered huge by us.]

'Consuetudine oculorum assuescunt animi, neque admirantur, neque requirunt rationes earum rerum quas semper vident.' [When we grow used to seeing anything it accustoms our minds to it and we cease to be astonished by it; we never seek the causes of things like that.][〔4〕] What makes us seek the cause of anything is not size but novelty.

5. We ought to judge the infinite power of Nature with more reverence and a greater recognition of our own ignorance and weakness. How many improbable things there are which have been testified to by people worthy of our trust: if we cannot be convinced we should at least remain in suspense. To condemn them as impossible is to be rashly presumptuous, boasting that we know the limits of the possible. If we understood the difference between what is impossible and what is unusual, or between what is against the order of the course of Nature and what is against the common opinion of mankind, then the way to observe that rule laid down by Chilo, Nothing to excess, would be, Not to believe too rashly: not to disbelieve too easily.

6. When we read in Froissart that the Comte de Foix knew the following morning in Béarn of the defeat of King John of Castille at Juberoth, and when we read of the means he is alleged to have used, we can laugh at that; we can laugh too when our annals tell how Pope Honorius, on the very same day that King PhilipAugustus died at Mante, celebrated a public requiem for him and ordered the same to be done throughout Italy, for the authority of such witnesses is not high enough to rein us back.

7. But wait. When Plutarch (leaving aside the many examples which he alleges from Antiquity) says that he himself knows quite definitely that, at the time of Domitian, news of the battle lost by Antony several days' journey away in Germany was publicly announced in Rome and spread through all the world on the very day that it was lost; and when Caesar maintains that it was often the case that news of an event actually anticipated the event itself: are we supposed to say that they were simple people who merely followed the mob and who let themselves be deceived because they saw things less clearly than we do![〔5〕]

8. Can there be anything more delicate, clear-cut and lively than the judgement of Pliny when he pleases to exercise it? Is there anything further from triviality? (I am not discussing his outstanding erudition; I put less store by that: but in which of those two qualities are we supposed to surpass him?) And yet every little schoolboy convicts him of lying and lectures him about the march of Nature's handiwork.

9. When we read in Bouchet about miracles associated with the relics of Saint Hilary we can shrug it off: his right to be believed is not great enough to take away our freedom to challenge him. But to go on from there and condemn all similar accounts seems to me to be impudent in the extreme. Such a great saint as Augustine swears that he saw:[〔6〕] a blind child restored to sight by the relics of Saint Gervaise and Saint Protasius at Milan; a woman in Carthage cured of a cancer by the sign of the cross made by a woman who had just been baptised; his close friend Hesperius driving off devils (who were infesting his house) by using a little soil taken from the sepulchre of our Lord, and that same soil, borne into the Church, suddenly curing a paralytic; a woman who, having touched the reliquary of Saint Stephen with a posy of flowers during a procession, rubbed her eyes with them afterwards and recovered her sight which she had recently lost-as well as several other miracles which occurred in his presence. What are we to accuse him of-him and the two holy bishops, Aurelius and Maximinus, whom he calls on as witnesses? Is it of ignorance, simple-mindedness, credulity, deliberate deception or imposture? Is there any man in our century so impudent as to think he can be compared with them for virtue, piety, scholarship, judgement and ability? 'Qui, ut rationem nullam afferent, ipsa authoritate me frangerent.' [Why, even if they gave no reasons, they would convince me by their very authority.][〔7〕]

10. Apart from the absurd rashness which it entails, there is a dangerous boldness of great consequence in despising whatever we cannot understand. For as soon as you have established the frontiers of truth and error with that fine brain of yours and then discover that you must of necessity believe some things even stranger than the ones which you reject, you are already forced to abandon these frontiers.

11. Now it seems to me that what brings as much disorder as anything into our consciences during our current religious strife is the way Catholics are prepared to treat some of their beliefs as expendable. They believe they are being moderate and well-informed when they surrender to their enemies some of the articles of faith which are in dispute. But, apart from the fact that they cannot see what an advantage you give to an adversary when you begin to yield ground and beat a retreat, or how much that excites him to follow up his attack, the very articles which they select as being less weighty are sometimes extremely important ones.

12. We must either totally submit to the authority of our ecclesiastical polity or else totally release ourselves from it. It is not for us to decide what degree of obedience we owe to it.

13. Moreover I can say that for having assayed it; in the past I made use of that freedom of personal choice and private selection in order to neglect certain details in the observances of our Church because they seemed to be rather odd or rather empty; then, when I came to tell some learned men about it, I discovered that those very practices were based on massive and absolutely solid foundations, and that it is only our ignorance and animal-stupidity which make us treat them with less reverence than all the rest.

14. Why cannot we remember all the contradictions which we feel within our own judgement, and how many things which were articles of belief for us yesterday are fables for us today?

15. Vainglory and curiosity are the twin scourges of our souls. The former makes us stick our noses into everything: the latter forbids us to leave anything unresolved or undecided.

NOTE

〔1〕　Cicero, Academica, II, ii, 127.

〔2〕　Horace, Epistles, II, ii, 208-9.

〔3〕　Lucretius, II, 1037-8; 1032-5.

〔4〕　Lucretius, VI, 674-7; Cicero, De natura deorum, II, XXXVIII, 96.

〔5〕　Plutarch, Life of Paulus Aemilius. The reference to Caesar is puzzling.

〔6〕　St Augustine, City of God, XII, viii.

〔7〕　Cicero, Tusc. disput., I, xxi, 49, adapted.

3
On the art of conversation

1. It is a custom of our justice to punish some as a warning to others. For to punish them for having done wrong would, as Plato says, be stupid: what is done cannot be undone. The intention is to stop them from repeating the same mistake or to make others avoid their error.[〔1〕]We do not improve the man we hang: we improve others by him. I do the same. My defects are becoming natural and incorrigible, but as fine gentlemen serve the public as models to follow I may serve a turn as a model to avoid:

Nonne vides Albi ut male vivat filius, utque

Barrus inops? magnum documentum, ne patriam rem

Perdere quis velit

[You can see, can't you, how wretchedly Albus' son is living and how poor Barrus is? An excellent lesson in not squandering your inheritance.][〔2〕]

2. The act of publishing and indicting my imperfections may teach someone how to fear them. (The talents which I most esteem in myself derive more honour from indicting me than praising me.) That is why I so often return to it and linger over it. Yet, when all has been said, you never talk about yourself without loss: condemn yourself and you are always believed: praise yourself and you never are.

3. There may be others of my complexion who learn better by counter-example than by example, by eschewing not pursuing. That was the sort of instruction which the Elder Cato was thinking of when he said that the wise have more to learn from the fools than the fools from the wise;[〔3〕] as also that lyre-player in antiquity who, Pausanias says, used to require his students to go and listen to some performer who lived across the street so that they would learn to loathe discords and faulty rhythms.[〔4〕]My horror of cruelty thrusts me deeper into clemency than any example of clemency ever could draw me. A good equerry does not make me sit up straight in the saddle as much as the sight of a lawyer or a Venetian out riding, and a bad use of language corrects my own better than a good one. Every day I am warned and counselled by the stupid deportment of someone. What hits you affects you and wakes you up more than what pleases you. We can only improve ourselves in times such as these by walking backwards, by discord not by harmony, by being different not by being like. Having myself learned little from good examples I use the bad ones, the text of which is routine. I strove to be as agreeable as others were seen to be boring; as firm as others were flabby; as gentle as others were sharp. But I was setting myself unattainable standards.

4. To my taste the most fruitful and most natural exercise of our minds is conversation. I find the practice of it the most delightful activity in our lives. That is why, if I were now obliged to make the choice, I think I would rather lose my sight than my powers of speech or hearing. In their academies the Athenians, and even more the Romans, maintained this exercise in great honour. In our own times the Italians retain some vestiges of it-greatly to their benefit, as can be seen from a comparison of their intelligence and ours. Studying books has a languid feeble motion, whereas conversation provides teaching and exercise all at once. If I am sparring with a strong and solid opponent he will attack me on the flanks, stick his lance in me right and left; his ideas send mine soaring. Rivalry, competitiveness and glory will drive me and raise me above my own level. In conversation the most painful quality is perfect harmony.

5. Just as our mind is strengthened by contact with vigorous and well-ordered minds, so too it is impossible to overstate how much it loses and deteriorates by the continuous commerce and contact we have with mean and ailing ones. No infection is as contagious as that is. I know by experience what that costs by the ell. I love arguing and discussing, but with only a few men and for my own sake: for to serve as a spectacle to the great and indulge in a parade of your wits and your verbiage is, I consider, an unbecoming trade for an honourable gentleman.

6. Stupidity is a bad quality: but to be unable to put up with it, to be vexed and ground down by it (as happens to me) is another, hardly worse in its unmannerliness than stupidity. And that is what at present I wish to condemn in myself.

7. I embark upon discussion and argument with great ease and liberty. Since opinions do not find in me a ready soil to thrust and spread their roots into, no premise shocks me, no belief hurts me, no matter how opposite to my own they may be. There is no idea so frivolous or odd which does not appear to me to be fittingly produced by the mind of man. Those of us who deprive our judgement of the right to pass sentence look gently on strange opinions; we may not lend them our approbation but we do readily lend them our ears. When one scale in the balance is quite empty I will let the other be swayed by an old woman's dreams: so it seems pardonable if I choose the odd number rather than the even, or Thursday rather than Friday; if I prefer to be twelfth or fourteenth at table rather than thirteenth; if I prefer on my travels to see a hare skirting my path rather than crossing it, and offer my left foot to be booted before the right. All such lunacies (which are believed among us) at least deserve to be heard. For me they only outweigh an empty scale, but outweigh it they do. Similarly the weight of popular and unfounded opinions has a natural existence which is more than nothing. A man who will not go that far perhaps avoids the vice of superstition by falling into the vice of stubbornness.

8. So contradictory judgements neither offend me nor irritate me: they merely wake me up and provide me with exercise. We avoid being corrected: we ought to come forward and accept it, especially when it comes from conversation not a lecture. Whenever we meet opposition, we do not look to see if it is just but how we can get out of it, rightly or wrongly. Instead of welcoming arms we stretch out our claws. I can put up with being roughly handled by my friends: 'You are an idiot! You are raving!' Among gentlemen I like people to express themselves heartily, their words following wherever their thoughts lead. We ought to toughen and fortify our ears against being seduced by the sound of polite words. I like a strong, intimate, manly fellowship, the kind of friendship which rejoices in sharp vigorous exchanges just as love rejoices in bites and scratches which draw blood. It is not strong enough nor magnanimous enough if it is not argumentative, if all is politeness and art; if it is afraid of clashes and walks hobbled. 'Neque enim disputari sine reprehensione potest.' [It is impossible to debate without refuting.][〔5〕]

9. When I am contradicted it arouses my attention not my wrath. I move towards the man who contradicts me: he is instructing me. The cause of truth ought to be common to us both. - What will his answer be? The passion of anger has already wounded his judgement. Turbulence has seized it before reason can. - It would be a useful idea if we had to wager on the deciding of our quarrels, useful if there were a material sign of our defeats so that we could keep tally on them and my manservant say: 'Last year your ignorance and stubborn-ness cost you one hundred crowns on twenty occasions.'

10. I welcome truth, I fondle it, in whosesoever hand I find it; I surrender to it cheerfully, welcoming it with my vanquished arms as soon as I see it approaching from afar. And provided that they do not set about it with too imperious and schoolmasterish a frown I will put my shoulder to the wheel to help along the criticisms that people make of my writings: I have often made changes more for reasons of politeness than to effect reasonable corrections, preferring to please and encourage people's freedom to criticize me by my readiness to give way - yes, even when it cost me something. Yet it is difficult to attract men to do that in our days. They have no stomach for correcting because they have no stomach for suffering correction, always dissembling when talking in each other's presence.

11. I take such great pleasure in being judged and known that it is virtually indifferent to me which of the two forms it takes. My thought so often contradicts and condemns itself that it is all one to me if someone else does so, seeing that I give to his refutation only such authority as I please. But I fall out with anyone who is too high-handed, like one man I know who laments the fact that he gave you advice if you do not accept it and takes it as an insult if you shy at following it.

12. Socrates always laughingly welcomed contradictions made to his arguments. It could be said that since his arguments were the stronger the advantage would always fall to him and that he welcomed them as matter for fresh triumphs: but we, on the contrary, find that there is nothing which makes us more susceptible than convictions about our own surpassing excellence, our contempt for our adversary, and about its being reasonable for the weaker to be willing to accept refutations which set him back on his feet and redress him.

13. I do truly seek to frequent those who manhandle me rather than those who are afraid of me. It is a bland and harmful pleasure to have to deal with people who admire us and defer to us. Antisthenes commanded his sons never to give thanks or show gratitude to anyone who praised them.[〔6〕] I feel far prouder of the victory I win over myself when I make myself give way beneath my adversary's powers of reason in the heat of battle than I ever feel gratified by the victory I win over him through his weakness. In short I admit and acknowledge any attacks, no matter how feeble, if they are made directly, but I am all too impatient of attacks which are not made in due form. I care little about what we are discussing; all opinions are the same to me and it is all but indifferent to me which proposition emerges victorious. I can go on peacefully arguing all day if the debate is conducted with due order. It is not so much forceful and subtle argument that I want as order - the kind of order which can be found every day in disputes among shepherds and shop-assistants yet never among us. If they go astray it is in lack of courtesy. So do we. But their stormy intolerance does not make them stray far from their theme: their arguments keep on course. They interrupt each other. They jostle, but at least get the gist. To answer the point is, in my judgement, to answer very well. But when the discussion becomes turbulent and lacks order, I quit the subject-matter and cling irritably and injudiciously to the form, dashing into a style of debate which is stubborn, ill-willed and imperious, one which I have to blush for later.

14. It is impossible to argue in good faith with a fool. Not only my judgement is corrupted at the hands of so violent a master, so is my sense of right and wrong. Our quarrels ought to be outlawed and punished as are other verbal crimes. Since they are always ruled and governed by anger, what vices do they not awaken and pile up on each other? First we feel enmity for the arguments and then for the men. In debating we are taught merely how to refute arguments; the result of each side's refuting the other is that the fruit of our debates is the destruction and annihilation of the truth. That is why Plato in his Republic prohibits that exercise to ill-endowed minds not suited to it.[〔7〕]

15. You are in quest of what is. Why on earth do you set out to walk that road with a man who has neither pace nor style? We do no wrong to the subject-matter if we depart from it in order to examine the way to treat it-I do not mean a scholastic donnish way, I mean a natural way, based on a healthy intellect. But what happens in the end? One goes east and the other west; they lose the fundamental point in the confusion of a mass of incidentals. After a tempestuous hour they no longer know what they are looking for. One man is beside the bull's eye, the other too high, the other too low. One fastens on a word or a comparison; another no longer sees his opponent's arguments, being too caught up in his own train of thought: he is thinking of pursuing his own argument not yours. Another, realizing he is too weak in the loins, is afraid of everything, denies everything and, from the outset, muddles and confuses the argument, or else, at the climax of the debate he falls into a rebellious total silence, affecting, out of morose ignorance, a haughty disdain or an absurdly modest desire to avoid contention. Yet another does not care how much he drops his own guard provided that he can hit you. Another counts every word and believes they are as weighty as reasons. This man merely exploits the superior power of his voice and lungs. And then there is the man who sums up against himself; and the other who deafens you with useless introductions and digressions. Another is armed with pure insults and picks a groundless 'German quarrel' so as to free himself from the company and conversation of a mind which presses hard on his own.

16. Lastly, there is the man who cannot see reason but holds you under siege within a hedge of dialectical conclusions and logical formulae. Who can avoid beginning to distrust our professional skills and doubt whether we can extract from them any solid profit of practical use in life when he reflects on the use we put them to? 'Nihil sanantibus litteris.' [Such erudition as has no power to heal.][〔8〕] Has anyone ever acquired intelligence through logic? Where are her beautiful promises? 'Nec ad melius vivendum nec ad commodius disserendum.' [She teaches neither how to live a better life nor how to argue properly.] Is there more of a hotchpotch in the cackle of fishwives than in the public disputations of men who profess logic? I would prefer a son of mine to learn to talk in the tavern rather than in our university yap-shops.

17. Take an arts don; converse with him. Why is he incapable of making us feel the excellence of his 'arts' and of throwing the women, and us ignoramuses, into ecstasies of admiration at the solidity of his arguments and the beauty of his ordered rhetoric? Why cannot he overmaster us and sway us at his will? Why does a man with his superior mastery of matter and style intermingle his sharp thrusts with insults, indiscriminate arguments and rage? Let him remove his academic hood, his gown and his Latin; let him stop battering our ears with raw chunks of pure Aristotle; why, you would take him for one of us-or worse. The involved linguistic convolutions with which they confound us remind me of conjuring tricks: their sleight-of-hand has compelling force over our senses but it in no wise shakes our convictions. Apart from such jugglery they achieve nothing but what is base and ordinary. They may be more learned but they are no less absurd.

18. I like and honour erudition as much as those who have it. When used properly it is the most noble and powerful acquisition of Man. But in the kind of men (and their number is infinite) who make it the base and foundation of their worth and achievement, who quit their understanding for their memory, 'sub aliena umbra latentes' [hiding behind other men's shadows],[〔9〕] and can do nothing except by book, I loathe (dare I say it?) a little more than I loathe stupidity.

19. In my part of the country and during my own lifetime school-learning has brought amendment of purse but rarely amendment of soul. If the souls it meets are already obtuse, as a raw and undigested mass it clogs and suffocates them; if they are unfettered, it tends to purge them, strip them of impurities and volatilize them into vacuity. Erudition is a thing the quality of which is neither good nor bad, almost: it is a most useful adjunct to a well-endowed soul: to any other it is baleful and harmful; or rather, it is a thing which, in use, has great value, but it will not allow itself to be acquired at a base price: in one hand it is a royal sceptre, in another, a fool's bauble.

20. But to get on: what greater victory do you want than to teach your enemy that he cannot stand up to you? Get the better of him by your argument and the winner is the truth; do so by your order and style, then you are the winner!

21. I am persuaded that, in both Plato and Xenophon, Socrates debates more for the debater's than for debating's sake; more to teach Euthydemus and Protagoras their own absurdity than the absurdity of their sophists' art. He seizes hold of the first subject which comes to hand, as a man who has a more useful aim than to throw light on his subject as such: namely, to enlighten the minds which he accepts to train and to exercise. The game which we hunt is the fun of the chase: we are inexcusable if we pursue it badly or foolishly: it is quite another thing if we fail to make a kill. For we are born to go in quest of truth: to take possession of it is the property of a greater Power. Truth is not (as Democritus said) hidden in the bottom of an abyss: it is, rather, raised infinitely high within the knowledge of God.

22. This world is but a school of inquiry. The question is not who will spear the ring but who will make the best charges at it. The man who says what is true can act as foolishly as the one who says what is untrue: we are talking about the way you say it not what you say. My humour is to consider the form as much as the substance, and the barrister as much as his case, as Alcibiades told us to. Every day I spend time reading my authors, not caring about their learning, looking not for their subject-matter but how they handle it; just as I go in pursuit of discussions with a celebrated mind not to be taught by it but to get to know it.

23. Any man may speak truly: few men can speak ordinately, wisely, adequately. And so errors which proceed from ignorance do not offend me: absurdity does. I have often broken off discussing a bargain, even one advantageous to me, because of the silly claims of those I was bargaining with. For their mistakes I do not lose my temper above once a year with any of those who are subject to my authority, but when the point is the stupidity of their assertions or the obstinacy of their asinine excuses and their daft defences, then we are daily at each other's throats. They understand neither why nor what they are told: they answer accordingly. It is enough to make you despair. It is only when my head bangs against another head that I feel a big bump: I can come to terms with the failings of my servants better than with their thoughtlessness, insolence and downright silliness. Let them do less, provided that they can do something! You live in hope of making their wills warm to their work: but there is nothing to get from a blockhead, nothing to hope for.

24. Yes, but what if I myself am taking things for other than they are? That may well be: that explains first of all why I condemn my inability to put up with it, holding it to be equally a defect in those who are right and those who are wrong, since there is always an element of tyrannical bad temper in being unable to tolerate characters different from your own. Secondly, there is in truth no greater silliness, none more enduring, than to be provoked and enraged by the silliness of this world-and there is none more bizarre. For it makes you principally irritated with yourself: that philosopher of old would never have lacked occasion for his tears if he had concentrated on himself.[〔10〕] One of the Seven Sages, Myson, was of the same humour as Timon and Democritus: when asked what he was laughing at all by himself, he replied, 'At the fact that I am laughing all by myself.'

25. How many statements and replies do I make every day which are silly by my norms-so even more frequently, to be sure, by the standards of others! If I bite my lips for them, what must the others be doing! To his family alliances, more than half of which were false, that kind of man being most inclined to launch out on such stupid subjects when his escutcheon is more dubious and least certain: yet he too, if he had stood back and looked at himself, would have discovered that he was hardly less extravagant in broadcasting and less boring in stressing the claims to precedence of his wife's family. What a dangerous arrogance with which a wife is seen to be armed at the hands of her very husband! If they understood Latin we ought to say to such people:

Age! si haec non insanit satis sua sponte, instiga!

[That's the way! If she is not mad enough herself, egg her on!][〔11〕]

27. I do not mean that nobody should make indictments unless he is spotless; if that were so no one would make them. What I mean is that when our judgement brings a charge against another man over a matter then in question, it must not exempt us from an internal judicial inquiry. It is a work of charity for a man who is unable to weed out a defect in himself to try, nevertheless, to weed it out in another in whom the seedling may be less malignant and stubborn. And it never seems to me to be an appropriate answer to anyone who warns me of a fault in me to say that he has it too. What difference does that make? The warning remains true and useful. If we had sound nostrils our shit ought to stink all the more for its being our own. Socrates was convinced that if there was a man who, together with his son and a stranger, was found guilty of violence or injury, that man should begin with himself, first presenting himself to be sentenced by the judge and to beg for expiation at the hands of the executioner; next, he should present his son; then the stranger.[〔12〕] If that precept pitches it rather too high, at least he should be the first to be presented before his own conscience for punishment.

28. Our first judges are properly our senses, which perceive things only by their external accidents. No wonder then that in all the elements which contribute to our society there is such a constant and universal addition of surface appearances and ritual; with the result that the best and most effective part of our polities consists in that. We are always dealing with Man, whose nature is wondrously corporeal. Those who in recent years have wished to build up for us so contemplative and nonmaterial an exercise of worship should not be astonished if there are those who think that it would have slipped and melted through their fingers if it did not keep a hold among us as a mark, sign and means of division and of faction rather than for itself.

29. It is the same in discussion: the gravity, academic robes and rank of the man who is speaking often lend credence to arguments which are vain and silly. Who could believe that so redoubtable a lord with so great a retinue does not have within him some more-than-ordinary talent, or that a man who is entrusted with so many missions and offices of state, a man so disdainful and so arrogant, is not cleverer than another man who bows to him from afar and whom nobody ever employs! Not only the words of such people but their very grimaces are watched and put to their account, each man striving to give them some fine solid significance. If they condescend to join in ordinary discussions and you show them anything but approval and reverence, they clobber you with the authority of their experience: they have heard this; they have seen that; they have done this: you are overwhelmed with cases. I would like to tell such men that the fruit of a surgeon's experience lies not in a recital of his operations nor in his reminding us that he has cured four patients of the plague and three of the gout, unless he knows how to extract from them material for forming his judgement and unless he knows how to convince us that he has been made wiser by the practice of his medical art. So, in a consort of instruments, we do not hear the lute, the spinet and the flute but a global harmony, the fruit resulting from the combination of the entire group.

30. If they have been improved by their missions and their travels that should appear in the products of their understanding. It is not enough to relate our experiences: we must weigh them and group them; we must also have digested them and distilled them so as to draw out the reasons and conclusions they comport. There never were so many writing history! It is always good and profitable to listen to them, for they furnish us with ample instruction, fine and praiseworthy, from the storehouse of their memory: that is certainly of great value in helping us to live. But we are not looking for that at the moment: we are trying to find out whether the chroniclers and compilers are themselves worthy of praise.

31. I loathe all tyranny, both in speech and action. I like to brace myself against those trivial incidentals which cheat our judgement via our senses; and by keeping a watchful eye on men of extraordinary rank I have discovered that they are, for the most part, just like the rest of us:

Rarus enim ferme sensus communis in illa

Fortuna.

[Common sense is rare enough in that high station.][〔13〕]

32. Perhaps we esteem them and perceive them for less than they are, because they undertake to do more and so reveal themselves more. The porter must be stronger and tougher than his load. The man who has not had to use all his strength leaves you to guess whether he has any more in reserve, whether he has been assayed to the ultimate point: the man who succumbs under the weight betrays his limitations and the weakness of his shoulders. That is why, more than other people, so many of the learned can be seen to have inadequate souls. They could have been good farmers, good merchants, good craftsmen: their natural forces were tailored to such proportions. Knowledge is a very weighty thing: they sink beneath it. Their mental apparatus has not enough energy nor skill to display that noble material and to apportion its strength, to exploit it and to make it help them. Knowledge can lodge only in a powerful nature: and that is very rare. Feeble minds, said Socrates, corrupt the dignity of philosophy when they handle it; she appears to be useless and defective when sheathed in a bad covering.[〔14〕]

33. That is how they grow rotten and besotted, Humani qualis simulator simius oris,

Quem puer arridens pretioso stamine serum

Velavit, nudasque nates ac terga reliquit,

Ludibrium mensis.

[Like an ape, that imitator of the human face, which a boy dresses up, for a laugh, in precious silken robes, leaving the cheeks of its backside bare to amuse the guests at table.]

34. It is the same for those who rule over us and give orders, who hold the world in their hands: it is not enough for them to have an ordinary intelligence, to be able to achieve what we can. They are far beneath us if they are not way above us. Since they promise more, they owe more too; that is why keeping silent is not, in their case, merely a courteous and grave demeanour; it is also more often a profitable and gainful one. For when Megabysus went to see Appelles in his studio, he long remained silent. But when he began to discourse on the works of art, he received this rude reprimand: 'While you kept silent you appeared to be a great Somebody because of your chains-of-office and your retinue, but now we have heard you talk the very apprentices in my workshop despise you.'[〔15〕] Those magnificent decorations, that grand estate would not tolerate ordinary plebeian ignorance in him, nor inappropriate comments on paintings: he should have maintained that outward presumed connoisseurship. For how many men in my time has a cold, taciturn mien served their silly souls as signs of wisdom and ability!

35. Of necessity dignities and offices are bestowed more by fortune than by merit: you often do wrong to blame kings for that. On the contrary, it is a wonder that they have such good luck, enjoying as they do so few ways of finding out.

Principis est virtus maxima nosse suos,

[For a prince, the chief merit is to know his subjects,][〔16〕]

for Nature has not given them eyes which can extend over so many peoples, distinguishing pre-eminence and seeing into our bosoms, where is lodged the knowledge of our will and of our better qualities. They have to select us by fumbling guesses: by our family, our wealth, our learning and the voice of the people-the feeblest of arguments. Anyone who could discover the means by which men could be justly judged and reasonably chosen would, at a stroke, establish a perfect form of commonwealth.

36. 'Yes. But he brought this great matter to a successful conclusion.'-That means something, but not enough; for we rightly accept the maxim which says that plans must not be judged by results. The Carthaginians punished bad counsels in their captains even when they were put right by a happy outcome. And the Roman people often refused to mark great and beneficial victories because the qualities of leadership of the commander were inferior to his good luck. In this world's activities we often notice that Fortune rivals Virtue: she shows us what power she has over everything and delights in striking down our presumption by making the incompetent lucky since she cannot make them wise. She loves to interfere, favouring those performances whose course has been entirely her own. That is why we can see, every day, the simplest among us bringing the greatest public and private tasks to successful conclusions.

37. Siramnes the Persian replied to those who were amazed that his enterprises turned out so badly, seeing that his projects were so wise, by saying that he alone was master of his projects while Fortune was mistress of the outcome of his enterprises: they too could make the same reply to explain the opposite tendency.[〔17〕]

38. Most of this world's events happen by themselves:

Fata viam inveniunt.

[The Fates find a way.][〔18〕]

39. The outcome often lends authority to the most inept leadership. Our intervention is virtually no more than a habit, the result of tradition and example rather than of reason. I was once astounded by the greatness of a venture; I then learnt from those who had brought it to a successful conclusion what their motives were and what methods they used: I found nothing but ordinary notions.

40. Indeed the most ordinary usual ones are also perhaps the most reliable and the most suitable in practice if not for show. What if the most lowly reasons are the most solidly based? What if the most humble, most lax and best-trodden ones are the most suited to our concerns? If we are to safeguard the authority of the Privy Council we do not need laymen participating in it nor seeing further than the first obstacle. If we want to maintain its reputation it must be taken on trust, as a whole.

41. My thought sketches out the matter for a while and dwells lightly on the first aspects of it: then I usually leave the principal thrust of the task to heaven.

Permitte divis caetera.

[Entrust the rest to the gods.]

To my mind Good Luck and Bad Luck are two sovereign powers. There is no wisdom in thinking that the role of Fortune can be played by human wisdom. What he undertakes is vain if a man should presume to embrace both causes and consequences and to lead the progress of his action by the hand; and it is especially vain in counsels of war. Never were there more military circumspection and prudence than I sometimes see practised among us: perhaps we fear that we shall get lost en route, and therefore keep ourselves in reserve for the climax in the final act!

42. I will go on to say that our very wisdom and mature reflections are for the most part led by chance. My will and my reasoning are stirred this way and that. And many of their movements govern themselves without me. My reason is daily subject to incitements and agitations which are due to chance:

Vertuntur species animorum, et pectora motus

Nunc alios, alios dum nubila ventus agebat,

Concipiunt.

[Their minds' ideas are ever turning round; the emotions in their breasts are driven hither and thither like clouds before the wind.][〔19〕]

43. Look and see who wield most power in our cities; who do their jobs best. You will find that they are usually the least clever. There have been cases when women, children and lunatics have ruled their states equally as well as the most talented princes. Coarse men more usually succeed in such things, says Thucydides, better than the subtle ones do.[〔20〕] We ascribe the deeds of their good fortune to their wisdom.

Ut quisque fortuna utitur

Ita praecellet, atque exinde sapere illum omnes dicimus.

[Each outstanding man is raised by his good fortune; we then say that he is clever.]

44. That is why I insist that, in all our activities, their outcomes provide meagre testimony of our worth and ability.

45. Now I was just about to say that it merely suffices for us to see a man raised to great dignity; even though we knew him three days before to be a negligible man, there seeps into our opinions, unawares, a notion of greatness, of talents, and we convince ourselves that by growing in style and reputation he has grown in merit. Our judgements of him are not based on his worth but (as is the case with the counters of an abacus) on the tokens of rank. Let his luck turn again, let him have a fall and be lost in the crowd again, then we all ask in wonder what had made him soar so high! 'Is this the same man?' we ask. 'Did he not know more about it when he was up there? Are princes satisfied with so little? We were in good hands, indeed we were!'

46. That is something I have seen many times in my own days.

47. Why, even the mask of greatness which is staged in our plays affects us somewhat and deceives us. What I worship in kings is the crowd of their worshippers. Everything should bow and submit to our kings-except our intelligence. My reason was not made for bending and bowing, my knees were.

48. When Melanthius was asked how Dionysius' tragedy appeared to him, 'I never saw it,' he replied. 'It was obscured by the words!' So, too, most of those who judge what the great have to say ought to answer: 'I never heard his words: they were too much obscured by his dignity, grandeur and majesty.'[〔21〕]

49. One day, when Antisthenes urged the Athenians to command that donkeys be used, as their horses were, to plough their fields, he was told that donkeys were not born for such a service. 'That does not matter,' he retorted. 'It all depends on your issuing the order: for the most ignorant and incompetent men whom you put in command of your wars never fail to become suddenly most worthy of command, because it is you who employ them!'[〔22〕]

50. Related to this is the practice of so many people to sanctify the kings whom they have chosen from among themselves. They are not contented with honouring them: they need to worship them. The people of Mexico dare not look at the face of their king once they have completed the rites of his enthronement, but as though they had deified him by his royal state they make him swear not merely to maintain their religion, laws and liberties and to be valiant, just and debonair, he must also swear to cause the sun to run shining with its accustomed light, the clouds to break in due season, the rivers to flow in their courses and the earth to bring forth all things needful for his people.[〔23〕]

51. I am opposed to that widespread fashion and I most doubt a man's ability when I see it accompanied by great rank and public acclaim. We should remember what it means to a man to be able to speak when he wants to, to choose the right moment, to break off the discussion or switch the subject with the authority of a master, to defend himself against objections with a shake of the head, a little smile or with silence, in front of courtiers who tremble with reverence and respect.

52. A monstrously rich man, when some trivial matter was being aired casually over dinner, joined in the discussion and began with these very words: 'Anyone who says otherwise is either ignorant or a liar,' and so on. You had better follow up that philosophical thrust with a dagger in your hand!

53. Here is another warning, which I find most useful: in debates and discussions we should not immediately be impressed by what we take to be a man's own bons mots. Most men are rich with other men's abilities. It may well be that such-and-such a man makes a fine remark, a good reply or a pithy saying, advancing it without realizing its power. (That we do not grasp everything we borrow can doubtless be proved from my own case.) We should not always give way, no matter what beauty or truth it may have. We should either seriously attack it or else, under pretence of not understanding it, retreat a little so as to probe it thoroughly and to discover how it is lodged in its author. We may be helping his sword-thrust to carry beyond his reach, running on to it ourselves. There have been times when, pressed by necessity in the duel of words, I have made counter-attacks which struck home more than I ever hoped or expected. I was counting their number: they were accepted for their weight.

54. When I am disputing with a man of strong arguments I enjoy anticipating his conclusions; I save him the bother of explaining himself; I make an assay at forestalling his ideas while they are still unfinished and being formed (the order and stretch of his intelligence warn me and threaten me from afar). Similarly, with those others I mentioned I do quite the opposite: we should suppose nothing, understand nothing but what they explain. If their judgements are apposite but expressed in universals-'This is good: that is bad'-find out whether it is luck which makes them apposite. Make them circumscribe and restrict their verdict a little: 'Why is it good? How is it good?' Those universal judgements (which I find so common) say nothing. They are like those who greet people as a mass or a crowd: those who have genuine knowledge of them greet them by name and distinguish them as individuals. But it is a chancy business. Which explains why, on average more than once a day, I have seen men with ill-founded minds trying to act clever by showing me some beautiful detail in the book they are reading, but choosing so badly the point on which they fix their admiration that instead of revealing the excellence of their author they reveal their own ignorance.

55. When you have just listened to a whole page of Virgil you can safely exclaim, 'Now that is beautiful!' The cunning ones escape that way. But to undertake to go back over the detail of a good author, to try to indicate with precise and selected examples where he surpasses himself and where he flies high by weighing his words and his locutions and his choice of materials one after another: not many try that. 'Videndum est non modo quid quisque loquatur, sed etiam quid quisque sentiat, atque etiam qua de causa quisque sentiat.' [We should not only examine what each one says, but what are his opinions and what grounds he has for holding them.][〔24〕] Day after day I hear stupid people uttering words which are not stupid. They say something good; let us discover how deeply they understand it and where they got hold of it. They do not own that fine saying or that fine reasoning, but we help them to use it. They are only looking after it. Perhaps they only produced it fortuitously, hesitantly: it is we who give it credit and value. You are lending them a hand. But why? They feel no gratitude towards you for it and become all the more silly. Do not support them; let them go their own way: they will handle that material like a man who fears getting scalded: they dare not show it in a different light or context nor to deepen it. Give it the tiniest shaking and it slips away from them: then, strong and beautiful though it be, they surrender it to you. They have beautiful weapons, but the handles are loose! How often have I learnt that from experience!

56. Now, if you come and clarify and reinforce it for them, they immediately take advantage of your interpretation and rob you of it: 'That is what I was about to say,' or, 'That is how I understand it, exactly,' or, 'If I did not put it that way it was because I could not find the right words.'-Bluster on! We should use even cunning to punish such arrogant stupidity.

57. Hegesias' principle that we should neither hate nor blame but instruct is right elsewhere but not here.[〔25〕]There is neither justice nor kindness in helping a man to get up who does not know how to use your help and who is all the worse for it. I like to let them sink deeper in the mire and to get even more entangled - so deeply that, if possible, even they finally realize it!

58. You cannot cure silliness and unreasonableness by one act of warning. Of that sort of cure we can properly say what Cyrus replied to the man who urged him to give an exhortation to his troops at the moment of battle: that men are not made courageous warriors on the battlefield by a good harangue any more than you can become a good musician by hearing a good song.[〔26〕] Apprenticeships must be served, before you set hand to anything, by long and sustained study.

59. It is to our own folk that we owe this obligation to be assiduous in correcting and instructing; but to go preaching at the first passer-by or to read lectures on ignorance and silliness to the first man we come across is a practice which I loathe. I rarely do it during discussions in which I am involved; I prefer to let it all go by rather than to resort to such remote and donnish lecturing. My humour is unsuited, both in speaking and writing, to those who are learning first principles. But however false or absurd I judge things to be which are said in company or before a third party, I never leap in to interrupt them by word or gesture.

60. Meanwhile nothing in stupidity irritates me more than its being much more pleased with itself than any reasonableness could reasonably be. It is a disaster that wisdom forbids you to be satisfied with yourself and always sends you away dissatisfied and fearful, whereas stubbornness and foolhardiness fill their hosts with joy and assurance. It is the least clever of men who look down at others over their shoulders, always returning from the fray full of glory and joyfulness. And as often as not their haughty language and their happy faces win them victory in the eyes of the bystanders who are generally feeble in judging and incapable of discerning real superiority. The surest proof of animal-stupidity is ardent obstinacy of opinion. Is there anything more certain, decided, disdainful, contemplative, grave and serious, than a donkey?

61. Perhaps we may include in the category of conversation and discussion those short pointed exchanges which happiness and intimacy introduce among friends when pleasantly joking together and sharply mocking each other. That is a sport for which my natural gaiety makes me rather well-suited; and if it is not as tensely serious as the other sport I have just described, it is no less keen and clever, nor, as it seemed to Lycurgus, any less useful. Where I am concerned I contribute more licence than wit, being more happy in that than in finding my material; but I am a perfect target, for I can put up with retaliation without getting angry not merely when sharp but even when rude. When I am suddenly attacked, if I cannot at once find a good repartee I do not waste time following up that thrust with vague boring contestations akin to stubbornness but I let it go by, cheerfully flapping down my ears and waiting for a better moment to get my own back. No huckster wins every haggle.

62. Most people, when their arguments fail, change voice and expression, and instead of retrieving themselves betray their weaknesses and susceptibility by an unmannerly anger. In the excitement of jesting we can sometimes nip those secret chords of one another's imperfections which we cannot even pluck without offence when we are calm; we warn each other profitably of each other's faults. There are other sports, physical ones, rash and harsh in the French manner, which I hate unto death. I am touchy and sensitive about such things: in my lifetime I have seen two princes of the blood royal laid in their graves because of them. It is an ugly thing to fight for fun.[〔27〕]

63. In addition when I want to judge another man I ask him to what extent he is himself satisfied; how far he is happy with what he has said or written. I want him to avoid those fine excuses: 'I was only playing at it' -

Ablatum mediis opus est incudibus istud

[It was taken off the anvil only half finished][〔28〕]

- 'I only spent an hour on it'; 'I have not seen it since'. - 'All right,' I say: 'let us leave those examples. Show me something which does represent you entirely, something by which you are happy to be measured.' And then I say, 'What do you consider the most beautiful aspect of your work? Is it this quality or that quality? Is it its gracious style, its subject-matter, your discovery of the material, your judgement, your erudition?'

64. For I normally find that men are as wrong in judging their own work as other people's, not simply because their emotions are involved but because they lack the ability to understand it and to analyse it. The work itself, by its own momentum and fortune, can favour the author beyond his own understanding and research; it can run ahead of him. There is no work that I can judge with less certainty than my own: the Essays I place - very hesitantly and with little assurance - sometimes low, sometimes high.

65. Many books are useful for their subject-matter: their authors derive little glory from them. And there are good books which as far as good workmanship is concerned are a disgrace to their authors. I could write about our style of feasting, about our clothing - and I could write it gracelessly; I could publish contemporary edicts and the letters of princes which come into the public domain; I could make an abridgement of a good book (and every abridgement of a good book is a daft one) and then the book itself could chance to get lost. Things like that. From such compilations posterity would derive unique assistance: but what honour would I derive from them except for being lucky? A good proportion of famous books fall in that category.

66. When I was reading a few years ago Philippe de Commines - a very good author, certainly - I noted the following saying as being above average: 'We should be wary of doing such great services to our master that we render him unable to reward them justly.' I should have praised not him but his discovery of a topic. Not long ago I came upon this sentence in Tacitus: 'Beneficia eo usque laeta sunt dum videntur exolvi posse; ubi multum antevenere, pro gratia odium redditur.' [Good turns are pleasing only in so far as they seem repayable. Much beyond that we repay with hatred not gratitude.] Seneca puts it forcefully: 'Nam qui putat esse turpe non reddere, non vult esse cui reddat.' [He for whom not to repay is a disgrace wants his benefactor dead.] Quintus Cicero, with a laxer turn of phrase, writes: 'Qui se non putat satisfacere, amicus esse nullo modo potest.' [He who cannot repay his debt to you can in no wise love you.][〔29〕]

67. An author's subject can, when appropriate, show him to be erudite or retentive, but if you are to judge what qualities in him most truly belong to him and are the most honourable (I mean the force and beauty of his soul) you must know what is really his and what definitely is not; and in that which is not, how much we are indebted to him for his selection, disposition, ornamentation and the literary quality of what he had contributed. Supposing he has taken somebody else's matter and then ruined the style, as often happens! People like us who have little experience of books are in difficulties when we come across some fine example of ingenuity in a modern poet or some strong argument in a preacher. We dare not praise them for it before we have learned from a scholar whether that item is original to them or taken from another. Until I have done that I remain suspicious.

68. I have just read through at one go Tacitus' History (something which rarely happens to me: it is twenty years since I spent one full hour at a time on a book. I did it on the recommendation of a nobleman highly esteemed in France both for his own virtue and for that sustained quality of ability and goodness which he is seen to share with his many brothers). I know of no author who combines a chronicle of public events with so much reflection on individual morals and biases. And it appears to me (contrary to what appears to him) that, as he has the particular task of following the careers of the contemporary Emperors (men so odd and so extreme in their various characters) as well as the noteworthy deeds which they provoked in their subjects above all by their cruelty, he has a more striking and interesting topic to relate and discourse upon than if he had to tell of battles and world revolutions. Consequently I find him unprofitable when he dashes through those fair, noble deaths as though he were afraid of tiring us by accounts both too long and too numerous.

69. This manner of history is by far the most useful. The unrolling of public events depends more on the guiding hand of Fortune: that of private ones, on our own. Tacitus' work is more a judgement on historical events than a narration of them. There are more precepts than accounts. It is not a book to be read but one to be studied and learnt. It is so full of aphorisms that, apposite or not, they are everywhere. It is a seed-bed of ethical and political arguments to supply and adorn those who hold high rank in the governing of this world. He pleads his case with solid and vigorous reasons, in an epigrammatic and exquisite style following the affected manner of his century. (They were so fond of a high style that when they found no wit or subtlety in their subject-matter they resorted to witty subtle words.) He is not all that different from Seneca, but while he seems to have more flesh on him Seneca is more acute. Tacitus can more properly serve a sickly troubled nation like our own is at present: you could often believe that we were the subject of his narrating and berating. Those who doubt his good faith clearly betray that they resent him from prejudice. He has sound opinions and inclines to the right side in the affairs of Rome. I do regret though that, by making Pompey no better than Marius and Scylla only more secretive, he judged him more harshly than is suggested by the verdict of men who lived and dealt with him.[〔30〕] True, Pompey's striving to govern affairs has not been cleared of ambition nor a wish for vengeance: even his friends feared that victory might make him go out of his mind, though not to the extremes of insanity of those other two. Nothing in his life suggests to us the menace of such express tyranny and cruelty. Besides we ought never to let suspicions outweigh evidence: so on this point I do not trust Tacitus.

70. That the accounts which he gives are indeed simple and straight can perhaps be argued from the very fact that they do not exactly fit his concluding judgements, to which he is led by the slant he had adopted; they often go beyond the evidence which he provides - which he had not deigned to bias in the slightest degree. He needs no defence for having assented to the religion of his day, in accordance with the laws which bade him to do so, and for being ignorant of the true religion. That is his misfortune not his fault.

71. What I have chiefly been considering is his judgement: I am not entirely clear about it. For example, take these words from the letter sent to the Senate by the aged ailing Tiberius: 'What, Sirs, should I write to you, what indeed should I not write to you at this time? I know that I am daily nearing death; may the gods and goddesses make my end worse if I know what to write.' I cannot see why he applies them with such certainty to a poignant remorse tormenting Tiberius' conscience. Leastways when I came across them I saw no such thing.[〔31〕]

72. It also seemed to me a bit weak of him when he was obliged to mention that he had once held an honourable magistracy in Rome to go on and explain that he was not referring to it in order to boast about it. That line seemed rather shoddy to me for a soul such as his: not to dare to talk roundly of yourself betrays a defect of thought. A man of straight and elevated mind who judges surely and soundly employs in all circumstances examples taken from himself as well as from others, and frankly cites himself as witness as well as third parties. We should jump over those plebeian rules of etiquette in favour of truth and freedom. I not only dare to talk about myself but to talk of nothing but myself. I am wandering off the point when I write of anything else, cheating my subject of me. I do not love myself with such lack of discretion, nor am I so bound and involved in myself, that I am unable to see myself apart and to consider myself separately as I would a neighbour or a tree. The error is the same if you fail to see the limits of your worth or if you report more than you can see. We owe more love to God than to ourselves. We know him less, yet talk about him till we are glutted.

73. If Tacitus' writings tell us anything at all about his character, he was a very great man, upright and courageous, whose virtue was not of the superstitious kind but philosophical and magnanimous. You could find some of his testimony rather rash; for example he maintains that when a soldier's hands grew stiff with the cold while carrying a pile of wood they adhered to his load, broke away from his arms and stuck there dead.[〔32〕] In similar cases my custom is to bow to the authority of such great witnesses. When he says that, by favour of Serapis the god, Vespasian cured a blind woman in Alexandria by anointing her eyes with his saliva and also performed some additional miracle or other, he was following the dutiful example of all good historians who keep a chronicle of important happenings: included among public events are popular rumours and opinions. Their role is to give an account of popular beliefs, not to account for them: which part is played by Theologians and philosophers as directors of consciences. That is why his fellow-historian, great man as he was, most wisely said: 'Equidem plura transcribo quam credo: nam nec affirmare sustineo, de quibus dubito, nec subducere quae accepi.' [I do indeed pass on more than I believe. I cannot vouch for the things which I doubt, nor can I omit what I have been told by tradition.] And another says: 'Haec neque affirmare, neque refellere operae pretium est: famae rerum standum est.' [These things are neither to be vouched for nor denied: we must cling to tradition.][〔33〕] Tacitus, writing during a period in which belief in portents was on the wane, says that he nevertheless does not wish to fail to provide a foothold for them, and so includes in his Annals matters accepted by so many decent people with so great a reverence for antiquity.

74. That is very well said. Let them pass on their histories to us according to what they find received, not according to their own estimate. I, who am monarch of the subject which I treat and not accountable for it to anyone, do not for all that believe everything I say. Sometimes my mind launches out with paradoxes which I mistrust and with verbal subtleties which make me shake my head; but I let them take their chance. I know that some men gain a reputation from such things. It is not for me alone to judge them. I describe myself standing up and lying down, from front and back, from right and left and with all my inborn complexities. Even minds of sustained power are not always sustained in their application and discernment.

75. That is, grosso modo, the Tacitus which is presented to me, vaguely enough, by my memory. All grosso-modo judgements are lax and defective.

NOTE

〔1〕　Plato, Laws, XI, 934 A-B.

〔2〕　Horace, Satires, I, iv, 109-11.

〔3〕　Erasmus, Apophthegmata, V, Cato Senior, XXXIX.

〔4〕　Anecdote not traced. Perhaps a confusion with the practice of the ancient musician Timotheus of Miletus. Cf. Quintilian, II, iii, 3.

〔5〕　Cicero, De finibus, I, viii, 28 (Torquatus defending Epicurus' style of conversation).

〔6〕　Plutarch (tr. Amyot), De la mauvaise honte, 81 B.

〔7〕　Plato, Republic, 539 A-C.

〔8〕　Seneca, Epist. moral., LIX, 15; then, Cicero, De finibus, I, xix, 63, criticizing Epicurean logic.

〔9〕　Seneca, Epist. moral., XXXIII, 7.

〔10〕　Heraclitus, the Sage who wept at the folly of the world; normally coupled with Democritus, who laughed at it. Followed by the most famous saying of Myson (Erasmus, Apophthegmata, VII, Myson, I).

〔11〕　Terence, Andria, IV, ii, 9.

〔12〕　Plato, Gorgias, 480 B—C.

〔13〕　Juvenal, Satires, VIII, 73-4.

〔14〕　Perhaps a reference to Plato, Republic, VI, 495 C-D.

〔15〕　Erasmus, Apophthegmata, VI, Diversorum Graecorum, XXXII.

〔16〕　Martial, Epigrams, VIII, 15.

〔17〕　Cited by Amyot in his Prologue to Les Vies de Plutarque.

〔18〕　Virgil, Aeneid, III, 395; then, Horace, Odes, I, ix, 9.

〔19〕　Virgil, Georgics, I, 420-2.

〔20〕　Thucydides, cited (with others of the above) from Justus Lipsius' Politici, as is the following, from Plautus' Pseudolus.

〔21〕　Plutarch (tr. Amyot), Comment il faut ouïr, 64 H.

〔22〕　Erasmus, Apophthegmata, VII, Antisthenes, XXX.

〔23〕　Lopez de Gomara (tr. Fumée), Histoire générale des Indes, II, lxxvii.

〔24〕　Cicero, De officiis, I, xli, 147.

〔25〕　Diogenes Laertius, Life of Aristippus.

〔26〕　Xenophon, Cyropaedia, III, iii, 49-50.

〔27〕　Henry II was killed while jousting; Henry, Marquess of Beaupréau died of wounds received in a tournament.

〔28〕　Ovid, Tristia, I, vii, 9.

〔29〕　Philippe de Commines, III, xii; Tacitus, Annals, IV, xviii; Seneca, Epist. moral., LXXXVI, 32; Cicero, De petitione consultatus, ix.

〔30〕　Tacitus, Histories, II, xxxviii.

〔31〕　Tacitus, Annals, VI, vi.

〔32〕　Tacitus, Annals, XIII, xxxv; then, IV, lxxi (seen by some as a parody of Christ's curing the blind man in Mark 8: 23).

〔33〕　Quintus Curtius, IX, i; Livy, VIII, vi.

4
On idleness

1. Just as fallow lands, when rich and fertile, are seen to abound in hundreds and thousands of different kinds of useless weeds so that, if we would make them do their duty, we must subdue them and keep them busy with seeds specifically sown for our service; and just as women left alone may sometimes be seen to produce shapeless lumps of flesh but need to be kept busy by a semen other than her own in order to produce good natural offspring: so too with our minds. If we do not keep them busy with some particular subject which can serve as a bridle to reign them in, they charge ungovernably about, ranging to and fro over the wastelands of our thoughts:

Sicut aquae tremulum labris ubi lumen ahenis

Sole repercussum, aut radiantis imagine Lunae

Omnia pervolitat late loca jamque sub auras

Erigitur, summique ferit laquearia tecti.

[As when ruffled water in a bronze pot reflects the light of the sun and the shining face of the moon, sending shimmers flying high into the air and striking against the panelled ceilings].[〔1〕]

2. Then, there is no madness, no raving lunacy, which such agitations do not bring forth:

velut aegri somnia, vanae

Finguntur species.

[they fashion vain apparitions as in the dreams of sick men.][〔2〕]

When the soul is without a definite aim she gets lost; for, as they say, if you are everywhere you are nowhere.

Quisquis ubique habitat, Maxime, nusquam habitat.

[Whoever dwells everywhere, Maximus, dwells nowhere at all.][〔3〕]

3. Recently I retired to my estates, determined to devote myself as far as I could to spending what little life I have left quietly and privately; it seemed to me then that the greatest favour I could do for my mind was to leave it in total idleness, caring for itself, concerned only with itself, calmly thinking of itself. I hoped it could do that more easily from then on, since with the passage of time it had grown mature and put on weight.

4. But I find -

Variam semper dant otia mentis

[Idleness always produces fickle changes of mind].[〔4〕]

- that on the contrary it bolted off like a runaway horse, taking far more trouble over itself than it ever did over anyone else; it gives birth to so many chimeras and fantastic monstrosities, one after another, without order or fitness, that, so as to contemplate at my ease their oddness and their strangeness, I began to keep a record of them, hoping in time to make my mind ashamed of itself.

NOTE

〔1〕　Virgil, Aeneid, VIII, 22.

〔2〕　Horace, Ars poetica, 7.

〔3〕　Martial, VII, lxxiii.

〔4〕　Lucan, Pharsalia, IV, 704.

5
On the affection of fathers for
their children

For Madame d'Estissac

1. Madame: unless I am saved by oddness or novelty (qualities which usually give value to anything) I shall never extricate myself with honour from this daft undertaking; but it is so fantastical and presents an aspect so totally unlike normal practice that it may just get by.

2. It was a melancholy humour (and therefore a humour most inimical to my natural complexion) brought on by the chagrin caused by the solitary retreat I plunged myself into a few years ago, which first put into my head this raving concern with writing. Finding myself quite empty, with nothing to write about, I offered myself to myself as theme and subject matter. It is the only book of its kind in the world, in its conception wild and fantastically eccentric. Nothing in this work of mine is worthy of notice except that bizarre quality, for the best craftsman in the world would not know how to fashion anything remarkable out of material so vacuous and base.

3. Now, Madame, having decided to draw a portrait of myself from life, I would have overlooked an important feature if I had failed to portray the honour which I have always shown you for your great merits. I particularly wanted to do so at the head of this chapter, since of all your fine qualities one of the first in rank is the love you show your children.

4. Anyone who knows how young you were when your husband Monsieur d'Estissac left you a widow; the proposals which have been made to you by such great and honourable men (as many as to any lady of your condition in France); the constancy and firmness of purpose with which you have, for so many years and through so many difficulties, carried the weight of responsibility for your children's affairs (which have kept you busy in so many corners of France and still besiege you); and the happy prosperity which your wisdom or good fortune have brought to those affairs: he will readily agree with me that we have not one single example of maternal love today more striking than your own.

5. I praise God, Madame, that your love has been so well employed. For the great hopes of himself raised by your boy, Monsieur d'Estissac, amply assure us that when he comes of age you will be rewarded by the duty and gratitude of an excellent son. But he is still a child, unable to appreciate the innumerable acts of devotion he has received from you: so I should like him, if this book should fall into his hands one day, to be able to learn something from me at a time when I shall not even have a mouth to tell it to him - something I can vouch for quite truthfully and which will be made even more vigorously evident, God willing, by the good effects he will be aware of in himself: namely, that there is no nobleman in France who owes more to his mother than he does, and that in the future he will be able to give no more certain proof of his goodness and virtue than by acknowledging your qualities.

6. If there truly is a Law of Nature - that is to say, an instinct which can be seen to be universally and permanently stamped on the beasts and on ourselves (which is not beyond dispute) - I would say that, in my opinion, following hard on the concern for selfpreservation and the avoidance of whatever is harmful, there would come second the love which the begetter feels for the begotten. And since Nature seems to have committed this love to us out of a concern for the effective propagation of the successive parts of the world which she has contrived, it is not surprising if love is not so great when we go backwards, from children to fathers. To which we may add a consideration taken from Aristotle,[〔1〕] that anyone who does a kindness to another loves him more than he is loved in return; that anyone to whom a debt is owed feels greater love than the one by whom the debt is owed; and that every creator loves what he has made more than it would love him if it were capable of emotions. This is especially true because each holds his being dear: and being consists in motion and activity; in a sense, therefore, everyone is, to some degree, within anything he does: the benefactor has performed an action both fair and noble: the recipient, on the other hand, has only performed a useful one, and mere usefulness is less lovable than nobility. Nobility is stable and lasting, furnishing the one who has practised it with a constant satisfaction. Usefulness, however, can easily disappear or diminish, and the memory of it is neither so refreshing nor so sweet. The things which have cost us most are dearest to us - and it costs us more to give than to receive.

7. Since it has pleased God to bestow some slight capacity for discursive reasoning on us so that we should not be slavishly subject to the laws of Nature as the beasts are but should conform to them by our free-will and judgement, we should indeed make some concessions to the simple authority of the common laws of Nature but not allow ourselves to be swept tyrannously away by her: Reason alone must govern our inclinations.

8. For my part, those propensities which are produced in us without the command and mediation of our judgement taste strangely flat. In the case of the subject under discussion, I am incapable of finding a place for that emotion which leads people to cuddle new-born infants while they are still without movements of soul or recognizable features of body to make themselves lovable. And I have never willingly allowed them to be nursed in my presence. A true and well-regulated affection should be born, and then increase, as children enable us to get to know them; if they show they deserve it, we should cherish them with a truly fatherly love, since our natural propensity is then progressing side by side with reason; if they turn out differently, the same applies, mutatis mutandis: we should, despite the force of Nature, always yield to reason.

9. In fact, the very reverse often applies; we feel ourselves more moved by the skippings and jumpings and babyish tricks of our children than by their activities when they are fully formed, as though we had loved them not as human beings but only as playthings or as pet monkeys. Some fathers will give them plenty of toys when they are children but will resent the slightest expenditure on their needs once they have come of age. It even looks, in fact, as if we are jealous of seeing them cut a figure in the world, able to enjoy it just when we are on the point of leaving it, and that this makes us miserly and close-fisted towards them: it irritates us that they should come treading on our heels, as if to summon us to take our leave. Since in sober truth things are so ordered that children can only have their being and live their lives at the expense of our being and of our lives, we ought not to undertake to be fathers if that frightens us.

10. For my part, I find it cruel and unjust not to welcome them to a share and fellow-interest in our property - giving them full knowledge of our domestic affairs as co-partners when they are capable of it - and not to cut back on our own interests, economizing on them so as to provide for theirs, since we gave them birth for just such a purpose. It is unjust to see an aged father, broken and only half alive, stuck in his chimney-corner with the absolute possession of enough wealth to help and maintain several children, allowing them all this time to waste their best years without means of advancement in the public service and of making themselves better known. They are driven by despair to find some way, however unjust, of providing for their needs: I have seen in my time several young men of good family so addicted to larceny that no punishment could turn them from it. I know one young man, very well connected, with whom I had a word about just such a matter at the earnest request of his brother, a brave and most honourable nobleman. In reply the young man admitted quite openly that he had been brought to such vile conduct by the unbending meanness of his father, adding that he had now grown so used to it that he could not stop himself. He had just been caught stealing rings from a lady whose morning reception he was attending with several others. It reminded me of a story I had heard about another nobleman who had so adapted himself to the exigencies of that fine profession that when he did become master of his inheritance and decided to give up this practice he nevertheless could not stop himself from stealing anything he needed when he passed by a stall, despite the bother of having to send somebody to pay for it later. I have known several people so trained and adapted to thieving that they regularly steal from their close companions things which they intend to return.

11. I may be a Gascon but there is no vice I can understand less. My complexion makes me loathe it rather more than my reason condemns it: I have never even wanted to steal anything from anyone. It is true that my part of the world is rather more infamous for theft than the rest of our French nation: yet we have all seen in our time, on several occasions, men of good family from other provinces convicted of many dreadful robberies. I am afraid that we must partly attribute such depravity to the fault of their fathers.

12. If anyone then tells me, as a very intelligent nobleman once did, that the only practical advantage he wanted to get from saving up all his money was to be honoured and courted by his children (since now that age had deprived him of strength that was the only remedy he had left against being treated with neglect and contempt by everybody, and so maintaining his authority over his family - and truly, not only old age but all forms of weakness are, according to Aristotle, great encouragements to miserliness)[〔2〕] - then there is something in that. But it is medicine to cure an illness the birth of which ought to have been prevented. A father is wretched indeed if he can only hold the love of his children - if you can call it love - by making them depend on his help.

13. We should make ourselves respected for our virtues and our abilities and loved for our goodness and gentlemanliness. The very ashes of a rare timber have their value, and we are accustomed to hold in respect and reverence the very bones and remains of honourable people. In the case of someone who has lived his life honourably, no old age can be so decrepit and smelly that it ceases to be venerable - especially to the children, whose souls should have been instructed in their duty not by need and want, nor by harshness nor force, but by reason:

et errat longe, mea quidem sententia,

Qui imperium credat esse gravius aut stabilius

Vi quod fit, quam illud quod amicitia adjungitur.

[if you ask my opinion, it is quite untrue that authority is firmer or more stable when it relies on force than when it is associated with affection.][〔3〕]

14. I condemn all violence in the education of tender minds which are being trained for honour and freedom. In rigour and constraint there is always something servile, and I hold that you will never achieve by force what you cannot achieve by reason, intelligence and skill.

15. That was the way I was brought up. They tell me that I tasted the rod only twice during all my childhood, and that was but lightly. I owed the same treatment to the children born to me; they all die, though, before they are weaned. But Leonor, an only daughter who has escaped that calamity, has reached the age of six or more (her mother's gentleness readily predisposing her that way) without our having used in her upbringing and in the punishment of her childish faults anything but words - gentle ones at that. And even if my hopes for her turn out to be frustrated, there are other causes in plenty to blame for that without finding fault with my method of upbringing, which I know to be just and natural.

16. I would have been even more punctilious with boys, who are less born to serve and whose mode-of-being is freer: I would have loved to make their hearts overflow with openness and frankness. I have never seen caning achieve anything except making souls more cowardly or more maliciously stubborn.

17. Do we want to be loved by our children? Do we want to remove any occasion for their wishing us dead? - though no occasion for so horrible a wish could ever be right or pardonable: 'nullum scelus rationem habet' [no crime has rational justification] - then let us within reason enrich their lives with whatever we have at our disposal. To achieve that we ought not to get married so young that our adult years almost become confounded with theirs. Such unseemliness can plunge us into many great difficulties - I mean especially in the case of the nobility, whose way of life is one of leisure and who can live, as we say, on their income. In other cases, where life is a struggle for money, the fellowship of a great many children is a help to the whole family; they are so many new ways and means of helping to enrich it.

18. I was thirty-three when I married; and I approve of thirty-five - the opinion attributed to Aristotle. Plato does not want any man to marry before thirty; he is also right to laugh at spouses who lie together after fifty-five, judging their offspring unworthy to live and eat.[〔4〕]

19. It was Thales who gave the right ages; his mother pressed him to get married when he was young: 'Too soon,' he said. When he was older: 'Too late!' Accept no time as opportune for any inopportune activity!

20. The Ancient Gauls reckoned it to be extremely reprehensible for a man to lie with a woman before he was twenty, particularly advising those who wanted to train for war to remain chaste well into adulthood, because sexual intercourse makes minds soft and deflects them.

Ma hor congiunto a giovinetta sposa,

Lieto homai de' figli, era invilito

Ne gli affetti di padre e di marito.

[But now, married to a young wife, happy to have children, he was weakened by his love as father and husband.][〔5〕]

21. The history of Greece notes how Iccus of Tarentum, Chryso, Astylus, Diopompus and others deprived themselves of any sort of sexual activity during all the time they were getting their bodies in trim for the races, wrestling and other contests at the Olympic Games.[〔6〕]

22. Muley Hassan, the Dey of Tunis (the one whom the Emperor Charles V restored to his throne) was critical of his father's memory because he was always with his wives, calling him a weak effeminate spawner of children.

23. In a certain province in the Spanish Indies men were allowed to marry only after forty, yet girls could marry at ten.[〔7〕]

24. If a nobleman is only thirty-five it is too soon for him to make way for a twenty-year-old son: he has still got to achieve a reputation in military expeditions or at the Court of his monarch: he needs his cash; he should allow his son a share but not forget himself. Such a man can rightly give the answer which fathers often have on their lips: 'I have no wish to be stripped bare before I go and lie down'. But a father who is brought low by age and illness, whose weakness and ill-health deprive him of ordinary human fellowship, does wrong to himself and to his family if he broods over a great pile of riches. If he is wise, he has reached the period when he really ought to want to get stripped and lie down - not stripped to his shirt but down to a nice warm dressing-gown. He has no more use for all the remaining pomp: he should give it all away as a present to those whom it ought to belong to by Nature's ordinance.

25. It is right that he should let them use what Nature deprives him of: otherwise there is certainly an element of malice and envy. The finest gesture the Emperor Charles V ever made was when, in imitation of some ancient holders of his rank, he was able to recognize that reason clearly commands us to strip off our garments when they weigh us down and get in our way, and to go and lie down when our legs fail us. Once he began to feel deficient in the strength and energy needed to continue to conduct his affairs with the glory he had earned, he handed over his wealth, his rank and his power to his son:

Solve senescentem mature sanus equum, ne

Peccet ad extremum ridendus, et ilia ducat.

[Be wise enough to unharness that tired old nag lest it ends up short-winded, stumbling while men jeer at it.][〔8〕]

26. This defect of not realizing in time what one is, of not being aware of the extreme decline into weakness which old age naturally brings to our bodies and our souls - to them equally in my opinion unless the soul actually has the larger share - has ruined the reputation of most of the world's great men. I have seen in my lifetime and intimately known great men in authority who had clearly declined amazingly from their former capacities, which I knew of from the reputation they had acquired in their better years. For their honour's sake I would deeply have wished that they had withdrawn to their estates, dropping the load of public or military affairs which were no longer meant for their shoulders.

27. There was a nobleman whose house I used to frequent who was a widower, very old but still with some sap in him. He had several daughters to marry and a son already old enough to enter society, so that his house was burdened with considerable expenditure and quite a lot of outside visitors; he took little pleasure in this, not only out of concern for economy but even more because, at his age, he had adopted a mode of life far different from ours. In that rather bold way I have I told him one day that it would be more becoming if he made room for us youth, leaving his principal residence to his son (for it was the only one properly equipped and furnished) and withdrew to a neighbouring estate of his where nobody would trouble his rest, since, given his children's circumstances, there was no other way he could avoid our unsuitable company. He later took my advice and liked it.

28. That is not to say we should make a binding gift of our property and not be able to go back on it. I am old enough to have to play that role now, and would leave the young the use of my house and property but be free to withdraw my consent if they gave me cause. I would let them have use of them because they no longer gave me pleasure, but I would retain as much general authority over affairs as I wanted to, for I have always thought that it must be a great happiness for an old father to train his own children in the management of his affairs; he could then, during his lifetime, observe how they do it, offering advice and instruction based on his own experience in such things, and personally arranging for the ancient honour and order of his house to come into the hands of his successors, confirming in this way the hopes he could place in their future management of them.

29. To do this I would not avoid their company; I would like to be near so as to watch them and to enjoy their fun and festivities as much as my age permitted. Even if I did not live among them (as I could not do without embarrassing the company by the gloominess of my age and by my being subject to illnesses - and also without being forced to restrict my own rules and habits), I would at least like to live near them in some corner of my house - not the fanciest but the most comfortable. Not (as I saw a few years ago) a dean of St-Hilaire-de-Poitiers brought to such a pitch of solitude by the troublesome effects of his melancholy that, when I went into his room, he had not set foot outside it for twenty-two years; yet he could still move about freely and easily, apart from a rheumatic flux discharging into his stomach. He would let scarcely anyone in to see him even once a week; he always stayed shut up in that room all by himself except for a valet who brought him his food once a day and who merely went in and out. His only occupation was to walk about reading a book (for he had some acquaintance with literature), obstinately determined as he was to die in those conditions - as soon afterwards he did.

30. I would try to have gentle relations with my children and so encourage in them an active love and unfeigned affection for me, something easily achieved in children of a well-born nature; of course if they turn out to be wild beasts (which our century produces in abundance) then you must hate them and avoid them as such.

31. I am against the custom of forbidding children to say 'Father' and requiring them to use some other, more respectful title, as though Nature had not sufficiently provided for our authority. We address God Almighty as Father and scorn to have our own children call us by that name.

32. It is also unjust, and mad, to deprive our grown-up children of easy relations with their fathers by striving to maintain an austere and contemptuous frown, hoping by that to keep them in fear and obedience. That is a quite useless farce which makes fathers loathsome to children and, what is worse, makes them ridiculous. Since youth and vigour are in their children's hands they enjoy the current favour of the world; they treat with mockery the fierce tyrannical countenance of a man with no blood left in his veins or his heart - scarecrows in a field of flax! Even if I were able to make myself feared I would rather make myself loved.

33. There are so many drawbacks in old age, so much powerlessness; it so merits contempt that the best endowment it can acquire is the fond love of one's family: its arms are no longer fear and commands.

34. I know one man who had a most imperious youth. Now that old age is coming upon him, despite trying to accept it as well as he can, he slaps and bites and swears - the stormiest master in France; he frets himself with cares and watchfulness: but it is all a farce which the family conspire in; the others have access to the best part of his granary, his cellar and even his purse: meanwhile he keeps the keys in his pouch, dearer to him than sight itself. While he is happy to keep so spare and thrifty a table, in various secret places in his house all is dissipation, gambling, prodigality and tales about his fits of temper and his precautions. Everybody is on the lookout against him. If some wretched servant happens to become devoted to him, suspicion is immediately thrown on to him - a quality which old age is only too ready to ruminate upon. How many times has that man boasted to me of keeping his family on a tight rein, of the meticulous obedience and reverence he received because of it, and of the lucid watch he kept over his affairs:

Ille solus nescit omnia!

[He alone is unaware of the lot!][〔9〕]

No man of my acquaintance can claim more qualities, natural and acquired, proper for maintaining his mastery; yet he had failed completely, like a child. That is why I have picked him out as an example from several other cases that I know.

35. It would make a good scholastic debate: whether or not he is better off as he is. In his presence, all things defer to him; his authority runs its empty course: nobody ever resists him; they believe what he says, they fear and respect him ... as much as he could wish! Should he dismiss a servant he packs his bag and is off at once - but only out of his presence. Old people's steps are so slow and their senses so confused that the valet can live a full year in the house doing his duty without their even noticing it. At the appropriate time a letter arrives from distant parts, a pitiful one, a submissive one, full of promises to do better in the future; the valet then finds himself back in favour.

36. Does my Lord strike a bargain and send a missive which the family do not like? They suppress it, sometimes inventing afterwards reasons to explain the lack of action or reply. Since no letters from outside are ever brought to him first, he only sees the ones which it seems convenient for him to know. If he happens to get hold of any, he always has to rely on somebody else to read them for him, so they invent things on the spot: they are always pretending that someone is begging his pardon in the very letter that contains abuse. In short he sees his affairs only through some counterfeit image designed to be as pleasing to him as they can make it so as not to awake his spleen or his anger.

37. Under various guises, but all to the same effect, I have seen plenty of households run long and steadily in this way.

38. Wives are always disposed to disagree with their husbands. With both hands they grasp at any pretence for contradicting them; any excuse serves as full justification. I know one who used to rob her husband wholesale - in order, she told her confessor, to 'fatten up her almsgiving'. (There's a religious spendthrift for you to trust!) Whatever their husbands agree to never provides them with enough dignity. To give it grace and authority they must have usurped it by ruse or by force, but always unjustly. When, as in the case I am thinking of, they are acting against some poor old man on behalf of the children, they seize on this pretext and are honoured for serving their own passions; and, as though they were all slaves together, readily plot against his sovereignty and government. If the children are male and grown-up, in the bloom of youth, then their mothers gang up with them and corrupt the steward, the bursar and everyone else by force or favour.

39. Old men without wives and children fall into this evil less easily but more cruelly and with less dignity. Cato the Elder already said in his time, 'So many valets: so many enemies.' Given the gulf separating the purity of his century from ours, just think whether he was not really warning us that wife, sons and valet are all 'so many enemies' in our case.

40. It is a good thing that decrepitude furnishes us with the sweet gifts of inadvertency, ignorance and a readiness to be cheated. If we were to resist, what would happen to us, especially nowadays when the judges who settle our quarrels are usually on the side of the children - and venal?

41. The cheating may escape my sight, but it does not escape my sight that I am very cheatable. Thrice and four times blessed is he who can entrust his pitiful old age into the hands of a friend. And shall we have ever said enough about the value of a friend and how totally different it is from bonds based on contracts! Even that counterpart to a friend which I see between beasts, how devoutly I honour it! Am I better or worse off for having savoured a friend? Better off, certainly. My regret for him consoles me and honours me. Is it not a most pious and pleasant task in life to be ever performing his obsequies? Can any pleasure possessed equal that pleasure lost? I would readily let myself be rapt insensible lingering over so caressing a notion.

42. Others may deceive me, but at least I do not deceive myself into thinking that I can protect myself against it; nor do I cudgel my brains for ways of making myself able to do so. Only in my own bosom can I find salvation from treachery like this - not in disquieting and tumultuous inquisitiveness but in diversion and constancy. Whenever I hear of the state that some other man is in, I waste no time over that but immediately turn my eyes on to myself to see how I am doing. Everything which touches him touches me too. What has happened to him is a warning and an alert coming from the same quarter. Every day, every hour, we say things about others which ought more properly to be addressed to ourselves if only we had learned to turn our thoughts inward as well as widely outward. Similarly many authors inflict wounds on the cause they defend by dashing out against the attackers, hurling shafts at their enemies which can properly be hurled back at them.

43. The late Monsieur de Monluc, the Marshal, when talking to me of the loss of his son (a truly brave gentleman of great promise who died on the island of Madeira), among other regrets emphasized the grief and heartbreak he felt at never having revealed himself to his son and at having lost the pleasure of knowing and savouring him, all because of his fancy to appear with the gravity of a stern father; he had never told him of the immense love he felt for him and how worthy he rated him for his virtue. 'And all that poor boy saw of me,' he said, 'was a frowning face full of scorn; he is gone, believing I was unable to love him or to judge him as he deserved. Whom was I keeping it for, that knowledge of the special love I harboured for him in my soul! Should not he have felt all the pleasure of it, and all the bonds of gratitude? I forced myself, I tortured myself, to keep up that silly mask, thereby losing the joy of his company - and his goodwill as well, which must have been cold towards me: he had never received from me anything but brusqueness or known anything but a tyrannous facade.'

44. I find that lament to be reasonable and rightly held: for as I know only too well from experience when we lose those we love there is no consolation sweeter than the knowledge of having remembered to tell them everything and to have enjoyed the most perfect and absolute communication with them.

45. As much as I can I open myself to my own folk, and am most ready to tell them or anyone else what I intend towards them and what is the judgement I make on them. I hasten to reveal myself, to make myself known, for I do not want them to be misled about me in any way whatsoever.

46. According to Caesar, among the customs peculiar to our ancient Gauls there was the following: sons were not presented to their fathers and never dared to appear in public with them until they had begun to bear arms, as if to signify that the time had now come for the fathers to admit them to their intimate acquaintance.[〔10〕]

47. Yet another abuse of paternal discretion which I have seen in my time is when fathers are not content with having deprived their children of their natural share of the property during their long lifetime, but then go and leave authority over all of it after their death to their widows, free to dispose of it at their pleasure. One lord I have known (among the highest officers of the Realm) could rightfully have expected to come into property worth fifty thousand crowns a year: yet he died in need, overwhelmed with debts at the age of fifty, while his mother, despite advanced senility, still enjoyed rights over the entire property under the will of his father, who himself had lived to be eighty.

48. To me that seems in no way reasonable.

49. For all that, I cannot see it helps much when a man whose affairs are prospering goes and seeks a wife who burdens him with a large dowry: no debt contracted outside the family is more ruinous to a household. My ancestors have all followed this precept, most fittingly; so have I.

50. Yet those who warn us against marrying rich wives out of fear that they might be less beholden to us and more difficult wrongly lose a real advantage for a frivolous conjecture. If a woman is unreasonable it costs her no more to jump over one reason than another. Such women are most pleased with themselves when they are most in the wrong: it is the injustice which allures them; whereas for good women it lies in their virtuous deeds: the richer they are the more gracious they are, just as beautiful women are more willingly and more triumphantly chaste.

51. It is reasonable to let mothers run affairs until the sons are legally old enough to assume the responsibility; but the father has brought them up wrongly if (considering the normal weakness of the female) he could not expect them to be wiser and more competent than his wife once they have reached that age. But it would be even more unnatural to make mothers depend on the discretion of their sons. They should be given a provision generous enough to maintain their state according to the condition of their family and their age, especially since want or indigence are far more difficult for them to bear with decorum than for males: that burden ought to be put on the sons rather than on the mother.

52. On the whole, the soundest way of sharing out our property when we die is (I believe) to follow local customary law. The Law has thought it out better than we have, so it is better to let the Law make the wrong choice than rashly hazard doing so ourselves. The property does not really belong to us personally, since without our leave it is entailed by civil law to designated heirs. And even though we have some discretion as well, I hold that it would take a great and very clear reason to justify our depriving anyone of what he was entitled to by the fortune of his birth and of what common law leads him to expect; it would be an unreasonable abuse of that freedom to make it serve whims both frivolous and private.

53. Fate has been kind, sparing me opportunities which might have tempted me to change my predilection for the dictates of common law. I know people whom it would be a waste of time to serve long and dutifully: one word taken the wrong way can wipe out ten years of merit. Anyone able to butter them up when they are just about to go is lucky indeed! The latest action scoops the lot: it is not the best and most frequent services which prove efficacious but recent ones, present ones.

54. There are people who exploit their wills as sticks and carrots to punish or reward every action of those who may claim an interest in the inheritance. But this is a matter of long-lasting consequence; it is too weighty to be changed from moment to moment: wise men settle it once and for all - and have regard for the reasonable customs of the community.

55. We are a little too fond of male entail; we foresee a ridiculous eternity for our family name and attach too much weight to silly conjectures about the future based on the minds of little boys. Somebody might easily have been unjust to me, ousting me from my place because I was more lumpish, more leaden, more slow and more I will establish laws which make it known that private interests must reasonably yield to those of the community. Go, gently and willingly, whither human necessity bids you. It is for me, who favour all things equally and who take care of the people in general, to take care also of what you leave behind you.'[〔11〕]

57. To return to my subject, it seems to me right, somehow, that women should have no mastery over men save only the natural one of motherhood - unless it be for the chastisement of those who have wilfully submitted to them out of some feverish humour; but that does not apply to old women, the subject of our present discussion. It is the manifest truth of this consideration which has made us so ready to invent and entrench that Salic Law - which nobody has ever seen - which debars women from succeeding to our throne; and though Fortune has lent it more credence in some places than others, there is scarcely one jurisdiction in the world where that law is not cited as here, because of the genuine appearance of reason which gives it authority.

58. It is dangerous to leave the superintendence of our succession to the judgement of our wives and to their choice between our sons, which over and over again is iniquitous and fantastic. For those unruly tastes and physical cravings which they experience during pregnancy are ever-present in their souls. They regularly devote themselves to the weakest and to the feeblest, or to those (if they have any) who are still hanging about their necks. Since women do not have sufficient reasoning-power to select and embrace things according to their merits they allow themselves to be led to where natural impressions act most alone - like animals, which only know their young while they are still on the teat.

59. Incidentally, experience clearly shows us that the natural love to which we attach such importance has very shallow roots. For a very small sum of money we daily tear their own children out of women's arms and get them to take charge of our own; we make them entrust their babes to some wretched wet-nurse to whom we have no wish to commit our own or else to a nanny-goat; then we forbid them not only to give suck to theirs no matter what harm it might do them but even to look after them; they must devote themselves entirely to the service of our children. And then we see that in most cases custom begets a kind of bastard love more distracted than the natural kind; they are far more worried about the preservation of those foster-children than of the children who really belong to them.

60. I mentioned nanny-goats because the village-women where I live call in the help of goats when they cannot suckle their children themselves; I have now two menservants who never tasted mothers' milk for more than a week. These nanny-goats are trained from the outset to suckle human children; they recognize their voices when they start crying and come running up. They reject any other child you give them except the one they are feeding; the child does the same to another nanny-goat. The other day I saw an infant who had lost its own nanny-goat as the father had only borrowed it from a neighbour: the child rejected a different one which was provided and died, certainly of hunger.

61. The beasts debase and bastardize maternal affection as easily as we do.

62. Herodotus tells of a certain district of Libya where men lie with women indiscriminately, but where, once a child can toddle, it recognizes its own father out of the crowd, natural instinct guiding its first footsteps.[〔12〕] There are frequent mistakes, I believe ...

63. Now once we consider the fact that we love our children simply because we begot them, calling them our second selves, we can see that we also produce something else from ourselves, no less worthy of commendation: for the things we engender in our soul, the offspring of our mind, of our wisdom and talents, are the products of a part more noble than the body and are more purely our own. In this act of generation we are both mother and father; these 'children' cost us dearer and, if they are any good, bring us more honour. In the case of our other children their good qualities belong much more to them than to us: we have only a very slight share in them; but in the case of these, all their grace, worth and beauty belong to us. For this reason they have a more lively resemblance and correspondence to us. Plato adds that such children are immortal and immortalize their fathers - even deifying them, as in the case of Lycurgus, Solon and Minos.[〔13〕]

64. Since our history books are full of exemplary cases of the common kind of paternal love, it seemed to me not inappropriate to cite a few examples of this other kind too.

65. Heliodorus, that good bishop of Tricca, preferred to forgo the honour of so venerable a bishopric with its income and its dignity rather than to destroy his 'daughter', who still lives on - a handsome girl but attired perhaps with a little more care and indulgence than suits the daughter of a priest, of a clerk in holy orders - and fashioned in too erotic a style.

66. In Rome there was a figure of great bravery and dignity called Labienus; among other qualities he excelled in every kind of literature; he was, I think, the son of that great Labienus who was the foremost among captains who served under Caesar in the Gallic Wars, subsequently threw in his lot with Pompey the Great and fought for him most bravely until Caesar defeated him in Spain. There were several people who were jealous of the Labienus I am referring to; he also probably had enemies among the courtiers and favourites of the contemporary Emperors for his frankness and for inheriting his father's innate hostility towards tyranny, which we may believe coloured his books and writing. His enemies prosecuted him before the Roman magistrates and obtained a conviction, requiring several of the books he had published to be burnt. This was the very first case of the death-penalty being inflicted on books and erudition; it was subsequently applied at Rome in several other cases. We did not have means nor matter enough for our cruelty unless we also let it concern itself with things which Nature has exempted from any sense of pain, such as our renown and the products of our minds, and unless we inflicted physical suffering on the teachings and the documents of the Muses.

67. Labienus could not bear such a loss nor survive such beloved offspring; he had himself borne to the family vault on a litter and shut up alive; there he provided his own death and burial. It is difficult to find any example of fatherly love more vehement than that one. When his very eloquent friend Cassius Severus saw those books being burnt, he shouted that he too ought to be burnt alive with them since he actively preserved their contents in his memory.

68. A similar misfortune happened to Greuntius Cordus who was accused of having praised Brutus and Cassius in his books. That slavish base and corrupt Senate (worthy of a worse master than Tiberius) condemned his writings to the pyre: it pleased him to keep his books company as they perished in the flames by starving himself to death.

69. Lucan was a good man, condemned by that blackguard Nero; in the last moments of his life, when most of his blood had already gushed from his veins (he had ordered his doctors to kill him by slashing them) and when cold had already seized his hands and feet and was starting to draw near to his vital organs, the very last thing he remembered were some verses from his Pharsalian War; he recited them, and died with them as the last words on his lips. Was that not saying farewell to his children tenderly and paternally, the equivalent of those adieus and tender embraces which we keep for our children when we die, as well as being an effect of that natural instinct to recall at our end those things which we held dearest to us while we lived?

70. When Epicurus lay dying, tormented they say by the most extreme colic paroxysms, he found consolation only in the beauty of the philosophy he had taught to the world;[〔14〕] are we to believe that he would have found happiness in any number of well-born, well-educated children (if he had had any) to equal what he found in the abundant writing which he had brought forth? And if he had had the choice of leaving either an ill-conceived and deformed child behind him or a stupid and inept book, would - not he alone but any man of similar ability - have preferred to incur the first tragedy rather than the other?

71. It would probably have been impious of Saint Augustine (for example) if someone had obliged him to destroy either his children (supposing he had had any) or else his writings (from which our religion receives such abundant profit) and he had not preferred to destroy his children.

72. I am not at all sure whether I would not much rather have given birth to one perfectly formed son by commerce with the Muses than by commerce with my wife. As for this present child of my brain, what I give it I give unconditionally and irrevocably, just as one does to the children of one's body; such little good as I have already done it is no longer mine to dispose of; it may know plenty of things which I know no longer, and remember things about me that I have forgotten; if the need arose to turn to it for help, it would be like borrowing from a stranger. It is richer than I am, yet I am wiser than it.

73. Few devotees of poetry would not have been more gratified at fathering the Aeneid than the fairest boy in Rome, nor fail to find the loss of one more bearable than the other. For according to Aristotle, of all artists the one who is most in love with his handiwork is the poet.[〔15〕]

74. It is hard to believe that Epaminondas (who boasted that his posterity consisted in two 'daughters' who would bring honour to their father one day - he meant his two noble victories over the Spartans) would have agreed to exchange them for daughters who were the most gorgeous in the whole of Greece; or that Alexander and Caesar had ever wished they could give up the greatness of their glorious feats in war in return for the pleasure of having sons and heirs however perfect, however accomplished; indeed I very much doubt whether Phidias or any other outstanding sculptor would have found as much delight in the survival and longevity of his physical children as in some excellent piece of sculpture brought to completion by his long-sustained labour and his skill according to the rules of his art.

75. And as for those raging vicious passions which have sometimes inflamed fathers with love for their daughters, or mothers for their sons, similar ones can be found in this other kind of parenthood: witness the tale of Pygmalion who, having carved the statue of a uniquely beautiful woman, was so hopelessly ravished by an insane love for his own work that, for the sake of his frenzy, the gods had to bring her to life:

Tentatum mollescit ebur, positoque rigore

Subsedit digitis.

[He touches the ivory statue; it starts to soften; its hardness gone, it yields to his fingers.][〔16〕]

NOTE

〔1〕　Aristotle, Nicomachaean Ethics, IX, vii, 4-6.

〔2〕　Aristotle, Nicomachaean Ethics, IV, i, 37.

〔3〕　Terence, Adelphi, I, i, 40-3.

〔4〕　Aristotle, Politics, VII, xvi (age of thirty-seven not thirty-five); Plato, Republic, V, 460A ff.; cf. Tiraquellus, De legibus connubialibus, VI, §§ 44-7; 52.

〔5〕　Plutarch, Life of Thales; Caesar, Gallic Wars, VI (cf. Tiraquellus, ibid., VI, § 47); Torquato Tasso, Gierusalemme liberata, X, 39-41.

〔6〕　Tiraquellus, ibid., XV, § 26, citing Plato, Laws, VIII, 839E-840A.

〔7〕　Paolo Giovio, Historia sui temporis, on 'Muleasses' (Muley Hassan); Lopez de Gomara, Histoire générale des Indes.

〔8〕　Horace, Epistles, I, i, 8. (The 'old nag' is his Muse: hence the following development.)

〔9〕　Terence, Adelphi, IV, ii, 9.

〔10〕　Caesar, Gallic Wars, VI, xviii.

〔11〕　Plato, Laws, XI, 922 D-924 A.

〔12〕　Tiraquellus, De legibus connubialibus, VII, § 51; Herodotus, History, IV.

〔13〕　Plato, Phaedrus, 258 C, dealing with a man's writings, his 'brainchildren'; but Montaigne has transcribed Minos for Darius.

〔14〕　Cicero, De finibus, II, xxx, 96.

〔15〕　Aristotle, Nicomachaean Ethics, IX, vii, 3.

〔16〕　Ovid, Metamorphoses, X, 243 ff., citing 283-4.

6
On moderation

1. It is as though our very touch bore infection: things which in themselves are good and beautiful are corrupted by our handling of them. We can seize hold even of Virtue in such a way that our action makes her vicious if we clasp her in too harsh and too violent an embrace. Those who say that Virtue knows no excess (since she is no longer Virtue if there is excess within her) are merely playing with words.

Insani sapiens nomen ferat, aequus iniqui,

Ultra quam satis est virtutem si petat ipsam

[The name of 'insane' is borne by the Sage and the name of 'unjust' is borne by the Just, if in their strivings after Virtue herself they go beyond what is sufficient.][〔1〕]

That is a subtle observation on the part of philosophy: you can both love virtue too much and behave with excess in an action which itself is just. The Voice of God adapts itself fittingly to that bias: 'Be not more wise than it behoveth, but be ye soberly wise.'[〔2〕]

2. I have seen one of our great noblemen harm the reputation of his religion by showing himself religious beyond any example of men of his rank.[〔3〕]

3. I like natures which are temperate and moderate. Even when an immoderate zeal for the good does not offend me it still stuns me and makes it difficult for me to give it a Christian name. Neither Pausanias' mother (who made the first accusation against her son and who brought the first stone to wall him up for his death) nor Posthumius (the Dictator who had his own son put to death because he had been carried away by youthful ardour and had fought - successfully - slightly ahead of his unit) seem 'just' to me: they seem odd.[〔4〕] I neither like to advise nor to imitate a virtue so savage and so costly: the archer who shoots beyond his target misses it just as much as the one who falls short; my eyes trouble me as much when I suddenly come up into a strong light as when I plunge into darkness.

4. Callicles says in Plato[〔5〕] that, at its extremes, philosophy is harmful; he advises us not to go more deeply into it than the limits of what is profitable: taken in moderation philosophy is pleasant and useful, but it can eventually lead to a man's becoming vicious and savage, contemptuous of religion and of the accepted laws, an enemy of social intercourse, an enemy of our human pleasures, useless at governing cities, at helping others or even at helping himself - a man whose ears you could box with impunity. What he says is true, for in its excesses philosophy enslaves our native freedom and with untimely subtleties makes us stray from that beautiful and easy path that Nature has traced for us.

5. The affection which we bear towards our wives is entirely legitimate: yet Theology nevertheless puts reins on it and restrains it. Among the reasons which Saint Thomas Aquinas[〔6〕] cites in condemnation of marriages between relatives who are within the forbidden affinities I think I once read the following: There is a risk that the love felt for such a wife might be immoderate; for if the marital affection between them is full and entire (as it ought to be) and then you add on to it the further affection proper among kinsfolk, there is no doubt that such an over-measure would ravish such a husband beyond the limits of reason.

6. Those sciences which govern the morals of mankind, such as Theology and philosophy, make everything their concern: no activity is so private or so secret as to escape their attention or their jurisdiction. Only mere beginners criticize their freedom to do so: they are like the kind of women whose organs are as accessible as you wish for copulation but who are too bashful to show them to the doctor. On behalf of these sciences I therefore want to teach husbands the following - if, that is, there are any who are still too eager: even those very pleasures which they enjoy when lying with their wives are reproved if not kept within moderation; you can fall into licence and excess in this as in matters unlawful. All those shameless caresses which our first ardour suggests to us in our sex-play are not only unbecoming to our wives but harmful to them when practised on them. At least let them learn shamelessness from some other hand! They are always wide enough awake when we need them. Where this is concerned what I have taught has been natural and uncomplicated.

7. Marriage is a bond both religious and devout: that is why the pleasure we derive from it must be serious, restrained and intermingled with some gravity; its sensuousness should be somewhat wise and dutiful. Its chief end is procreation, so there are those who doubt whether it is right to seek intercourse when we have no hope of conception, as when the woman is pregnant or too old. For Plato that constitutes a kind of homicide. There are whole peoples, including the Mahometans, who abominate intercourse with women who are pregnant, and others still during monthly periods. Zenobia admitted her husband for a single discharge; once that was over she let him run wild throughout her pregnancy, giving him permission to begin again only once it was over. There was a fine and noble-hearted marriage for you![〔7〕]

8. It was from some yearning sex-starved poet that Plato borrowed his story about Jupiter's making such heated advances to his wife one day that he could not wait for her to lie on the bed but tumbled her on the floor, forgetting the great and important decisions which he had just reached with the other gods in his celestial Court and boasting that he had enjoyed it as much as when, hidden from her parents, he had first taken her maidenhead.[〔8〕]

9. The kings of Persia did invite their wives as guests to their festivities, but once the wine had seriously inflamed them so that they had to let their lust gallop free, they packed them off to their quarters so as not to make them accomplices of their immoderate appetites, sending instead for other women whom they were not bound to respect.[〔9〕]

10. It is not every pleasure or favour that is well lodged in people of every sort. Epaminondas had a dissolute boy put in prison: Pelopidas, for his own purposes, begged for his freedom; Epaminondas refused but granted it to one of his whores who also begged for it, saying that it was a favour due to a mistress but not to a captain. Sophocles, when a Praetor with Pericles, happened to see a handsome youth go by: 'What a handsome boy,' said he to Pericles. 'That', said Pericles, 'would be all right coming from anyone but a Praetor, who must not only have pure hands but pure eyes.'[〔10〕]

11. When the wife of the Emperor Aelius Verus complained of his permitting himself affairs with other women, he replied that he acted thus for reasons of conscience, marriage being a term of honour and dignity not of wanton and lascivious lust. And our old Church authors make honourable mention of a wife who rejected her husband since she had no wish to be a partner to his lascivious and immoderate embraces.[〔11〕]

12. In short there is no pleasure, however proper, which does not become a matter of reproach when excessive and intemperate.

13. But, seriously though, is not Man a wretched creature? Because of his natural attributes he is hardly able to taste one single pleasure pure and entire: yet he has to go and curtail even that by arguments; he is not wretched enough until he has increased his wretchedness by art and assiduity.

Fortunae miseras auximus arte vias.

[The wretched paths of Fortune we make worse by art.][〔12〕]

14. Human wisdom is stupidly clever when used to diminish the number and sweetness of such pleasures as do belong to us, just as she employs her arts with diligence and fitness when she brings comb and cosmetics to our ills and makes us feel them less. If I had founded a school of philosophy I would have taken another route - a more natural one, that is to say a true, convenient and inviolate one; and I might have made myself strong enough to know when to stop.

15. Consider the fact that those physicians of our souls and bodies, as though plotting together, can find no other way to cure us and no other remedy for our illnesses of soul and body than by torment, pain and tribulation. Vigils, fasting, hair-shirts and banishments to distant solitary places, endless imprisonments, scourges and other sufferings have been brought in to that end: but only on condition that the suffering is real and should cause bitter pain, and that there should not befall what happened to a man called Gallio who was banished to the island of Lesbos: Rome was told that he was enjoying himself there and that what had been inflicted as a punishment was turning into a pleasure, at which he was ordered back to wife and home and commanded to stay put, so as to adapt the punishment to his real feelings.[〔13〕] For if a man's health and happiness were made keener by fasting, or if he found fish more tasty than meat, it would cease to be a salutary prescription: just as drugs prescribed by the other kind of doctor have no effect on anyone who swallowed them with pleasure and enjoyment. The bitter taste and the hardship are attributes which make them work. A constitution which could regularly stand rhubarb would spoil its efficacy: to cure our stomachs it must be something which hurts it: and here the usual axiom that 'contraries cure contraries' breaks down; for in this case illness cures illness.

16. This notion is somewhat like that other very ancient one which was universally embraced by all religions and which leads us to think that we can please Heaven and Nature by our murders and our massacres.

17. Even in our fathers' time Amurath, when he conquered the Isthmus, sacrificed six hundred Greek youths for the soul of his father, so that their blood might serve as a propitiation, expiating the sins of that dead man.[〔14〕] And in those new lands discovered in our own time, lands pure and virgin compared with ours, the practice is accepted virtually everywhere: all their idols are slaked with human blood, not without various examples of dreadful cruelty. Men are burned alive; when halfroasted they are withdrawn from the fire so that their hearts and entrails can be plucked out; others, even women, are flayed alive: their skin, all bloody, serves as a cloak to mask others; and there are no less examples of constancy and determination. For those wretches who are to be immolated, old men, women and children, beg for alms a few days beforehand as offertories at their sacrifice, and present themselves to the slaughter singing and dancing with the congregation. The ambassadors from the King of Mexico, to make Fernando Cortez realize the greatness of their master, first told him that he had thirty vassal-lords, each one of whom could muster a hundred thousand fighting men, and that he dwelt in the strongest fairest city under Heaven; they then added that he had fifty thousand men sacrificed to the gods every year. It is truly said that he cultivated war with some great neighbouring peoples not merely to train the youth of his country but chiefly to furnish prisoners of war for his sacrifices. In another place there was a town where they welcomed Cortez by sacrificing fifty men at the same time. And I will relate one more account: when Cortez had conquered some of these peoples they sent messengers to find out about him and to seek his friendship. They offered him three sorts of gifts in this wise: 'Lord, here are five slaves; if thou art a fierce god who feedest on flesh and blood, eat them and we shall bring thee more. If thou art a kindly god, here are feathers and incense; if thou art human, accept these birds and these fruits.'[〔15〕]

NOTE

〔1〕　Horace, Epistles, I, vi, 15-16.

〔2〕　Romans 12: 3, following the Vulgate Latin version in which Montaigne read his Bible.

〔3〕　Perhaps King Henry III.

〔4〕　Diodorus Siculus, XI, x; XII, xix.

〔5〕　Plato, Gorgias, 484C-D.

〔6〕　Thomas Aquinas, Summa theologica, IIa, IIac, 154, art. 9.

〔7〕　Plato, Laws, VIII, 838A ff.; Guillaume Postel, Histoire des Turcs; for Zenobia, Tiraquellus, De legibus connubialibus, IX, 88.

〔8〕　Plato, Laws, III, 390 BC, after Homer, Iliad, XIV, 294-341.

〔9〕　Plutarch (tr. Amyot), Préceptes de mariage, 146E.

〔10〕　Plutarch (tr. Amyot), Instruction pour ceux qui manient les affaires d'Estat, 167 H; Cicero, De officiis, I, xl, 144, distinguishing between moderation (modestia) and orderly conduct (eutaxia).

〔11〕　E.g., Eusebius (Pamphilus), Ecclesiastical History, IV.

〔12〕　Propertius, III, vii, 32.

〔13〕　The Senator Junius Gallio; cf. Tacitus, Annals, VI, iii.

〔14〕　Related by Laonicus Chalcocondylas (tr. Blaise de Vigenère), Histoire de la décadence de l'empire grec, VII, iv.

〔15〕　All from Francisco Lopez de Gomara, Historia de Mexico, Antwerp, 1554 (tr. A. de Cravaliz as Historia del Capitano Don Fernando Cortes, Rome, 1556).

7
That we should not be deemed happy
till after our death

1.

Scilicet ultima semper

Expectanda dies homini est, dicique beatus

Ante obitum nemo, supremaque funera debet.

[You must always await a man's last day: before his death and last funeral rites, no one should be called happy.][〔1〕]

There is a story about this which children know; it concerns King Croesus: having been taken by Cyrus and condemned to death, he cried out as he awaited execution, 'O Solon, Solon!' This was reported to Cyrus who inquired of him what it meant. Croesus explained to him that Solon had once given him a warning which he was now proving true to his own cost: that men, no matter how Fortune may smile on them, can never be called happy until you have seen them pass through the last day of their life, on account of the uncertainty and mutability of human affairs which lightly shift from state to state, each one different from the other. That is why Agesilaus replied to someone who called the King of Persia happy because he had come so young to so great an estate, 'Yes: but Priam was not wretched when he was that age.'[〔2〕] Descendants of Alexander the Great, themselves kings of Macedonia, became cabinet-makers and scriveners in Rome; tyrants of Sicily became school-teachers in Corinth. A conqueror of half the world, a general of numerous armies, became a wretched suppliant to the beggarly officials of the King of Egypt: that was the cost of five or six more months of life to Pompey the Great. And during our fathers' lifetime Ludovico Sforza, the tenth Duke of Milan, who for so long had been the driving force in Italy, was seen to die prisoner at Loches - but (and that was the worst of it) only after living there ten years. The fairest Queen, widow of the greatest King in Christendom, has she not just died by the hand of the executioner?[〔3〕] There are hundreds of other such examples. For just as storms and tempests seem to rage against the haughty arrogant height of our buildings, so it could seem that there are spirits above us, envious of any greatness here below.

Usque adeo res humanas vis abdita quaedam

Obterit, et pulchros fasces saevasque secures

Proculcare, ac ludibrio sibi habere videtur.

[Some hidden force apparently topples the affairs of men, seeming to trample down the resplendent fasces and the lictor's unyielding axe, holding them in derision.][〔4〕]

Fortune sometimes seems precisely to he in ambush for the last day of a man's life in order to display her power to topple in a moment what she had built up over the length of years, and to make us follow Laberius and exclaim: 'Nimirum hac die una plus vixi, mihi quam vivendum fuit.' [I have lived this day one day longer than I ought to have lived.][〔5〕]

2. The good counsel of Solon could be taken that way. But he was a philosopher: for such, the favours and ill graces of Fortune do not rank as happiness or unhappiness and for them great honours and powers are non-essential properties, counted virtually as things indifferent. So it seems likely to me that he was looking beyond that, intending to tell us that happiness in life (depending as it does on the tranquillity and contentment of a spirit well-born and on the resolution and assurance of an ordered soul) may never be attributed to any man until we have seen him act out the last scene in his play, which is indubitably the hardest. In all the rest he can wear an actor's mask: those fine philosophical arguments may be only a pose, or whatever else befalls us may not assay us to the quick, allowing us to keep our countenance serene. But in that last scene played between death and ourself there is no more feigning; we must speak straightforward French; we must show whatever is good and clean in the bottom of the pot:

Nam verae voces tum demum pectore ab imo

Ejiciuntur, et eripitur persona, manet res

[Only then are true words uttered from deep in our breast. The mask is ripped off: reality remains.][〔6〕]

That is why all the other actions in our life must be tried on the touchstone of this final deed. It is the Master-day, the day which judges all the others; it is (says one of the Ancients)[〔7〕] the day which must judge all my years now past. The assay of the fruits of my studies is postponed unto death. Then we shall see if my arguments come from my lips or my heart.

3. I note that several men by their death have given a good or bad reputation to their entire life. Scipio, Pompey's father-in-law, redeemed by a good death the poor opinion people had had of him until then. And when asked which of three men he judged most worthy of honour, Chabrias, Iphicrates or himself, Epaminondas replied, 'Before deciding that you must see us die.' (Indeed Epaminondas would be robbed of a great deal if anyone were to weigh his worth without the honour and greatness of his end.)

4. In my own times three of the most execrable and ill-famed men I have known, men plunged into every kind of abomination, died deaths which were well-ordered and in all respects perfectly reconciled: such was God's good pleasure.

5. Some deaths are fine and fortunate. I knew a man[〔8〕] whose thread of life was progressing towards brilliant preferment when it was snapped; his end was so splendid that, in my opinion, his great-souled search after honour held nothing so sublime as that snapping asunder: the goal he aimed for he reached before he had even set out; that was more grand and more glorious than anything he had wished or hoped for. As he fell he surpassed the power and reputation towards which his course aspired.

6. When judging another's life I always look to see how its end was borne: and one of my main concerns for my own is that it be borne well - that is, in a quiet and muted manner.

NOTE

〔1〕　Ovid, Metamorphoses, III, 135.

〔2〕　Plutarch, tr. Amyot, Dicts notables des Lacedaemoniens, p. 211C.

〔3〕　Ludovico Sforza, ousted in 1500, spent eight years in the dungeon at Loches; Mary Stuart (widow of Francis II of France) was beheaded in 1587.

〔4〕　Lucretius, V, 1233. (The fasces and axes were Roman symbols of State.)

〔5〕　Macrobius, Saturnalia, II, vii.

〔6〕　Lucretius, III, 57.

〔7〕　Seneca, Epist. moral., XXIV and XXVI.

〔8〕　Etienne de La Boëtie.

译者导读

玛丽·沃斯通克拉夫特（1759—1797），出身于一个普通市民家庭，她的家庭生活很不幸福，父亲酗酒成性，母亲愚蠢无能。玛丽从小没有享受家庭的温暖和接受过良好的家庭教育。她很早就自谋生路，做过小学教师、护理师和家庭女教师。艰辛的谋生之路磨炼了玛丽的意志，生活中男性和女性的各种不公现象激发了她写作的冲动。她一生写就了多篇小说和论文、一本旅行书简、一本法国大革命史、一本行为手册以及一本儿童文学。《女权辩护》（1792）是她最知名的作品。玛丽在这本书中表现出的超越普通女性的真知灼见，让她当之无愧地成为当代女性主义的先驱。

对普通大众—特别是女权主义者而言，沃斯通克拉夫特的一生要比她的作品更吸引人们的注意，这主要是由于她另类的生活方式。在与无政府主义运动的先驱者威廉·戈德温结婚之前，沃斯通克拉夫特还曾与两个男人有过两段不幸的爱情：其一是画家亨利希·菲斯利，其二是商人吉尔伯特·伊姆利。沃斯通克拉夫特与戈德温有一个女儿，即《弗兰肯斯坦》的作者玛丽·雪莱。38岁时，沃斯通克拉夫特死于产后并发症，遗留下几部未完成的手稿。

在沃斯通克拉夫特死后，戈德温出版了《〈女权辩护〉作者传》（1798），其中透露了她另类的生活方式。本为纪念妻子的戈德温，却在无意之间将她的名誉破坏了长达一个世纪之久。但是，随着20世纪初女权主义运动的兴起，沃斯通克拉夫特对性别平等的提倡以及对传统女性特质的批评开始变得日益重要。如今，她已被视作是女权主义哲学家的鼻祖之一，而女权主义者们也经常提到她的生活与作品。

在《女权辩护》中，她以实际生活中的各种鲜活事例，精辟地指出了女人温柔端庄的本质，并分析了致使男女不平等的各种陈规陋习。她指出社会上各种关于女性优点的意见造成了女性性格的软弱和无能，而女性的教育制度使女性处于一种“无知的奴隶式依附”状态。她主张女人应当以自己的理智赢得世人的敬重，而不是靠外表的装饰、性格的软弱博得男人的爱慕和同情。作为人类的女性，应当享有与男性相同的教育权和其他基本权利，而不应被视作社会的装饰品或婚姻交易中的财产。而要想从根本上改善女人的品格和风尚，就必须给予她们精神上的自由，培养她们的理性，让她们自由地思考，独立履行家庭责任，成为一个“人”。她的这些在当时看起来“离经叛道”的观点却成为很多女权主义者奋斗的准则。即使在现代，当我们重温这位伟大女性在200多年前写下的文字时，仍然不得不惊叹于她敏锐的洞察力和深刻的思索。

作者前言

我带着焦虑关切的心情审视历史和观察世界之后，产生了一种非常郁闷的悲愤感，让我的情绪十分低落。在不得不承认，造物主让人和人之间有巨大的差别，以及世界文明发展至今也是有失偏颇时，我不由得长叹一声。我曾经翻阅过很多本讨论教育问题的书，也耐心观察过父母的教育方式和学校的管理模式，但是结果如何呢？—我坚信，造成我强烈谴责的不幸境遇的主要原因，是对我的女性同胞教育问题的忽视；我还坚信，特别是女人，由于一个轻率结论导致的各种综合因素共同作用，使其陷入软弱和悲惨的境地。事实上，女人的行为举止显然证明了她们的思想是不健康的。就像生长在过于肥沃土壤里的花朵一样，为了美丽牺牲了力量和用途；而那些鲜艳的花朵，令那些评头论足的观赏者感到心满意足之后，在它们远未达到成熟期之前就凋谢了，无人问津。我通过阅读论述教育问题的书籍，认为这种华而不实的现象起因之一是一套错误的教育体制，写这些书的男人与其说把女性当作人来看，不如说把女性当作女人来看。他们热切渴望将女性变成迷人的情妇，而不是深情的妻子和理性的母亲。女人的理智被这种华而不实的论调蒙蔽太深，甚至现代社会的文明女性，除了极少数人之外，在应该拥有一种更为高尚的志向，并且通过自己的才能和品德赢得尊重的时候，却只是一门心思地试图激发别人对她们的爱慕。

因此，在讨论女人权利和行为的专著中，那些致力于改善女人权利和行为的著作不应忽略，特别是有些著作根本不讳言，女人虚伪的优雅已经使她们意志薄弱。有才华的作家创作的教科书和那些比较轻浮的作品一样具有相同的倾向。按照某些地区伊斯兰教的习俗，女人被看作是一种附属品，而不是人类的一部分。人们用差强人意的理由夸大男人和女人的差别，这种夸大的差别将男人区别于野兽，并把一根自然的权杖交给一个软弱的人。

但是作为一个女人，我无意引导读者认为我有意热烈探讨这些关于女人品行和低劣地位等有争议的问题；但是既然这个话题出现在我的面前，我就不能避而不谈，否则我的主要论点就会遭到曲解，因此我要花一点时间简单论述我的观点。在自然界，女人大多体力上不如男人，这是显而易见的。这就是自然法则，而这条法则似乎并没有为了女人而被废除或取消。因此男人在体力上有一定的优势是不容置疑的，而且这是一种高贵的天赋特权！但是男人仍然不满足于这种天然的优越地位，他们竭力将女人的地位贬得更低，只是为了让女人变成一时诱人的玩物。而女人沉溺于男人在肉欲支配下对她们表达的爱慕之情，内心不会努力追求一种永恒的兴趣，也不会尝试成为这些以和她们交往为消遣的同胞们的朋友。

我意识到了一个明显的推论。我到处都能听到反对女人男性化的呼声，但是哪里有这样的女人呢？如果男人如此疾呼，只是为了打击女人对打猎、射击和赌博的热情的话，那我也会十分乐意加入男人的疾呼；但是如果是为了反对女人模仿，确切地说，获取男人的才能和性格的话，那么我想，那些以理性、冷静眼光看待女人的人会和我一样，希望女人日益男性化，因为这些才能和品德能够提升人类的品格，让女人成为更高尚的动物，进而被广泛地称为人。

讨论至此，自然我们的话题就要一分为二。首先，我要以一种宏观的视角，将女人当作人来讨论，她们和男人一样，被神安放到这个世界上施展她们的才华；然后我要更加详细地探讨她们独特的职责。

我还希望避免犯一个很多作家都犯过的错误，因为目前女人接受的教育，其实是针对贵妇的，如果我们不包括《桑德夫和莫顿》[1]里面一点零散的间接建议的话。但是我以更加坚定的语气告诉我的女同胞们，我将特别关注那些中产阶级的女人，因为她们似乎处在最自然的状态。也许华而不实、道德败坏和爱慕虚荣的种子一直都是大人物播撒的。软弱而做作的人以一种不成熟、不自然的状态，超越了女性同胞的正常需求和感情，败坏了道德基础，将腐化堕落散布到社会大众中！这些人作为人类的一个阶级，是最需要别人怜悯的。有钱人的教育会让她们变得浮华而无助，而因为不用履行那些能提升人类品格的责任，她们正在发展的心灵无法得到锻炼。她们活着只是为了享乐，这种生活方式令她们很快就只能提供无聊的享乐了。

但是我的目的是分别探讨社会不同阶层的人和不同阶层中女人的道德品格，所以目前来看上述提示已经足够了。我只是指出了这个话题，因为我认为前言的精要就是对其所介绍的作品内容作一个大致的概括。

我希望我的女性同胞原谅，因为我把她们当作理智的人来看待，既不奉承她们迷人的魅力，也不认为她们处于一种永远也无法独立的幼稚状态。我真诚希望能指出什么是真正的尊严和人类的幸福。我希望说服女人努力争取身心两方面的力量，使她们相信：那些温柔的蜜语、敏感的心灵、细腻的情感和优雅的品位，都是软弱的同义词；而那些只配供人怜悯的人和爱情，很快就会成为人们鄙视的对象。

因此，我不愿意使用那些男人奉承我们或滋养我们奴隶般依赖性的甜言蜜语；我鄙视那些被认为是软弱女人特点的脆弱优雅的思维、精致细腻的情感和可爱顺服的行为；我希望指出品德比优雅更重要，我们追求的首要目标就是不论性别，培养人的品格，而所有的次要目标都应当用这个简单的标准来检验，这种追求是值得赞赏的。

这就是我计划的概述。如果我一想到这个问题就感受到强烈的情感，并因此表达我的信念的话，那么我的一部分读者必然也会感觉到我这样做是出于经验和思考。受到这个重大目标的激励，我就不屑于再推敲词语修饰文风了。我希望我的作品于人有益，真诚让我无法做作，因为我希望用论证的力量说服我的读者，而不是用华丽的词语令人炫目。我不会浪费时间咬文嚼字，更不会编造一些言不由衷的矫情的夸大之词。我将关注事情的本质，而不是玩文字游戏！另外，我非常热切地希望女人能成为社会上更受尊敬的成员，因此我将极力避免用那些从散文进入小说，又从小说进入日常书信和对话中的华丽辞藻。

这些信手拈来的夸张的漂亮言辞损坏了品位，并且造成了一种背离朴实真理的病态娇弱；而泛滥的虚伪感情和夸大的情调扼杀了内心的自然情感，让家庭生活变得无趣。而家庭本应承担教导一个理性的不朽灵魂为更崇高的事业而奋斗的责任，并为这个教导的过程提供乐趣。

目前女性教育比以前更受关注，但是女人依然被看作是轻薄的人，遭到那些试图以讥讽或教育改善她们的作家的嘲弄和怜悯。应该承认，女人年轻的时候把大把的光阴都花在学习些许才艺上面，同时为了美貌的放荡观念和通过婚姻抬升自己地位（这是女人提升自己地位的唯一办法）的欲望而牺牲对身心的培养。这种欲望让女人变得跟牲畜一样，她们结婚之后，行为规范像孩童般幼稚：她们梳妆打扮，浓妆艳抹，她们还给造物主的创造物起诨名。这些软弱的人只配被男人当作性玩物！谁能指望她们明智地管理一个家庭，或者照顾自己带到这个世界上来的可怜孩子呢？

既然如此，如果我们可以从女人目前的行为，从目前普遍流行的对享乐的嗜好（这种嗜好代替了伟大志向和能够提升心灵的高尚感情）公正地推断出以下结论：女人一直以来接受的教育和文明社会的体制，加速了女人成为微不足道的欲望的对象—只不过是繁殖笨蛋的机器罢了！—如果指望女人有所成就，却不培养她们的理智，这种行为会让她们忽略自己应尽的责任，在韶华逝去之后变成荒唐而无益的人，那么我认为，理性的男人就会因为我试图说服女人变得更加男性化、更加受尊重而原谅我。

其实“男性化”只不过是个唬人的字眼而已，永远不必担心女人会获得过多的勇气或坚毅，因为她们明显在体力方面不如男人，这让她们在生活的各个方面不得不对男人有一定的依赖。但是为什么要用那些认为品格有性别之分，并使简单的真理和性欲的狂想混淆不清的偏见，使这种不平衡更加严重呢？

女人这种做作的软弱导致了一种压制他人的倾向，并且让她们变得狡猾（狡猾是力量天然的对手），她们装出一副令人鄙夷的幼稚模样，即使这样能激起性欲，却也损伤了尊严。事实上，女人被那些女性品质的错误观点贬得太低，以致我在作出以上主张的时候，并不想要作奇谈怪论。让男人变得更贞洁，更节制吧，如果女人没有因此在同等比例上变得更聪明，那么显而易见，女人的智力确实比较低劣。似乎不用强调我现在说的是女性整体。有很多女性比她们的男性亲属更通情达理。既然在世间那些争夺外部平衡的永恒斗争中始终没有胜出，那么，思想作为一种内在力量自然更重要。有些女性在夫妻关系中无须贬低自己，因为智力永远处于统治地位。

关于两性品格流行观点的讨论

为了给男性专制寻找理由，确切地说是借口，人们想出很多精致的言论，来证明两性在修身养性的时候，应当以培养完全不同的性格为目标；确切地说，女人不能拥有心智的力量，而这种力量恰是修得真正的美德所必需的。但是似乎上帝只给人类指明了一条通向美德和幸福的道路，即让人类拥有灵魂。

既然女人并不是短命的虚度年华者，那为何要让她们深陷无知还美其名曰天真呢？男人不是用语言刻薄地挖苦我们任性的情欲和卑微的恶习，就是振振有词地抱怨我们的愚笨和善变。我会回应，看，这就是无知的必然结局！仅仅依傍偏见的思维必将永远多变；当这种偏见的思维不受约束时，它将带着毁灭性的力量蔓延。以她们的母亲为榜样，女人自小就明白，略微知晓一些人性的弱点、行事精明、性情温和、表面顺从和恪守凡庸礼节，就会得到男人的庇护。对于一个拥有美貌的女子来说，其他任何东西都不重要，因为她们生命中至少20年光阴可安享男人的保护。

弥尔顿[2]就是这样描写人类初始、脆弱的母亲[3]的；可是我还是不明白他说女人生当性情温柔、妩媚动人是什么意思，除非他真正以穆罕默德的口吻，意欲剥夺我们的灵魂，并暗示我们只不过是美貌和盲从的生物，在男人不能乘着思考的翅膀翱翔时取悦他们的感官。

那些劝告我们成为温顺家奴的人，多么粗野地侮辱了我们！例如他们经常热心地建议我们：要靠温柔顺从来取得支配权，这些言论多么愚蠢幼稚，一个堕落到用这种险恶手段取得支配权的人是多么渺小卑微—她是永生的人吗？“毫无疑问，”培根勋爵[4]）说，“人类肉体上和野兽同类，如果他灵魂上不能和上帝同类，他就是低下卑微的东西！”男人试图通过让女人永远保持孩童般的幼稚来确保她们行为端正，在我看来，这是极其不明智的。卢梭希望男女两性都停止理性的探索，这似乎比较合乎情理。因为一旦男人品尝了智慧果[5]，女人必然也紧随其后；然而，她们的理智的培养并不健全，使得她们只能获得有害的知识。

孩童应当天真，我赞成这点；但这个词用在男人或女人身上，就成了软弱的委婉说法。因为如果女人注定能够获得人类的种种美德，并且通过智慧获得坚贞的性格—这种性格是我们寄托未来希望的最坚实的基础，那女人也必然有权面对光明之源泉，而不是被迫在微弱的星光下摸索前行。当然，弥尔顿和我的想法大相径庭。因为他只强调美貌的不容置疑性，虽然从下面两段诗中（我摘录下来以作对比），我们很难看出他思想的一致性，不过伟大的男人经常因为直觉犯这种矛盾的错误：

于是绝美的夏娃回答道：

我的主人，我任由你差遣，

你的命令，我完全无条件服从；

这原本就是上帝的安排；

上帝为你立法，而你是我的准则：

不求甚解即女人最满意的知识和荣耀。

这些正是我曾对孩子们说过的论点，只是我还补充说，你们的理智正在发展，你们必须尊重我的意见，直到它成熟到一定阶段，—之后你们应当独立思考，一切完全依靠上帝……

因此在讨论女人的言谈举止时，我们应当摒弃那些关于身体的世俗言论，探寻我们应努力让她们成为什么样的人，以和上帝合作—如果这种说法不是太过分的话。

个人教育这个词目前还没有明确的定义，我对它的理解是：赋予孩子一种关注，使其见识增长，性情成形，学会控制蠢蠢欲动的情欲，并在身体成熟之前锻炼自己的理性思维；这样他们成年以后，就可以继续踏上思考和推理的重要征程，而不是从头开始。

为了避免误解，我必须声明，我不认为个人教育可以收到一些乐观学者声称的奇效。男人和女人一定会在很大程度上受到他们所在社会的舆论和行为规范的教育。每个时代都有一种主流的舆论导向，似乎是为了赋予这个时代一种不变的特征。因此我们可以断定，除非社会结构发生变化，否则我们无法期待教育能带来什么改变。然而考虑到我当前的目的，我只要声明一点就够了：无论环境对个人的才能产生什么影响，每个人都可以通过理性成为有道德的人；因为只有生来有恶的倾向的人，才是真正的坏人，那么，还有什么可以阻止我们成为无神论者呢？或者如果我们崇拜一个神，那这个神难道不是个魔鬼吗？

因此，我眼中最完备的教育就是对理智的锻炼，使人的品格和心灵得到最大限度的培养和发展。或者说教育是为了使个人获得能使其独立的优秀品德习惯。事实上，称呼那些并非通过独立思考而获得某些品质的人为高尚的人，是很荒唐的。这是卢梭描述男人的观点，我将其延伸到女性身上，并坚信，她们之所以有越轨行为，是因虚假的优雅，而非对男性品格的探求。但是她们过于沉醉于帝王般的崇拜，除非时代风貌发生改变，转而建立在更理性的基础上，否则也许无法说服她们，她们通过贬低自己获得的不合理权力其实是个祸害；或者让她们相信，必须回归本性，和男性站在平等的地位上才能保持纯洁爱情带来的宁静和满足。但我们必须等待这个时代的到来—也许要等到王公贵族们受到理智的启示后，推崇人的尊严而非幼稚状态，抛弃他们华而不实的世袭权。如果那个时候女人还不放弃滥用美丽获得的为所欲为的权利—那确实证明她们在智力上不及男人。

也许有人会指责我傲慢自大，但我仍然要申明，我坚信：所有写过关于女性教育和行为举止这个话题的作家，从卢梭到格雷戈里博士[6]，都曾促使女人的性格更加虚伪和懦弱，否则她们不至于这样；也正因此，女人成了社会上更加无用的群体。我似乎可以更加温和地表达我的信念，但是我担心这样就成了虚伪的满腹牢骚，而不是强烈情感的真实表达，也无法展现我通过经验体会和反复思考得到的明确结论……在我看来，所有那些有意侮辱作为一半人类的女性群体，并使其牺牲所有坚贞品质以取悦于人的著作，我都将对其整体主旨予以反对。

但是，按照卢梭的逻辑，如果男人身体成熟之后，心智也在一定程度上获得了完善，为了保持男人和他妻子的一体性，做妻子的完全依赖丈夫的理智也许是有一定道理的；就像优雅的常青藤缠绕在支撑它的橡树上，构成力量和美貌相得益彰的整体。但是，天哪！丈夫们，以及他们的贤内助们，往往不过是大孩子，—哦，不，多亏了早年的放荡风流，这些丈夫连男子汉大丈夫的外形都没有，—正如让瞎子给瞎子带路，我们还需要上帝来告诉我们后果的严重性吗？

在如今这个腐败的社会状况下，有很多因素导致女性被奴役，通过束缚女人智力、折磨她们的感官而奴役女人。这其中之一，也许是最有害的因素，莫过于女人做事毫无头绪。

做事有条不紊是非常重要的能力，男人从小就养成了这种能力，因此行事缜密，而女人一般接受的是杂乱不堪的教育，因此很难会像男人那样，注意到这个问题。这种漫不经心、毫无条理的瞎猜（还有什么其他的词，可以更好地形容这种丝毫不经过理智推敲，肆意运用凭借本能得到的常识的行为？）使女人缺乏对事物的总结归纳能力。因此她们重复着昨天做过的事情，仅仅因为昨天她们也做了这件事。

这种在早期对理智的忽略，产生的后果比我们想象的要严重。因为这些意志坚强的女人学到的少得可怜的知识，鉴于各种原因，不如男人的有条理，况且这些知识更多地是纯粹通过对实际生活的观察得到的，她们很少会将个人观察到的现象和通过抽象经验而得到的结论作一番比较。她们更多地是通过从属地位和处理家务而获得社会交往，因此她们学习的都是零碎的点滴知识。另外由于学习对她们来说基本上只是次要的事情，所以她们不会以持之以恒的热情钻研任何一门学问，而这种热情是使人激发才智、保持头脑清醒不可或缺的因素。在目前的社会状况下，男人需要学习一点儿知识来维持绅士身份，而男孩们需要接受几年的教育。但是相对于锻炼理智，对于女人的教育更注重优雅体态的培养。女人因生育和恪守端庄的错误观念而精疲力竭，身体发育不良，无法展现某些优美的姿态。此外，她们年轻时没有通过竞争锻炼自己的才智；即使她们天资聪颖，由于没有从事过严肃的科学研究，这种天赋也很快因注重生活品质和衣着举止而渐渐消逝。她们一味追求结果和改进，从不追根溯源；那些规范行为的繁文缛节，其实只是简单原则的蹩脚替代品而已。

为了证明女性柔弱的外表是教育制度造成的，我们可以以军人为例：他们和女人一样，在头脑中的知识还未积累起来、原则还未得到强化时就进入社会。结果也是一样：他们从混乱的谈话中获得一点肤浅的知识，通过在社会上厮混见了些世面。人们经常将这种对风俗和习惯的了解，误认为是对人类情感的认识。但是这种随意观察得到的粗糙结论，从未经过理性的检验，也非通过比较理论和经验得来，能称得上是对人类情感的认识吗？士兵和女人一样，拘泥于那些微不足道的品德。若男女受的教育相同，两性之间还有什么区别呢？我现在看到的一切区别不过是由于男人拥有更多的自由，得以见更多世面罢了。

现在作一番政治评论也许有点偏离我要论述的主题，但是它是在我一系列思考中自然而然产生的，因此我不能避而不谈。

常备军中永远不可能有意志坚定、精力充沛的士兵；军队也许是纪律严明的机械化队伍，却很少有热情奔放、才华横溢的军人；至于深刻的洞察力，我敢断言在军队中和在女人中一样，极为罕见。我认为造成这种情况的原因是一样的。我们甚至可以更进一步断言，军人同样也特别注意外表，热爱跳舞、热闹场所、冒险和嘲弄别人。他们像美丽的女人一样，把阿谀奉承当作每天的主题；他们受的教导就是要取悦于人，他们活着就是为了取悦于人。但是在两性对比中他们并未丧失优势地位，因为人们仍然认为男人地位比女人优越。尽管除了我刚才所述以外，我们很难看到他们的优越性表现在哪里。

最大的不幸在于，他们在尚未进行道德修养之时就学会了一套表面的规矩；在未经过深思熟虑，对人性宏大理想的轮廓深入认识时就学会了人情世故。后果显而易见。他们满足于对一般人性的认识，就很容易产生偏见；他们人云亦云，盲目地屈从权威。所以即使他们有点理智，那也不过是一种出于本能的一知半解，以及对行为方式作出的判断，但是在追究根源或者分析观点时，就派不上用场了。

这种评论对女性是否适用呢？不但适用，我们还可以把这个观点更引申一步，因为他们都是受文明社会里建立起来的不合理差别所害，而失去了有利的地位。财富和世袭的荣耀，让人们认为女性一文不名，她们只是关注财产的多寡；游手好闲使社会上出现了一批既殷勤又粗暴的人，他们一边甘受情妇奴役，一边对自己的姐妹、妻子和女儿作威作福。确实，这样做只是为了让她们安守本分。女人心胸开阔，意志坚强，就不会盲目服从；但是，掌权者需要这种盲目服从，因此暴君和好色者竭力使女性处于蒙昧无知的状态是有道理的，因为暴君只需要奴隶，而好色者只需要玩物。好色者其实是危害最大的暴君；女人被她们的情人欺骗，正如年幼的君主被侍臣玩弄一样，还梦想着自己在统治着他们。

现在我主要谈谈卢梭，因为他对索菲亚[7]性格的塑造无疑非常扣人心弦，虽然在我看来极不自然。但是我要抨击的不是她性格的上层结构，而是形成她性格的基础，即那些使她所接受的教育得以建立的原则。不仅如此，虽然我极为钦佩这位才华横溢的作家的天赋，并且经常引用他的观点，但是在我读到他露骨撩人的奇谈怪论时，没有一点钦佩之情，取而代之的是无尽的愤怒。他对美德的侮辱让我眉头紧蹙，他优美的文笔带给我的微笑也因此荡然无存，我一点都不满意。这就是那位因大力倡导美德而主张摒弃一切和平手段，简直要把我们带回古代接受斯巴达式严格训练的作家吗？这就是那位热衷于歌颂激情的有益抗争、优秀品性的辉煌胜利，以及光辉灵魂自由翱翔的作家吗？当他描写他可心的人儿迷人的双脚和诱人的风姿时，这些伟大的情操多么苍白无力啊！但现在我暂且不谈这个问题，我不想严厉指责这种突然泛滥的自负感，我只想说，任何抱着善意态度观察社会的人，一定会对普通男女的爱情感到满意，因为这种爱情既不会因柔情万种而变得高贵，也不会因共同的知识渴求而得到加强。日常的家庭琐事足以提供愉悦的谈资，天真的抚爱缓解了无须运用智力或大量思考的劳作带来的辛劳；然而这种平凡的幸福景象在我们心中激起的情感，难道不是爱怜多于尊重吗？—这种情感跟我们看到儿童玩耍或动物嬉戏时的感受一样。但是在我们想到那些功德非凡的人在苦难中依旧战斗不止时，我们不得不肃然起敬，我们的思绪就被带到另一个世界，这里，理性战胜了感性。

因此女人或是被视为有道德的人，或是被视为软弱到必须完全依赖男人的优秀方可生存下去的人。

让我们来分析一下这个问题。卢梭宣称女人永远都不应该把自己看成是独立的人，必须在恐惧的支配下，发挥她天生的狡猾的才能，变成一个卖弄风姿的奴仆，这样才能更加吸引男人，成为情欲的对象，当男人需要放松时成为他更亲密的伴侣。卢梭自认为从天性中为自己的观点找到论据，甚至更进一步，旁敲侧击地暗示：人类一切品德的基石，即真理和坚韧，应当有所限制地培养，因为从女人的性格看，服从才是她们需要一丝不苟永远铭记在心的最重要的一课。

简直一派胡言！何时才能出现一位伟人，以足够的力量将因傲慢和肉欲而笼罩在这个问题上的迷雾一扫而尽呢？虽然女人体质比不上男人，但她们的品质一定和男人相同，即使程度可能有别，否则品德将成为一个相对的概念。因此她们的行为应当建立在与男人相同的原则基础上，并具有同样的目标。

女人作为男人的女儿、妻子和母亲，和男人有父女、夫妻和母子的关系，她们的道德品质可以通过履行这些简单责任的方式来判断。但她们努力的目标，即她们伟大的目标，应当是展示她们的才华，树立自觉的高尚品德。她们可以努力使自己的道路充满乐趣；但是她们应该和男人一样，永远不能忘记：生活不会给不朽的灵魂带来永恒的快乐。我并不是暗示男人或女人应当沉迷于抽象的思考或模糊的观点中不能自拔，以致忘记了摆在他们面前的爱和责任，而这两者正是孕育生命成果的途径；相反，我极力推崇爱和责任，我甚至还主张，只有严肃认真地对待它们，才能从中获得最大的满足。

也许当时流行的认为女人因男人而生的观点来源于摩西[8]富有诗意的故事；但是据推测，在真正认真考虑过这个问题的人中，只有极少数相信夏娃真是亚当的一根肋骨，因此这个推论肯定是不成立的；或者至此我们只能承认，这个看法说明，男人从远古时期开始，就发现用实力来征服伴侣对自己有利，并且捏造事实证明女人应该乖乖把脖子伸到轭上，甘受压迫，因为她整个人就是为男人的方便和享乐而存在的。

不要对我所说的妄作结论，认为我意图颠倒世间万物的顺序。我已经承认，从身体的构造来看，男人似乎受上帝青睐，注定要比女人获得更大程度的美德。我这是针对男人整体来说的；但是我实在找不到理由表明男人和女人的品德在本质上有何不同。如果美德实际上只有一个永恒不变的标准，那么如何区分不同美德的性质呢？因此如果我的推导过程没有纰漏，我必定坚决主张：所谓的不同美德都指向同一个简单的方向，正如上帝是唯一的一样。

如此说来，我们不应当将狡猾和智慧对立起来，将琐碎的操劳和巨大的努力对立起来，将美其名曰文雅的平淡无奇和只有伟大抱负才能激发的坚韧意志对立起来。

有人会告诉我，女人如果拥有这些精神力量，就会失去独特的魅力，并且他们可能会引用一位著名诗人的观点来驳斥我离经叛道的主张。因为蒲伯[9]曾以全体男性的名义说：

当她接触到我们所憎恨的一切事物的边缘时，

那我们的愤怒带来的后果将无法预料。

这个警句将男人和女人置于何种地位我不作评判，留待公正的人士去定夺。现在我只想说明，我实在不明白为何女人应当受制于爱情和淫欲，永远处于屈辱的地位，难道她们真的都该下地狱吗？

我知道对爱情发表不敬言论，是对情操和美好感情的严重背叛；但是我只是想从理性而非感性的角度，讲述一个简单的真理。企图说服世人放弃爱情，如同从塞万提斯[10]的作品中剔除堂·吉诃德一样，是不可能，也是违背常识的；但是努力抑制这种骚动的情欲，证明不应该允许它破坏较其更加优越的力量，或者任其篡夺理智的支配权，这种努力，也许是正当的。

青年时代是男女沉迷于爱情的时期；但是在无忧无虑尽情享乐的时候，应当为日后人生更重要的阶段作准备，那时理性思考将代替感性妄为。但是卢梭和那些步其后尘的男性作家们满怀热情地指出，整个女性教育应当只有一个目标，即取悦于男人。

请允许我和那些对人性有所了解却支持这个观点的人理论一番。他们是否认为婚姻会消除生活中的习俗呢？一生都被教导要取悦于人的女人很快就会发现，她的魅力就像残阳余晖，逐渐消逝；过了盛夏光年，青春不再，在和丈夫朝夕相处时，她已然不能在丈夫心中激起一丝涟漪。到那时她还会有足够的天赋自寻慰藉，挖掘她潜在的才能吗？或者我们是不是更有理由相信，她们会试图与别的男人寻欢，并且因为得到新的情人而被激情冲昏了头脑，忘记了她的爱情和自尊遭受的屈辱？当丈夫不再是至爱的时候—这个时候必然会到来—她取悦于人的欲望就会消退，或者变成痛苦的源泉；那时，也许作为所有感情中最转瞬即逝的爱情，就会被嫉妒或虚荣替代。

现在我要谈谈那些受到原则或偏见约束的女人。她们虽然对男女私通深恶痛绝，可是仍然希望别的男人对她们献殷勤，以此证明她们被残忍的丈夫冷落了；不然她们就会日复一日地幻想情投意合的夫妻所享受的幸福生活，直到变得满腹牢骚，身心俱疲。由此看来，取悦于人的绝妙艺术怎么会是一项非学不可的技巧呢？它只对情妇有用罢了。对于贞洁的妻子和认真的母亲来说，这种技巧不过是为品德锦上添花的方式，而丈夫的爱情不过是让她的工作更轻松、生活更幸福的慰藉。但是，无论她的丈夫是爱她还是冷落她，她首先应当使自己受人尊敬，而不是把所有的幸福寄托在一个和她拥有同样人性弱点的人身上。

尊敬的格雷戈里博士也犯了同样的错误。我尊重他的用心，但是完全不能赞同他那篇著名的《给女儿的赠言》。

他建议她们培养对衣着打扮的爱好，因为他断言女人天生爱打扮。他和卢梭都经常使用“天生”这个含糊不清的词，我不明白他们的意思。也许他们会告诉我，先身体而存在的灵魂本身就爱好打扮，并且把这种爱好带到一个新的肉体中，我会似笑非笑地听着，正如在人们对所谓的内在优雅高谈阔论时，我也是这种反应。但是如果他仅仅指运用这种天生的能力就能产生这种爱好，我不能苟同。这种爱好绝不是天生的，和男人狂妄的野心一样，都是由权力欲催生的。

格雷戈里的主张远不止这些；他甚至推崇弄虚作假，建议天真无邪的女孩子隐藏自己的真实情感，不要兴高采烈地舞蹈，因为这时她的脚步会因激动而随心所欲，而她的举止应当庄重。按道理和常识来说，为什么女人不能承认她可以比别人多作一点锻炼呢？或者换句话说，不能承认她有健全的体魄；为什么要压制她天真活泼的天性，还在暗地里告诉她，男人会从她的一举一动中得出她意想不到的结论呢？随那些浪荡公子妄下结论去吧！我希望明智的母亲不要给女儿灌输这种不妥当的警告，以此来抑制女孩子年轻时应有的率性。“言为心声”，确实如此；一个比所罗门更聪明的人曾经说过，人的心地应当纯洁，不拘小节；即使是内心充满邪恶的人，如果谨慎小心，也不难做到这点。

女人应当努力净化心灵。但是，如果她们的理智没有接受训练，就会完全凭感情行事和娱乐；她们因缺乏高尚的追求而无法放下日常的无足轻重的虚荣，也不能抑制炽热的激情，这种激情如同一根芦苇，稍有风吹草动就会使它左右摇摆，在这样的情况下，她们的心灵能够纯洁吗？为了获得一个有道德的男人的感情，有必要弄虚作假吗？女人天生体质比男人弱；但是，为了赢得丈夫的感情，一个做妻子的，当她在履行作为女儿、妻子和母亲的责任时，已经通过思想和身体的双重锻炼保持了天生的体力和思想的健全，难道还必须降低身份，玩弄手段，伪装病态的孱弱，来确保丈夫对她的感情吗？软弱也许会让男人心生爱怜，满足男人自大的傲慢，但是一颗渴求并且理应受尊重的心灵不会满足于救世主般高傲的抚爱。抚爱代替不了夫妻之间的情谊。

我承认，在帝王的后宫里，这些卖弄风情的手段是必不可少的；因为必须要激发享乐主义者的趣味，才能防止他情绪消沉，表现冷漠；但是女人就如此胸无大志，欣欣然以此为乐？难道她们就这样无精打采地在极度享乐和百无聊赖中虚度光阴，而不是坚持追求合理的快乐吗？难道她们不想去实践那些为人类赢得尊严的美德，而让自己受到重视吗？当然如果一个女人只是把生命消磨在穿着打扮上面，以此来取悦一个倦怠的男人，缓解他的顾虑，这样的女人是没有不朽灵魂的。男人完成生活中正经的工作后，当然愿意从她的微笑和小把戏中得到乐趣。

此外，注重增强体魄、锻炼心智的女人，通过经营家庭和修习各种美德，会成为她丈夫的朋友，而非卑微的依赖者。如果她因拥有这些高贵的品格而赢得了丈夫的赞赏，她就会发现没有必要隐藏自己的感情，或者不自然地装出冷漠的样子，以激发丈夫的情欲。追溯历史，我们就会发现杰出的女性既不是女人中最美丽的，也不是最温柔的。

大自然，或者更确切点说，上帝，把万事万物都安排得恰到好处；但是男人却总在试图捏造各种事情，破坏上帝的杰作。我现在指的是格雷戈里博士的那篇文章，他建议妻子永远不要让丈夫知道她的感受或爱情的深度。这种刺激肉欲的预防手段，既荒谬又无益。爱情究其本质来说，就是转瞬即逝的。试图找到使爱情永恒的秘诀，就如同寻找点金石或者万能药一样荒唐；即使找到这个秘诀，也对人类毫无裨益，甚至是有害的。社会最神圣的阶层就是友谊。一位精明的讽喻家说得好：真爱难求，真正的友情更难拥有。

这是一个显而易见的事实，没有什么高深的缘由，稍加研究便会明白。

爱情是人人皆有的情欲，在爱情中，偶然和感性代替了选择和理性，大多数人都体会过爱情；现在没有必要谈论那些比爱情高尚或低微的情感。这种感情，很自然地因悬念和困难而加强，使理智脱离常规，激情得到推崇；但是，婚姻的保障使爱情的狂热渐渐消退，达到一种有益的温度，只有那些不够明智的人，无法用冷静自然的友谊、相互尊重的信任代替盲目的赞美和肉欲的喜好，才会把这种健康平和的状态看成是索然无味的。

这是，也必须是，自然而然的趋势。继爱情之后必定是友谊或冷淡。这种规律似乎和人类精神世界中普遍适用的支配规律完全一致。激情能够激发行动、启迪心灵；但是目的达到后，这种激情就会沦落为纯粹的性欲，变成个人和瞬时的满足，而满足的心也会安于享乐。一个男人在争夺王冠时，尚拥有一定的美德；但他成功加冕之后，往往都会变成骄奢的暴君；况且，如果男人在年老以后仍像情人般对待自己的妻子，这个年老昏聩的男人就是被幼稚的任性和溺爱的嫉妒所俘虏，他忽略了人生的重大责任，将本应施与孩子以取得他们的信任的爱抚，浪费在他的大孩子—妻子的身上。

为了履行人生的责任，一个家庭里的男女主人不应当继续热烈相爱，应该精力充沛地致力于塑造良好的道德品质。我的意思是不应当沉溺在那些扰乱社会规范的感情之中，把本来可以用在其他方面的心思用在彼此谈情说爱上。从未被一件事情吸引的心灵缺乏充沛的精力—而当它长期被某一事情吸引时，就会变得软弱。

错误的教育、狭隘的缺乏教养的心灵以及许多性别歧视，往往使女人比男人更忠贞不渝。但是现在，我暂时不讨论这个问题。我要进一步提出我的观点，并且声明，不幸福的婚姻往往对于家庭是有利的，而被冷落的妻子一般都是最优秀的母亲，我并不是故作悖论。如果女人的心胸再开阔一点，那么这一结论几乎就永远成了必然的结果。因为这通常看起来像是上天的安排：凡是我们从现时的享乐中得到的，都必须从生活的宝库—经验中去除；当我们摘下了鲜花，纵情于享乐之时，我们就不可能同时拥有辛勤耕耘和智慧浇灌带来的丰硕果实了。人生的道路在我们面前展开，我们必须选择向左走或向右走；一个穿梭于各种享乐场合虚度人生的人，不应当抱怨自己得不到智慧或可敬的品格。

让我们暂时假设灵魂不是永生的，人的存在只是为了活在当下—我认为我们有理由抱怨，爱情就如孩童一时兴起的爱好一样，渐渐会变得索然无味，令人生厌。让我们吃喝玩乐谈恋爱吧，因为明天我们就会死去，这种说法实际上是合情合理的，也是人生的道理；除了傻瓜，谁愿意脱离现实去追求那个短暂的幻影呢？但是，当我们因观察到心智中不可思议的奇妙力量而心生敬畏时，我们就不屑于将希望和思想局限在这样一个相对平庸的活动范围之内，这种活动只是表面上看起来光辉而重要，因为它是跟无限的前景和崇高的理想联系在一起的，那我们还有什么必要在为人处世中虚假做作，我们还有什么理由去触犯神圣至高无上的尊严，来保全摧毁道德根基的虚伪幸福呢？为什么女人要被那套卖弄风情的技巧毒害心灵，以迎合好色之徒呢？为什么要阻止爱情蜕变为友情，或者在缺乏建立友情的根本条件时，蜕变为富有同情心的柔情呢？将真实的心境展露出来吧，让理性来教导情欲，让它服从必然性；或者让对道德和知识的崇高渴望把理智从情感中解脱出来，这些情感如果不加以控制，将使人生的杯子里装满更多的痛苦而非甘甜。

我指的并不是与天才相伴而生的浪漫感情，谁又能折断爱情的双翼呢？但是，这种伟大的情感只忠于感情，并且自由发展，人生中微不足道的享乐是无法与其比拟的。那些因持久而著称的感情往往都是不幸的。它们因缺乏感情和固有的忧郁而获得力量。他们对想象中的一种朦朦胧胧的“美”心存希冀；但是一旦得以接触并熟悉之后，男女之间的爱慕就可能会转变为厌倦，或者至少是冷淡，并给想象力以空间，开始新一轮的追求。根据这种观点，卢梭非常有风度地使自己精神上的情妇—艾洛伊斯，在生活日渐乏味的时候爱上了圣普乐，但这也不足以证明爱情的不朽。

格雷戈里博士关于美好爱情的忠告也出于同样的考虑。他建议女人，如果她已下定决心要结婚，就不要轻易产生爱情。但是他把这种和他以往忠告完全一致的决心看作是粗俗的，尽管它会支配她们的行为，格雷戈里还是真诚劝诫他的女儿们要隐藏这种决心，似乎拥有人性中正常的情欲是不美好的。

多么崇高的道德说教！那些谨慎卑微的灵魂一定会赞成这种说教，他们无法将自己的眼界扩展到目前狭小的生活圈子以外。如果培养一个女人理智方面所有的能力，只是因为这些能力与她对男人的依赖有关；如果她一旦有了丈夫，就认为自己人生的目标已经达到，并且毫不羞耻地引以为荣，满足于这顶微不足道的王冠；那么就让她心甘情愿匍匐在男人脚下，从事动物界以内的活动吧；但是，如果她是为了她的崇高事业而奋斗，并且富有前瞻性，那就让她培养理性，不必停下来思考她注定要结婚的丈夫拥有何种性格。她不应过于担心眼前的幸福，要下定决心去获得那种能使理性的人变得高贵的品质；一个鲁莽粗野的丈夫也许会打击她的趣味，但扰乱不了她平静的内心。她不会为了适应丈夫的种种缺点来改造自己的灵魂，她会容忍这些缺点；丈夫的性格对她来说绝不是修得美德的障碍，仅仅是考验而已。

如果格雷戈里博士的评论只限定于对永恒爱情和志同道合感情的浪漫期待上，那么他应该想到，在想象力以牺牲理性为代价依然活跃时，我们的经验就会驱除掉那些让我们不会再抱有希望的建议。

我承认这种情况经常发生：有些女人抱着浪漫的不合实际的美好情感，她们整天无所事事，幻想着自己与丈夫幸福地生活在一起，她们的男人对她们炽热的爱慕与日俱增，直到永远。但是她们结婚了也许也和单身的时候一样，与期待有一个好男人相比，和一个不称职的丈夫在一起也未必更不快乐。我主张一种合理的教育，更确切地说，一个有教养的头脑，可以让女人过着有尊严的单身生活；但是说她应当放弃培养个人的情趣，避免遭受丈夫突然的破坏，这就未免有点本末倒置了。说实话，如果一个人不能超脱于人生的各种得失，如果他不能打开获得快乐的新源泉（这些快乐完全来源于个人思考的力量），那么还需要高尚的情趣做什么。有品位的人，无论单身还是已婚，无一例外都会厌恶各种各样的事情，不仅仅是洞察人们的思想。我们的观点当然不能依据这个结论得出；但是就享乐的整体而言，情趣可以算作一种幸福吗？

问题是，情趣带来的更多的是痛苦还是快乐？这个问题的答案将会决定格雷戈里博士的劝告是否合理：他规定了一种奴隶制度，并且他没有试图用纯粹理性推导出来的对人类普遍适用的规则去教育有道德的人，是多么荒谬而专横。

举止温柔、宽容忍耐和逆来顺受，都是非常亲切的神圣品质，这些在高尚的诗篇中都被颂扬为上帝的品德；或者可以说，除了上帝宽厚怜悯和欣然宽恕的品质外，没有一种表现上帝仁行的品德能够更好地维系人类的感情。从这个角度看，“温柔”确实是结合了庄严伟大和谦逊屈就的所有特征；但是，在温柔只是顺从依赖的行事方式，只是急需保护的软弱爱情的后盾时，它表现出的是多么不同的状态；在爱情需要默默承受伤害时，温柔是宽容忍耐；在鞭打之下还要强颜欢笑，丝毫不敢作出反击。这幅图像描绘的卑怯景象，就是一个所谓杰出女人的肖像，而这是以社会公认的女性优秀品质为依据的，那些徒有虚名的理论家们竟然把女性的优秀品质和人类的优秀品质区分开。否则，他们[11]最好还是把那根肋骨归还原位，再造出一个将男人和女人融于一体的有道德的人，并且不要忘了赋予这个人所有的“谦卑的魅力”。

我们不清楚女人在没有婚嫁的情况下是如何生存的。因为尽管道德家们一致认为生命的演变似乎证明男人为更好地为未来作准备而受到各种情境的磨练，而他们却经常一致教导女人只要为当下着想即可。基于此，温柔、顺从以及阿谀奉承的感情被看作是女性最重要的美德。有位作家不顾不容违抗的自然法则，公然声称女人多愁善感就是男性化的表现。她生来就是男性的玩物，他的拨浪鼓，无论何时，在男人停止理性的探索需要娱乐时，它就必须在他的耳边当啷当啷地响。

确实，从广义上来说，劝人温柔和蔼是极为明智的。一个意志脆弱的人是应当努力追求温柔的。但是当过度的宽容忍耐，变成是非颠倒时，温柔就不是一种美德了；不管在伴侣身上看到这种品德是如何恰当，这种伴侣将永远被视为低人一等，只会使人感到一种味同嚼蜡的温柔，并且很快变成轻蔑。再者，如果劝告真的能使那些天生朽木不可雕的人变得温柔，那么社会秩序一定会得到一定的改良；但是正如我们马上就可证明的那样，这种不分青红皂白的建议只会导致矫揉造作，在不断改进的道路上丢掷一块绊脚石，妨碍了性情的真正提高。女人牺牲了真正的美德换来的只是徒有表面的优雅，并没有得到什么好处，虽然就个人来说她们可能在短短几年内赢得帝王般的统治地位。

作为一个哲学家，我怀着愤怒的心情阅读了男人用来粉饰他们侮辱女性言辞的种种看似有理的言论；作为一个伦理学家，我想问诸如“美丽的不足”“可爱的弱点”这些奇怪的自相矛盾的联想到底是什么意思？假如只有一个道德标准，只有一种男人的原型，根据穆罕默德灵柩的世俗传说[12]，女人似乎命中注定就是介于人兽之间的生物；她们既不像野兽那样有万无一失的本能，也不被允许用理智的眼睛注视一个完美的榜样。她们是为爱而生，不应该以寻求别人的尊重为目的，否则她们就会因具有男性的特征而被主流社会排除在外。

我们不妨从另一个角度来看这个问题。顺从的、懒惰的女人就一定是最好的妻子吗？把我们的讨论限定在目前的状况下，我们可以看看这些软弱的女人如何履行她们的责任。这些女人因为获得了一些表面的成绩，就加深了对流行的成见，她们仅仅是为了丈夫的幸福而努力吗？她们浑身散发的魅力仅仅是为了愉悦丈夫吗？自幼就受消极服从观念熏陶的女人拥有足够的品行来相夫教子吗？事实完全不是这样。通过回顾女性历史，我不得不同意那位刻薄的讽刺家所言，认为女性是人类最软弱和受压迫最多的性别。历史除了揭示女人地位低下的特点之外，还告诉我们什么？而又有几个女人从高高在上的男人的可恶束缚中得到解脱呢？这种女人太少了，让我想到了关于牛顿的一个绝妙的猜想—牛顿大概是一个精灵，偶然投入人世。顺着这条思路往下走，我不由想到了那些不走寻常路的杰出女性，本是男人的灵魂，却错投了女胎。假如认为在谈论灵魂时还区分性别是不合理的，那么女人处于劣势地位一定是因为身体构造和男人不同；或是上帝在捏土造人时，给的火候不一样。

正如我一如既往所坚持的那样，我避免对两性集体作任何直接的比较，或者根据目前的状况，坦率地承认女人不如男人，但是，我坚持认为男人使女人更加低劣，直到女人堕落到理性生物正常标准以下。让她们的才能有用武之地，她们的品德得以发展，然后再确定女性整体在知识领域应当占有的地位。再次声明，我不只是为那些少数杰出的女人寻求地位。

我们凡夫俗子很难预测，如果废除那些使我们举步维艰的专制主义，人类的发现和发展将会达到何种高度；但是，如果道德能够拥有更坚实的基础，那我无须拥有预知未来的天赋，就可以大胆预言女人要么成为男人的朋友，要么成为他们的奴隶。我们也就不会像现在这样，分不清她到底是一个有道德的人，还是一个介于人兽之间的生物。但是，如果那时她们看起来和禽兽一样，造出来就是供男人使用，那么他就会让她们安于缰绳束缚之下，而不再用空洞的赞扬来嘲笑她们了。或者，如果那时事实证明女性是有理性的，那么男人也就不会仅为了满足他的肉欲而阻碍她们的发展。他不会再用各种辞令来诱惑女人，使她们自己的理智盲目屈从于男人的控制。讨论女性教育问题时，他就不会叫嚣女人永远不应该拥有运用理智的自由，也不会建议那些像他一样修习人类道德品质的人，去做一个狡猾虚伪的人。

如果道德有永恒的根基，那么真理必然只有一个。任何牺牲真正意义上的品德来谋求眼前利益的人，以及那些以这种处事方式视为己任的人，都只是为了当下而活，他们不会成为一个负责人的人。

这就是为什么诗人创作下面这个诗句时应当摒弃他的嘲讽和不屑：

如果软弱的女人误入歧途，

那么名人们的责任比她们更大。

因为如果女人永远不运用自己的理智，永远不能独立，永远没有自己独立的思想，或者永远无法感受理性意志的尊严（理性意志只向上帝屈膝，并且常常忘记宇宙中除了它自己以及它热烈关注的完美模范之外，还包括其他东西），永远不去追求那些转化成美德时可以效仿的品质，尽管在程度上它会战胜那颗因其狂喜的心灵，那么毫无疑问，女人就会被困在坚不可摧的命运锁链上，无法挣脱。

我不想给人留下虚张声势的印象，因此如果我说当理智能够让女人清醒思考，如果她们真的有能力像理性生物那样处事，那么就不要把她们当奴隶对待，或者，像对待禽兽那样对待女人，在人类利用它们的时候，让它们完全受人类理智的支配；而是应当培养她们的心智，给她们以一定的有益而高贵的原则上的约束，通过让她们感觉到上帝是唯一可以依赖的对象，来获得自觉的尊严。像教育男人一样教育她们服从自然规律，而不是为了让女人更讨男人欢心而硬给道德加以性别区分。

再说，如果经验证明她们的智力、坚韧和刚毅都无法和男人达到同等程度，那么也应该让她们的品德在性质上与男人相同，虽然女人试图追求与男人同等程度的品德是徒劳无益的。这样男人的优越性即使不会表现得更明显，也会同样地清晰。真理是一项简单的原则，不容篡改，应当对于两性同样适用。现在规范的社会秩序也不会被颠覆，因为那时女性仅仅拥有理性给她安排的地位，玩弄手段不能带来男女平等，更不可能使男人屈从于女人。

这些观点也许可以称之为乌托邦般的幻想。感谢上帝让这些理论在我的灵魂上留下深刻的印记，并赋予我足够的智慧，让我敢于运用我的理智，直到我只依赖上帝来获得品德的提升。我愤怒地看待那些奴役女性的错误观念。

我把男人作为我的同类来爱戴。但是无论他的权力是真正属于他的，还是从别处篡夺的，他都不能把它强加到我的头上，除非某个人的理智值得我尊重；即使是那样，我也是服从于理性，而不是人。事实上，一个负责任的人的行为必须受到他自己理智的支配，否则上帝的绝对地位从何而来呢？

我还有必要详述一下这些显而易见的真理，因为女性似乎已经被孤立起来；她们被剥夺了那些使人类受益的品德，却还被人用各种虚伪的优雅粉饰，使她们维持短暂的专制。爱情在她们的心中代替了所有其他更高贵的感情，她们唯一的目标就是使自己更加美丽，吸引男人的爱慕而非激起别人的尊重。而这个低劣的欲望，正如绝对君主体制里的奴隶性一样，毁灭了品格的所有力量。自由是美德之母，如果女人因为自己本身的原因成为奴隶，没有权利呼吸振奋人心的自由空气，她们就一定会像旅居异地的人一样郁郁寡欢，被看作是天然的美丽缺陷。应当铭记，只有她们是有缺陷的。

关于女性受统治的论点同样适用于男人。多数人总是受到少数人的奴役；那些丝毫不能辨别人类优秀品质的怪物却残暴地欺压着成千上万的同胞。为何拥有卓越才能的人要遭受如此的侮辱呢？皇帝们从整体上来看，在能力和品德方面，都比不上从普通百姓中选出来的同等数目的那些人，这难道没有得到大家普遍的赞同吗？但是他们曾经并将继续享有人们的尊崇，这种尊崇何尝不是对理性的侮辱呢？把一个尚在世的人供奉为神的国家不止一个。男人为了安享眼前的快乐而向强势力量屈服；女人不过是做了同样的事情。因此，除非我们能够证明一个卑躬屈膝地放弃人类应得权利的廷臣，不配做一个有道德的人，否则无法说明因为女性一直处在被奴役的地位，所以她们本质上就比男人低劣。

残暴的力量一直统治着我们的世界，政治科学仍处在襁褓中，这一点从哲学家在传授对人类最有利的知识时有所顾忌就可看出，而正是这种知识决定了两性的区别。

关于这个话题我不想作更深入的探讨，我只是想得出一个明显的结论：当合理的政治体制得以传播自由之时，整个人类，包括女人，就会变得更为理智和高尚。

再论关于两性品格的流行观点

强壮的身体本来是英雄的优秀特性，但是现在却遭到了不公平的鄙视，甚至男人和女人都认为这无关紧要：女人这样认为，是因为它破坏了她们的阴柔气质和可爱娇弱，而这些正是她们谋得特权的源泉；男人这样认为，是因为强壮的体魄看起来和一位有身份的绅士的品格不符。

男人和女人都从一个极端滑到了另一个极端，这很容易证明。但是首先应当注意到的是，有种世俗的错误已经赢得了一些人的信任，并导致了一个错误的结论，错把结果当成了原因。

天资聪颖的人，往往因为潜心研究或不关注健康而伤害了自己的身体，他们激情的强烈程度和智慧的活力程度相对应的，以至于剑刃伤了剑鞘，毁了自己的身体，这个事实几乎是人人皆知的，于是一些肤浅的评论家就会由此推断：聪明人的体质都不好，或者用时兴的话来说，体质孱弱。但我相信，事实似乎正好相反；因为我经过孜孜不倦地调查发现，在大多数情况下，智慧的力量总是和强壮的体魄同在，我说的是天生的健全体质，而非从事体力劳动导致的头脑简单、四肢发达，干这种体力劳动时大脑不是处于呆滞状态就是仅仅用来支配双手。

普里斯特利博士[13]曾在他传记图表的前言中提到，大多数伟人的寿命都超过45岁。考虑到他们在钻研自己钟爱的科学的时候，毫无顾忌地倾注他们所有的精力，他们废寝忘食地燃烧着生命之灯；抑或，当他们沉浸在诗意的梦境里，幻想充满了整个情景，心灵受到了震撼，直到冥思引起的激情使身体颤动—这时他们幻想的东西，想象中的空中楼阁，才从他们疲惫的双眼中褪去—只考虑到这些，我们就可以推断这些人是拥有钢铁般体质的。莎士比亚不是用虚弱的手去抓住幻想的匕首，而弥尔顿也不是颤颤巍巍地带领魔鬼远离阴森沉闷牢狱的禁闭。这些不是乱七八糟的呓语，也不是神经病的病态发泄，而是丰富饱满的幻想，这种幻想以一种“美好的疯狂”状态四处漫游，而不会频繁因身体而受限。

我知道这个结论将使我要谈论的内容比人们设想的还要更进一步；但是我信奉真理，并坚持我的第一个观点，我承认身体素质的差距确实给予男人一种天生的优越性；而这也正是男人优越性的唯一的有力证据。但我仍坚持认为，男人和女人的知识，正如他们的品德一样，应当拥有同样的本质，虽然程度可能有所差别。女人，既然被视为有道德有理性的人，就应当以同样的方式奋力追求人类的美德（或者说完满），而不应该在接受教育时，被当成一个想象中的半个人，如卢梭笔下所述的怪物那样。

但是如果体力是男人理所应当拿来夸耀的东西，女人为何如此执迷不悟，以自己的缺点为荣呢？卢梭曾经为她们提出了一个貌似可信的理由，而这个理由完全是由一个异想天开的人对感受美妙之后的印象加工后提出来的；他认为女人这样就可能真正有了一个屈服于天然欲望的托词，又不会违反她们浪漫谦逊的规范，从而满足了男人的自傲和放荡。

女人受到这些观点的蒙蔽，时不时会吹嘘她们的弱点，并利用男人的弱点来巧妙地获得权利；她们甚至会以不正当手段得到的权势为荣，因为她们就像土耳其的傲慢权贵一样，比君主拥有更多的实权；但是她们为了暂时的满足牺牲了品德，为了瞬间的胜利牺牲了一生的尊严。

如果将世界划分为若干个王国，将王国进一步划分成若干个家庭，而统治这个世界的法律是由理性力量制定的，那么女人以及暴君都不会拥有现在这么大的权力。但是进一步对比我们就会发现，在争权夺利的过程中，她们的品行堕落了，而整个社会充斥着淫荡的风气。大多数人被少数人踩在脚下。在此，我斗胆断言，除非女性接受更加合理的教育，否则人类美德的发展和知识的进步还会持续遭受阻碍。如果承认女人不只是为了满足男人的欲望而生，也不是为了成为照料男人饮食起居的高级奴仆，那么那些真正关注女性教育的父母，他们所关心的首要问题即使不是加强孩子们的体质，至少也不要用“美丽”“女性的优点”等错误的观念来摧残她们的躯体；也不可以使女孩子受到这种致命观点的毒害，妄想通过各种推理过程，使缺点发生质变，变成优点。

……

即使女性天生比男性软弱已经得到证明，那请问她为何还要努力使自己变得比原来更软弱呢？这种观点是对常识的侮辱，并且带着情欲的味道。我们希望在这个开明的年代，质疑丈夫的神圣权利和质疑君主的神圣权利一样，不会带来危险。也许我们的信念不能让诸多吵闹的争论者满意，但是在任何流行偏见遭到攻击时，智者就会思考，任由那些没有头脑的心胸狭隘的人对改革肆意抨击。

那些试图培养女儿拥有真正高贵品格的母亲，一定不要在意无知者的嘲讽，采取一种和卢梭推荐方法相反的教育方案。因为卢梭是动用一切虚假动人的修辞和哲学诡辩推荐，他的诡辩使荒谬的言谈看起来合情合理，而他草率的结论即使没有说服力，也会迷惑那些无力反驳它们的人。

在整个动物世界中，几乎所有幼小的生物都需要不断锻炼，同样由此可知，儿童应当在各种无害的嬉戏打闹中度过童年时期，以此锻炼手脚，不需要大脑给出什么精细的指令，也不需要保姆一刻不离的照顾。实际上，孩子照顾自己，是其锻炼运用理智的第一项活动，正如用于娱乐当下的小发明会拓展想象力一样。但是这些自然的伟大构思，被错误的溺爱和盲目热情破坏。孩子没有一刻自主行动的自由，女孩尤其如此，因此逐渐养成了依赖性。这样，依赖性就成了孩子的天性。

为了保持个人美貌—女人的荣耀—她的四肢和能力所受的束缚比中国的裹脚布带来的约束更大。当男孩子在户外玩耍嬉闹时，女孩子只能听从宣判，过着久坐的生活，这种生活让她们肌肉衰竭，思维钝化。卢梭的意见，后来又得到了几个作者的拥护，认为女孩天生，也就是说从她们出生起，接受教育之前，天生就喜欢娃娃、打扮和聒噪，这些观点太愚蠢了，我懒得反驳。一个女孩，被判定要连续坐长达几个小时，听那些没文化的保姆无聊的闲谈，或是整天坐在母亲的化妆室里看她梳妆打扮，她要加入谈话很自然；她会模仿母亲或者阿姨，以她们打扮她的方式为布娃娃打扮聊以自娱，可怜天真的孩子，这种结果是再自然不过的了。最能干的人也很少能做到不受周围环境的影响；如果记录天才事迹的书页不可避免地会受到时代偏见的影响，那女性，像国王们一样，也总是通过错误的方式看待事情，就更应该理解了。

通过这种方式，我们就可以很容易为女性特别喜爱打扮找到理由，而无须假定这是为了取悦她们依赖的男人。简而言之，认为女孩天生就爱卖弄风骚是十分荒诞的；而认为一种和繁衍后代冲动相关的自然欲望早就存在，甚至早于不正当的教育方式，通过煽动想象力过早激发这种欲望的行为之前就已存在，实在是太不合理了。卢梭这样睿智的观察家要不是习惯了使理性屈从于好奇的心态，使真理顺从于他喜爱的悖论，是不会有这种观点的。

但是对于一个成功地为灵魂不朽激烈争辩的人来说，为心灵加上性别的区分是多么不符合他的原则啊。但是当真理成为假想的障碍，它是一道多么虚弱的屏障啊。卢梭尊重—近乎崇拜美德—但是他放纵自己，沉迷于情色。他的想象力经常使他的性欲之火熊熊燃烧。但是，为了调和他对自制、坚韧和其他英勇品德的尊重，一个像他那样的人是不可能冷静推崇这些美德的，他试图颠倒自然法则，并且提出一套暗藏危害、玷污至高智慧的学说。

他没有去观察现实生活中的例子，就试图通过他的那些荒谬故事证明女孩天生注重打扮自己，这些故事不配被我们鄙夷。

……

可以说我观察女孩子的童年时代的机会比卢梭多，我仍能想起自己的感受，并且总是不断地观察我周围的女孩子。我敢断定，如果女孩子没有因为一成不变的生活精神沮丧，没有因为虚伪的害羞而丢失天真无邪，那么她一定会蹦蹦跳跳，活泼精明，而且布娃娃永远不会吸引她的眼球，除非禁闭的生活剥夺了她的其他选择。总之，如果在自然造成任何差别之前，家长不向男孩和女孩灌输性别之差这个概念，那么男孩和女孩是可以很友好地在一起玩耍的。我还要进一步声明，在我的观察范围内，多数表现理性、智慧超群的女性都是得以无拘无束地发展的，这也是不可置疑的事实，正如有些优雅的女智者暗示的那样。

童年和青年时期不注意身体导致的恶果超出了我们的想象—身体的依赖自然就会导致精神上的依赖。如果女人把大部分时间都花在防御或忍受疾病折磨上，那她怎么能成为好妻子或好母亲呢？如果一个女人的行为动机，在早年的时候就被关于美貌的错误观念和多愁善感的虚伪描述所侵蚀，那我们就不能期待她能意志坚定地努力增强体质、免于沉溺于各种伤身的放纵行为。有时候大多数男人不得不忍受身体的不适，或者和恶劣天气抗争，但是优雅的女性，简直已经成了她们身体的奴隶，甚至不以为耻反以为荣。

我以前认识一位身体孱弱的时髦女性，她对于自己的虚弱体质和多愁善感的神经异常自豪。她认为，挑剔的口味和很小的食量是人类完美的高级状态，并以之为行为规范。我曾经看到这位可怜的虚荣女人把生活的一切责任抛到九霄云外，扬扬自得地躺在沙发上，吹嘘着她没有什么好胃口，以此证明身体虚弱导致了她多愁善感，或者是多愁善感让她身体虚弱；将她那套愚蠢可笑的理论说明白太难了。但是就在那时，我看到她在侮辱一个可敬的老妇人，这个老妇人因为突然的横祸，不得不依赖这个女人卖弄的施舍，其实，老妇人境况尚佳的时候还帮过这个女人一把。如果一个人像西巴里特[14]人那样沉溺于奢靡享乐，其道德仍未丧尽，或者从未受到道德戒律的熏陶（这种道德戒律虽然可以防御罪恶，但是委实不能替代心灵培养），那她会变成这种软弱而堕落的人吗？

……

世界各地的女人都处于这种可悲的境地。因为要保持她们的天真，而天真只是无知的比较温和的说法，人们不让她们看到真理，而在她们的能力得到发展之前，就培养她们表现出一种虚伪的性格。女人从小就被教导，美貌是女人统治一切的权杖，心灵要以身体塑造自己，在囚困它的金丝鸟笼周围转悠，只为了表达对这座囚笼的溢美之词。男人有各种工作和追求来吸引他们的注意力，因此造就了他们心胸开阔的性格，但女人只关注一件事情（美貌），总是将精力耗费在自己身上最微不足道的地方，很少能将视野拓展到当前享乐以外去。男人的自大和情欲，以及女人自己如同暴君般统治下的欲望，使她们处在一种被奴役状态，一旦她们的理智从这种奴役中解放出来，我们也许就会惊奇地发现她们的弱点。

请允许我在这个问题上深入阐述。

《圣经》中有段寓言，描述魔鬼四处游荡寻找可以吞噬的人，如果我们认同这样一个邪恶灵魂的存在，那么败坏人类品行最有效的方法莫过于赋予一个人绝对的权利。

这个论点可以派生出几个分论点。出身、财富和一切使人无须运用智慧就可以凌驾于其同伴之上的外在优势，实际上都使之堕落到不如别人。根据其软弱程度，他们将被各种富有心计者玩弄，直到这些傲慢的怪物失去所有的人性特征。而那一群如绵羊般盲从的人，心甘情愿地成为这种人的从众，这种奇怪的现象只能归咎于后者贪图眼前享乐的欲望和有限的智力水平。受着奴隶般依赖性的教育，精力因奢靡和懒惰而日渐衰竭，我们该从哪去寻找那种敢于挺身而出维护人权，或者为有道德的人寻求特权的人呢（这是有道德的人达到卓越的唯一途径）？人们受着君主和侍臣们的奴役，这种奴役阻碍了人类思想的发展，至今仍未被废除，世界从这种奴役中解放出来还遥遥无期。

因此男人在夸耀权势的时候，就不要再用那些暴君和贪婪的侍臣们用过的论调，错误地主张女人应该受奴役，因为她们一直被奴役着。但是，男人受合理法制的统治，享受着他的天赋自由，而如果女人不能与之同享自由，那就让男人鄙视女人吧。在那个光辉时代到来之前，男人在抨击女人的愚蠢时，请他们也不要忘记自己的愚钝。

确实，女人通过不正当的手段取得权力，或者通过心怀恶意做一些不道德的事来获得权力，她们显然丧失了理智她们的地位，不是变成卑鄙的奴隶，就是成为暴虐的君王。她们在争夺权力时丧失了所有的天真浪漫、心灵的尊严，她们表现得和那些我们观察到的以通过同样的方法取得权贵的男人一样。

现在到了变革女性行为方式的时候了，为她们争取失去的尊严，使她们作为人类的一部分，通过改造自己进而改变世界。到了将不容改变的道德和当地习俗划分界限的时候了。如果男人是半人半神，那我们为什么还要服侍他们？如果女性灵魂的尊严和禽兽一般值得质疑，如果她们的理性不足以指导她们的行为，而她们又不像禽兽一般拥有万无一失的本能，那她们毫无疑问成了所有生物里面最悲惨的了。她们就只好屈膝于命运的铁蹄之下，无奈地承认自己是上帝造出来的一个“美丽的缺陷”了。但是为上帝把大多数人都造成既负责任又不负责任的样子，寻求一些生硬的无可辩驳的理由，目的是为了证明上帝如此对待她们是正确的，想必即使是最机智的诡辩家也会因此困惑不已。

……

真希望女人能对他们的丈夫倾注感情，这种感情赖以存在的基础应当和支撑忠诚的根基相同，天底下除此之外没有其他坚实的基础了—因为她们提防那种欺骗性的感情；感情很多时候都只是肉欲的傀儡。因此我认为，女人从幼年时期开始，就应当要么像东方王子那样被隔离，要么就接受恰当的教育，以培养她们独立思考和行事的能力。

为什么男人总是在这两种想法之间徘徊不决，并且期待不可能发生的事情呢？他们为什么期待一个奴隶有道德，期待一个受文明社会制度戕害变得软弱（如果我们不称之为邪恶）的人拥有道德呢？

我心里很清楚，要想彻底清除好色之徒培植的根深蒂固的偏见需要很长时间；同样，要想让女人相信在受到娇柔这个词的蛊惑时，刻意培养甚至装出一副软弱的样子的做法，是极其违反她们本质利益的；或是要想让世人相信，导致女人邪恶和愚蠢的毒瘤（如果有必要使用一些比较缓和的符合习惯的同义词），是对美—更确切地说是容貌美的色情崇拜，这些是需要一些时间的。因为一位德国作家曾经敏锐地观察到，漂亮的女人是情欲的对象，这一点得到了各类男人的一致赞同；而一个因为表现出了智慧的魅力而激发了更多崇高情感的有教养的女人，也许会受到那些以满足情欲为乐的男人的忽略或冷淡。我预料明显有人会反驳我—如果男人同他以前一样一直是个不完美的存在，那他沦为欲望的奴隶也无可厚非；而那些女人为了满足一种主要的欲望而谋取最大的权力，她们的堕落即使不是道德上使然，也必然是身体使然。

我承认，这个反对意见有一定道理；尽管有“像上帝那样纯洁”一样崇高的戒律，但男人的品德似乎并没有受到唯一能够限制这些品德的上帝的约束；而且他可以继续前进，而不去考虑沉溺于这种崇高的志愿是否超出了他的范围。汹涌的波浪接到上帝指令：“你只能前进到这里，不许再向前跑；你们骄傲的波涛必须要止步于此。”奔驰的行星受到自然力量的约束，在其轨道内运转，而这种力量也制约着翻腾的浪花，使之不能前进。物质始终都是要屈服于支配一切的伟大神灵的。但是不朽的灵魂，不受力学定律的束缚，奋力从物质的枷锁中挣脱出来。它和上帝合作，试图用制约宇宙的永恒定律（在某种程度上这些定律是我们无法想象的）来指导自己的行为时，不仅没有扰乱万物的秩序，反而帮助万物建立了秩序。

况且，如果女人接受的教育让她们依赖别人，也就是说让她们按照另外一个容易犯错的人的意志行事，而且盲从权威，那我们折腾到什么时候才能结束？那是不是应该把她们看作是拥有一块狭小领地的代理，而她们的行为是由一个不能免于谬误的高级法庭负责呢？

我们不难证明，这种代理会表现得跟受了恐吓的男人一样，迫使他的孩子和仆人都屈从于他暴虐的压迫下。既然女人会毫无缘由地屈从，她们在教导子女和管理仆人方面没有一贯的准则，她们对人是好是坏，完全凭一时兴起；她们无法承受枷锁的重负时，就会强行将之转嫁到更加弱小人的肩上，并恶意地以此为乐。当我们看到这一幕时，没有必要大惊小怪。

但是，我们假设一个被训练得服服帖帖的女人，嫁给了一个明智的男人。他决定她的判断力，却不会让她感觉到受压迫的奴隶性，正如理性可以间接影响一个人，这个男人折射出来的光辉能够使她得体地安排事情。但是她终究不能保全她的庇护者的性命，他也许会撒手西去，留给她一大家人要养活。

双重责任落在了她的肩上：她要以父亲和母亲双重的身份来教育子女，要培养他们的品行，还要保护他们的财产。但是，哎呀！她从来没有为自己想过，或者依照自己的意志行事。她只学会了取悦男人，优雅地以他们为生；但是现在她被孩子所累，如何才能找到另外一个保护人—一个丈夫来扮演理性的角色呢？一个理性的男人（因为我们现在不是在说故事，而是从实际出发）也许会认为她是一个温顺可爱的人儿，但是世界上更有姿色的女人比比皆是，他为什么要为了爱情娶一个拖家带口的女人呢？那她要如何是好呢？她要么很轻易地成为一个卑鄙的企图通过结婚发财的男人的猎物，将子女应得的父亲的遗产拱手相送，变得十分凄惨；要么成为失意不满和盲目放纵的牺牲者。她无力教育子女，又无法赢得他们的敬重（如果一个人本身不值得尊敬，即使他身居要职，也不会得到人们的尊敬，这种说法并不是文字游戏）。她追悔莫及，却徒劳无益，于是在痛苦中郁悒而终。即使她不贫困，但魔鬼的毒牙插入了她的灵魂深处，青春时代放荡不羁的恶习带给她的无尽悔恨挥之不去，随她一起埋入地下。

我并没有渲染什么；相反，这种情形非常可能出现，每一个善于观察的人一定亲眼目睹过类似的场景。

当然我是理所当然地假定一切顺利，然而经验表明，盲人就算走在熟悉的路上，也可能会掉进水沟。但是我们可以假定（这并不是一个完全不可能的猜想）一个只会取悦他人的人，肯定能在讨好别人时得到快乐；这对于她天真的女儿来说，就算不是一个坏榜样，也是一个非常愚蠢的榜样啊！母亲会在卖弄风情时败下阵来，她们不但不能和女儿和睦相处，反而会对自己的女儿怒目相视，因为女儿成了她争风吃醋的对手，而且是最残酷的对手。而人们会拿女儿和她比较，使她相形见绌，她从未想过要在理性的长凳上占有一席之地，而现在她又被赶下了美丽的宝座。

要描述这样一个家庭主妇带给这个家庭的痛苦和轻微的罪恶，并不需要生动的笔墨或漫画家清晰的勾勒。但她也只是按照卢梭的那一套理论做了女人应该做的事情罢了。人们永远不会责备这样的女人有男性化，或者行为超出了自己的范围；而且，她还遵守了他的另一条重要准则，即小心谨慎地保护她的名誉免遭玷污，因此被看作是优秀的女人。可是她哪一方面能称得上优秀呢？确实，她无须挣扎，就可以免于犯下滔天大恶，但是她怎样去履行自己的责任呢？责任！其实她整天梳妆打扮、照料自己虚弱的身子都来不及，更别谈责任了。

至于宗教，她从来不敢擅自作决定；就像一个依赖别人的人应该做的那样，她严格遵守那个看着她长大的教堂的规矩，虔诚地相信有更聪明的人已经把一切安排妥当；无疑，永不质疑是她的完美优点。因此她会按时交纳她那份1/10的薄荷和小茴香子[15]，她对上帝感恩戴德，庆幸自己不像其他女性那样。这就是良好教养带来的喜人结果！这就是男人伴侣应有的美德！

为了缓解我的情绪，我必须描述另一番景象。

现在我们假设有这样一个女人，拥有差强人意的智力水平（我作此假设，是因为不想把普通人排除在外），她的身体由于经常锻炼而充满活力，同时她的思想逐渐发展到深谙人生的道义责任，也知晓人类美德和尊严的意义。

通过履行应尽的义务，她养成了优秀的品质；她因爱而婚，却没有遗失小心谨慎；她的眼光不局限于夫妻幸福生活的琐事，因此得到丈夫的尊重，而无须通过玩弄卑劣把戏博取丈夫的欢心，试图挽救行将熄灭的爱情之火。当情人变成熟悉的枕边人，当友情和忍耐代替了狂热的爱情，爱情之火注定会熄灭。这是爱情的自然灭亡，家庭的安宁不会因挽救爱情的努力而破坏。我假设这个男人也是品德高尚的人，否则这个女人还需要更多的独立品质。

但是，命运拆散了这对璧人。她变成了寡妇，甚至生活上都捉襟见肘；但是，她并不悲惨！她自然会悲痛欲绝，但是时间抚平了悲伤，她凄然地接受了命运的安排，一心扑在子女身上，比以前更加爱护他们，企盼将他们抚养成人，这种深情为她的母爱抹上了一丝神圣的英雄色彩。她希望，不仅她的子女看见了她的贤惠和劳作（他们现在是她一切慰藉的源泉，而他们的赞颂就是她的生命），而且她那因过度悲伤而心不在焉、同时又受到激发的想象力，还让她满怀希望，希望那双她用颤抖的双手合上的眼睛也能够看到，她如何克制了内心所有骚动的情欲，履行了她既做父亲又做母亲的双重责任。她因不幸而成了英雄，她在自然的情欲发展为爱情之前，就将其扼杀在摇篮里，并且在女人一生最丰满的阶段忘记了自己是女人—忘记了让人觉醒的热情带来的快乐，这种热情受到激发很可能会重新燃烧。她不会再想到取悦他人，而她自觉的尊严也使她不会因为她的行为应得的赞扬而骄傲。她的子女有她的爱，她最光明的希望绝非是那个坟墓，虽然她时常会幻想一下那个地方。

我想我看到了她的孩子们环绕左右，他们都来报答她的养育之恩。孩子们聪明伶俐的目光和她的目光相遇，他们红润的脸颊上挂满了健康天真的微笑，孩子长大后，他们对母亲感恩的照料减轻了她生活上的操劳。她亲眼看到自己根据原则努力培养的各种美德，成为他们的习惯，目睹了孩子们培养了坚强的性格，使他们在经受逆境考验时，时刻铭记母亲的榜样。

她在这样完成了人生的使命之后，静静地等待着死亡的到来，等待长眠于地下。她从坟墓中升入天堂的时候可以和上帝说：“看，你给了我1000银币，现在我有5000银币！”[16]

我想用几句话总结一下我刚刚所说的内容。在这里，我已经下了战书，我不承认美德有性格差别，就连谨慎端庄也不例外。真理，按照我的理解，对于男人和女人来说必然是相同的；但是在诗人和小说家的生动描绘下，幻想中的女性品格却以牺牲真理和正直为代价，使得品德成为一个相对的概念，仅以功利性为基础。而对于这种功利性，男人却自命不凡，根据自己的利益，随心所欲地加以评判。

我承认，女性可能有很多不同的责任需要履行；但那都是人的责任，因此我坚决认为，指导履行这些责任的原则必须是一样的。

为了成为可敬的人，女人需要运用她们的理智，这是取得人格独立的唯一基础；我的意思是明确地说，就是指她们只能听从理性的权威，而不应该成为舆论谦卑的奴才。

在上流社会里，遇到一个拥有杰出能力，或有普通成就的人，是多么不易啊！在我看来个中缘由很简单，他们出生并生长的环境不正常。人的性格都是由个人或阶级所从事的活动塑造的。如果人的才智不因需要接受磨炼，那就永远处在不开化阶段，无法发展。这个说法对于女人也同样适用，因为她们很少做正经的事情，对于享乐的追求使她们养成了卑微的性格，这就是为什么贵妇的社交场合都如此无聊。同样的原因也导致她们缺乏坚定的意志，迫使她们涌向喧嚣的享乐和虚伪的激情，直到虚荣取代了一切社会情感，而在她们身上也丝毫看不到人性的痕迹。目前组织起来的市民政府带来了这样一种恶果：财富和女性的软弱都导致了人类的堕落，而且出于同样的原因；但是如果承认女人是有理性的人，就应该鼓励她们去追求那些属于她们的美德。因为一个理性的人，如果不通过自己的努力去争取什么，那他怎么能赢得大家的尊重呢？

关于使女人堕落的原因探讨

女人究竟是天生软弱，还是受到客观环境中各种因素的共同作用而堕落，我想，已经很明白了。但我只是想把这种立场，和我经常从那些拥护贵族政体的聪明人口中听到的结论作一对比。他们说，不要把普通民众太当回事，否则那些甘受驱使、阿谀奉承的奴隶就会意识到自己的重要性，抛开他们的镣铐。他们进一步发表评论：如果他们只需抬头就可甩掉束缚，一定是处处都受压迫；他们不追求自己应得的权力，而是甘心舔食着尘土，说道：“我们尽情吃喝吧，因为明天我们就会死去[17]。”以此类推，女人堕落也同样是受贪图眼前享乐这一习性的驱使，最终她们没有足够的品德争取到自由，可她们对此却不屑一顾。我必须说得更清楚一些。

大家一致同意心灵的培养和性别无关，但女性在智力方面不如男人这个问题，却从未被人忽略过。女人只是拥有“绝对的可爱”，给予女人的理性却是微乎其微的；既然不承认她们拥有天才和判断力，我实在想不明白还有什么可以代表智慧了。

灵魂不灭的精义（如果我可以这样说的话）就在于人类理性的可完善性。因为，如果一个人生来完美，或当其步入成年时，一股知识的浪潮汹涌而至，使之豁然开朗，不致犯任何错误，那我就会怀疑在其肉体分解之后，灵魂是否还将存在。但是依目前的情况来看，凡是在人类道德这一问题上，在大家讨论之后仍然悬而未决且使知识渊博的思想家和洞察力非凡的智者都困惑不解的难题都是我建立灵魂不朽信仰的依据。因此理智归根结底是推动进步的一种原动力，更确切地说，是一种分辨真理的原动力。每个人都拥有一个理性的世界，可能理性程度因人而异，在某些人身上表现得比较明显。但如果理性是来自于神的力量，是连接人和造物主的纽带，那么所有人的理性的性质一定是相同的。因为如果一个人不能通过运用理智的力量日趋完美，那他的灵魂又怎么会有上帝的印记呢？然而由于精心打扮而风姿绰约的女人，用迷人的外表来使男人开心，“他可以体面地和她谈情说爱”，但是女人的灵魂却不能拥有理智，男人总是挡在她和理智之间。人们总是认为她天生就应该通过一个巨大的媒介看世界，并且不容置疑。但是抛开这些奇怪的言论，将女人当作一个整体来看，可以把她看成任何东西，但不能是男人的一部分。让我们来探究一下，她到底有没有理性。暂时假定她有，那她不仅仅是为了安慰男人而存在，而女性也不会破坏人类的品格。

男人犯有这样的错误，也许是因为他们看待教育的视角不对。他们没有把教育当作帮助一个人走向完美的第一步，只是把它看作一种生活的准备。我必须称这种态度为感觉论的错误，在这种错误基础上建立起了一个关于女性作风的错误体系，这个体系剥夺了整个女性群体的尊严，将女人，不论美丑，和那些只能点缀大地的鲜花归为一类。这一直是男人们的论调，甚至连那些智慧超群的女人，因为害怕失去男人期待的那种女性气质，也对此应声附和。因此，严格来说，就是否认女性拥有理智；为了生存，女人的本能升华为聪明和狡猾，代替了理智。

归纳总结各种思想的能力，即从个别的例子中概括出全面的结论的能力，对于一个不朽的灵魂来说，是唯一能称为知识的能力。对现象只观察，不作任何解释，也许可以作为生活的常识保留，虽然是以极不完满的方式存在，但是当灵魂离开肉体时，我们还保留了什么为灵魂遮风挡雨？

人们不仅认为女性没有这种能力，而且作家们，除了极个别的人，还坚持说这种能力是和女性的性格不符的。如果男人能证明这个说法，我就承认女人是为男人而生。但是我要事先声明，这种深度的归纳总结的能力，对于男人女人来说都不常见。但是对这种能力的训练是真正意义上的对智慧的培养；而所有原因共同导致在女性身上培养理智比在男性身上更加困难。

这个主张自然而然地把我引到了这一章的主要内容。现在我要谈谈那些导致女性堕落、使她们无法对观察的现象归纳总结的原因。

我不必从遥远的古代史料中追溯女性的历史，我只要承认女性一直以来，或是奴隶，或是暴君，并且这两种状态都同样阻碍了女性理智的发展就已足够。在我看来，似乎女性的各种愚蠢行径和恶劣行为都主要来源于心胸狭隘；而国民政府的制度也在培养女性理性的道路上设下了不可逾越的障碍，可是这是培养美德的唯一根基。富人们也面临着同样的障碍，因此他们也要承受同样的后果。

有句格言叫“需求乃发明之母”，这句格言也可应用到美德上。美德是后天培养的，并且必须以牺牲享乐为代价才能获得。如果一个人没有经历磨难，心胸狭隘，意志脆弱，如果没有现实的需要迫使他追求知识，谁愿意放弃唾手可得的快乐呢？为了生活所需操劳的人是幸福的，因为这种操劳可使他们不至于因懈怠而被那些耗费人精力的恶习所害。如果男人和女人从出生起就被放置在热带地区，正午炽热的阳光直射在他们身上，那么他们怎么能在思想上作好充分的准备，履行人生的责任呢，甚至去享受使他们飘然欲仙的爱情了呢？

从目前的社会状况来看，享乐已经成了女人生活的主要内容，长此以往，我们无法期待这些软弱的人能有什么作为。人们从最初一位女性那里继承了天然的缺陷，即凭借美貌来统治，为了维持她们的权利，放弃了运用智力能够带给她们天赋的权利，宁可选择做短命的女王，也不愿意费神于源自平等的清醒的快乐。她们因为地位低劣而意气风发（这话听起来非常矛盾），她们经常依仗自己是女人，而要求别人对之服服帖帖，虽然她们应当从经验中学会：那些以无可挑剔的恰到好处的态度，随意向女性表达无礼的崇拜，并以此为荣的男人，往往是最有可能践踏和鄙视女人视若珍宝的弱点的男人。

……

我以关切的心情写道，啊，为什么女人要屈尊接受陌生人的这种勉强的殷勤和尊敬呢？这种殷勤和尊敬，与人性规范和文明礼貌规定的人与人之间的礼尚往来不同。为什么她们领会不了，当她们处在“美貌的特权如日中天”时，被男人像女王般供着，只是因为被虚伪的尊崇欺骗，直到她们放弃或不想再享有她们天生的权利？随后她们就会像鸟雀一样被关在笼子里，无所事事，偶尔修饰一下自己的羽毛，假装很有威严地从笼子的一头踱到另一头。确实，她们可以不劳而获，丰衣足食，但是她们为此牺牲了健康、自由和美德。然而，人世间有谁拥有足够坚强的意志，愿意放弃这些恩赐的特权呢？又有谁，能够拥有冷静理智的尊严，超越世俗舆论的束缚，敢于以人类本质的天赋权利为骄傲呢？当世袭的权利扼杀了人的感情，把理性消灭在萌芽状态时，作这种期待是徒劳无益的。

男人的激情就是这样把女性放到王位上，在人类变得更理智之前，我担心女人会继续利用这种不费吹灰之力就可得到的不容置疑的特权。她们会面带微笑，是的，她们笑得出来，尽管她们会听到这样的声音：

美丽的王国里没有中间道路，

女人不是奴隶，就是国王，

一旦不受崇拜必遭唾弃。

问题是她们首先得到的是崇拜，不会想到有朝一日会遭唾弃。

特别是路易十四，他在社会上树立了弄虚作假的风气，并用华而不实的方法，让整个国家跟着他受累。他狡诈地建立起一条专制枷锁，让全体民众尊重他的王权，拥护他的统治，以获取个人私利。他用一种幼稚的殷勤奉承所有女性，使女人在他统治期间获得了贵如王公的地位，但这些对理智和美德都是致命的。

国王永远是国王，女人永远是女人。国王的权威和女人的色情是他们之间不变的主题和合理的交换物。我承认，对于情人，她应当如此，而她的敏感自然会让她竭力激发情感，但不是为了满足虚荣心，而是为了使心灵愉悦。我不认为这是卖弄风情；这是未加修饰的自然冲动。我反对的只是没有爱情的性爱征服欲。

……

女人因为接受一些微不足道的殷勤而一步步走向堕落，我为她们感到惋惜。男人认为向女人献出这种殷勤很合适，实际上，他们正是通过这种侮辱别人的方式维护他们自己的优越地位。向一个地位不如自己的人低头，并不是屈尊。当我看到一个男人迫不及待地万分庄重地帮女人拾起手帕或关上门时，其实这位女士仅需走一两步就可以自己办到，我不禁觉得这些礼节是那么滑稽可笑，我甚至忍不住要发笑。

适才有个疯狂的想法从我的心底涌现，飞入我的脑海，虽然它可能会让大家笑掉大牙，我还是不得不说。我诚挚地希望除了爱情激起的行为外，社会上没有两性的区别。我坚信这种区别是女性软弱性格的根源，这就是为什么女人勤学才艺的时候会忽略理智的培养，同样的原因也解释了为什么女人偏爱优雅的性格胜于英勇的品质。

人类，包括形形色色的人，都希望受到某种爱戴和尊敬，而普通人总是会走捷径来实现他们的愿望。对财富和美色的尊崇是最不容置疑和毫不含糊的，因此也最容易吸引庸俗民众的眼球。毫无疑问，一个人要想从普通人中脱颖而出，上升到显要地位，能力和美德是必需的，这自然就会导致一个臭名昭著的结果：中等阶层最富有美德和能力。男人至少有在一个在岗位上有尊严地为自己努力的机会，这种努力能够真正地使一个有理性的人得到提升，使他拥有更高的社会地位。但是所有的女人，在她们的性格形成之前，处在和富人同样的境地，因为她们生来（我现在谈的是文明社会）就有一定性别上的特权。她们无偿享用这些特权，因此很少会有人想到去付出额外的努力，来赢得少数上层人的尊重。

我们何时听说过，出身贫贱的女人敢于凭借自己的伟大才干和勇敢品行来要求别人尊重自己呢？我们从哪里可以找到这种女人呢？……女人，所谓的上流社会的女士们，不能被当众驳斥，不能做体力活。如果她们具有任何品德的话，也只能是消极的品德，诸如耐心、温顺、好脾气和韧性等，这些品德和任何智慧的有效发挥都是不相容的。另外，因为女人生活起居大多数时候都是在一起，她们很少有绝对独处的时候，因此她们更多地是受到别人情感的影响，而不是自己感情的支配。要使愿望具有热情的力量，确保想象力扩大目标，使之变为自己最想要的东西，那么独处和思索是必需的。对于富人来说也是如此，他们不能充分考虑远大的理想来获得坚强的性格，而这种理想必须依靠热情的思索和冷静的调研才能得到，因此他们无法作出举足轻重的决定。

……

在中等阶级的社会里，男人在年轻时代是为了未来的职业作准备，但婚姻不是他们生活中的大事；而女人正好相反，她们没有什么其他计划来增加才能。吸引她们的不是事业、远大的计划和伟大的抱负；不，她们不会思考怎样建立这些宏伟的整体构架。要想在社会上有头有脸并且能肆意寻欢，她们必须寻求有利的婚姻。她们为了达到这个目标，耗费了自己的时间，并最终从事着“合法的卖淫”。男人一旦进入一个行业，就会把精力集中在未来的利益上（当精力完全集中于某一点时，思维就会变得强壮），并且因为他忙于工作，享乐对他来说只是暂时的休息；而女人却将享乐当成人生的主要目标。实际上，她们从社会上所受的错误教育使得我们可以认为，贪图享乐控制了所有的女人，但是这如何说明灵魂有性别区分呢？若果真如此，我们就可以宣称法国所有的廷臣都不是男人，因为这种摧毁人性的专制制度造就了他们的性格，他们以自由、美德和人性为代价，追求享乐和虚荣。这些都是致命的欲望，它们一直统治的恰恰是整个人类！

女性教育的整体方针培养了女人贪图享乐的习惯，这使得她们在很多情况下，为人处世拘泥于琐碎的细节。比如，她们总是关注次要的事情；她们总是对各种冒险感兴趣，而不去履行自己的责任。

男人踏上征程时，一般都是有目标的。而女人则更关注一些偶然的遭遇，那些在路上发生的奇怪的事情以及自己给旅伴留下的印象。但她最关心的莫过于她身上穿着的华丽服饰，在她要奔赴一个新的地方，或者用一个恰当的法国人的说法，就是在她要制造一场轰动时，服饰就比以往任何时候都重要，更是成为她身体的一部分了。当一个人整天都关心这些细枝末节时，她还会有精神上的尊严吗？

简而言之，从整体上看，女人和富人一样，染上了文明社会所有的愚蠢和罪恶，却错过了文明社会的有益成果。我无须每次都说明，我是就女性的整体状况而言的，不考虑特殊情况。她们燃烧着欲火，却忽略了理性，结果她们成为感官的牺牲品，还美其名曰多愁善感，每次突然迸发的感情都可以让她们不能自持。因此文明社会的妇女被虚伪的教养毒害得如此深重，以致如果让她们处在一个更贴近自然的环境里，道德方面所能达到的水平也会比现在高得多。她们总是心神不定，左顾右盼，她们过度的敏感让她们自己不舒服，也让别人（用一个语气温和的词）觉得讨厌。她们应当用理智思考时，思维都转移到了能够刺激感情的那些事物上去了。她们的行为不坚定，想法也是左右摇摆，不是因为深思熟虑或渐进式发展的观点而踌躇，而是因为她们矛盾的情感而摇摆。她们会一时兴起，对很多东西感兴趣，但是这种热情绝不会发展成精力集中的坚韧不拔的力量，并且很快就会冷却；等到热情自行消退，或者是碰上其他理性上毫无意义、转瞬即逝的热情，就产生了无所谓的态度。如果一个人对心灵的培养只关注如何激发感情，那这个人一定很悲惨！激发感情和加强感情之间应有区别。这样放纵感情去培养判断力，会有什么好结果呢？无疑，结果就是疯狂和愚蠢的混合物！

这种看法不仅仅适用于女性，不过，我现在只是将它用在女性身上。

小说、音乐、诗歌和献殷勤都会使女人成为感性动物，因此她们在培养才艺的时候，就会塑造出这样的性格。这些才艺是她们的社会地位促使其获得的唯一进步。这种被过分强调的多愁善感，自然不利于心灵其他方面能力的发展，而且妨碍了智力控制一切。一个有理性的人要想有利于人，或者满足于自己的地位，其智力必须要取得这种地位。因为大自然告诉我们，随着生命的发展，运用理智是能够克制情欲的唯一方法。

过分享乐会导致另外一种完全不同的结果。我时常会因为看到对精神毁灭的生动刻画而深受震撼，描述的是一个人总是充满渴求的欲望，但身体已伤，因为没有敏锐的感觉器官，因此感受不到任何事物的乐趣。然而，女人却完全变成了她们感官的奴隶，因为她们就是靠着敏感获取手头权利的。

道德学家们会假惺惺地主张：占人类半数的女人应当以一种无精打采的消极表现和愚蠢默认的态度处在这种状态，这就是我们大力推崇的状态。善良的导师们！我们是为何而生呢？也许人们会说，为了保持天真，他们想说的其实是保持一种幼稚的状态。女性从泥土中来，也自甘堕落其中，永远不翻身；要不是创造女人的必要性是使男性能够获得理智的高贵权利和辨别善恶的能力，那么女人根本不用来这个世界走上一遭。

女人由于一种流行的意见沦入各种卑贱、忧虑和悲哀之中，这些情形不一而足，无法全部列举。这种意见认为女人生来就应当凭感官感知，而不是凭智力理论；认为她们必须靠美貌和软弱获得权力，即：

因缺陷而美丽，因软弱而可爱！

这种可爱的软弱使她们完全依赖男人，除了用不正当的权力谋得一些利益外，她们向男人寻求保护和忠告。她们漠视只有理性才能指明的责任，拒绝锻炼她们的心智，绞尽脑汁为自己的不足罩上优雅的外套，以求加强自己在好色之徒眼中的吸引力。这些没什么奇怪，尽管她们这么做只会使自己堕落到道德底线以下。

她们实在是软弱的人，她们必须得依靠男人获得慰藉。即使是碰到最不足挂齿的“危险”，她们也要缠着男人帮助自己，像个寄生虫似的黏住男人不放，可怜地乞求援助。于是她们的天生护花使者就会伸出手臂，提高嗓门保护这些瑟瑟发抖的小可爱们。但他们到底为女人排除了什么样的险情呢？也许是吼叫的老牛，或是窜逃的老鼠，一只大老鼠就已经是个重大灾难了。即使她们是温柔动人的，但就理性或常识来说，她们的行为怎么能使自己免受轻视呢？

这些恐惧如果不是装模作样的话，也许会带来一些惹人怜爱的状态；但这些状态恰恰是低能和愚蠢的一种表现。女人不知不觉地降低了一个有理性的人的身份—因为爱情和尊重是完全不同的概念。

我坚信，如果允许女孩子作适量的锻炼，不把她们关在密闭的房间里，直到她们的肌肉变得无力、消化系统遭到破坏的话，就绝不会有这些幼稚的现象。进一步说，假如社会不去培养，也许更确切地说是创造女孩子的胆怯，而是像对待男孩子的怯懦那样胆怯，我想很快我们就能看到，女人会更有尊严。确实，那时称她们是男人生活道路上绽放的鲜花并不恰当；但是她们一定是社会上更有尊严的成员，并在自己理性的指引下，履行人生的重要责任。卢梭说：“用男人的教育方式来教导女人，她们和我们男人越相似，她们支配我们的权力就会越小。”这也正是我想说的。我不希望她们有支配男人的权力，只是希望她们有能力支配自己。

……

无知是品德脆弱的基础！然而，那些强烈支持男人拥有优越地位的作家们一直坚持认为，无知是女人与生俱来的特点；男人的优越不是指他们程度上比女性更高，而是他们拥有胡作非为的特权。虽然，为了使自己的论调更为温和，他们以骑士般的宽宏大量，极力证明不应当将男女两性作对比；男人生来是运用理智的，而女人生来是凭感觉的，将理性和感觉整合为一个完整的性格，就会得到灵和肉的结合，造就一个最完美的整体。

敏感究竟是什么？“感觉快，知觉快，灵敏度高。”这是约翰逊博士[18]给敏感下的定义。可是这个定义给我的感觉莫过于是在用最精致简练的语言说本能罢了。不论是在感觉上还是在实质上，我都看不出哪里提到了神的形象。即使提炼70次，反复推敲，它仍然是感觉；没有理智的存在；火永远也不能把铅炼成金子！

再回到我以前的论点上来：如果承认一个女人有不朽的灵魂，那么作为人生的一项任务，她就必须锻炼自己的理智。她为使现状更为完整（虽然一切现象都表明，现状只不过是庞大总体内部极小的一个部分），为了满足眼前的享乐而忽略了伟大目标时，她们就阻碍了天性的发展。除非她生下来就是为了繁殖后代，然后死亡腐烂；要不然就是承认各种禽兽都有灵魂（虽然不是理性的灵魂），运用本能和感觉是它们在此生所采取的一个步骤，为来世拥有理性作准备。因此它们将永远落后于人类，因为人类从存在之初，就享有取得理性的能力，虽然我们并不知道原因。

我在像讨论一个公民或者一个父亲的特殊责任那样讨论女人的特殊责任时，就发现，我并非想暗示她们（我指的是大多数）应该走出家庭生活。但是社会的福利并非建立在个别杰出人士努力奋斗的基础上。而且如果社会组织方式更加合理，也许我们就不需要伟大的才干或是英雄的美德了。

在管理一个家庭和教育子女方面，理智（真正意义上的理智）特别重要—身心两方面都需要坚强有力。但是那些通过著述而费尽心机提倡把女人圈养在家里的男人们，却试图采用粗俗的欲望支配的观点（这种欲望因为过度享乐而变得十分挑剔），来削弱女性的体质，禁锢她们的思维。但是，即使他们通过一些邪恶的手段，成功地利用了女人的感情，说服了她们，使她们安心待在家里履行母亲和主妇的责任，我还是会慎重地反对某些指导女人纠正她们行为方式的主张，这些主张试图说服女人，让她们把这些所谓的重要责任当成是人生的主要职责，这种主张是有损理性的。可是，我根据经验判断，如果她们由于理智疏忽，对这些家务活不管不问，与她们在认真追求知识时（虽然我可以说，人类中绝大多数人永远不会求知不倦）表现出来的对家务活的漠然程度相同或者还要严重的话，我还是可以得出以下推论：理性乃是女人正确完成任何工作必不可少的因素，同时我还要重复一遍，敏感并不是理性。

……

另一个对我很有分量的观点，也许会引起任何一位体贴善良人士的共鸣。那些没有接受良好教育的女孩子，往往被父母残忍地抛弃。她的父母去世以后，没有给她们留下任何生活物资，因此她们不仅要依赖理性，还有依靠兄弟的养活。往最好的方面想，这些兄弟都是善良的人，他们把同一父母生育的孩子所应该享有的同等权利当作恩赐还给她们。在这种不明显的屈辱环境下，一个温顺的女人可能能勉强舒适地维持一段时间。但是一旦她的兄弟结了婚—这个可能性是很大的—她就不再被看作是家庭的女主人，而是遭到横眉冷对，被当作可恶的入侵者，对于男主人和他的新欢的善心来说，是个不必要的负担。

很多在身心方面都很软弱的可怜人，没有工作能力，却耻于乞讨，又有谁能够描述她们在这种情况下遭受的痛苦呢？她兄弟的妻子，一个心肠冷酷、心胸狭隘的女人（这个说法并不会有失公允，因为现在的教育制度并不可能让女性豁达大度、视野开阔），因为丈夫对他的亲属表现出了一点善行而心生嫉妒。她的敏感也让她不近人情，因此当她看到自己子女的财产糟蹋在这个没有自立能力的小姑子身上时是很不悦的。

这些都是事实，我一次又一次亲眼看到这些情况发生。结果很明显：妻子用狡猾的手段暗中破坏她所不敢公然反对的惯常的兄妹之情；她甚至不惜用自己的泪水和抚摸，来打动丈夫，直到这个“间谍”被逐出家门，流落到社会上，毫无准备地面对社会的各种挑战；或者这位妻子表现出一种极大的慷慨—也许她认为这比较合乎时宜，给这个女人一小笔活命钱，让她带着这笔钱和一颗未经教化的心灵独自度过郁郁寡欢的日子。

这两个女人也许在理性和人性方面没什么差别，如果交换角色的话，可能表现出同样的自私；但是，如果她们接受的是另外一种教育的话，情况将会有天壤之别。妻子不会有以自我为中心的感觉，理性也会指引她不要期待丈夫的爱情，更不要在他的丈夫因爱情违反他的重要职责时，以这种爱情为骄傲。她会希望不仅仅是因为丈夫爱她，她才爱自己的丈夫，而是因为丈夫的品德而爱她；那个作姐妹的也可能会自己去努力，而不是寄人篱下，讨要嗟来之食。

我确实相信感情和理智一样是靠培养和对官能的锻炼（这点好像不太明显）获得的。我现在谈的不是转瞬即逝的感情，而是爱情。在男人和女人的教育工作中最艰巨的一项任务，也许就是采用一种恰到好处的教育方式，使之既不限制他们理智的发展，让他们的内心洋溢着一种由青春期激发起来的活力带来的温情，也不要因为思考的问题都是与生活关系不大的研究而使感情逐渐冷淡。

至于女人，她们接受了周全的教育之后，或是成为优雅的淑女，多愁善感，天马行空，反复无常；或是成为优秀的家庭主妇。后者通常都是友好、真诚的人，精明有头脑，又不乏世俗的谨慎，虽然她们没有伟大的思想和高级的趣味，但是和那些优雅的多愁善感的淑女比起来，往往是这些品质让她们成为对社会更有用的人。知识的大门是向她们关闭的。当她们走出家庭或社区，她们就无所适从；思想没有寄托，因为虽然文学提供了丰富的娱乐资源，但是她们未试图去享受，还经常对之嗤之以鼻。那些更有教养的人的感情和品位对她们来说是非常荒唐的，即使是那些由于机缘巧合或者家庭关系而让她们深爱的人也不例外；至于那些泛泛之交，她们认为这些都是矫揉造作。

一个明智的男人之所以爱这样的女人，是因为她是女性；之所以尊重她，是因为她是一个可以信赖的仆人。他为了求清静，任由她去责骂奴仆，让她穿着最好材质做的衣服去教堂做礼拜。一个与她智力相当的男人也许就不会事事顺着她，因为他也许想要侵犯她的特权，他想要自己管理一些家务；但是女人，她们因未接受教化而心胸狭隘，她们天生自私自利，不会因深思而拥有宽广的胸襟，因此她们是不适合管理家庭的，因为一旦她们手头的权力泛滥，她们就会采取专制手段，来维持用大笔财富堆积起来的优越地位。这种恶行有时候会变本加厉，使家仆没有任何放松，不得不超负荷工作，为了让这个显要的女人享受豪宴，或者让她在和邻居夸耀衣服和排场时有谈资。当她照看孩子的时候，会给孩子们穿非常昂贵的衣服，无论这种疼爱是出于虚荣还是母爱，这对她的孩子来说都是百害无一利的。此外，有多少这样的女人整天闷闷不乐地打发着日子，或者至少一到晚上她们就郁郁寡欢。尽管她们的丈夫承认她们是好管家和忠贞的妻子，但是他们还是会离家去寻找更心仪的—请允许我用一个意味深长的法语词—富有刺激性（piquant）的社交伙伴。这个有耐心的苦人儿，就像磨坊里蒙了眼睛的骡子一样，勤勤恳恳地完成了她的工作，却没有得到她应得的报酬，因为对她来说，丈夫的爱抚就是她的薪酬。而本来就没有什么资源的女人，绝对不会逆来顺受，接受这种被剥夺自然权利的行为。

相反，文雅的淑女接受的教育是，让她们用鄙夷的态度对待日常生活中的琐碎小事。虽然人们只不过让她学习一点比常识略高一筹的才艺而已；因为除非通过练习锻炼她的理智，否则她也不可能很精准地获得一些体力方面的才能。没有原则作基础，品位也是肤浅的；优雅必须来源于比模仿更为深刻的东西。但是，想象力开始沸腾，感情即使没有世故复杂，也会变得吹毛求疵；或者虽然她的心灵依然质朴（但却过于温和），却无法作出有见地的判断。

……

如果爱情是一种极致的美德，那就只教育女人去激发爱情即可，让她们尽情发挥自己的魅力去迷醉人们的感官吧。但是如果她们是有道德的人，那就应该给她们机会成为有智慧的人，让她们对男人的爱情仅仅成为热情洋溢的普遍大爱中的一部分，在普泽众生之后，升华为对上帝的感恩。

履行家庭责任需要很大的决心，还要有坚强的毅力，这种毅力需要比感情更加坚固的东西做后盾，无论感情是多么活跃和真挚。要做一个自律的榜样，一个有道德的人必须在行为上严格要求自己，而这是一个自幼受个人感觉影响的人所做不到的。任何在理性上想要有所作为的人，都必须有严格的行为规范。我们在履行最简单的责任时，经常不得不违背自己一时兴起的怜悯之心或慈悲情怀。严厉往往是感情最坚实和最高尚的证据；正是由于缺乏这种控制感情的力量，缺乏一种更高尚的感情—这种感情让人意识到自己深爱的人的未来幸福比当下的享乐重要得多—很多溺爱的母亲对她们的孩子万般宠爱，却产生了究竟忽略和纵容哪一坏处最大的疑问；在我看来，后者遗害最深。

人类似乎相信孩子在童年时期应当由母亲来管教。但是现在，据我观察，多愁善感的女人最不适合这项工作，因为她们很容易被情绪左右，宠坏了孩子的性情。性情的管理是教育中最初和最重要的部分，需要根据理性作出冷静沉着的观察。孩子的行为规范既不是专制暴虐，也不是溺爱纵容，但是敏感的人往往不是陷入这个极端，就是走到那个极端，始终把握不好尺度。我曾经进一步推论得出结论，一个极富天赋的人是最不适合从事教育工作的，无论是公共教育还是家庭教育。这类极少数的人看问题好从大处着眼，很少有好脾气（如果曾经有过的话）。这种惯常性的乐天派脾气，即我们所说的好性情，也许很难和卓越的智力结合，正如它不会和强烈的感情兼容一样。有些人怀着好奇心和崇拜之情追随放荡不羁的天才，或者是带着冷静的赞许之情，吸收那些学富五车的智者为他们精心准备的指示，一旦发现天才暴躁易怒，智者郁郁寡欢，就不应该感到厌恶。因为活跃的想象力和深刻的洞察力与顺从的谦恭文雅是难以相容的，这种文雅至少会让一个人屈从于大众的意见和偏见，而不是勇敢地予以反驳。

但是在谈论教育或者礼仪时，我们可以不考虑那些智力卓群的人，让他们顺其自然吧；我们谈的是能力平平的普通大众，他们需要接受教育，会因周围环境的影响而近朱者赤。

我认为这些可敬的民众，无论男女，都不应当躺在奢侈和懒惰的温床上增强他们的情感，而牺牲他们的理智。因为，除非有一定的智力作基础，否则他们不可能成为有道德的人或是自由的人：一个靠财富或真正的智慧发家的贵族，永远都会让那些时而胆小怯懦时而凶恶勇猛的情感奴隶努力臣服。

……

女人很少能有足够认真的工作来平静她们的心情；四周琐碎的挂念或虚荣的追求耗尽了她们身心的精力，她们自然而然地只成为了感觉的对象。简言之，整个女性教育（社会教育）的宗旨就是要让那些状况最好的女人变得浪漫、不专一；让剩下的女人变得虚荣和刻薄。在目前的社会状况下，恐怕这种弊端很难克服。也许一种更远大的理想在社会上占主流趋势时，女人就会比较接近自然和理性，在她们变得日益高尚的同时，成为更有美德、更有益的人才。

但是我还是要大胆声明，当世界上大多数人的主要愿望是向世人炫耀摆阔时，女人的理智就永远得不到长足的发展，理性也就无法规范她们的行为，因为自然的情感和最有益的美德都成为这种愚蠢欲望的牺牲品。女孩结婚的目的，借用一个意味深长的俗话来说，就是为了荣华富贵，并且如此巧妙地控制自己的情感，除非一个家财万贯的男人来求婚，否则绝不坠入爱河。我要在另一章讨论这个话题，现在我只需点到为止。因为年轻女人总是过早患上成年人自私的精明，浇灭了她们青春的热情，从而日益堕落。

同样的来源传出了一种说法，年轻女孩应该把大多数时间用来做针线活；但是，这种活计把她们的思维限制在自己的穿着打扮上，因此比其他任何可选择的事情都更阻碍她们智力的发展。男人吩咐别人为他做衣裳，交代完了就不再提起；女人的衣服，无论是必需的还是装饰性的，都需要自己缝制，而且总是在絮絮叨叨地说这个话题，而她们的大脑也跟着双手运动。实际上削弱她们思维的不是那些必需的衣服，而是那些廉价的华丽服装。因为当一个处于社会底层的女人为她的丈夫和孩子缝制衣服时，她是在履行她的责任，这是她家务活的一部分；但是那些想要华丽衣服却又消费不起，只好自己缝制的女人，她们损失的不仅仅是时间。贫穷的女人必须工作才能拥有道德。中等阶层的女人如果不盲目追求贵族阶层的时髦，不贪图闲适安逸的生活，那她们也许会雇用贫穷的女人，因为她们需要料理家务、教育子女和锻炼自己的心智。园艺、实验哲学和文学会为她们提供思考的内容和谈论的话题，这些在一定程度上可以锻炼她们的思维。虽然那些不会僵坐在椅子上一动不动地缝衣襟、织花边的法国妇女谈论的话题已经够肤浅了，但是我认为，她们的交谈远没有英国女人的无聊，她们整天把时间花在做各种帽子和所有用来装饰的玩意儿上面。因为这些事情而堕落的往往是体面、谨慎的女人，因为她们的动机仅仅是爱慕虚荣。那些利用自己的品位让自己感情更有诱惑力的放荡女人，心里想的更多。

我的这些论点都是从一个总的论点发展而来的，这个论点我以前提过，并且多次强调，因为说到男人、女人和职业，我们会发现思维塑造性格，对于人类和对于个人来说都是如此。女人的脑子里整天都是她自己的容貌，那她把外貌当作是最重要的事又有什么奇怪的呢？但是即使是长得容颜秀丽，一定程度的心灵自由也是必不可少的；这也许就是有些温柔的妻子除了性的吸引力之外，再没有其他魅力的原因吧。除此之外，需要久坐的工作让大多数女人体弱多病—而对于女性品质的错误观念使她们以这种柔弱为荣，虽然这种柔弱实则为一副枷锁，通过让女人不断关注自己的外表，而禁锢了心灵的发展。

那些高贵的女性很少亲自缝制衣服，因而她们只需运用自己的鉴赏力，而且她们在化完妆以后，不会再想那些华丽的服饰，因此拥有了一份闲适的淡定；而那些为了打扮而打扮的女人，很少会表现出这种淡然。实际上，我所作的关于中产阶级（在中产阶级，有才能的人最能大展拳脚）的评价，并不是对所有女人都适用。因为那些上流社会的女人，至少读过一些文学作品，而且和男人谈论过一些宏观问题，因此会比那些盲目模仿她们时髦和缺点，却无法享有她们优势的女人拥有更多的学识。而谈到美德，我说的是广义上的美德，我在下层社会中见到的最多。很多贫苦的女人，呕心沥血地养育子女，竭力维持着因男人的恶行而濒临破碎的家庭；但是上层社会的淑女们懒惰成性，不会主动去培养自己的品格，有文化并不会使她们更优雅，反而更软弱。确实，我亲眼目睹了许多贫困的女人非常通情达理，她们没有接受教育的机会，却表现出英勇的行为，这些有力地证实了我的观点，无聊琐事只会让女人变成没有追求的人。男人占有了女人的身体，却任其心灵腐烂；因此肉体之爱让男人疲惫不堪（其实这是他最喜欢的娱乐活动）时，他就会想办法奴役女人—而谁又能预测需要多少世代的发展，才能使这些卑贱的奴隶的后代获得自由，拥有高尚的品德和富有创造性的思想呢？

在追溯那些我认为曾导致女性堕落的原因时，我将范围局限在那些对整个女性的道德和行为产生普遍影响的因素上，并且我认为，这些因素显然都是由于缺乏理智而导致的。至于这种不足到底是因为身体内在的还是偶然的智力缺陷导致的，迟早会为我们揭开谜底。因为我不想过度强调那些极少数受过男性教育、英勇非凡意志坚定的女性的例子。我只是补充一句，那些处在同样环境中的男人也获得了和这些女人相似的性格—我说的是普通的男人，那些聪颖过人的男人都是来自于某一个阶层，然而没有一个女性属于这个阶层。

各种关于良好声誉重要性的性别观念对道德的损害

我很早就意识到，那些不遗余力向女人灌输的有关行为举止的忠告和保持良好声誉的方法，都是华而不实的毒药，它们为道德包了一层外壳，却侵蚀了它的本质。何况，用这种徒有其表的标准来衡量人，必定会带来错误的结果，就如同影子一样，它的长短在很大程度上取决于太阳的高度和很多偶然性的因素。

……

如果女性不是常常被教导要孜孜不倦地保持她们表面性格的光鲜和美好，并把它们看作是女人的全部职责；如果人们不是总用规范行为和保持良好声誉的规矩来代替道德义务，我就没有必要对此话题展开论述，使之成为贯穿我所有作品的主要原则。但是，谈到良好声誉，注意力就被局限到一种品德上—贞洁。如果一个女人的声誉（用这种荒谬的方法来称谓）得到保全，那她就可以忽略所有的社会责任，甚至可以沉溺于玩乐和奢侈，将她的家庭带向毁灭；但是她仍然表现出一副道貌岸然的样子—因为她确实是一个值得尊敬的女人。

麦考莱夫人曾公正声明：“只有一种错误，体面的女人犯了之后不能免于惩罚。”她随后公正而仁慈地补充，“因此就导致了一种愚蠢的老生常谈，认为女人第一次犯了出卖贞操的错误，就会从根本上败坏她的声誉。但是造物主创造出的生物不可能这么脆弱。人类心灵的本质很高贵，不会这么容易受侵蚀。虽然女人在境遇和教育方面处于劣势，但是除非她们遭到同性恶毒的诅咒而流于绝望的境地，否则她们很少被完全抛弃。”

虽然女人将贞洁的声誉视为珍宝，但是男人却对它嗤之以鼻，这两种极端态度对道德危害都很大。

无疑，男人比女人更容易受到欲望的诱惑，而且他们的欲望往往因为肆意享乐和欲壑难填而更为堕落。奢侈的生活让人们在饮食上挑三拣四，使身体每况愈下；还导致了人们的贪食行为，这种行为过于粗俗，以致我们已经在这类人身上看不到任何礼貌得体的概念了。他们在别人面前肆无忌惮地纵情饕餮，事后还因为自己毫无节制造成的腹内胀痛牢骚满腹。有些女人，特别是法国女人，已经在这方面有失端庄了，因为她们会坦然自若地谈论消化不良。我们只希望杜绝那些以食腐为生的成群的夏虫，那些由游手好闲的人在财富的温床上滋养出来的，只有这样我们才不会因为看到这种粗俗的贪婪而心生厌恶。

我认为，有一条行为规范方面的准则，是可以制约其他所有准则这就是对人类抱有习惯性的尊重，防止我们因一时贪图享乐而招来同伴的憎恶。很多已婚女人和其他稍微上了年纪的人，经常因为懒惰成性而颜面尽失。虽然大家坚信外貌是联系两性的纽带，然而又有多少女人纯粹因为懒惰，或是贪图毫无意义的自我放纵，而遭致别人的厌恶呢？

那种让两性结合的堕落腐化的欲望，有更致命的后果。天性应当是品位的唯一标准，欲望的永恒量尺—然而好色之徒多么粗暴地侮辱了天性。我们暂且不论高尚的爱情。为了保证人类的传宗接代，天性，在这一方面和所有其他方面一样，将对欲望的满足规定为维持人类繁衍生息必要的自然法则，因此抬高了肉欲的地位，并让肉欲掺杂了一些理智和感情的成分。为纯粹的动物本能加上一些为人父母的感情，可以使这种本能更加尊贵；男人和女人为了孩子经常相聚，对孩子共同的感情激发了相互之间的关心和感情。女人因此有了比打扮自己更加崇高的责任，为了履行职责，她们不会心安理得地沦为无耻淫欲的奴隶。而现在相当多的女人都是这种奴隶，更准确点说，她们就是所有贪食者的常备佳肴。

也许有人会反驳我，虽然这种堕落情节恶劣，但它不过影响了一部分甘于奉献的女人，她们为了挽救其余的女人而牺牲自己。但是这种允许小部分罪恶存在的以追求更大利益的说法，和其他所有错误的主张一样，很容易得到证实。它们的危害远不止于此，因为女性中比较贞洁的人，她们的道德品质和心灵安宁都受到了这种女人的破坏。她们认为这些女人犯的罪行不可饶恕；她们坚决认为这些女人通过各种手段引诱她们的丈夫，导致她们的儿子放荡堕落，并且逼他们（正派的女人不要惊讶）也在某种程度上作同样的勾当。因为我要大胆断言，所有导致女性软弱和堕落（正如我刚才详细阐述）的因素，都是出自同样一个主要的原因—男人贞洁观念的匮乏。

这种放荡行为的流毒甚广，它使性欲堕落到只有靠淫荡的刺激才能为之兴奋的程度。但是他们辜负了造物主充满慈爱的良苦用心，脑子里完全被容貌占据。这些沉迷于美色的无耻之徒，他们的行为日渐放荡，甚至开始对女人的柔情吹毛求疵。在意大利和葡萄牙，男人甚至会穿梭于各种暧昧场所，去寻求比女性柔情更有吸引力的刺激。

为了让这类男人如意，女人整体变得日益放荡，尽管程度不同，但是她们心甘情愿和男人发生没有感情的性交，使两性都变得堕落，因为这种行为影响了男人的品位。而各个阶层的女人，必然会为了满足男人已败坏的品位，而调整自己的行为，以追求享乐和权势。女人因此在身体和心灵上都变得不堪一击，但是如果她们考虑到她们存在的重大目标之一—生育并抚养孩子，就不会变得如此软弱，她们现在已经没有足够的能力来履行做母亲的首要责任；父母之情使本能变得高贵，而女人却因为淫荡而愿意牺牲为人父母的权利，她们或是打掉腹中尚在发育的胎儿，或是在孩子出生之后将之抛弃。一切事物中的自然法则都值得尊重，很少有人能够破坏自然的法则而免于惩罚。那些特别吸引好色之徒的软弱女人是不配做母亲的，虽然她们可能会怀孕。那个有钱的好色之徒，在女人堆里寻欢作乐，到处散播堕落和痛苦，在他想要传宗接代时，却只能从妻子那里得到一个继承了两人缺点的发育不良的孩子。

人们将现代的人文精神和古代的野蛮行为作对比时，总是强调古人有一种把养不起的孩子抛弃到野外的野蛮风俗。但是那些对此愤愤不平的情感丰富的男人，也许正因为自己混乱的男女关系，造成了一种非常具有破坏性的不育现象和广为扩散的无耻风尚。毫无疑问，造物主从来无意让女人通过满足性欲而破坏他让人类拥有性欲的真正目的（即繁衍后代）！

我前面已经提过，男人应当对他们引诱过的女人负责，这将成为改善女人行为方式的一种手段，同时也可以阻止这种对人口和道德都有毁灭性打击的恶行进一步发展。还有一种同样明显的方法，就是将女人的注意力转移到贞洁这项真正的美德上来。因为这种一边对好色之徒放荡情欲的受害者和她们自己的愚蠢嗤之以鼻，一边又对他们笑脸相迎的女人，也许会有洁白如雪花的名声，但是就端庄来说，她们是不会赢得多少人尊重的。

另外，在她费尽心思打扮自己，只是为了吸引男人的眼球，得到他们尊敬的赞叹和称之为天真奉承的无聊崇拜时，也许她会自诩纯洁，但实际上她已经沾染了同样的愚蠢。因为如果女人真正因为美德本身而尊崇美德，她们就不会从虚荣中寻求补偿，以弥补为了保全声誉而必须去履行的自我克制，她们也不会和蔑视声誉的男人有任何来往。

男人和女人之间是相互腐化、共同进步的。我相信这是一个不容置疑的真理，适用于一切美德。贞洁、端庄、公德心以及一系列高贵的品德，都是社会道德和幸福得以建立的基础，应当得到所有人的认同和培养，否则培养这些品德就没有什么意义。为了不让邪恶或懒惰的人为自己破坏某种神圣的责任寻找托辞（他们会称这种责任为女性的责任），更明智的办法就是让大家知道造物主并没有区分两性的品德。因此不贞的男人双重地违反了造物主的意图，他不仅让女人无法生育，而且伤害了自己的身体，虽然他不会像女人犯罪那样为世人所不齿。这些都是生理上的后果，道德上的危害就更令人警醒；因为公民、丈夫、妻子、父亲、母亲和一家之主的责任仅仅成为寻求一己私利的关系时，道德就已名存实亡。

既然如此，那为何哲学家们还要期待公德心呢？公德心必须靠私德来培育，要不然就会成为女人为保护声誉，男人为维持声誉而表现的虚情假意。这种感情没有道德和高尚品行的支撑，而高尚的品行把对某种责任的惯常性破坏视为对整个道德法则的破坏。

社会上既定的不合理差别造成的有害影响

人们对财产的尊重，就像有毒的喷泉一样，带来了很多灾祸和罪恶，使这个世界在一个爱好思考的人眼里是一派萧条荒凉的景象。因为正是在文明高度发达的社会里，害虫和毒蛇才会潜藏在茂密的丛林中；还有死气沉沉的气氛孕育的耽于享乐，使得一切优秀的性情在发展成为美德之前就夭折了。

一个阶级压迫另一个阶级，所有的人都指望凭借自己的财富获得尊重，一旦有了财富，就可以拥有只有才能和美德才配享有的尊重。那些忽略了人类应当履行责任的人，却仍被当作半个神一样供着。宗教和美德被一层礼仪的幕布分开了，可是人们还在惊讶，这个世界严格意义上来说已经腐化成骗子和压迫者的巢穴了。

有一句朴实的格言精辟地道出了真理：魔鬼专门指使游手好闲的人为自己干活。世袭的财富和头衔除了带来习惯性的懒惰，还能带来什么呢？因为人的天性如此，只有通过锻炼自己的天赋，才会合理使用它们，可是除非出于某种需要首先迫使他采取行动，他才会运用自己的天赋。同样，美德也只有通过履行相关的责任才能获得；但是一个人听尽了甜言蜜语忘乎所以，甚至丧失人性的时候，他是不会感受到这些神圣责任的意义的。社会上必须建立更多的平等，否则道德将永远不会有进展。如果人类的一半因为命运而被困在深渊里，那么即使这种道德的平等性以岩石为根基也不会有稳固的基础，因为这些人会不断通过无知或骄傲来将它毁坏。

在女人在某种程度上脱离男人而独立之前，指望女人有美德是徒劳无益的；同样，也不能指望女人拥有自然感情的力量，让她们成为贤妻良母。她们完全依赖丈夫时就会变得狡猾、卑鄙、自私；而那些因哈巴狗样逢迎奉承的爱情而满足的男人，也不会有什么细腻的情感，因为爱情不是商品。不管怎么理解这句话的意义，如果寻求的爱情没有同样的感情作为回报，爱情的羽翼就会立即被折断。但是，男人因为财富而变得软弱，而女人似乎是以个人魅力为生时，我们怎么能期待他们会履行那些需要努力和自制才能使他们高尚的责任呢？世袭的财产使人心变得复杂，那些一出生就受财产牵绊的不幸受害者—如果我可以这么说的话—很少会运用他们身体或精神的力量，他们只能通过一个媒介来观察万物，而这个媒介还是假的，因此他们无法辨别真正的美德和幸福包括什么。一个人被地位的帷幕遮蔽了双眼，并且因此戴着面具耀武扬威，愚蠢而又无所事事地拖着没有知觉的四肢，从一个放浪场所晃到另外一个，转动着茫然无神的眼珠，眼神明显告诉我们：这是个没有思想的躯壳，这种人的观点必然是谬误的。

因此我想推导出下面的结论，如果社会不迫使男人和女人分别履行各自的责任，并使之成为人们获得同胞赞同的唯一途径（这种赞同是每一个人或多或少都希望得到的），那么这个社会一定组织得不够完善。结果，对财富和美色的推崇成了真正的东北风，摧毁了爱情和美德的娇嫩花蕊。造物主英明地将感情和责任结合，从而使劳作变得甜蜜，并且赠与理智只有心灵才能给予的活力。但是，如果仅仅因为爱情是某种性格合适的标志而表现出虚情假意，却不去履行爱情应尽的责任，那么这种爱情不过是邪恶和愚蠢不得不向美德和事物的真正本质作出的空洞恭维罢了。

为了证明我的观点，我只需要作如下陈述：一个女人因自己的美貌而受人追捧，而她又因为沉溺于这些赞美不能自拔，以致忽视了自己作为母亲不可推卸的职责时，她就是自甘堕落，因为她疏于培养一种同样能够让她有价值和幸福感的感情。真正的幸福，我指的是在目前不完善状态下能够得到的所有的满足感和道德上的幸福，必须来源于有节制的感情，而感情是包含责任的。男人没有意识到由于他们一味鼓励女人取悦他人，而给她们造成的深重苦难和因此纵容的可怕的软弱。他们没有考虑到他们这样做，让女人为具有色情概念的美貌而牺牲了一生的幸福和尊严，造成天然责任和人为责任走的对立，而实际上二者是和谐一致的。

如果一个男人看到自己的妻子在哺乳孩子时，觉得还不如淫荡的行为带给他的快乐多，而他也不是因为早年的不羁行径变得极不正常，那他一定就是铁石心肠。但是金钱让女人抛弃了哺乳孩子这种加强婚姻关系、把尊严和爱慕的回忆结合起来的自然道路。女人为了保持容颜美丽，得到那顶使她短期内对异性有某种统治权的花环，而忽略了在丈夫心中留下深刻的印象，而当他们两鬓斑白、热情退却时，这种印象会比动人的处女魅力唤起更多的温柔回忆。一个通情达理感情丰富的女人具有的女性关怀是让人感动的，孩子的父亲一直兢兢业业地履行应尽的职责，而女人和她的孩子则以高尚的尊严来回报他的抚爱，这种景象让人肃然起敬，赏心悦目。当我看到无病呻吟的庄严和卑躬屈膝的礼节以炫耀代替家庭感情的时候，我深感厌恶，我的感情确实很奇怪（其实我已经竭力避免太做作的感情了），以至于我不得不转向其他的场面，将注意力转移到自然中随处可见的令人眼前一亮的绿色景致上，以获得解脱。于是我兴奋地看到了一个女人在照顾她的孩子，完成她应尽的责任，也许只有一个女仆替她承担辛劳的家务劳作。我看见她把自己和孩子都收拾得很整齐，迎接晚上归来的疲惫不堪的丈夫，他看到的是孩子微笑的脸庞和干净整洁的家。我的心俨然已经融入了这个家庭，在熟悉的脚步声引起一阵欢乐的骚动时，我的心甚至也会产生共鸣，怦怦跳动。

当我的善意因为凝视这幅不加任何修饰的图画而得到满足时，我曾经想：这样的一对夫妇因为各自都履行了自己应尽的责任，因此相互依存又各自独立，他们拥有了生活能够赋予他们的一切。如果他们积攒了一定的财富，脱离了赤贫状态，不必为他们花的每一笔钱左右掂量；有了足够的钱，他们不必考虑让人心胸狭隘的拮据的家庭经济计划，我断言（其实我的想法很简单），我不知道这个家庭还需要什么才能成为世界上最幸福、最值得尊重的境况，除非需要有一点文学鉴赏的品位，为社交谈话增加一点变化和趣味，还额外需要一笔钱接济穷人、购买书籍。在人们内心充满怜悯之情，脑子里一积极安排各种有用的计划时，却有一个一本正经的小人儿不停地拽着胳膊，不让伸手拿出那个几乎瘪下去的钱包，同时还悄悄地说一些关于正义第一的深谋远虑的大道理，实在让人不悦。

虽然财产和继承的荣誉对于人类的性格有毁灭性的打击，但是女人因此而受到的伤害和束缚比男人更大（如果她们确实受其影响），因为男人仍然可以通过成为军人和政客，在一定程度上展现他们的才能。

……

不合理的等级制度让文明成为祸害，它把世人分成骄奢淫逸的暴君和狡猾嫉妒的寄生虫，这种分法让这两种人几乎同等地陷入堕落。因为尊重与履行人生的责任无关，却由地位决定。当人们没有完成分内职责时，就不会有足够深厚的感情来巩固美德，而有美德的人自然能够得到爱情作为回报。男人仍然可以悄悄地钻一些空子，为了自己敢想敢做；而女人的任务就艰巨得多，因为她要战胜很多女性特有的困难，而克服它们需要超出常人的力量。

一个真正仁慈的立法者，总是会努力使每一个品德高尚的人都能从中获益，这样私德就会促进公德的建设，而有秩序的整体会因为所有的部分都趋向于一个共同的中心而得到加强。但是对女人来说，私德或公德的区分确是有问题的，因为卢梭和很多男性作家都坚决声称女人应当一生都受到礼法严格的约束。但是如果她完全有能力依照一个更高尚的动机行事，如果她是不朽灵魂的继承者，那她为何还要屈从于礼法，而且是盲目的礼法呢？糖必须永远要用维持生命的血液来制造吗？当原则是更可靠的保证时，难道人类的一半就注定要像悲惨的非洲黑奴一样，只是为了让男人的生命之杯更加甜蜜，而屈从于残酷荼毒她们身心的偏见吗？这又何尝不是间接否认女人的理智呢？因为如果天赋不发挥任何作用，那就只是嘲弄。

女人和男人一样，因财富带来的轻松享乐而变得软弱和奢侈；除此之外，还使她们成了外貌的奴隶。她们必须把自己打扮得花枝招展，这样男人才可能把自己的理智施舍给她们，带领步履蹒跚的女人走向正途。如果她们胸怀大志，就必须用狠毒的伎俩来统治她们的暴君，因为她们没有权利，也就没有必须承担的义务。在本书下一部分我要讨论关于女性的法律，这些法律将男人和他妻子的结合视为荒谬之事；然后由于轻率转变为只认为男人是有责任的，女人就被置于无足轻重的位置。

那些履行了应尽职责的人都是独立的人。我将详细阐述女人，她们的首要责任就是将自己视为理性的人；按重要性来说，其次就是把自己视作公民，公民的责任包含甚广，做母亲的责任也包括在内。女人生活中的地位免除了她们的这种责任，让她们仅仅变成一具玩偶，必然也导致她们堕落。或者她们把注意力从只为自己光滑的肉体寻找合体光鲜的衣服，转移到更重要的事情上去时，她们的大脑也只会被某种温柔的柏拉图式的理想爱情占据；或者实际上用阴谋行为来保持她们思维的活跃。因为她们在忽略家庭责任之时，就没有能力像士兵一样占领阵地，前进或后撤，或者在议会中辩论，以防自己的思维因被锈蚀而倒退。

我知道，卢梭为了证明女性的低劣，曾兴高采烈地大喊：她们怎么能离开育婴室奔赴战场呢！有些道德学家曾经证明：军营是培养最英勇品质的地方。尽管我认为，要想证明很多造就了所谓英雄的战争是合理的，即使是最聪明的诡辩家也会感到为难吧。我并不打算批评性地看待这个问题，因为国家在被蚕食、森林被战火和刀枪夷为平地之时，我也会经常把这种野心勃勃的怪事当作是文明社会的首选自然方式，因此我也不将战争称为祸害；但是肯定的一点是，现在的战争体制与所有的美德都没有丝毫联系，战争再也不是培养坚强意志的学校，而是训练阴险手腕和软弱性格的地方。

但是在目前社会高度发达的状况下，如果防御型战争，唯一的无可非议的战争，被认为是正义和光荣的，在这类战争中，美德能够展现它的面貌，并且在净化山顶空气的呼啸寒风中日益成熟，那么古代真正的英雄主义也许会再次激起女性内心的激情。但是公正儒雅的读者，无论您是男人还是女人，请不要惊慌，因为尽管我把现代军人的性格和有教养的女人对比，我并非规劝她们将手中的卷线杆换成火枪，虽然我真心希望看到刺刀能够变成修剪树枝的钩刀。我只是厌倦了财富浊流带来的罪恶和愚蠢，这支浊流玷污了自然感情的清澈溪流，所以我对未来重新设想了一番，希冀有朝一日未来社会可以是这样的组成：男人必须履行作为一个公民的责任，否则他就会遭到鄙视；他在公民生活的任何部门任职时，他的妻子也是一个积极的公民，她也应当集中精力来料理家务，教育子女，帮助邻居。

但是要使她真正成为道德高尚、有用的人，假如她履行了自己的公民责任，她就不需要民法的特别保护；她不要在丈夫在世时仰仗他的恩惠过活，或去世后指望他的遗产来赡养；因为如果一个人自己就身无分文，他如何能慷慨解囊？或是自己没有自由，如何能拥有高尚的道德？在目前的情况下，一个对丈夫忠贞不渝的妻子，如果她既不生育也不培养子女，她就不配称作妻子，也无权享有公民之名。但是既然自然权利被剥夺，责任当然也就无从谈起了。

女人的思想和身体都非常虚弱，以致只有在追求空虚的享乐或制作一些轻浮的时装时才能集中精力，这时女人一定会被看作仅仅是男人放荡的慰藉。一个有思想的人，当看到清晨无数的马车载着脸色苍白的女人在大都市的街道上飞快横冲直撞时，还有什么比这幅景象更让他郁闷呢！我一直和约翰逊博士的意见一样，希望把她们中的一些人放置在一个小工坊中，那里有半打的孩子仰望着她们倦怠的面容等着养活。如果潜在的力量不能很快让她们的眼睛充满健康的活力；她们以前只会浮现出笑靥而现在却变得苍白的脸庞，因为运用理智也爬上了几道皱纹，如果这样的脸庞不能让她们恢复品德上业已丧失的尊严，更确切地说，无法让品德获得本质上真正的尊严的话，那我确实是大错特错了。美德不是来源于空想，更不是来源于财富滋生的消极懈怠。

此外，贫穷甚至比罪恶还要可耻时，道德岂不是更加可耻吗？为了避免误解，尽管我认为平民阶层的普通女人是受宗教和理性的感召而履行妻子和母亲的责任，但我仍然禁不住扼腕叹息：没有一条道路可供上流社会的女人选择，以追求更广泛的计划，实现有为和独立。我下文要讨论一个问题，在这里我只是提一下，这可能会招来大家的耻笑，因为我真的认为女性应该有自己的国会代表，而不是对专横统治的逆来顺受，在政府审议中没有任何直接参与的权利。

但是，因为这个国家现在的整个代议制度不过是专制者统治的便利手段，她们就无须抱怨，因为她们和很多辛勤工作的机械工人一样，被别人代表着，甚至这些工人在无法养活孩子的时候还要掏钱来维持王室奢侈的花销。那些用血汗来维持王子的豪华马群，或是修饰那些目中无人、恬不知耻的贵妇的华盖的人，他们是如何被代表的呢？对生活必需品征收税，让一群无所事事的王子和公主带着愚蠢的炫耀，在目瞪口呆的群众面前招摇过市，这场检阅让他们付出了如此高昂的代价，而他们却以几乎崇敬的心情瞻仰着检阅队伍。这只是哥特般的奇观，有点像在白厅[19]前对骑马哨兵的检阅，野蛮而毫无意义。每当我看到这种情形，心中便不由地轻蔑又愤怒。

一个人对这种景象印象深刻时，他的思维一定会是一种奇怪的迷惑状态！但是在美德将这些愚蠢行为的残留消除之前，类似的愚蠢行为还会毒害所有群众。因为同样性质的事情在一定程度上会在社会群体中盛行；富人的浮华奢靡，穷人心怀嫉恨的恶意抱怨，都会败坏代表一个文明社会的美德，或者仅仅允许美德作为文化人穿着的花哨衣服上的一条花纹出现。

在上层社会，一切责任都是由代理去执行的，就好像责任是可以放弃的一样，有钱人因此懒惰成性，不得不去追求虚荣的享乐，这一切对下层人民来说极有诱惑力，不计其数的拜金者不惜牺牲一切来步他们的后尘。最神圣的职务被看成是挂名的差事，因为它们是靠走关系得到的，并且只是为了使一个人能够结识好朋友。女人尤其如此，她们都希望能够成为贵妇。而贵妇就是成天无所事事，只是无精打采地到处游荡，去哪她们也不在意，因为她们自己也不知道。

也许有人会这样问：除了悠闲自得地到处闲逛，女人还需要在社会中做什么呢？你总不能罚她们去喂养傻瓜和记录那些无聊的琐事吧？不。女人当然可以去学习救死扶伤的本领，成为医生或护士。她们也可以去接生，这似乎是比较合乎礼法的，但是我担心我们词典中“接生婆”这个词很快就会被男助产士代替，因而我们语言中证明过去女性遵循礼法的证据也将会被抹去。

她们也可以钻研政治，把她们的仁慈建立在最广泛的基础上。因为如果仅仅把历史当作是一本传记来看，而不去关注时代特征、政治发展和政治手腕，那么阅读历史就和看传奇小说一样毫无裨益。简单说来，如果不把历史当作人类的历史来读，那就毫无益处。历史也不是个别人物的传记，他们被放在名誉殿堂的神龛里，被漆黑一片奔腾向前的时间洪流吞噬，这股洪流将面前的一切都卷入无形的空洞，这个空洞就是“永恒”。既然是“形”，那我们不妨称之为“无形之形”吧。

如果女人能够接受更加系统的教育，她们也可以从事各行各业的工作，也许这样就可以将很多女人从私下或合法的卖淫中解救出来。男人在政府中有了一官半职而无视其应尽的责任时，女人也不会因为无法自足而和他们结婚。她们更不会为了维持基本生计这种最值得称赞的目的，而堕落到像那些靠卖淫为生的被抛弃的可怜虫一样的地位。因为那些女帽商和女裁缝们，不就认为是比娼妓略高一点的等级吗？现在接受女人的少数行业并非是高尚的工作，而只是一些卑贱的行业；有的女人接受了高级点的教育，有能力担任教育孩子的女教师，但是她们没有受到作为孩子老师应有的待遇，虽然即使是牧师老师也不会永远受到应得的礼遇，成为孩子眼中可敬的人，因此也就无从谈起什么个人生活的舒适了。但问题是那些像上层女性一样受过教育的女人，从来没有计划过要去担任那些让她们感到羞辱的职位，即使是因生活所迫她们不得不去做。她们认为这些职位是对自己身份的侮辱。她们对人类感情知之甚少，因而有必要告诉她们，再没有什么事情能比生活中的沦落这样能加重她们痛苦的感受了。

这种女人中有一些人可能会因为一种恰到好处的谨慎态度而克制自己不去结婚，而另外一些人可能就没有能力以这种可悲的方法逃脱奴役。如果政府无力鼓励诚实、独立的女性从事体面的工作而养活她们，那么这个政府难道不是一个失职的政府，对它半数公民的幸福置之不理吗？但是为了让女人的个人品德服务于社会公益，无论她们是单身还是已婚，都必须能使她们在国家中过着文明的生活；否则我们将不断看到一些可敬的女人，因为受到不应该有的鄙视，神经变得异常脆弱和痛苦，像“耕犁下夭折的百合花”一样枯萎。

这是一个可悲的事实，这也就是文明带来的“福祉”！最值得尊敬的女人受到的压迫最深重，她们因为一直被当作下贱的人对待，而最终真的堕落成为下贱的人，除非她们拥有理智，拥有远高于一般人（两性都包括在内）的理智。有多少女人就这样悲惨地耗尽了光阴，本来她们可以成为医生，也可以经营农场、管理商店，靠她们自己的勤劳谋生，而无须因多愁善感尝尽苦涩的泪水，抬不起头来，这种多愁善感最初增加了她们的风采，现在却消耗了她们的美貌。不仅如此，我还怀疑怜惜和爱情是不是像诗人宣扬的那样有密切的联系，因为我很少看到女人的无依无靠能激起很多人的同情，除非她们仍然秀色可餐；所以也许怜悯只是爱情的软弱侍女，否则它就是情欲的先兆。

依靠履行责任来自谋生计的女人，跟多才多艺的女人相比，多么令人尊敬啊！这才是我所说的“美”啊！我深深地体会到美德之魅力，和恰到好处的和谐，一个自律的人的情欲因为这种和谐得到规范，因此将这些美德和女人世俗的美进行对比时，我感到很惭愧；但是又有多少女人愿意从令人晕眩的享乐漩涡中退出，或是从善良女子陷入其中就会变得愚蠢和懒散的宁静中脱身呢？一想到愿意以此求得尊严的女人实在寥寥无几，我就不禁失望叹息。

然而，她们以自己的弱点为荣，她们必须永远受别人庇护，远离操劳和一切让心灵更加高贵的辛苦劳动。如果这是生命的安排，如果她们心甘情愿变得微不足道、受人鄙夷，轻松美妙地“虚度生命”的话，那她们也不要指望在自己容颜已老的时候，得到别人的重视，因为最鲜艳的花朵注定要受到赞美，然后被采摘它们的双手漫不经心地撕成碎片。我抱着最单纯的善意，曾经多么希望通过各种方式让我的女同胞牢记这个真理；但是我担心她们不会倾听那些用昂贵代价换来的经验教训已经说服了很多内心焦躁急切的人的道理，她们也不会为了得到人类的权利而放弃地位和性别的特权，而那些不履行人生责任的人是没有资格获得这些权利的。

有些作家认为无论人身处何职，或者用什么样虚假的感情来保护自己，都应该对人类抱有同情心，我认为这样的作家值得称赞。我也因此愿意说服有理智的人，让他们意识到我的某些说法的重要性，并劝说他们冷静地衡量我的这些观点的整体要旨。我作为他们的同胞，以一个女性的名义，呼吁他们理性地思考，要求他们心中有一点同情心。我恳求他们伸出援手，解放他们的伴侣，使女性成为真正的配偶！

男人只需要慷慨地折断我们的枷锁，愿意让我们享有合理的伙伴关系，而不是奴隶般的屈从，他们就会发现女人是更敏锐的女儿，更热情的姐妹，更忠贞的妻子，更理智的母亲—总之，更好的公民。这时我们一定会真心实意地爱他们，因为我们要学会尊重我们自己；而一个值得尊重的男人的平静内心也就不会被他无聊虚荣的妻子所打扰，也不会把一个从未享受过母爱的婴儿送到一个陌生人的怀抱。

论国民教育

……

很明显，我对国民教育的评价都是一些提示而已；但是我主要希望实现：有必要让两性在一起接受教育，使双方趋于完美；有必要让孩子住在家里，这样他们才能学会热爱家庭；不过为了支持而不是扼杀公共感情，他们应当被送到学校，和同龄人待在一起，因为只有和同龄人公平竞争，我们才能形成对自己的公正评价。

为了让人类更有道德，当然也是让人类更幸福，男女两性都必须依据同样的准则来行动；但是如果这种合理性只适用于一个性别，那又如何能期待实现这一点呢？同样，要想让社会契约真正达到公平状态，使这些本身就可以改善人类命运的富有启示的原则得到推广，我们就必须允许女人将她们的品德建立在知识的基础上，这几乎是不可能的，除非女人和男人拥有同样的抱负，接受同样的教育。现在女人因为愚昧和低级的欲望而沦于卑微的地位，她们不配和男人相提并论；不然她们就像魔鬼一样，狡猾地蠕动着爬上智慧之树，得到的只是足以将男人引入歧途的东西。

各国的历史告诉我们，不能将女人局限在家庭琐事上面，因为除非她们的心胸比较开阔，否则她们是不会履行家庭责任的。她们处在无知状态时，同样会成为享乐的奴隶，正如她们是男人的奴隶一样。但是也不能把她们关在伟大事业的大门外，尽管她们无法理解这些事业，狭隘的心胸也经常使之遭受损失。

上层社会男人的玩乐思想，甚至他们的美德，总是会赋予某种女人支配他们的大权。这些软弱的女人，在幼稚的激情和自私的虚荣影响下，对很多事物抱有一种错误的认识。而那些本应该启发她们见识的男人，却反而用她们的眼光来看待这些事物。那些充满幻想的男人，还有那些掌握着人类事务支配大权的乐观男人，一旦扎入女人堆里就没有了自持力。我实在没有必要为那些不了解历史的读者，引用无数因受宠的女人私下通奸而导致罪恶和压迫的例子，更不需要提那些虽然出于好意却笨拙又愚蠢的干涉行为所造成的危害了。因为在处理事情时，对付一个恶棍比敷衍一个傻瓜要好得多，因为这个恶棍行事有一定的计划；但任何有道理的计划都会比一时兴起的愚蠢更容易被人看穿。那些卑鄙愚蠢的女人对拥有理智的聪明男人有支配权，这是众所周知的，我只是举一个例子而已。

谁能描绘出比卢梭更高尚的女性性格呢？虽然就总体来看，他总是竭力贬低女性。他为何如此焦虑呢？当然是为了给他对愚蠢的特雷莎的爱情辩护，软弱和美德使卢梭对她心生爱慕。卢梭不能把她提升到女性的一般水平，所以他殚精竭虑将女人压低得跟她一样。他发现她是适合自己的卑微的伴侣，男人的傲慢驱使他决心在自己选择相处一辈子的人身上发现一些高贵的品质；他称她为“神圣的天真的人”，但是她在他生前死后的行为难道没有清楚表明他如此称呼她是个多么荒唐的错误吗？不仅如此，他的心里也会痛苦地悲叹，他由于身体虚弱再也不能把她当作一个女人来对待时，她对他的爱情也就消散了。

她做出这样的行为也很正常，因为他们之间没有什么共同的感情，一旦性关系破裂了，他还能用什么留住她呢？她的感情是局限于男性，但不是仅限于一个男人的，要想挽留她的感情，需要理性把感觉转移到更广阔的人性渠道上去。很多女人并没有足够的心思去关心一个女人，或是跟一个男人交朋友。但是性别的弱点让女人必须依赖男人的才能，对男人产生了一种猫一样的感情，让妻子在丈夫身边满足地喵喵叫，其实对任何一个喂饱并抚摸她的男人，她都会做同样的事。

但是男人却经常对这种爱情很满足，并以一种野蛮的方式把它占为己有。但是如果他们能够拥有更加高尚的品德，那他们在和情妇闹够了之后，一定会希望在火炉旁和一位朋友促膝长谈。

除此之外，为了给感官享受增加多样性和趣味性，理智必不可少，因为如果在品德和理智不能赋予兽欲人文特征时，一个人仍然拥有爱情，那这个人一定处在智力标尺的下端；但是理智总会占主导地位。因此总体上来说，如果女人的智力不上升到与男人同等的水平上，有些优秀的女人就会像希腊的高级妓女一样，将有能力的男人聚集到她们周围，吸引很多公民背叛家庭。但是如果这些人的妻子更有理智，或者因为运用理智和想象力（它们是品位的合理源泉）更具魅力的话，他们也许不会这样做。一个有才能的女人，如果她不是非常丑陋的话，往往会获得很大的权利，她的地位因为同类的软弱而得到提升。男人经过理性思考，具有美德和谨慎时，他们也希望女人拥有这些品德，而女人只有通过和男人相同的方法才能获得它们。

法国和意大利的女人将自己局限在家庭生活中了吗？虽然她们至今也无权参与政治，但是难道她们没有通过不正当的方法获得巨大的控制权，使得她们曾经玩弄过的男人随自己一同堕落吗？总之，不管我从哪个方面来看这个问题，理智和经验告诉我，唯一能够带领女人完成她们独特责任的方法，就是将她们从各种束缚中解放出来，允许她们享有人类与生俱来的权利。

女人一旦获得自由，将会很快变得聪明和有德行，而男人也会更聪明更有道德，因为这种进展是相互的，否则人类一半的成员会因为自己被迫受到的不公而向压迫者展开报复，而男人的美德也会被他踩在脚下的虫蚁所蚕食殆尽。

让男人作出自己的选择吧。男人和女人是天造地设的一对，虽然二者的存在并不是为了合成一体，如果男人不让女人变得更好，女人就会让男人堕落。

我这里说的是提高和解放全体女性同胞，因为我知道少数女人出于偶然或是因为天生的兴趣爱好，获得了一些超越其他女人的知识，她们总是表现得傲慢自大；但仍有些女人，获得了知识，也没有摒弃谦逊，她们从来不会自恃有点学识而鄙视她们曾经努力在内心驱除的无知愚昧。而任何关于女性学习的忠告所引起的尖叫，特别是那些漂亮女人发出的尖叫，往往是出于嫉妒。当一个比较有教养的女人竭力转向理性交谈时，那些漂亮女人就会发现，即使是她们含情脉脉的双眸和轻浮淫荡的卖弄风情，也不会在整个夜晚一直引起男人注意。在这种情况下，大家的共同慰藉就是：这样的女人很少能找到丈夫。我见过愚蠢的女人用各种各样的挑逗手段—一个描写这种花招的意味深长的词语—来打断一段富有理性的谈话，正是这样的谈话让男人忘记了她们是美丽的女人。

我们承认，拥有非凡才能的人确实很容易产生令人讨厌的傲慢自负情绪，这也是人之常情。但是当那些被讥讽为学识渊博的女人学习了一点点知识就被认为是非凡之举时，那女人的才能已经枯竭到何种低下的程度了？何况这些女人的学识也只够令她们沾沾自喜，同时让她的同代人和有些异性心生嫉妒而已。不仅如此，不是还有很多女人因为有一点理性而遭到最严厉的指责吗？我注意到了一些大家都知道的事实，我经常听到有些女人被人嘲弄，各种微笑的缺点都暴露了，仅仅因为她们在照顾婴儿的时候，采取了一些医生的建议，没有采用常规的方法。我甚至还听到有人对改革的残酷厌恶进一步加剧，把一个通情达理的女人污蔑为不称职的母亲，原因是她很聪明，一直关心着孩子们的健康，但是在她的照顾下，一个孩子因为婴儿期不可避免的事故而夭折了。她的熟人指责她，认为这是新奇想法—关于舒适和清洁的新奇想法带来的后果。那些自命经验丰富的人，一直固守某种偏见，根据最明智的医生的观点，这种偏见曾让人类大量死亡，但是他们却对这个不幸事件幸灾乐祸，因为它证实了他们的偏见。

确实，如果仅仅从这个角度来考虑的话，对于女人的国民教育也是至关重要的，因为人类已经为莫洛克[20]偏见作出了多大的牺牲啊！而男人的放荡不羁又如何以各种方式毁灭着孩子？很多女人因为男人的爱慕和他人的无知而放弃自己应尽的责任，她们缺乏天然的情感，这种缺乏让人的童年比野兽的幼年还要危险。但是男人至今还不愿意将女人放在合适的位置，使她们获得足够的理智，至少明白应当如何养育婴儿。

这个事实让我最受震撼，因此我下面大部分的讨论都将与此相关，因为任何剥夺女人母性特征的倾向都会让女人丧失其女性特征。

但是现在我们自然无法指望这些软弱的母亲能够合理照顾孩子的身体，如果孩子没有受到父亲罪恶的影响，那么这种照顾是给良好体质打下基础所必不可少的；同样也无法期待这些母亲能明智地引导孩子的性情，这样他长大之后就不必努力挣脱他的母亲—他的第一任导师直接或间接教给他的东西。除非孩子的心灵具有超乎寻常的活力，否则他的一生都将带有女人的愚蠢。母亲的弱点会遗传给她的孩子。如果女人受教育要依赖她们丈夫的判断力作决定，结果必然如此，因为提高理性不能半途而废，任何人都不可能总是靠模仿作出明智的举动，在每一种生活环境下都有特殊情况，这时候需要运用判断力来调整普遍规律。一个能在某一方面恰当思考的人很快就会拓展他的知识领域；而拥有足够判断力来管教孩子的女人也不会一味地屈从于丈夫，更不会安心屈从于将女人看得一文不名的社会律法。

在公立学校里，为了防止无知造成的错误，应当教给女人解剖学和药理学，不仅让她们能合理照顾自己的身体，同时还能让她们成为孩子、父母和丈夫的理性的护士；因为那些固执成性的老女人，对人体构造毫不知晓，就按照自己的所谓秘方给病人治疗，正是因为她们的错误，使人类死亡数字不断攀升。如果仅仅从家庭角度来看，让女人熟知心理分析，也是很合适的。采取的方法是让男人和女人共同学习每一门课程，引导她们观察人文科学发展过程中人类理智的进步，同时绝不能忽略道德学和人类政治史的学习。

男人被称作小宇宙，每一个家庭都可以被称作一个国家。确实，很多国家都是靠侮辱人类品格的手段统治的，而那些深谙人事的贤德人士的观点也因为缺乏公正的宪法和平等的法律而纠缠不清，使这些人更加质疑竭力争取人权的合理性。这样，道德在国家的水库中受到了污染，它释放出罪恶的支流去腐蚀政体的各个组成部分；法律应当是统治社会的力量，而不是那些执行法律的人，如果用更高尚或者准确来说更加公平的原则来规范法律，那么责任也许会成为每个人的行为准则。

另外，通过锻炼身体和心灵，女人会获得母性性格所必需的精神活力，这种活力和坚毅融为一体，而坚毅则是将坚决的行为和固执反常的弱点区分开来的品质。建议懒惰的人行事坚决是很危险的，因为他们很快就会变得很严厉，为了给自己减少麻烦，会严厉惩罚犯错的人。而如果他们有耐心、有毅力地运用理智，也许这些错误就可以避免了。

但是坚毅的前提是心智的力量，而心智的力量可以通过懒惰的顺从获得吗？通过寻求建议，而不是运用理智就获得吗？通过战战兢兢地服从而不是锻炼我们所有人都亟需的忍耐力获得吗？我想得出的结论是很显而易见的。让女人成为理智的人和自由的公民，她们很快就会成为优秀的妻子和母亲—当然是在男人不忽略他们自己作为丈夫和父亲的责任的前提下。

正如我刚才简单提及的，在讨论结合公共教育和私立教育可能带来的好处时，我主要谈论那些和女性世界密切相关的观点，因为我觉得女人是受压迫的群体。但是因压迫产生的罪恶而滋生的坏疽不会仅局限于患病的部位，而是会蔓延到整个社会。所以每当我希望女人变成更有道德的人时，我的心就会因为期待伟大的事业在各地得到弘扬而激动不已，而只有美德才能把这种伟大的事业传播开来。

女人的无知导致的数例蠢行；结束语：论女性习俗的变革必然期望带来的道德进步

很多蠢行—无论是违反常理的越权还是渎职—在某种程度上都是女性所独有的，但这些蠢行都是因为无知或偏见导致的。我只指出那些看起来特别有损于她们道德品质的事情。在批评她们时，我特别希望能证明男人出于各种动机，竭力使女人在智力和身体上永远软弱下去，从而阻碍了女人履行她们特有的责任。当女人脆弱的身体使她们无法哺育自己的孩子，脆弱的心灵使她们宠坏了孩子的性情时，能说女人的这种状态是自然状态吗？

……

第二节

狭隘的教育常常会导致女人软弱性格的另外一种情形，即心灵的浪漫扭曲，用多愁善感来形容最为贴切。

无知女人容易受她们感情的支配，她们接受的教育只是让她们从爱情中寻求幸福，提高感官享受，并且采取形而上学的爱情观念，这种观念让她们不知羞耻地忽略人生的责任，并且在这种高尚的优雅中不断堕入真正的罪恶中。

这些女人迷恋于愚蠢小说家们编造的白日梦，这些小说家们对人性知之甚少，却总是粗制滥造一些老掉牙的故事，描写一些淫荡的场面，其中充满了各种多愁善感的字眼，这些字眼同样也导致人们趣味低下，并且忽略日常的责任。我不谈理智，因为它从未被人利用，它沉睡的力量未被激发，就像潜伏着的火的微粒，被认为存在于所有物质之中。

事实上，女人没有任何政治权利，而结了婚以后，除了刑事案件外，她们不享有作为公民存在的权利，因此她们的注意力自然而然就从整个社会的利益转移到了琐碎的小事上，虽然任何社会成员如果不将个人责任和公共利益联系起来，就一定无法完美地履行他的个人责任。女人生活中的大事就是取悦于人，她们由于政治和法律上的压迫无法参与重要的事务，于是多愁善感成了大事。如果她们能够更广泛地运用理智，就不会在情感中越陷越深。

但是受困于无足轻重的琐事，她们自然而然地被那种为无知轻浮的人量身定制的庸俗读物中的观点所左右，她们无法把握任何重要的东西，所以如果她们发现读史非常枯燥，并认为富于理智的演讲和论文非常无聊而且几乎无法理解，这又有什么值得惊奇的呢？她们必须依靠那些小说来消遣。不过我反对读小说，是把小说和那些锻炼理智、控制幻想的作品作对比来说的。我认为不论读什么都比什么都不读要好，因为稍微思考一下，心灵就一定会得到充实并获得一点力量。另外，即使是纯粹幻想的作品，也会让读者的情趣得到提升，超越粗俗的性欲满足，心灵对这种满足完全没有兴趣。

这个观点来源于经验，因为我认识几个优秀的女性，特别是其中一个，她是非常优秀的女人—达到了她狭隘的心胸所允许的最优秀的状态，她关心她的女儿（她有3个女儿），不准她们看小说。她是一个富有的上层人物，所以她请了好几个老师来教孩子，还有一个家仆似的女教师来注意她们的一举一动。她们从老师那里学会了如何用法语和意大利语表达桌子、椅子等，但是因为摆在她们面前的几本书远远超过了她们的接受能力，或者说信仰的接受能力，所以她们既没有获得思想，也没有获得情感。在她们不需要背诵单词的时候，她们就把时间消磨在穿着打扮、相互争吵或者是偷听女仆的谈话上，直到她们到了出嫁的年龄，找到伴侣为止。

与此同时，她们的母亲—这位寡妇，也忙于和有头有脸的人保持联系，正如她所说的，要多认识一点人，以免她的几个女儿因缺少合适的人介绍而无法进入上层社会。这些年轻的淑女们，成了不折不扣的粗俗人，带着乖戾的脾性走入了社会，她们脑子里满是自命不凡的想法，鄙夷地看着那些穿着和排场比不上她们的人。

至于爱情，造物主或者说她们的育婴者已经费心教给她们这个词的自然含义；由于她们没有什么可谈论的话题，也缺乏优雅的感情，当她们自由谈论婚姻时，只能用一些很不优雅的词句来表达她们粗俗的愿望。

这些女孩也是受了小说的毒害吗？我差点忘了她们中间某个人性格上有阴影，她装出一种近乎愚蠢的单纯样，面带傻笑毫不害羞地说出极其粗俗无礼的评价和问题，她在与世隔绝的时候就已经完全明白了这些词的意义，只是不敢在施加高压的母亲面前谈起。正如她炫耀的那样，她们接受的是模范教育，每天早餐前诵读她们日常诵读的章节，从来不会去读那些愚蠢的小说。

这只是一个例子而已，但是我还记得有很多其他的女人，没有适当接受循序渐进的教育，也不允许作出自由的选择，她们简直是畸形发展的孩子；或者有的女人在同社会接触中获得了一些所谓的常识，其实也就获得了她们独立生活时清楚看待平常事物的方法。但是那些称得上智力的本事，即获取普遍或抽象概念的能力，或者甚至是获得中间概念的能力，都谈不上。她们的思维处在沉睡状态，她们在没有受到那些感官事物或者事件刺激时就会情绪低落，或是痛哭或是睡觉。

因此，我劝告女性同胞们不要读那些肤浅的作品时，是想建议她们多读些更好的作品。我的这个想法恰好和一位智慧的男人吻合，他的女儿和侄女，在他的照顾下采取了完全不同的教育方式。

他的侄女智力超群，在托给他照顾之前曾沉溺于读各种读物。他努力并且成功地引导她阅读历史和道德文集；但是他的女儿，被溺爱子女的软弱母亲惯坏了，对每件需要努力用功去做的事情都很反感，于是他就让她读小说。他曾经这样解释自己的做法，只要她因读小说感受到了一点乐趣，他就能在这个基础上对她进行教育，错误的观点总比什么想法也没有要好得多。

确实，女性的思维一直被人们完全忽视，这就使她们只能从这些污秽的源泉中获得知识，直到有些才能出众的女人从读小说中学会了鄙视这样的书籍为止。

我想，纠正女性对小说的偏爱的最好办法就是嘲弄它们：但不是没有取舍地嘲弄，因为这样效果不大；但是如果一个明智的人带着幽默感给年轻女孩子读上几篇，并同时用语调将之与历史中的动人故事和英雄气概作恰当对比，指出小说是如何愚蠢而可笑地丑化了人类的天性，也许合理的意见就能代替浪漫情怀了。

但是大部分男人和女人在一个方面是相似的，而且同样地缺乏品位和庄重。无知的女人为了声誉不得不保持贞洁，因此任由想象力沉醉在当代小说家描绘的不合理的淫荡画面中，认为历史上严肃庄重的事迹和妇女的优美形象平淡无奇，对之不屑一顾。而男人干脆将腐朽的品位带入生活，抛弃质朴迷人的美德和庄重体面的理性，追求色情之乐。

此外，阅读小说还让女人，特别是上层社会的淑女，喜欢在谈话中用强烈的措辞和极端的表达；虽然她们放荡虚伪的生活让她们无法培养出任何强烈的真实情感，但是她们如簧的巧舌却总能用矫揉造作的声调蹦出热情的语言，而且芝麻粒大的事情都能带来突然的磷光，而这些磷光只不过是对黑暗中热情之火的模仿罢了。

第三节

造物主在弱者脑子里刻下的作为自卫原则的无知和错误的狡猾，让女人非常热衷于梳妆打扮，而这种热爱自然会导致各种虚荣，甚而超出了争强好胜和宽宏大量的限度。

卢梭认为取悦于人的有形手段在于装饰美化，我同意他的看法。也正因如此，我要提防女孩子染上软弱女人所常有的对于穿着的钟爱，让她们不要停留在有形部分。不过，女人们幻想她们可以长期受人宠爱，而不诉诸理智，或者换句话说，不诉诸取悦于人的道德艺术，她们是多么软弱啊！但是当这种道德艺术（如果使用艺术这个词不至于亵渎上帝的话）所指的优美并不是行为的动机，而是美德的结果时，这种道德艺术永远不可能和无知并存。两性中故作矜持的放荡之徒喜好的无知调戏和高级优雅在本质上有很大不同。

对于外表装饰的强烈爱好，在蛮荒时代就曾经出现过，不过当时打扮自己的是男人而不是女人。现在允许女人在这一方面和男人处在同一水平，社会文明至少已经前行了一步。

因此我认为，穿着打扮对于人类来说很自然，虽然人们一直认为这是女性的嗜好。但是我应该把我的观点说得更明确点。思维还未完全发展，不能从思考中获取快乐时，就会十分注意打扮自己的身体；而志趣也只会表现在文身或涂脂抹粉上面。

这种最初的爱好至今依然存在，甚至奴隶制度地狱般的枷锁都不能扼杀这些黑人英雄从他们父母那里继承下来的对于美貌的野蛮渴望，因为一个奴隶辛辛苦苦攒下的积蓄一般都花在便宜花哨的衣服上了。我还真没有见过哪个善良的男仆或女仆不爱修饰。他们的衣服就是他们的财产。而我用类比同理推证，女性过分爱好打扮也是出于同样的原因—心灵培养的匮乏。男人相遇会谈论事业、政治或者文学，但是正如斯威夫特[21]所言：“女人们多么自然地就会伸手去抚摸彼此衣服的裙摆和褶纹啊。”这也很自然，因为她们没有感兴趣的事业，没有文学的品位，而且她们认为政治枯燥无趣，没有把精力转到提升整个人类、增进共同幸福的伟大事业上来，因此缺乏对人类的博爱。

另外，男人偶然或主动选择走上不同的追求权势和名誉的道路，虽然因为同行是冤家，他们相互争斗，但是他们还是不会和大多数男人发生冲突。可是女人之间的关系却与此大相径庭，因为女人总是相互竞争。

她们出嫁以前的任务就是取悦男人，结婚之后仍然本能地以锲而不舍的顽强精神做着同样的事情。即使是有道德的女人在社交中也从来不会忘记自己是女人，因为她们总是努力让自己讨人喜欢。女人的美貌和男人的才智似乎都同样渴望将人群的目光吸引到自己身上；而憎恨同代人的才智也是众所周知的。

女人把所有的志向局限于美貌上面，对美貌的兴趣又加重了她们的虚荣心，结果导致女人间无休止的争风吃醋，这又有什么大惊小怪的呢？她们都在进行同一场竞争，如果她们不以怀疑甚至嫉妒的眼光对待彼此，也许她们就会拥有常人无法企及的德行。

对于打扮、享乐和权利的过度追捧，是野蛮人的欲望。这种欲望占据了他们尚未开化的心灵，他们没有开发智力，更没有学会如何思考，如何运用能力将一连串抽象的思维联系起来，进而总结出原则。而女人，从她们的教育和文化生活的现状来看，也处在同样的境地。我想，这是个无可争辩的事实。当一个人从来没有权利按照自己的理智自由行动时，嘲笑甚至是讥讽她们的愚蠢是既荒谬又残忍的；因为受教导要盲目服从权威的人，都会努力巧妙地躲避权威，这是合情合理的，也是必然的。

如果能证明女人应当完全服从男人，我就会立即承认，女人的责任就是培养对服饰的喜好，以取悦别人；并为了保全自己，养成狡猾的毛病。

但是建立在无知基础上的品德肯定会一直摇摇欲坠，正如沙滩上的房子无法经受暴风雨的捶打。做这个推断几乎都是毫无必要的。如果要用权威强迫女人变得有道德（这本身就是一个矛盾的说法），那就把她们禁闭在闺房，并用猜忌的眼光看待她们。不要担心她们的心灵会受到伤害，因为能够忍受如此待遇的心灵是用柔软材料做成的，这些材料拥有足够的活力使她们的身体拥有生命。

柔软的材料无法铭记永恒的记号，

最便于辨认的只是黑色、棕色或白色。

最痛苦的创伤当然很快就会愈合，女人仍旧可以生儿育女，让人类的世界得以生存。她仍会精心打扮去取悦男人—这就是某些著名的作者所认为的：女人注定要实现的目标。

第四节

人们认为女人应当比男人更重感情、更仁慈，这可以从她们强烈的依恋和瞬间的同情心看出来。但是这种出于无知的依赖性爱情却没有任何高贵成分，而且很可能转变为自私的或是孩童或是野兽般原始的感情。我认识很多软弱的女人，她们把感情完全灌输到丈夫身上；而她们的仁慈实在微不足道，倒不如说是转瞬即逝的同情心而己。一个优秀的演说家说过，仁慈不仅需要“一个敏感的耳朵，还需要投入智慧和感情”。

但是这种独占的爱情虽然使人堕落，却不能拿来当作女性低劣地位的证明，因为这是狭隘观点的必然结果。即使是拥有远见卓识的女人，如果她们把注意力集中在烦琐的小事和个人的计划上，也很少会作出什么英雄事迹，当然她受到爱情激励的时候除外！然而爱情是一种崇高的感情，就如天才一样，百年罕见。因此我同意一个道德学家的观点，他断言“女人很少能像男人那样慷慨大方”；而她们经常为了狭隘的感情而牺牲公正和仁慈，这种感情明显地让她们显得更为低劣，特别是因为这些感情通常都是由男人激起的。不过我仍然相信如果女人不是从出生起就饱受压迫的话，随着理智的发展，她们的心胸也会宽广起来。

我知道轻微的敏感加上极度的软弱就会对异性产生强烈的依恋，而理智可以促进友谊；因此我承认男人比女人拥有更多的友谊，而且男人的正义感更强。女人独占的爱情看起来确实很像加图[22]对他国家的那种极其没有正义感的感情。他主张消灭迦太基，不是为了挽救罗马，而是为了增强他的虚荣心。一般来说，仁慈也是为了同样的原则—虚荣而牺牲的，因为真正的责任是相互支撑的。

此外，当女人沦为不公正的奴隶时，她们怎么可能会公正或慷慨呢？

第五节

人们充满正义感地坚持认为，养育子女，为下一代的身心健康打下良好的基础，是女人独特的责任，因此让她们变得无能的愚蠢一定是有悖常理的。我坚信，她们的头脑可以，而且应当容纳更多的知识，否则她们将永远无法成为理智的母亲。很多人注重马匹的繁殖，却忽略马厩的管理，这些人如此缺乏理智和感情，真是难以想象！他们认为对育婴室稍加留意就会降低自己的身份；可是有多少孩子完全是因为母亲的无知而夭折！但是如果他们能够有幸逃脱死亡的厄运，也没有因不人道的忽视或盲目的溺爱而毁灭，那么又有多少孩子的心灵能得到合理的培育呢？人们认为孩子在家就会变得乖戾暴躁，为了打消他的锐气，家长把他送到学校；而为了在一大群孩子中建立秩序，学校必须采取各种各样的措施，这些措施几乎将所有的罪恶种子都播撒到了这片强行开垦的土地上。

如果孩子受到合理的管教，那么他们永远不应该也不会感到受约束。我经常将这些可怜孩子的挣扎，和活泼的小马驹绝望的蹦跶作对比，我曾看到一匹小马在海滩上接受驯服，每当它试图甩掉骑马人的时候，它的双蹄只会在沙中越陷越深，直到它最后无可奈何地屈服。

我发现当我用仁慈和一贯的态度对待马—我喜爱的动物—的时候，它们常常都很驯服，因此我怀疑那些粗暴的驯马手段能不能真正伤到它们。但是我坚信绝不能在不理智地情况下允许一个孩子放肆之后还强制他听话；因为在对待孩子时，任何违反公正和理智的行为都会削弱他们的智力。经验让我作出推断，他们的性格塑成期非常早，甚至在7岁以前就形成了道德品行的基础，这期间孩子的母亲被认为是唯一的管教者。以后最常见的情况就是教育的一半的责任就是纠正孩子们的错误，而如果过于急于求成，效果常常很不完满；其实如果他们的母亲更理智一些，他们就绝对不会犯这样的错误。

另一个表现妇女愚蠢的突出事例绝不能忽略。她们在孩子面前对待仆人的态度，让孩子们认为仆人应该伺候他们，应该忍受他们的臭脾气。孩子应当总是将接受男人或女人的帮助当作一种恩惠；作为独立的第一节课，应该以他们的母亲为榜样用事实教育他们，不要让别人服侍自己，因为在自己身体健康时让别人服侍自己是对人性的侮辱；不要引导他们表现出一副自命不凡的样子，而应该让他们首先感觉到自己的弱点从而意识到人类生来平等。可是使我愤怒的是我常常听到家长趾高气昂地使唤仆人，叫他们过来伺候小孩子睡觉，又一次次地将他们打发走，因为少爷或小姐还想赖在妈妈身边多待一会。这样奴隶般地伺候这个小祖宗，就会让孩子身上所有令人讨厌的脾气都发作了，就这样宠坏了这个孩子。

总之，大多数的母亲都会把自己的孩子完全交给仆人照顾；或是因为是自己的孩子，就把他们当神仙供着。但是据我一贯的观察，那些把自己的孩子奉为神仙的女人，很少对仆人表现出一般的仁慈，或是对其他人的孩子表现出哪怕是一丁点的疼爱。

这些无知独占的感情和个人看待事物的方式，使女人在发展方面总是停滞不前，还让很多女人为了孩子呕心沥血，结果却削弱了他们的体质，宠坏了他们的脾气，同时还让一个比较理性的父亲可能采用的任何教育方式无效，因为如果没有母亲的合作，一个管教孩子的父亲总是会被当成暴君。

一个体格健全的女人在履行母亲的责任时，仍然可以一丝不苟地保持个人容貌的整洁，必要时帮助管理家庭，或用读书和毫无区别地同男人和女人交谈的方法来提升自己的理智。因为造物主非常英明地将一切事情安排得井井有条，如果女人哺乳她们的孩子，她们就会保持自身的健康，并且在每个孩子出生的前后都会有一段间隔，因此我们很少会见到满屋子都是孩子的状况。如果她们遵循行为规划，不将光阴虚度在追求时髦服装的奇怪念头上面，那么照料家务和孩子不会让她们和文学作品完全隔离，也不会妨碍她们以一种有助于加强心智的坚定态度爱好一门科学，或者学习一种能够培养情操的优雅艺术。

但是，为了炫耀华丽服饰的走亲访友、打牌和舞会，更不要提清晨无聊地奔忙于琐事，使女人忽略了她们的责任，并因此变得微不足道，还因此变得讨人喜欢，按照这个词目前的意义来说，是讨所有男人的喜欢，除了自己的丈夫。因为提到一场没有运用什么感情的享乐，我们不能说它促进了理智的发展，虽然人们错误地称这种享乐为见过世面。这种毫无意义的交际，让人的内心变得冷漠以及想要逃避责任，甚至当这种交际不再能带给人快乐的时候，它由于习惯仍旧必不可少。

除非更多的公平得以在社会上建立，等级得以废除，女人得以解放，否则我们是不会看到女人拥有深厚感情的，我们也不会看到高尚的家庭幸福，无知和堕落的人无法体味到这种幸福质朴的庄严。同样，只有在人们更看重女人的思想而不是容貌之时，教育的艰巨任务才能真正有序地开始。因为指望愚蠢无知的女人成为优秀的母亲，就如同盼望莠草上结出谷粒，或是荆棘上长出无花果，是一样的。

第六节

现在我的讨论进入到结束语阶段了，我没有必要告诉聪明的读者，关于这个话题的探讨仅仅局限于提出一些简单的原则，并扫除那些让这些简单的原则变得晦涩难懂的废话。但是，因为并不是所有的读者都是洞悉一切的人，所以必须允许我稍加解释，以便让那些有理性的人完全明白这个问题—我说的是那些怠惰的有理性的人，这些人轻信别人的意见，并且为了免去自己思索的麻烦而顽固地坚信不疑。

道德学家曾达成一致意见，认为品德若没有自由来培育，就永远得不到应有的力量。这是他们针对男人的评论，我把它拓展到整个人类。我坚持认为，在一切情形下，道德都应当固定在不变的基础上；而一个服从除了理性以外的其他任何权威的人，就不能称之为有理性或是有道德的人。

为了让女人成为社会上真正有用的人，我主张应当大范围培养她们的理智，引导她们获得一种建立在知识基础上的合理的爱国之情，因为很明显，我们很少会对自己不了解的东西感兴趣。为了让这种一般性的知识得到应有的重视，我已经努力说明：除非理智让心胸开阔，否则个人的责任永远不可能合理履行，而公德不过是私德的总和而已。但是社会上既定的各种区别，把品德的坚固黄金捶打得仅仅成为掩盖罪恶的金箔，而让公德和私德受到了伤害；因为财富比美德更能为人赢得尊重时，人们就会追求财富而不是道德；女人的外表受到抚爱，幼稚的傻笑表现了她内心的空虚时，女人的心灵就会荒芜。然而真正的感官之乐是来源于心灵的—有什么感情能和起源于相互爱慕、并由相互尊重而维持的感情相媲美呢？那些冷酷或狂热的肉欲爱抚，相对于纯洁感情和崇高想象的适度表露相比，不是孕育着死亡的罪恶又是什么呢？是的，当充满幻想的放荡之徒鄙视女人的理智时，让我告诉他正是他漠视的心灵赋予一切热烈的感情以生命，只有这种感情才能带来快乐，虽然这种快乐转瞬即逝。我还要告诉他，没有道德的性爱关系，正如烛台上的蜡烛一样，必然会熄灭，产生让人难以忍受的厌恶。为了证明这一点，我只需指出，那些把人生大部分时间浪费在和女人厮混、带着强烈的饥渴与她们寻欢作乐的男人，对女人怀着最粗鄙的看法。道德，你是快乐真正的提炼者！如果愚蠢的人要把你从地球上吓走，以便毫无节制地放任他们的肉欲，那些懂得情趣的好色之徒为了给激情增添一点趣味，一定会爬上天堂把你请回来！

现在的女人因为无知而变得愚蠢恶毒，我想这是无须争辩的事实。似乎从我的论述之中可以得到以下结论：人们也许可以期待，一场妇女作风的“变革”，会带来有助于提高整个人类的最有益的效果，至少是有这种可能性。因为婚姻被称作使人类区别于禽兽的可爱的慈悲之源，而财富、懒惰和愚蠢在两性之间造成的腐败交往对道德造成了普遍的危害，这比人类所有其他的罪恶共同对道德造成的危害还大。最圣洁的责任因淫乱的情欲而牺牲，男人在婚前同女人过多的亲密接触，学会了将爱情当作一种自私的满足—不仅将爱情和尊重分开，而且把爱情和仅仅以掺杂了一点点人性的习惯为基础的感情分开。正义和友情也公然受到挑战，纯洁的感情受到破坏，这种感情自然而然地引导人们享受毫不做作的感情表露，而不是矫揉造作的姿态。但是那些敢于毫不掩饰地表露出的高贵质朴的感情，对好色之徒没有任何吸引力，尽管这种感情是一种魅力，通过加强婚姻的纽带，让温暖爱情的结晶得到来自父母的关注；在父母拥有友情之前，孩子是永远不可能得到恰当教育的。品德会飞离一个内部分崩离析的家庭，任由一群魔鬼驻留。

丈夫和妻子之间没有什么共同情感，家庭里面无法建立相互信任时，男人和女人之间就不可能拥有纯粹的感情，他们的追求不同必然也会出现这种情况。那种孕育柔情的亲密关系不会，也不可能存在于邪恶人之间。

所以我坚决认为，那种男人们强烈坚持的男女之间的差别是很武断的。我一直在思考一个观点，几个我曾与之谈论过这个话题的理智男人承认，这个观点是有理有据的。简单说来就是这样，在男性中很少存在的贞洁和他们对廉耻之心的抛弃，很可能造成两性的共同堕落。不仅如此，作为女性特征的端庄，经常不过是掩盖放荡之心的虚伪面纱，而不是纯洁的自然反应，除非廉耻之心普遍得到尊重。

我坚信，大部分女人的愚蠢行为产生于男人的专制，而狡猾（我承认狡猾目前是女性性格的一部分）是由压迫造成的，我也曾多次努力证明这个论点。

举个例子，异教徒不也千真万确地被刻画成是一伙奸诈的人吗？我是否可以强调这个事实以证明：当理智以外的任何力量遏制了人类的精神自由时，人们就会弄虚作假，自然也就会出现各种形形色色的伎俩？巴特勒[23]对异教徒的讽刺将这样一幅景象摆在我们面前：对礼法的苛求已经到了让人拘谨的程度，而所有关于琐事的幼稚忙碌和自命不凡的庄严嘴脸，把他们的外貌和内心都塑造成一副呆板的卑鄙小人形象。我是针对整体而言的，因为我知道在各个宗教派系里，有不少教徒拥有能为人性增光的优秀品质。但是我敢断言，如同女人对家庭持有偏见一样，在异教徒社区，一定会流行一种对于自己教派的狭隘偏见，虽然他们在其他方面值得敬佩；而且我认为他们和女人一样胆怯谨慎，鲁莽顽固，这些特质经常为异教徒和女人的努力蒙羞。压迫让他们在性格上形成了很多特点，和人类中受压迫的半数人的特点完全吻合。因为异教徒就和女人一样，喜欢聚在一起思考，相互征求意见，直到通过一些错综复杂的小伎俩，来达到一些琐碎的目的，这难道不是人人皆知的吗？在异教徒和女人的世界里，他们同样注意保护自己的声誉，并且是出于同样的原因。

我主张女人应该和男人一样争取权利，但是我并未试图掩盖她们的过失，我只是证明这些过失是她们接受的教育和社会地位产生的自然结果。因此我们有理由相信，当她们在身体、道德和公民地位上获得自由时，就会改变自己的性情，并且避免自己的罪恶和愚蠢。

让女人享受权利，她就可在品德上效仿男人；她得以解放的时候，就一定会变得更加完美，否则就证实了将软弱的女人束缚在她职责上的权威是正确的。如果是后者的话，同俄国一起开辟一个贩卖鞭子的新行业倒是权宜之计：这将是一位父亲在女婿成婚之日送给他的礼物，而丈夫也需要通过这种方法维持家庭的秩序。他只要挥舞这根权杖，就能拥有统治权，不会违反任何公正，他是家庭唯一的主人，因为家中只有他拥有理智—这是宇宙的主人赋予人神圣不容废除的尘世间的统治权。如果女人承认了自己的这种地位，就不享有任何天生的权利；而根据同样的规则，也无须承担任何义务，因为权利和义务是不可分割的。

哦，你们这些有理智的男人，何不变得公正起来？不要关注女人犯的错比关注你们所饲养的马或驴的恶习还要严厉—既然你们剥夺了女人理性的权利，那就允许她们有无知的特权吧；否则如果你们期待从造物主没有给予理智的人身上寻找美德，那你们真是连埃及的监工都比不上。

[1]英国作家托马斯·戴所作的一本关于儿童教育的小说，桑德夫和莫顿是书中主人公。——译者注

[2]弥尔顿（John Milton，1608—1674），英国杰出诗人、政论家、革命家，17世纪英国资产阶级革命参加者。——译者注

[3]即夏娃，《圣经》中第一个女人。——译者注

[4]培根（Francis Bacon， 1561—1626），英国杰出哲学家、科学家、历史学家。——译者注

[5]参见《圣经·创世记》第2、3章。——译者注

[6]格雷戈里博士（Dr.Gregory，1724—1773），苏格兰有名的医学家，写有许多医学著作和一篇《给女儿的赠言》。——译者注

[7]索菲亚（Sophia）是卢梭名著《爱弥儿》中的女主人公。——译者注

[8]摩西，《圣经》故事中古代犹太人的领袖。——译者注

[9]蒲伯（Alexander Pope，1688—1744），18世纪英国启蒙运动时期著名诗人。——译者注

[10]塞万提斯（Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra，1547—1616），西班牙伟大作家。堂·吉诃德是其名著《堂·吉诃德》中的主人公。——译者注

[11]参看卢梭和史韦登伯格的著作。——译者注

[12]指伊斯兰教徒死后，送葬时女人不能扶灵柩的风俗。——译者注

[13]普里斯特利博士（Dr.Priestley，1733—1804），英国科学家、哲学家，当时英国进步组织“革命协会”的领导者。——译者注

[14]西巴里特（Sgbarite），意大利南部古城，据传当地居民喜爱奢侈享乐，因此引申为不务正业、安于享乐的人的别名。——译者注

[15]基督教实行的什一税，每年缴纳货物的1/10，作为信徒上缴给教堂的年赋。——译者注

[16]见《圣经·新约》“马太福音”25章14—30节。——译者注

[17]见《圣经·旧约》“以赛亚书”22章13节。——译者注

[18]塞缪尔·约翰逊（Samuel Johnson，1709—1784），英国文学家，《英文字典》（Dictionary of the English Language）编纂者。——译者注

[19]英国伦敦的一条宽阔大道，因为政府办公机构聚集而成名。——译者注

[20]莫洛克（Moloch）是古代腓尼基人信奉的火神，索要儿童作为祭品。——译者注

[21]乔纳森·斯威夫特（Jonathan Swift，1667—1745），英国著名的讽刺作家。——译者注

[22]加图（Cato，公元前234—前149），古罗马政治家、爱国者。公元前175年出使迦太基，发现迦太基的强大，故主张消灭这个城市。——译者注

[23]巴特勒（Alban Butler，1711—1773），天主教徒，传记作家。——译者注

Observations on the State of Degradation to which Woman is Reduced by Various Causes

That woman is naturally weak, or degraded by a concurrence of circumstances, is, I think, clear. But this position I shall simply contrast with a conclusion, which I have frequently heard fall from sensible men in favour of an aristocracy: that the mass of mankind cannot be anything, or the obsequious slaves, who patiently allow themselves to be driven forward, would feel their own consequence, and spurn their chains. Men, they further observe, submit everywhere to oppression, when they have only to lift up their heads to throw off the yoke; yet, instead of asserting their birthright, they quietly lick the dust, and say, ‘Let us eat and drink, for tomorrow we die.' Women, I argue from analogy, are degraded by the same propensity to enjoy the present moment, and at last despise the freedom which they have not sufficient virtue to struggle to attain. But I must be more explicit.

With respect to the culture of the heart, it is unanimously allowed that sex is out of the question; but the line of subordination in the mental powers is never to be passed over. Only ‘absolute in loveliness', the portion of rationality granted to woman is, indeed, very scanty; for denying her genius and judgement, it is scarcely possible to divine what remains to characterize intellect.

The stamen of immortality, if I may be allowed the phrase, is the perfectibility of human reason; for, were man created perfect, or did a flood of knowledge break in upon him, when he arrived at maturity, that precluded error, I should doubt whether his existence would be continued after the dissolution of the body. But, in the present state of things, every difficulty in morals that escapes from human discussion, and equally baffles the investigation of profound thinking, and the lightning glance of genius, is an argument on which I build my belief of the immortality of the soul. Reason is, consequentially, the simple power of improvement; or, more properly speaking, of discerning truth. Every individual is in this respect a world in itself. More or less may be conspicuous in one being than another; but the nature of reason must be the same in all, if it be an emanation of divinity, the tie that connects the creature with the Creator; for, can that soul be stamped with the heavenly image, that is not perfected by the exercise of its own reason? Yet outwardly ornamented with elaborate care, and so adorned to delight man, ‘that with honour he may love' , the soul of woman is not allowed to have this distinction, and man, ever placed between her and reason, she is always represented as only created to see through a gross medium, and to take things on trust. But dismissing these fanciful theories, and considering woman as a whole, let it be what it will, instead of a part of man, the inquiry is whether she have reason or not. If she have, which, for a moment, I will take for granted, she was not created merely to be the solace of man, and the sexual should not destroy the human character.

Into this error men have, probably, been led by viewing education in a false light; not considering it as the first step to form a being advancing gradually towards perfection; but only as a preparation for life. On this sensual error, for I must call it so, has the false system of female manners been reared, which robs the whole sex of its dignity, and classes the brown and fair with the smiling flowers that only adorn the land. This has ever been the language of men, and the fear of departing from a supposed sexual character, has made even women of superior sense adopt the same sentiments. Thus understanding, strictly speaking, has been denied to woman; and instinct, sublimated into wit and cunning, for the purposes of life, has been substituted in its stead.

The power of generalizing ideas, of drawing comprehensive conclusions from individual observations, is the only acquirement, for an immortal being, that really deserves the name of knowledge. Merely to observe, without endeavouring to account for anything, may(in a very incomplete manner) serve as the common sense of life; but where is the store laid up that is to clothe the soul when it leaves the body?

This power has not only been denied to women; but writers have insisted that it is inconsistent, with a few exceptions, with their sexual character. Let men prove this, and I shall grant that woman only exists for man. I must, however, previously remark, that the power of generalizing ideas, to any great extent, is not very common amongst men or women. But this exercise is the true cultivation of the understanding; and everything conspires to render the cultivation of the understanding more difficult in the female than the male world.

I am naturally led by this assertion to the main subject of the present chapter, and shall now attempt to point out some of the causes that degrade the sex, and prevent women from generalizing their observations.

I shall not go back to the remote annals of antiquity to trace the history of woman; it is sufficient to allow that she has always been either a slave or a despot, and to remark that each of these situations equally retards the progress of reason. The grand source of female folly and vice has ever appeared to me to arise from narrowness of mind; and the very constitution of civil governments has put almost insuperable obstacles in the way to prevent the cultivation of the female understanding; yet virtue can be built on no other foundation. The same obstacles are thrown in the way of the rich, and the same consequences ensue.

Necessity has been proverbially termed the mother of invention; the aphorism may be extended to virtue. It is an acquirement, and an acquirement to which pleasure must be sacrificed; and who sacrifices pleasure when it is within the grasp, whose mind has not been opened and strengthened by adversity, or the pursuit of knowledge goaded on by necessity? Happy is it when people have the cares of life to struggle with, for these struggles prevent their becoming a prey to enervating vices, merely from idleness. But if from their birth men and women be placed in a torrid zone, with the meridian sun of pleasure slanting directly upon them, how can they sufficiently brace their minds to discharge the duties of life, or even to relish the affections that carry them out of themselves?

Pleasure is the business of woman's life, according to the present modification of society; and while it continues to be so, little can be expected from such weak beings. Inheriting in a lineal descent from the first fair defect in nature – the sovereignty of beauty – they have, to maintain their power, resigned the natural rights which the exercise of reason might have procured them, and chosen rather to be short-lived queens than labour to obtain the sober pleasures that arise from equality. Exalted by their inferiority (this sounds like a contradiction), they constantly demand homage as women, though experience should teach them that the men who pride themselves upon paying this arbitrary insolent respect to the sex, with the most scrupulous exactness, are most inclined to tyrannize over, and despise the very weakness they cherish.

[...]

Ah! why do women – I write with affectionate solicitude – condescend to receive a degree of attention and respect from strangers different from that reciprocation of civility which the dictates of humanity and the politeness of civilization authorize between man and man? And why do they not discover, when ‘in the noon of beauty's power', that they are treated like queens only to be deluded by hollow respect, till they are led to resign, or not assume, their natural prerogatives? Confined, then, in cages like the feathered race, they have nothing to do but to plume themselves, and stalk with mock majesty from perch to perch. It is true they are provided with food and raiment, for which they neither toil nor spin; but health, liberty, and virtue are given in exchange. But where, amongst mankind, has been found sufficient strength of mind to enable a being to resign these adventitious prerogatives – one who, rising with the calm dignity of reason above opinion, dared to be proud of the privileges inherent in man? And it is vain to expect it whilst hereditary power chokes the affections, and nips reason in the bud.

The passions of men have thus placed women on thrones, and till mankind become more reasonable, it is to be feared that women will avail themselves of the power which they attain with the least exertion, and which is the most indisputable. They will smile – yes, they will smile, though told that:

In beauty's empire is no mean,

And woman, either slave or queen,

Is quickly scorned when not adored.

But the adoration comes first, and the scorn is not anticipated.

Louis XIV, in particular, spread factitious manners, and caught, in a specious way, the whole nation in his toils; for, establishing an artful chain of despotism, he made it the interest of the people at large individually to respect his station, and support his power. And women, whom he flattered by a puerile attention to the whole sex, obtained in his reign that prince-like distinction so fatal to reason and virtue.

A king is always a king, and a woman always a woman. His authority and her sex ever stand between them and rational converse. With a lover, I grant, she should be so, and her sensibility will naturally lead her to endeavour to excite emotion, not to gratify her vanity, but her heart. This I do not allow to be coquetry; it is the artless impulse of nature. I only exclaim against the sexual desire of conquest when the heart is out of the question.

[...]

I lament that women are systematically degraded by receiving the trivial attentions which men think it manly to pay to the sex, when in fact, they are insultingly supporting their own superiority. It is not condescension to bow to an inferior. So ludicrous, in fact, do these ceremonies appear to me that I scarcely am able to govern my muscles when I see a man start with eager and serious solicitude to lift a handkerchief or shut a door, when the lady could have done it herself, had she only moved a pace or two.

A wild wish has just flown from my heart to my head, and I will not stifle it, though it may excite a horselaugh. I do earnestly wish to see the distinction of sex confounded in society, unless where love animates the behaviour. For this distinction is, I am firmly persuaded, the foundation of the weakness of character ascribed to woman; is the cause why the understanding is neglected, whilst accomplishments are acquired with sedulous care; and the same cause accounts for their preferring the graceful before the heroic virtues.

Mankind, including every description, wish to be loved and respected by something, and the common herd will always take the nearest road to the completion of their wishes. The respect paid to wealth and beauty is the most certain and unequivocal, and, of course, will always attract the vulgar eye of common minds. Abilities and virtues are absolutely necessary to raise men from the middle rank of life into notice, and the natural consequence is notorious – the middle rank contains most virtue and abilities. Men have thus, in one station at least, an opportunity of exerting themselves with dignity, and of rising by the exertions which really improve a rational creature; but the whole female sex are, till their character is formed, in the same condition as the rich, for they are born – I now speak of a state of civilization – with certain sexual privileges; and whilst they are gratuitously granted them, few will ever think of works of supererogation to obtain the esteem of a small number of superior people.

When do we hear of women who, starting out of obscurity, boldly claim respect on account of their great abilities or daring virtues? Where are they to be found? ... Women, commonly called ladies, are not to be contradicted, in company, are not allowed to exert any manual strength; and from them the negative virtues only are expected, when any virtues are expected – patience, docility, good humour, and flexibility – virtues incompatible with any vigorous exertion of intellect. Besides, by living more with each other, and being seldom absolutely alone, they are more under the influence of sentiments than passions. Solitude and reflection are necessary to give to wishes the force of passions, and to enable the imagination to enlarge the object, and make it the most desirable. The same may be said of the rich; they do not sufficiently deal in general ideas, collected by impassioned thinking or calm investigation, to acquire that strength of character on which great resolves are built.

[...]

In the middle rank of life, men, in their youth, are prepared for professions, and marriage is not considered as the grand feature in their lives; whilst women, on the contrary, have no other scheme to sharpen their faculties. It is not business, extensive plans, or any of the excursive flights of ambition, that engross their attention; no, their thoughts are not employed in rearing such noble structures. To rise in the world, and have the liberty of running from pleasure to pleasure, they must marry advantageously, and to this object their time is sacrificed, and their persons often legally prostituted. A man when he enters any profession has his eye steadily fixed on some future advantage (and the mind gains great strength by having all its efforts directed to one point), and, full of his business, pleasure is considered as mere relaxation; whilst women seek for pleasure as the main purpose of existence. In fact, from the education, which they receive from society, the love of pleasure may be said to govern them all; but does this prove that there is a sex in souls? It would be just as rational to declare that the courtiers in France, when a destructive system of despotism had formed their character, were not men, because liberty, virtue, and humanity, were sacrificed to pleasure and vanity. Fatal passions, which have ever domineered over the whole race!

The same love of pleasure, fostered by the whole tendency of their education, gives a trifling turn to the conduct of women in most circumstances; for instance, they are ever anxious about secondary things; and on the watch for adventures instead of being occupied by duties.

A man, when he undertakes a journey, has, in general, the end in view; a woman thinks more of the incidental occurrences, the strange things that may possibly occur on the road; the impression that she may make on her fellow-travellers; and, above all, she is anxiously intent on the care of the finery that she carries with her, which is more than ever a part of herself, when going to figure on a new scene; when, to use an apt French turn of expression, she is going to produce a sensation. Can dignity of mind exist with such trivial cares?

In short, women, in general, as well as the rich of both sexes, have acquired all the follies and vices of civilization, and missed the useful fruit. It is not necessary for me always to premise, that I speak of the condition of the whole sex, leaving exceptions out of the question. Their senses are inflamed, and their understandings neglected, consequently they become the prey of their senses, delicately termed sensibility, and are blown about by every momentary gust of feeling. ‘Civilized' women are, therefore, so weakened by false refinement, that, respecting morals, their condition is much below what it would be were they left in a state nearer to nature. Ever restless and anxious, their over-exercised sensibility not only renders them uncomfortable themselves, but troublesome, to use a soft phrase, to others. All their thoughts turn on things calculated to excite emotion and feeling, when they should reason, their conduct is unstable, and their opinions are wavering – not the wavering produced by deliberation or progressive views, but by contradictory emotions. By fits and starts, they are warm in many pursuits; yet this warmth, never concentrated into perseverance, soon exhausts itself; exhaled by its own heat, or meeting with some other fleeting passion, to which reason has never given any specific gravity, neutrality ensues. Miserable, indeed, must be that being whose cultivation of mind has only tended to inflame its passions! A distinction should be made between inflaming and strengthening them. The passions thus pampered, whilst the judgement is left unformed, what can be expected to ensue? Undoubtedly, a mixture of madness and folly!

This observation should not be confined to the fair sex; however, at present, I only mean to apply it to them.

Novels, music, poetry, and gallantry, all tend to make women the creatures of sensation, and their character is thus formed in the mould of folly during the time they are acquiring accomplishments, the only improvement they are excited, by their station in society, to acquire. This overstretched sensibility naturally relaxes the other powers of the mind, and prevents intellect from attaining that sovereignty which it ought to attain to render a rational creature useful to others, and content with its own station; for the exercise of the understanding, as life advances, is the only method pointed out by nature to calm the passions.

Satiety has a very different effect, and I have often been forcibly struck by an emphatical description of damnation; when the spirit is represented as continually hovering with abortive eagerness round the defiled body, unable to enjoy anything without the organs of sense. Yet, to their senses, are women made slaves, because it is by their sensibility that they obtain present power.

And will moralists pretend to assert that this is the condition in which one-half of the human race should be encouraged to remain with listless inactivity and stupid acquiescence? Kind instructors! what were we created for? To remain, it may be said, innocent; they mean in a state of childhood. We might as well never have been born, unless it were necessary that we should be created to enable man to acquire the noble privilege of reason, the power of discerning good from evil, whilst we lie down in the dust from whence we were taken, never to rise again.

It would be an endless task to trace the variety of meannesses, cares, and sorrows, into which women are plunged by the prevailing opinion, that they were created rather to feel than reason, and that all the power they obtain must be obtained by their charms and weakness:

Fine by defect, and amiably weak!

And, made by this amiable weakness entirely dependent, excepting what they gain by illicit sway, on man, not only for protection, but advice, is it surprising that, neglecting the duties that reason alone points out, and shrinking from trials calculated to strengthen their minds, they only exert themselves to give their defects a graceful covering, which may serve to heighten their charms in the eye of the voluptuary, though it sink them below the scale of moral excellence.

Fragile in every sense of the word, they are obliged to look up to man for every comfort. In the most trifling danger they cling to their support, with parasitical tenacity, piteously demanding succour; and their natural protector extends his arm, or lifts up his voice, to guard the lovely trembler – from what? Perhaps the frown of an old cow, or the jump of a mouse; a rat would be a serious danger. In the name of reason, and even common sense, what can save such beings from contempt; even though they be soft and fair.

These fears, when not affected, may produce some pretty attitudes; but they show a degree of imbecility which degrades a rational creature in a way women are not aware of – for love and esteem are very distinct things.

I am fully persuaded that we should hear of none of these infantine airs, if girls were allowed to take sufficient exercise, and not confined in dose rooms till their muscles are relaxed, and their powers of digestion destroyed. To carry the remark still further, if fear in girls, instead of being cherished, perhaps, created, were treated in the same manner as cowardice in boys, we should quickly see women with more dignified aspects. It is true, they could not then with equal propriety be termed the sweet flowers that smile in the walk of man; but they would be more respectable members of society, and discharge the important duties of life by the light of their own reason. ‘Educate women like men,'says Rousseau, ‘and the more they resemble our sex the less power they will have over us.' This is the very point I aim at. I do not wish them to have power over men; but over themselves.

[...]

Ignorance is a frail base for virtue! Yet, that it is the condition for which woman was organized, has been insisted upon by the writers who have most vehemently argued in favour of the superiority of man; a superiority not in degree, but offence; though, to soften the argument, they have laboured to prove, with chivalrous generosity, that the sexes ought not to be compared; man was made to reason, woman to feel: and that together, flesh and spirit, they make the most perfect whole, by blending happily reason and sensibility into one character.

And what is sensibility? ‘Quickness of sensation, quickness of perception, delicacy.' Thus is it defined by Dr Johnson; and the definition gives me no other idea than of the most exquisitely polished instinct. I discern not a trace of the image of God in either sensation or matter. Refined seventy times seven they are still material; intellect dwells not there; nor will fire ever make lead gold!

I come round to my old argument: if woman be allowed to have an immortal soul, she must have, as the employment of life, an understanding to improve. And when, to render the present state more complete, though everything proves it to be but a fraction of a mighty sum, she is incited by present gratification to forget her grand destination, nature is counteracted, or she was born only to procreate and rot. Or, granting brutes of every description a soul, though not a reasonable one, the exercise of instinct and sensibility may be the step which they are to take, in this life, towards the attainment of reason in the next; so that through all eternity they will lag behind man, who, why we cannot tell, had the power given him of attaining reason in his first mode of existence.

When I treat of the peculiar duties of women, as I should treat of the peculiar duties of a citizen or father, it will be found that I do not mean to insinuate that they should be taken out of their families, speaking of the majority [...] But the welfare of society is not built on extraordinary exertions; and were it more reasonably organized, there would be still less need of great abilities, or heroic virtues.

In the regulation of a family, in the education of children, understanding, in an unsophisticated sense, is particularly required – strength both of body and mind; yet the men who, by their writings, have most earnestly laboured to domesticate women, have endeavoured, by arguments dictated by a gross appetite, which satiety had rendered fastidious, to weaken their bodies and cramp their minds. But, if even by these sinister methods they really persuaded women, by working on their feelings, to stay at home, and fulfil the duties of a mother and mistress of a family, I should cautiously oppose opinions that led women to right conduct, by prevailing on them to make the discharge of such important duties the main business of life, though reason were insulted. Yet, and I appeal to experience, if by neglecting the understanding they be as much, nay, more detached from these domestic employments, than they could be by the most serious intellectual pursuit, though it may be observed, that the mass of mankind will never vigorously pursue an intellectual object, I may be allowed to infer that reason is absolutely necessary to enable a woman to perform any duty properly, and I must again repeat, that sensibility is not reason.

[...]

Another argument that has had great weight with me must, I think, have some force with every considerate benevolent heart. Girls who have been thus weakly educated are often cruelly left by their parents without any provision, and, of course, are dependent on not only the reason, but the bounty of their brothers. These brothers are, to view the fairest side of the question, good sort of men, and give as a favour what children of the same parents had an equal right to. In this equivocal humiliating situation a docile female may remain some time with a tolerable degree of comfort. But when the brother marries – a probable circumstance – from being considered as the mistress of the family, she is viewed with averted looks as an intruder, an unnecessary burden on the benevolence of the master of the house and his new partner.

Who can recount the misery which many unfortunate beings, whose minds and bodies are equally weak, suffer in such situations – unable to work, and ashamed to beg? The wife, a cold-hearted, narrowminded woman – and this is not an unfair supposition, for the present mode of education does not tend to enlarge the heart any more than the understanding –is jealous of the little kindness which her husband shows to his relations; and her sensibility not rising to humanity, she is displeased at seeing the property of her children lavished on an helpless sister.

These are matters of fact, which have come under my eye again and again. The consequence is obvious; the wife has recourse to cunning to undermine the habitual affection which she is afraid openly to oppose; and neither tears nor caresses are spared till the spy is worked out of her home, and thrown on the world, unprepared for its difficulties; or sent, as a great effort of generosity, or from some regard to propriety, with a small stipend, and an uncultivated mind, into joyless solitude.

These two women may be much upon a par with respect to reason and humanity, and, changing situations, might have acted just the same selfish part; but had they been differently educated, the case would also have been very different. The wife would not have had that sensibility, of which self is the centre, and reason might have taught her not to expect, and not even to be flattered by, the affection of her husband, if it led him to violate prior duties. She would wish not to love him merely because he loved her, but on account of his virtues; and the sister might have been able to struggle for herself instead of eating the bitter bread of dependence.

I am, indeed, persuaded that the heart, as well as the understanding, is opened by cultivation, and by –which may not appear so clear – strengthening the organs. I am not now talking of momentary flashes of sensibility, but of affections. And, perhaps, in the education of both sexes, the most difficult task is so to adjust instruction as not to narrow the understanding, whilst the heart is warmed by the generous juices of spring, just raised by the electric fermentation of the season; nor to dry up the feelings by employing the mind in investigations remote from life.

With respect to women, when they receive a careful education, they are either made fine ladies, brimful of sensibility, and teeming with capricious fancies, or mere notable women. The latter are often friendly, honest creatures, and have a shrewd kind of good sense, joined with worldly prudence, that often render them more useful members of society than the fine sentimental lady, though they possess neither greatness of mind nor taste. The intellectual world is shut against them. Take them out of their family or neighbourhood, and they stand still; the mind finding no employment, for literature affords a fund of amusement which they have never sought to relish, but frequently to despise. The sentiments and taste of more cultivated minds appear ridiculous, even in those whom chance and family connections have led them to love; but in mere acquaintance they think it all affectation.

A man of sense can only love such a woman on account of her sex, and respect her because she is a trusty servant. He lets her, to preserve his own peace, scold the servants, and go to church in clothes made of the very best materials. A man of her own size of understanding would probably not agree so well with her, for he might wish to encroach on her prerogative, and manage some domestic concerns himself; yet women, whose minds are not enlarged by cultivation, or the natural selfishness of sensibility by reflection, are very unfit to manage a family, for, by an undue stretch of power, they are always tyrannizing to support a superiority that only rests on the arbitrary distinction of fortune. The evil is sometimes more serious, and domestics are deprived of innocent indulgences, and made to work beyond their strength, in order to enable the notable woman to keep a better table, and outshine her neighbours in finery and parade. If she attend to her children, it is in general to dress them in a costly manner; and whether this attention arise from vanity or fondness, it is equally pernicious.

Besides, how many women of this description pass their days, or at least their evenings, discontentedly. Their husbands acknowledge that they are good managers and chaste wives, but leave home to seek for more agreeable – may I be allowed to use a significant French word – piquant society; and the patient drudge, who fulfils her task like a blind horse in a mill, is defrauded of her just reward, for the wages due to her are the caresses of her husband; and women who have so few resources in themselves, do not very patiently bear this privation of a natural right.

A fine lady, on the contrary, has been taught to look down with contempt on the vulgar employments of life, though she had only been incited to acquire accomplishments that rise a degree above sense; for even corporeal accomplishments cannot be acquired with any degree of precision unless the understanding has been strengthened by exercise. Without a foundation of principles taste is superficial; grace must arise from something deeper than imitation. The imagination, however, is heated, and the feelings rendered fastidious, if not sophisticated, or a counter poise of judgement is not acquired when the heart still remains artless, though it becomes too tender.

[...]

Yet if love be the supreme good, let woman be only educated to inspire it, and let every charm be polished to intoxicate the senses; but if they be moral beings, let them have a chance to become intelligent; and let love to man be only a part of that glowing flame of universal love, which, after encircling humanity, mounts in grateful incense to God.

To fulfil domestic duties much resolution is necessary, and a serious kind of perseverance that requires a more firm support than emotions, however lively and true to nature. To give an example of order, the soul of virtue, some austerity of behaviour must be adopted, scarcely to be expected from a being who, from its infancy, has been made the weathercock of its own sensations. Whoever rationally means to be useful must have a plan of conduct; and in the discharge of the simplest duty, we are often obliged to act contrary to the present impulse of tenderness or compassion. Severity is frequently the most certain as well as the most sublime proof of affection; and the want of this power over the feelings, and of that lofty, dignified affection which makes a person prefer the future good of the beloved object to a present gratification is the reason why so many fond mothers spoil their children, and has made it questionable whether negligence or indulgence be most hurtful; but I am inclined to think that the latter has done most harm.

Mankind seem to agree that children should be left under the management of women during their child- hood. Now, from all the observation that I have been able to make, women of sensibility are the most unfit for this task, because they will infallibly, carried away by their feelings, spoil a child's temper. The management of the temper, the first, and most important branch of education, requires the sober steady eye of reason; a plan of conduct equally distant from tyranny and indulgence: yet these are the extremes that people of sensibility alternately fall into; always shooting beyond the mark. I have followed this train of reasoning much further, till I have concluded, that a person of genius is the most improper person to be employed in education, public or private. Minds of this rare species see things too much in masses, and seldom, if ever, have a good temper. That habitual cheerfulness, termed good humour, is, perhaps, as seldom united with great mental powers, as with strong feelings. And those people who follow, with interest and admiration, the flights of genius; or, with cooler approbation suck in the instruction which has been elaborately prepared for them by the profound thinker, ought not to be disgusted, if they find the former choleric, and the latter morose; because liveliness of fancy, and a tenacious comprehension of mind, are scarcely compatible with that pliant urbanity which leads a man, at least, to bend to the opinions and prejudices of others, instead of roughly confronting them.

But, treating of education, or manners, minds of a superior class are not to be considered, they may be left to chance; it is the multitude, with moderate abilities, who call for instruction, and catch the colour of the atmosphere they breathe. This respectable concourse, I contend, men and women, should not have their sensations heightened in the hot-bed of luxurious indolence, at the expense of their understanding; for, unless there be a ballast of understanding, they will never become either virtuous or free: an aristocracy, founded on property or sterling talents, will ever sweep before it the alternately timid and ferocious slaves of feeling.

[...]

Women have seldom sufficient serious employment to silence their feelings; a round of little cares, or vain pursuits frittering away all strength of mind and organs, they become naturally only objects of sense. In short, the whole tenor of female education (the education of society) tends to render the best disposed romantic and inconstant; and the remainder vain and mean. In the present state of society this evil can scarcely be remedied, I am afraid, in the slightest degree; should a more laudable ambition ever gain ground they may be brought nearer to nature and reason, and become more virtuous and useful as they grow more respectable.

But, I will venture to assert that their reason will never acquire sufficient strength to enable it to regulate their conduct, whilst the making an appearance in the world is the first wish of the majority of mankind. To this weak wish the natural affections, and the most useful virtues are sacrificed. Gifts marry merely to better themselves, to borrow a significant vulgar phrase, and have such perfect power over their hearts as not to permit themselves to fall in love till a man with a superior fortune offers. On this subject I mean to enlarge in a future chapter; it is only necessary to drop a hint at present, because women are so often degraded by suffering the selfish prudence of age to chill the ardour of youth.

From the same source flows an opinion that young gifts ought to dedicate great part of their time to needle – work; yet, this employment contracts their faculties more than any other that could have been chosen for them, by confining their thoughts to their persons. Men order their clothes to be made, and have done with the subject; women make their own clothes, necessary or ornamental, and are continually talking about them; and their thoughts follow their hands. It is not indeed the making of necessaries that weakens the mind; but the frippery of dress. For when a woman in the lower rank of life makes her husband's and children's clothes, she does her duty, this is her part of the family business; but when women work only to dress better than they could otherwise afford, it is worse than sheer loss of time. To render the poor virtuous they must be employed, and women in the middle rank of life, did they not ape the fashions of the nobility, without catching their ease, might employ them, whilst they themselves managed their families, instructed their children, and exercised their own minds. Gardening, experimental philosophy, and literature, would afford them subject to think of and matter for conversation, that in some degree would exercise their understandings. The conversation of Frenchwomen, who are not so rigidly nailed to their chairs to twist lappets, and knot ribands, is frequently superficial; but, I contend, that it is not half so insipid as that of those Englishwomen whose time is spent in making caps, bonnets, and the whole mischief of trimmings, not to mention shopping, bargain-hunting, etc.; and it is the decent, prudent women, who are most degraded by these practices; for their motive is simply vanity. The wanton who exercises her taste to render her passion alluring, has something more in view.

These observations all branch out of a general one, which I have before made, and which cannot be too often insisted upon, for, speaking of men, women, or professions, it will be found that the employment of the thoughts shapes the character both generally and individually. The thoughts of women ever hover round their persons, and is it surprising that their persons are reckoned most valuable? Yet some degree of liberty of mind is necessary even to form the person; and this may be one reason why some gentle wives have so few attractions beside that of sex. Add to this, sedentary employments render the majority of women sickly – and false notions of female excellence make them proud of this delicacy, though it be another fetter, that by calling the attention continually to the body, cramps the activity of the mind.

Women of quality seldom do any of the manual part of their dress, consequently only their taste is exercised, and they acquire, by thinking less of the finery, when the business of their toilet is over, that ease, which seldom appears in the deportment of women, who dress merely for the sake of dressing. In fact, the observation with respect to the middle rank, the one in which talents thrive best, extends not to women; for those of the superior class, by catching, at least, a smattering of literature, and conversing more with men, on general topics, acquire more knowledge than the women who ape their fashions and faults without sharing their advantages. With respect to virtue, to use the word in a comprehensive sense, I have seen most in low life. Many poor women maintain their children by the sweat of their brow, and keep together families that the vices of the fathers would have scattered abroad; but gentlewomen are too indolent to be actively virtuous, and are softened rather than refined by civilization. Indeed, the good sense which I have met with, among the poor women who have had few advantages of education, and yet have acted heroically, strongly confirmed me in the opinion that trifling employments have rendered woman a trifler. Man, taking her body, the mind is left to rust; so that while physical love enervates man, as being his favourite recreation, he will endeavour to enslave woman: – and, who can tell, how many generations may be necessary to give vigour to the virtue and talents of the freed posterity of abject slaves?

In tracing the causes that, in my opinion, have degraded woman, I have confined my observations to such as universally act upon the morals and manners of the whole sex, and to me it appears clear that they all spring from want of understanding. Whether this arise from a physical or accidental weakness of faculties, time alone can determine; for I shall not lay any great stress on the example of a few women who, from having received a masculine education, have acquired courage and resolution; I only contend that the men who have been placed in similar situations, have acquired a similar character – I speak of bodies of men, and that men of genius and talents have started out of a class, in which women have never yet been placed.

Morality Undermined by Sexual Notions of the Importance of a Good Reputation

It has long since occurred to me that advice respecting behaviour, and all the various modes of preserving a good reputation, which have been so strenuously inculcated on the female world, were specious poisons, that encrusting morality eat away the substance. And, that this measuring of shadows produced a false calculation, because their length depends so much on the height of the sun, and other adventitious circumstances.

[...]

The leading principles which run through all my disquisitions, would render it unnecessary to enlarge on this subject, if a constant attention to keep the varnish of the character fresh, and in good condition, were not often inculcated as the sum total of female duty; if rules to regulate the behaviour, and to preserve the reputation, did not too frequently supersede moral obligations. But, with respect to reputation, the attention is confined to a single virtue – chastity. If the honour of a woman, as it is absurdly called, be safe, she may neglect every social duty; nay, ruin her family by gaming and extravagance; yet still present a shameless front – for truly she is an honourable woman!

Mrs Macaulay has just observed, that ‘there is but one fault which a woman of honour may not commit with impunity.' She then justly and humanely adds – ‘This has given rise to the trite and foolish observation, that the first fault against chastity in woman has a radical power to deprave the character. But no such frail beings come out of the hands of Nature. The human mind is built of nobler materials than to be easily corrupted; and with all their disadvantages of situation and education, women seldom become entirely abandoned till they are thrown into a state of desperation, by the venomous rancour of their own sex.'

But, in proportion as this regard for the reputation of chastity is prized by women, it is despised by men: and the two extremes are equally destructive to morality.

Men are certainly more under the influence of their appetites than women; and their appetites are more depraved by unbridled indulgence and the fastidious contrivances of satiety. Luxury has introduced a refinement in eating, that destroys the constitution; and, a degree of gluttony which is so beastly, that a perception of seemliness of behaviour must be worn out before one being could eat immoderately in the presence of another, and afterwards complain of the oppression that his intemperance naturally produced. Some women, particularly French women, have also lost a sense of decency in this respect; for they will talk very calmly of an indigestion. It were to be wished that idleness was not allowed to generate, on the rank soil of wealth, those swarms of summer insects that feed on putrefaction, we should not then be disgusted by the sight of such brutal excesses.

There is one rule relative to behaviour that, I think, ought to regulate every other; and it is simply to cherish such an habitual respect for mankind as may prevent us from disgusting a fellow-creature for the sake of a present indulgence. The shameful indolence of many married women and others a little advanced in life, frequently leads them to sin against delicacy. For, though convinced that the person is the band of union between the sexes, yet, how often do they from sheer indolence, or, to enjoy some trifling indulgence, disgust?

The depravity of the appetite which brings the sexes together, has had a still more fatal effect. Nature must ever be the standard of taste, the gauge of appetite – yet how grossly is nature insulted by the voluptuary. Leaving the refinements of love out of the question; nature, by making the gratification of an appetite, in this respect, as well as every other, a natural and imperious law to preserve the species, exalts the appetite, and mixes a little mind and affection with a sensual gust. The feelings of a parent mingling with an instinct merely animal, give it dignity; and the man and woman often meeting on account of the child, a mutual interest and affection is excited by the exercise of a common sympathy. Women then having some necessary duty to fulfil, more noble than to adorn their persons, would not contentedly be the slaves of casual lust; which is now the situation of a very considerable number who are, literally speaking, standing dishes to which every glutton may have access.

I may be told that great as this enormity is, it only affects a devoted part of the sex – devoted for the salvation of the rest. But, false as every assertion might easily be proved, that recommends the sanctioning a small evil to produce a greater good; the mischief does not stop here, for the moral character, and peace of mind, of the chaster part of the sex, is undermined by the conduct of the very women to whom they allow no refuge from guilt; whom they inexorably consign to the exercise of arts that lure their husbands from them, debauch their sons, and force them, let not modest women start, to assume, in some degree, the same character themselves. For I will venture to assert, that all the causes of female weakness, as well as depravity, which I have already enlarged on, branch out of one grand cause – want of chastity in men.

This intemperance, so prevalent, depraves the appetite to such a degree, that a wanton stimulus is necessary to rouse it; but the parental design of Nature is forgotten, and the mere person, and that for a moment, alone engrosses the thoughts. So voluptuous, indeed, often grows the lustful prowler, that he refines on female soft ness. Something more soft than women is then sought for; till, in Italy and Portugal, men attend the levees of equivocal beings, to sigh for more than female languor.

To satisfy this genus of men, women are made systematically voluptuous, and though they may not carry their libertinism to the same height, yet this heartless intercourse with the sex, which they allow themselves, depraves both sexes, because the taste of men is vitiated; and women, of all classes, naturally square their behavigur to gratify the taste by which they obtain pleasure and power. Women becoming, consequently, weaker, in mind and body, than they ought to be, were one of the grand ends of their being taken into the account, that of bearing and nursing children, have not sufficient strength to discharge the first duty of a mother; and sacrificing to lasciviousness the parental affection, that ennobles instinct, either destroy the embryo in the womb, or cast it off when born. Nature in everything demands respect, and those who violate her laws seldom violate them with impunity. The weak enervated women who particularly catch the attention of libertines, are unfit to be mothers, though they may conceive; so that the rich sensualist, who has rioted among women, spreading depravity and misery, when he wishes to perpetuate his name, receives from his wife only an half-formed being that inherits both its father's and mother's weakness.

Contrasting the humanity of the present age with the barbarism of antiquity, great stress has been laid on the savage custom of exposing the children whom their parents could not maintain; whilst the man of sensibility, who thus, perhaps, complains, by his promiscuous amours produces a most destructive barrenness and contagious flagitiousness of manners. Surely nature never intended that women, by satisfying an appetite, should frustrate the very purpose for which it was implanted?

I have before observed, that men ought to maintain the women whom they have seduced; this would be one means of reforming female manners, and stopping an abuse that has an equally fatal effect on population and morals. Another, no less obvious, would be to turn the attention of woman to the real virtue of chastity; for to little respect has that woman a claim, on the score of modesty, though her reputation may be white as the driven snow, who smiles on the libertine whilst she spurns the victims of his lawless appetites and their own folly.

Besides, she has a taint of the same folly, pure as she esteems herself, when she studiously adorns her person only to be seen by men, to excite respectful sighs, and all the idle homage of what is called innocent gallantry. Did women really respect virtue for its own sake, they would not seek for a compensation in vanity, for the self-denial which they are obliged to practise to preserve their reputation, nor would they associate with men who set reputation at defiance.

The two sexes mutually corrupt and improve each other. This I believe to be an indisputable truth, extending it to every virtue. Chastity, modesty, public spirit, and all the noble train of virtues, on which social virtue and happiness are built, should be understood and cultivated by all mankind, or they will be cultivated to little effect. And, instead of furnishing the vicious or idle with a pretext for violating some sacred duty, by terming it a sexual one, it would be wiser to show that Nature has not made any difference, for that the unchaste man doubly defeats the purpose of Nature, by rendering women barren, and destroying his own constitution, though he avoids the shame that pursues the crime in the other sex. These are the physical consequences, the moral are still more alarming; for virtue is only a nominal distinction when the duties of citizens, husbands, wives, fathers, mothers, and directors of families, become merely the selfish ties of convenience.

Why then do philosophers look for public spirit? Public spirit must be nurtured by private virtue, or it will resemble the factitious sentiment which makes women careful to preserve their reputation, and men their honour. A sentiment that often exists unsupported by virtue, unsupported by that sublime morality which makes the habitual breach of one duty a breach of the whole moral law.

On National Education

[...]

My observations on national education are obviously hints; but I principally wish to enforce the necessity of educating the sexes together, to perfect both, and of making children sleep at home that they may learn to love home; yet to make private support, instead of smothering, public affections, they should be sent to school to mix with a number of equals, for only by the jostlings of equality can we form a just opinion of ourselves.

To render mankind more virtuous, and happier of course, both sexes must act from the same principle; but how can that be expected when only one is allowed to see the reasonableness of it? To render also the social compact truly equitable, and in order to spread those enlightening principles, which alone can ameliorate the fate of man, women must be allowed to found their virtue on knowledge, which is scarcely possible unless they be educated by the same pursuits as men. For they are now made so inferior by ignorance and low desires, as not to deserve to be ranked with them; or, by the serpentine wrigglings of cunning, they mount the tree of knowledge, and only acquire sufficient to lead men astray.

It is plain from the history of all nations, that women cannot be confined to merely domestic pursuits, for they will not fulfil family duties, unless their minds take a wider range, and whilst they are kept in ignorance they become in the same proportion the slaves of pleasure as they are the slaves of man. Nor can they be shut out of great enterprises, though the narrowness of their minds often make them mar, what they are unable to comprehend.

The libertinism, and even the virtues of superior men, will always give women, of some description, great power over them; and these weak women, under the influence of childish passions and selfish vanity, will throw a false light over the objects which the very men view with their eyes, who ought to enlighten their judgement. Men of fancy, and those sanguine characters who mostly hold the helm of human affairs, in general, relax in the society of women; and surely I need not cite to the most superficial reader of history the numerous examples of vice and oppression which the private intrigues of female favourites have produced; not to dwell on the mischief that naturally arises from the blundering interposition of well-meaning folly. For in the transaction of business it is much better to have to deal with a knave than a fool, because a knave adheres to some plan; and any plan of reason may be seen through much sooner than a sudden flight of folly. The power which vile and foolish women have had over wise men, who possessed sensibility, is notorious; I shall only mention one instance.

Whoever drew a more exalted female character than Rousseau? Though in the lump he constantly en- deavoured to degrade the sex. And why was he thus anxious? Truly to justify to himself the affection which weakness and virtue had made him cherish for that fool Theresa. He could not raise her to the common level of her sex; and therefore he laboured to bring woman down to hers. He found her a convenient humble companion, and pride made him determine to find some superior virtues in the being whom he chose to live with; but did not her conduct during his life, and after his death, clearly show how grossly he was mistaken who called her a celestial innocent? Nay, in the bitterness of his heart, he himself laments that when his bodily infirmities made him no longer treat her like a woman, she ceased to have an affection for him. And it was very natural that she should, for having so few sentiments in common, when the sexual tie was broken, what was to hold her? To hold her affection whose sensibility was confined to one sex, nay, to one man, it requires sense to turn sensibility into the broad channel of humanity. Many women have not mind enough to have an affection for a woman, or a friendship for a man. But the sexual weakness that makes woman depend on man for a subsistence, produces a kind of cattish affection, which leads a wife to purr about her husband as she would about any man who fed and caressed her.

Men are, however, often gratified by this kind of fondness, which is confined in a beastly manner to themselves; but should they ever become more virtuous, they will wish to converse at their fireside with a friend after they cease to play with a mistress.

Besides, understanding is necessary to give variety and interest to sensual enjoyments, for low indeed in the intellectual scale is the mind that can continue to love when neither virtue nor sense give a human appearance to an animal appetite. But sense will always preponderate; and if women be not, in general, brought more on a level with men, some superior women like the Greek courtesans, will assemble the men of abilities around them, and draw from their families many citizens, who would have stayed at home had their wives had more sense, or the graces which result from the exercise of the understanding, and fancy, the legitimate parents of taste. A woman of talents, if she be not absolutely ugly, will always obtain great power – raised by the weakness of her sex; and in proportion as men acquire virtue and delicacy, by the exertion of reason, they will look for both in women, but they can only acquire them in the same way that men do.

In France or Italy, have the women confined themselves to domestic life? Though they have not hitherto had a political existence, yet have they not illicitly had great sway, corrupting themselves and the men with whose passions they played? In short, in whatever light I view the subject, reason and experience convince me that the only method of leading women to fulfil their peculiar duties is to free them from all restraint by allowing them to participate in the inherent fights of mankind.

Make them free, and they will quickly become wise and virtuous, as men become more so, for the improvement must be mutual, or the injustice which one-half of the human race are obliged to submit to retorting on their oppressors, the virtue of man will be wormeaten by the insect whom he keeps under his feet.

Let men take their choice. Man and woman were made for each other, though not to become one being; and if they will not improve women, they will deprave them.

I speak of the improvement and emancipation of the whole sex, for I know that the behaviour of a few women, who, by accident, or following a strong bent of nature, have acquired a portion of knowledge superior to that of the rest of their sex, has often been overbearing; but there have been instances of women who, attaining knowledge, have not discarded modesty, nor have they always pedantically appeared to despise the ignorance which they laboured to disperse in their own minds. The exclamations then which any advice respecting female learning commonly produces, especially from pretty women, often arise from envy. When they chance to see that even the lustre of their eyes, and the flippant sportiveness of refined coquetry, will not always secure them attention during a whole evening, should a woman of a more cultivated understanding endeavour to give a rational turn to the conversation, the common source of consolation is that such women seldom get husbands. What arts have I not seen silly women use to interrupt by flirtation – a very significant word to describe such a manoeuvre – a rational conversation, which made the men forget that they were pretty women.

But, allowing what is very natural to man, that the possession of rare abilities is really calculated to excite overweening pride, disgusting in both men and women, in what a state of inferiority must the female faculties have rusted when such a small portion of knowledge as those women attained, who have sneeringly been termed learned women, could be singular? – sufficiently so to puff up the possessor, and excite envy in her contemporaries, and some of the other sex. Nay, has not a little rationality exposed many women to the severest censure? I advert to well-known facts, for I have frequently heard women ridiculed, and every little weakness exposed, only because they adopted the advice of some medical men, and deviated from the beaten track in their mode of treating their infants. I have actually heard this barbarous aversion to innovation carried still further, and a sensible woman stigmatized as an unnatural mother, who has thus been wisely solicitous to preserve the health of her children, when in the midst of her care she has lost one by some of the casualties of infancy, which no prudence can ward off. Her acquaintance have observed that this was the consequence of new-fangled notions – the new-fangled notions of ease and cleanliness. And those who pretending to experience, though they have long adhered to prejudices that have, according to the opinion of the most sagacious physicians, thinned the human race, almost rejoiced at the disaster that gave a kind of sanction to prescription.

Indeed, if it were only on this account, the national education of women is of the utmost consequence, for what a number of human sacrifices are made to that Moloch prejudice! And in how many ways are children destroyed by the lasciviousness of man? The want of natural affection in many women, who are drawn from their duty by the admiration of men, and the ignorance of others, render the infancy of man a much more perilous state than that of brutes; yet men are unwilling to place women in situations proper to enable them to acquire sufficient understanding to know how even to nurse their babes.

So forcibly does this truth strike me that I would rest the whole tendency of my reasoning upon it, for whatever tends to incapacitate the maternal character, takes woman out of her sphere.

But it is vain to expect the present race of weak mothers either to take that reasonable care of a child's body, which is necessary to lay the foundation of a good constitution, supposing that it do not suffer for the sins of its fathers; or to manage its temper so judiciously that the child will not have, as it grows up, to throw off all that its mother, its first instructor, directly or indirectly taught; and unless the mind have uncommon vigour, womanish follies will stick to the character throughout life. The weakness of the mother will be visited on the children. And whilst women are educated to rely on their husbands for judgement, this must ever be the consequence, for there is no improving an understanding by halves, nor can any being act wisely from imitation, because in every circumstance of life there is a kind of individuality, which requires an exertion of judgement to modify general rules. The being who can think justly in one track will soon extend its intellectual empire; and she who has sufficient judgement to manage her children will not submit, fight or wrong, to her husband, or patiently to the social laws which make a nonentity of a wife.

In public schools women, to guard against the errors of ignorance, should be taught the elements of anatomy and medicine, not only to enable them to take proper care of their own health, but to make them rational nurses of their infants, parents, and husbands; for the bills of mortality are swelled by the blunders of self-willed old women, who give nostrums of their own without knowing anything of the human frame. It is likewise proper, only in a domestic view, to make women acquainted with the anatomy of the mind, by allowing the sexes to associate together in every pursuit, and by leading them to observe the progress of human under standing in the improvement of the sciences and arts – never forgetting the science of morality, or the study of the political history of mankind.

A man has been termed a microcosm, and every family might also be called a state. States, it is true, have mostly been governed by arts that disgrace the character of man, and the want of a just constitution and equal laws have so perplexed the notions of the worldly wise, that they more than question the reasonableness of contending for the fights of humanity. Thus morality, polluted in the national reservoir, sends off streams of vice to corrupt the constituent parts of the body politic; but should more noble, or rather more just, principles regulate the laws, which ought to be the government of society, and not those who execute them, duty might become the rule of private conduct.

Besides, by the exercise of their bodies and minds women would acquire that mental activity so necessary in the maternal character, united with the fortitude that distinguishes steadiness of conduct from the obstinate perverseness of weakness. For it is dangerous to advise the indolent to be steady, because they instantly become rigorous, and to save themselves trouble punish with severity faults that the patient fortitude of reason might have prevented.

But fortitude presupposes strength of mind, and is strength of mind to be acquired by indolent acquiescence? By asking advice instead of exerting the judgement? By obeying through fear, instead of practising the forbearance which we all stand in need of ourselves? The conclusion which I wish to draw is obvious. Make women rational creatures and free citizens, and they will quickly become good wives and mothers – that is, if men do not neglect the duties of husbands and fathers.

Discussing the advantages which a public and private education combined, as I have sketched, might rationally be expected to produce, I have dwelt most on such as are particularly relative to the female world, because I think the female world oppressed; yet the gangrene, which the vices engendered by oppression have produced, is not confined to the morbid part, but pervades society at large; so that when I wish to see my sex become more like moral agents, my heart bounds with the anticipation of the general diffusion of that sublime contentment which only morality can diffuse.

导读

马可·奥勒留（Marcus Aurelius，121—180），出身罗马贵族，古罗马“五贤帝”时代最后一位皇帝。他也是晚期斯多葛学派的最后一位哲学家，自幼修习希腊和拉丁文学，对修辞、法律和绘画也颇有研究。柏拉图在《理想国》中说：“除非哲学家成为我们这些国家的国王，……使政治权力和聪明才智合而为一……否则……对国家甚至我想对全人类都将祸害无穷。”马可·奥勒留看起来似乎是实现了柏拉图的理想，他是西方历史乃至世界历史上唯一一位皇帝哲学家。但他并不是柏拉图所说的哲学王，攀上权力巅峰的人生背后更多的是无力与无奈。马可·奥勒留主政的时代，罗马帝国早已江河日下，不复昔日荣光，洪水、地震等自然灾害频发，与东方安息人及北方马科曼尼人的战乱以及内部叛乱不断，社会矛盾重重，帝国动荡不安。奥勒留无力化解当时的社会矛盾，但身为皇帝，他仍尽心尽力地恪守使命，应对危机，消除灾害，上马征战，扑灭叛乱与反叛之火。

奥勒留生命的最后十年，大部分时间都是在帝国的边疆或军营里度过。在鞍马劳顿的间隙，他的头脑常常会暂时屏蔽战场上的血肉厮杀、刀光剑影，思绪飘忽到遥远的天际，去思考宇宙和人生的终极问题。或者在营帐内昏暗的灯光下陷入沉思，向自己的内心倾诉，规划一个理想世界的蓝图。这部十二卷的《沉思录》就是奥勒留在戎马倥偬之际，以箴言形式记录下的自己与心灵的对话。在书中，他坦率地吐露内心的苦恼，思考在混乱纷争的世界中如何做一个高尚、正直的人，站在斯多葛派哲学的立场上探讨了自然与社会、自然与人生、理性与欲望、自我与他人的关系。虽然奥勒留所处的时代注定了他不可能成为凯撒、奥古斯都那样具备雄才大略、开疆拓土的统治者，但他留下的这部《沉思录》使人感受到德行的美好与存在的尊严，引导人们担负起人生的职责，努力追求精神富足的生活，传承千年仍具有击中人心、提升灵魂的力量。

奥勒留的《沉思录》有斯多葛学派哲学思想的鲜明印记。斯多葛学派认为每个人都是宇宙理性的一小部分，每个人都像是一个“小宇宙”，乃是“大宇宙”的缩影。他们因此相信宇宙间有公理存在，此公理建立在亘古长存的人类理性与宇宙理性之上，不会随时间、空间而改变。斯多葛学派强调，所有的自然现象，如生老病死，都是在遵守大自然不变的法则，因此人必须学习顺应接受自己的命运。没有任何事物是偶然发生的，每件事发生都有其必要性，当命运来敲你的门时，抱怨是没有用的。

过去我们受教条主义影响，未作深入辨析，将《沉思录》里的箴言断章取义后进行发挥，认为它的核心价值观是一种悲观、充满负能量的宿命论思想，从而加以否定和批判。不可否认，奥勒留的《沉思录》表达了人应该顺应宇宙理性或者命运的思想，但同时他也在这本书里对如何认识自我、担当责任进行了透彻的思考，试图找到人在自然、社会中最恰当的位置。他说：“纵然你能活上三千年，甚至三万年，你也要记住：人唯一能失去的生命就是他现在拥有的生命”（卷二14节），告诫人们生命短暂，一个人只拥有现在，应珍惜光阴。书中也有不少劝导人们自我修炼的金句，如“受到外界环境困扰时，要泰然自若；内心产生行为冲动时，要公平公正”（卷九31节）；“只要道路清晰可见，就心怀善意大步前行，不要回头。……倘若阻力继续出现，始终沿着正义指引的方向，尽量审慎地前进。”（卷十12节）书中还反复强调社会交往应树立平等、尊重、宽容的理念，为塑造健康心理，形成和谐友爱的人际关系提供了启示。奥勒留说：犯错之人与我情同手足，“对于同胞手足，我既不会生气，也不会与之起争执，因为我们天生就该合作，犹如一个人的双手、双脚、上下眼皮或者两排牙齿。”（卷二1节）

十九世纪的法国哲学家欧内斯特·勒南（Ernest Renan）曾这样评价道：“马可·奥勒留的书，没有教条作为基础，永远保持着活力。无论是无神论者，还是对宗教抱有最虔诚信仰的人，都可从中获得启迪与陶冶。”他超越种族、国家的博大胸怀与哲学思考，时至今日仍帮助着无数的人在纷繁世界中获得心灵的静谧与安顿。

刘芳

卷二

1.每日伊始都要这样告诫自己：今天或许会碰到好管闲事之人、忘恩负义之人、傲慢无礼之人、背信弃义之人、心怀鬼胎之人和自私自利之人。这一切皆源于他们善恶不分。而我早已深谙善恶之本，善之高尚及恶之卑劣，也深知犯错之人的本性，他与我情同手足（并非血缘关系，而指同样被赋予理性和些许神性的同胞）。所以，这些行为伤害不了我，因为谁也不能把我牵连到堕落的事件中去。对于同胞手足，我既不会生气，也不会与之起争执，因为我们天生就该合作，犹如一个人的双手、双脚、上下眼皮或者两排牙齿。相互阻碍有违大自然的法则。激怒或者厌恶不正是一种阻碍的表现吗？

2.区区血肉之体，悠悠几缕气息，加上统领全局的理性，这就是我（忘掉你的书本，别再渴求它们，那根本不是你的才能）。作为一只脚迈进死神门槛的人，莫要留恋血肉之躯，它那黏稠的血液、骨骼、复杂的神经、静脉和动脉。也莫要留恋那几缕气息。气息是什么？无非一缕气流，连每次呼出来再吸进去的空气都不相同。唯有第三者——理性，那才是你必须全神贯注的主宰。既然你已经两鬓斑白，就不要再把理性当作奴仆，在私利一次次驱动下，将它像木偶般扯来扯去，也不要再怒气冲冲地指责命运，抱怨今天，哀叹明天。

3.天意笼罩着整个神界。即便是无常的偶然性也在大自然的版图中占有一席之地。也就是说，天意已经将其编织进纷繁复杂的花毯之中。天意乃万物之源，且与必然性和宇宙的福祉息息相关。你本身只是那个宇宙的一部分。人性的任何组成部分，若由普遍本性授之，皆是好的组成部分。再者，维系整个世界存在的是变化，不仅基本元素在变化，而且由这些元素构成的更为庞大的结构也在变化。明白这番道理就能知足，就能永远把它们奉为准则。忘却对书的渴求吧。唯有如此，当大限来临时，你才不会低声抱怨，而是以优雅的风度，怀着对神灵由衷的感激迎接它。

4.好好反思一下你的那些蹉跎岁月吧，神灵是如何一再放宽你的时限，而你却没有好好利用。现在应该认识宇宙的本质，你就是宇宙的一部分；认识主宰万物的力量的本质，你就是这种力量的产物。现在应该懂得生命有时限，好好把握生命，才能增进自己的领悟，否则时光流逝，一去不还。

5.遇事要像个罗马人，更要像个男人一样时时刻刻决心以应有的尊严和仁爱之心，独立公正地去面对。抛开其他的私心杂念吧。只要你把每个行动当作最后的机会，摒弃任性的想法，摒弃感情上对理性命令的畏缩，摒弃自我表现的欲望，摒弃自我崇拜，摒弃对自己命运的不满，你就能做到这一点。要知道人只需掌控很少的东西，便可以平静虔诚地度过余生；只要他听从这为数不多的忠告，神灵就别无他求。

6.你错待了自己，我的灵魂；一切来得太快，已没有时间更改。生命只有一次；你已来日无多，却依然漠不关心自己的荣誉，将幸福寄望于他人的灵魂[5]。

7.外面的牵挂使你分心吗？那就给自己留一方净土，在那里可以增加对善的认识，学会克制内心的躁动。还要警惕另一种错误：有些人的愚蠢在于终日忙碌却漫无目标，不知自己的一切努力、一切想法，都为了什么。

8.一个人因对别人的想法漠不关心而遭受不幸，这种情形很难看到。然而，如果他对自己的意愿也漠不关心，那么不幸注定是对他的回报。

9.永远记住什么是普遍本性，什么是自己的本性，以及两者之间有什么样的关系。整体是那么的宏大，而部分是如此的渺小。记住，没人能阻止你按照普遍本性说话行事，因为你就是它的一部分。

10.当泰奥弗拉斯托斯比较各种罪恶的时候（至今它们都被普遍认为具有可比性），他坚信这样一个哲学真理，即欲望之罪比激情之罪更应受到惩罚。因为激情对理性的背离至少看起来带有一丝不安，让人感到一些羁绊；而欲望之罪则纯粹由满足感所驱使，意味着更多的自我放纵和缺乏男子气的倾向。况且，实践经验和哲学理论都支持这种论点，即带来满足感的罪行比带来痛苦的罪行应该受到更为严厉的谴责。一种情形是当事人因遭受不公而被迫失去自制力，另一种情形则是在欲望的驱使下主动犯错。

11.无论做事、说话还是思考问题，都要铭记：终止生命的权力始终掌握在自己手中。倘若真有神灵，你无需害怕离开人间，因为神灵会保佑你不受伤害。倘若神灵不存在，或者即便存在也不理人间俗事，那么在一个无神灵无天意的世界里，生活对我又有何意义？所幸的是，神灵确实存在，而且挂念人间之事。他们赐予我们力量，使我们免于陷入彻底的罪恶。纵然生活中其他方面存在罪恶，神灵也已经替我们未雨绸缪，赐予每个人避免罪恶的力量。如果神不会使一个人堕落，又怎么会让他的生活堕落？普遍本性不会对这种危险熟视无睹，也不会疏于防范和补救。本性既不缺乏能力也不缺乏手段，断不可能被引入歧途，任凭好运和恶运不问青红皂白地降临到有德君子和无耻小人身上。不过，好人与坏人同样会遇到这样的命运：生存和死亡，荣耀和耻辱，快乐和痛苦，富有和贫穷。凡此种种，不一而足。它们既不能使我们高尚也不能使我们堕落，因此它们也就没有好坏之分。

12.我们的思维能力使我们认识到万事万物都会飞快地消失：它们的形体消失在空间里，对它们的记忆消失在时间里。我们还应该认识到所有感官对象的实质，尤其那诱惑人的快乐、使人害怕的痛苦，或是那起劲地鼓动人自命不凡的声音。认清它们多么低贱卑劣，多么利欲熏心，它们的消亡多么迅速。我们应该明辨那些因真知灼见而广受赞誉的人的真正价值。我们还应该理解死亡的本质。只要我们静下心来对死亡好好思考一番，剖析一下我们对死亡的种种想象，我们很快就会明白，死亡不过是一种自然过程（只有孩童才会惧怕自然过程）。更确切地说，不只是一种过程，而且是对自然作出的一种积极贡献。我们还可以认识到人与神灵是如何沟通的，这种沟通是通过身体的哪一部分来实现的，这部分消失之后又会怎样。

13.没有比这更悲哀的事情了：想搞清世间万物，就像诗人吟唱的那样，“探索地球的深处”，好奇地窥探他人灵魂深处的秘密，却丝毫不明白我们唯一要做的只是守住内心的神灵，忠贞不二地为其效力。这种效力需要保持其纯净，免受激情的诱惑，切忌漫无目标，切忌对神和世人的杰作心怀不满。这是因为，前者的杰作由于卓越不凡而值得我们崇敬，后者的杰作由于手足情分而值得我们善待。有时或许也出于同情，同情世人对善恶的无知。因为这种缺陷与黑白不分一样有害。

14.纵然你能活上三千年甚至三万年，你也要记住：人唯一能失去的生命就是他现在拥有的生命。除此之外，他没什么可失去的。这就意味着最长的生命与最短的生命其实没有两样。这是因为，眼下正在经历的这一分钟同样属于每个人，但它一旦逝去便不再为我们所有。所以我们失去的仅仅限于这飞逝的瞬间。既然谁都无法失去已经逝去的或即将到来的，他怎么能被夺走他并不拥有的东西呢？因此，有两件事应当牢记在心：其一，自时间伊始，宇宙万物便以同样的方式周而复始，这种景象你看上一百年、两百年，或是永远看下去，其实根本没有区别。其二，当最长寿的人和最短命的人死去时，他们的损失分毫不差。这是因为，人唯一能被剥夺的东西便是现在。既然现在才是人拥有的一切，他就不会失去他未曾拥有的东西。

15.世人显然对犬儒主义者莫尼姆斯的论断持有异议。他认为：“事物取决于人们对它的看法。”然而如果我们承认他这一论断的实质也包含一定的真理，那么这一论断的价值同样是显而易见的。

16.对于肉体凡胎的人来说，他所犯的最严重的错误是把自己变成（如果能够做到的话）宇宙中的某种毒瘤或脓肿。抱怨客观环境始终是违背大自然的，因为每个人的天性都是大自然的一部分。第二个错误是，人们生气的时候常常会冷落或者恶意反对自己的同胞。第三个错误是，向快乐或痛苦屈服。第四个错误是，掩藏真情实感，虚情假意，言行不一。第五个错误是，做事随心所欲，没有明确目标，无谓浪费精力，缺乏应有思考。哪怕最微小的活动也应有目标。对于有理性的人来说，这一目标应该符合最古老的城邦和国家的法律、理性。

17.在人的一生中，他的时间只是短暂的瞬间，他的存在只是一种不停的流淌，他的感觉只是一种昏暗的微光，他的肉体只是蠕虫的一种食物，他的灵魂只是一种动荡的旋涡，他前途暗淡，名誉难料。总之，他肉体的一切犹如湍急的流水，他的灵魂犹如梦境般飘渺。人生如战争，它是在陌生土地上的短暂停留，声誉之后便是遗忘。如此说来，人从何处才能找到指引方向的力量？人能而且只能从一处找到答案：哲学。成为哲人，就是要保持内心的神性纯洁无瑕、完好无损，这样他才能超越所有的快乐和痛苦，做事目标明确，不弄虚作假，不依赖他人的作为或不作为，接受每一份分配物，把它看成和自己是出自同一来源的。最后，当然也是最重要的，要欣然等待死亡的来临，那只不过是组成每一生命的各种元素的一种简单分解过程。只要这种不停的组合和再组合对元素本身无害，为何要用不信任的眼光看待生命整体的变化和分解呢？这不过是大自然的一种规律罢了，而大自然的规律是没有邪恶的。

卷三

1.岁月蹉跎，来日无多。我们要考虑的还不止这些。即使人能够延年益寿，我们也必须考虑，他的大脑是否还有能力理解事物，是否还有能力进行沉思以便理解神灵和世俗事物。人的衰老，刚开始时不会表现为呼吸器官、消化功能或者感觉器官、脉搏跳动等诸方面的损失。但是，充分运用各项器官的能力，正确评估职责要求的能力，应付可能发生的各种问题的能力，判断是否大限将至的能力，以及娴熟运用智力进行决策的能力，都已经开始衰退了。我们必须赶紧奋力前行。这不仅因为每过一个小时，我们便离死亡更近一步，而且因为我们的认知和理解能力在那以前就已经开始走下坡路了。

还有一个值得我们关注的事情：即便是在大自然的运行中发生的偶然事件也有其优美和迷人之处。比如，一块面包在烤箱里烤制的时候，上面会出现一些裂纹。这种瑕疵虽然不是制作中有意为之，倒也出现得合情合理，而且还能激发人的食欲。再比如，熟透了的无花果会开裂。快要掉落的橄榄有一种临近腐败的状态，但它却给果实增添一种特殊的美感。同样，垂了头的玉米秆、狮子发怒时褶皱的皮肤、野猪嘴边滴落的白沫，凡此种种虽然本身看上去不悦目，但却是大自然运行的结果，为增添大自然的迷人魅力作出了自己的贡献。

2.因此，对一个感觉敏锐、对宇宙的运行有着深邃洞察力的人来说，几乎所有事情，即便只是其他事物的副产品，似乎也都能给他带来额外的愉悦。对那些龇牙咧嘴的活生生的狮子老虎，这样的人会认为，它们像艺术家或雕塑家对它们的模仿一样值得欣赏。凭借自己审慎的鉴赏力，这样的人不仅能看到青年诱人的可爱，而且懂得欣赏老年男女的成熟魅力。并非所有人都会被此类事物所吸引，只有对大自然及其杰作真正怀有亲近感的人才会被它们打动。

3.希波克拉底治愈了很多病患，但他自己却死于疾病。迦勒底人预言了很多人的死亡，但他们自己也没逃脱死亡的追逐。亚历山大、庞贝和凯撒大帝毁灭一座座城池，在战场上砍杀过成千上万的士兵和战马，可是大限来临时同样撒手人寰。赫拉克利特无休止地猜测大火将耗尽宇宙，到头来他自己却身患水肿，浑身沾满牛粪而死。德谟克利特死于寄生虫，苏格拉底死于另一种害虫。那么，这一切寓意何在？其寓意便是：你登船，远航，抵达港口，然后登岸。进入来世吗？神灵无处不在，甚至更遥远的远方也不例外。进入最终的无知觉状态吗？这样你就摆脱了痛苦和快乐的羁绊，不再受缚于这尘世的航船，这船比它的驾驭者卑鄙何止万倍。因为一方是理性和神圣，而另一方不过是肉体与腐败。

4.莫把有生之年浪费在猜测左邻右舍上，除非这种猜测能使双方有所受益。揣摩别人的行为、动机、言谈、想法和打算，总之，揣摩任何会分散你的精力，使你不能忠诚于内心神灵的事物，都意味着你丧失了做一些其他事情的机会。所以，务必要让你的思绪远离那些无聊而杂乱无章的猜想，尤其是那种多管闲事、不够厚道的想法。人应该习惯于这样一种思维：当突然被问到“你此刻在想什么”的时候，能坦然而毫不犹豫地给出答案。由此可以证明他的思想单纯而友善，与社会人的身份相称，对感官刺激、妒忌、羡慕、猜疑，或其他自己羞于承认的情感不感兴趣。这种力争上游的人，堪当神灵的祭司和使者，因为他把内心的力量发挥到极致：享乐不辱其名，痛苦不伤其身，羞辱不移其情，邪恶不动其心。他参加的是所有比赛中最伟大的一项，即为摆脱情欲的操控而抗争。他的秉性纯粹正直，全心全意地迎接命运的降临。除非为了公众利益，很少去揣测别人的想法、说法和做法。他严格控制自己的活动，只关心自己的事情，专注宇宙大网中自己这根细丝，确保自己的行为是高尚的，坚信发生在自己身上的一切必定是最好的，因为指导他自己的命运之神必定按照更高层的指令行事。他不会忘记所有理性生物共有的手足之情，也不会忘记关怀每一个人正是人性的一种体现。他懂得不应该顺从世俗的观念，而是要追随那些与大自然和谐相处的人们的观点。对于那些生活不太有序的人，他时常提醒自己，要记住他们在家和在外、白天和晚上所展现的不同品质，要记住他们经常交往的社会阶层。这些人对自己评价都不高，那么就更不值得他来赞许。

5.在行动上，你应积极主动，手脚麻利，但也要考虑公众的利益；应深思熟虑，但不要优柔寡断。在感情上，你不要自命不凡地过于精雕细刻，不要喋喋不休，也不要多管闲事。在内心神灵的主宰下，你应该是一个充满阳刚之气、成熟稳健的人，一个政治家，一个罗马人，一个执政官。你应该是一个坚守立场，像一名在人生战场上待命撤退的战士，随时欢迎接替者。你应该是一个功劳无需自我宣扬，也无需他人评说的人。这就是内心快乐的秘密，不依赖外来帮助，也不祈求他人恩赐安宁的秘密。我们必须自己挺立于天地之间，而不是被别人扶植起来。

6.假如世俗生活能给你比正义、真理、自制和勇气更美好的东西（也就是说，在你的行为符合理性法则时能心境安宁，在无法控制的命运从天而降时能心境安宁），或者假如你能认清更加崇高的理想，那么你就全心全意地奔向它，并且为发现了自己的追求而欢欣鼓舞。然而，如果在你看来没有比你内心的神灵更美好的东西可以抑制你的每一次冲动，权衡你的每一个想法，弃绝（苏格拉底语）肉体对你的诱惑，公开宣布你效忠神灵、体恤民众，如果你通过比较发现其他一切都很卑微渺小，那么你就不应允许自己从事任何相反的追求。因为你一旦犹豫不决、改变方向，就再也不能坚守自己选择的理想了。其他任何雄心壮志都不能与理智和公民义务所具有的美好相提并论。哪怕是全世界的掌声、权力、财富和快乐，也无法与之相比。这些东西，也许暂时令我们颇觉适意，但它们很快就能占领上风、使人失去平衡。要我说，你干脆就选择最高的理想，并坚守下去。也许你会说：“可是，对我最有利的便是我的最高理想。”假如你作为一个具有理性的人，它对你最有利，那就坚守下去。但如果你仅仅作为一个动物，它对你也最有利，那就不妨直说，并谦卑地维持你的观点，只要确保你已经正确地探究过这个问题。

7.永远不要看重靠违背诺言、丧失自尊、仇恨、猜疑、诅咒他人、伪善等手段而获得的好处，也不要试图得到别人掩藏起来的东西。如果人优先考虑的是自己的思想、内心的神灵和对神灵的供奉，他就不会装腔作势，满腹牢骚，既不渴望独处也不追求热闹。最大的好处在于，他的生命将摆脱不停的追逐和躲避。他不在意自己的灵魂在尘世的躯体中存在的时间是长是短。此刻若是大限来临，他会从容向前，一如完成其他事情那样，淡然而有条不紊。生命中，他别无牵挂，只专注于不让自己的思想误入歧途，不要走上与有理性的公民背离的道路。

8.受过训诫和净化的心灵，不会有腐败的污渍、不洁的污点、生脓的毒疮。死亡不会在中途匆匆带走他的生命，如同演员未及演出结束便中途退场。他既不是卑微的奴仆，也不是纨绔子弟。他不依靠别人，也不离群索居。他无需躲闪，也不逃避任何责任。

9.要尊重你自己形成意见的能力。仅凭这种能力，你内心的舵手便能使你避免产生与天性不符、与理性人的天性不符的意见。这种能力能使你变得审慎细心，能使你跟同胞愉快相处，能使你与神的意志取得一致。

10.抛开其他一切，牢记下面的真理。记住，人只活在当下，活在这飞逝的瞬间。人生命的其余时间不是已经逝去，便是还未来临。这个尘世的生命微不足道，生活在地上的一个微不足道的角落。即便是最长久的身后之名，也同样微不足道。况且，有无这种身后之名，还要仰仗一代代很快凋零、同样微不足道的人们。他们对自己都不甚了解，更何况对那个早已逝去的生命呢。

11.除上所述，另有箴言一则。当一个事物出现在你面前时，你要在脑海中对它形成清晰的印象，至少要记住它的轮廓。这样才能辨明其基本特征，并透过分散的特征看清真实的整体结构。自己弄清这一事物本身，弄清组成这一事物并由这一事物再次分解的元素。没有比这种能力更能发展你的头脑了。它使你能系统而精确地审视生命中的每一种体验，将其分类，确定其目的、对宇宙的价值、对至尊之城（其他的城池都是至尊之城的住户）的成员——人类的价值。举例说明，比如我此刻脑海中出现的印象。它是什么，由什么构成，能存在多久？它需要我作出什么样的道德反应？是亲切、坚毅、率真、真诚、诚实、自立还是其他品质？面对各种情况，都要学会说：这是神的意愿；或者，这是命运的安排，是复杂网络中的一根细丝，是偶然事件的巧合；又或者，这是与我同宗同种的同胞手足的所作所为，只是他对本性的要求还茫然无知。而我自己却不能承认这样的无知，所以要本着源于本性的手足之情，与他和睦相处，如若不涉及是非善恶的问题，我同时还必须根据事情的是非曲直作出公正的判断。

12.在你完成一项任务之前，如果你能始终热情饱满、精力充沛、充满仁爱地严格遵循理性的原则，如果你能抛弃一切次要追求，保持内心纯洁诚实的神性（如同此刻就面对神的召唤），如果你能坚持谨守，不为任何事情停留，也不因任何事情畏缩，但求自己每一个行为都与自然契合，每次讲话能大胆地讲述实情，那么你的人生将是美好的。而且，无人能阻挡你按这一方针行事。

13.要像外科医生总是把柳叶刀和解剖刀放在手边以备不时之需那样，你要时刻铭记自己的准则以便理解有关神灵和俗世的事情。即便在最琐碎的行动中也不要忘记这二者之间的紧密联系，因为不参照神灵的事情，世俗的事情就不可能处理好，反之亦然。

14.不要再误导自己。你再也不会阅读那些笔记，罗马人和希腊人的陈年往事，或者特意为晚年收藏的作品精选。努力向前，直至尽头，抛开一切奢望。假如你对自己还有一丝尊敬，就要尽可能拯救自己。

15.他们完全不懂下列词汇的含义：偷窃、播种、购买、平静和明白职责。这需要用一种与肉眼不同的眼光来理解。

16.肉体、灵魂和思想：肉体负责感知，灵魂是行动的源泉，而思想则制定准则。然而，被圈着的公牛也会有感知能力。野兽、同性恋者、尼禄和法拉里斯也不会仅凭冲动行事。就连那些不信奉神灵的人、背叛祖国的人、背地里干尽坏事的人，也有思想指引他们走上负责的大路。记住：其他一切都是各色人等的共有特点。君子的非凡之处在于他以赞许的态度迎接命运给他编织的每一个经历；在于他拒绝玷污心中的神灵，拒绝用杂念打扰心中的神灵；在于他决意维护神灵的安宁，庄重得体地遵循神灵的教诲，承诺不说不实之词、不行不义之事。他过着简朴而自尊的幸福生活，即便因此遭到世人的怀疑，他也不对任何人心生怨恨。他仍然坚定不移地走向生命的终点，在使命驱使下纯洁安详地到达终点，完美和谐地领受命运的分派，心甘情愿地离开。

卷四

1.若内心的主宰力量忠实于自然之道，它就能根据环境提供的各种可能与机遇随时调整自己。它不要求先决条件，为达目的也愿意妥协，并能将各种阻碍自己前进的事物转化为对自己有用的东西。好比垃圾堆上燃起的篝火，原本也许会湮灭成微弱的火光，但是它的烈焰迅速蔓延至整堆垃圾，烧尽整堆垃圾，升腾起更高的火焰。

2.从事任何事业都不可随意，不可无视那些确保其能正确执行的原则。

3.人们向往归隐荒野、海滨或崇山峻岭。这实在是人们心里珍藏的梦想。不过，这样的梦想对于一个哲人来说毫无价值，因为他若愿意可随时归隐于心。人无法寻找比自己的灵魂更宁静、更不受打扰的隐退之所了。更重要的是，他自身就具备这样的条件，只需凝神静思便能立即获得内心的宁静。这种宁静不过是井然有序的内心世界的别称而已。那么经常采用这种归隐方法吧，用它来不断更新自己。制定简练的生活准则，但要包含基本原则。时常温习它们，就可以平息一切烦恼，使你无忧无虑地回到应尽的职责中去。

说到底，你为何烦恼？因为人类的不端行为？要记住这一信条：一切理性生物天生要相互依存；容忍也是正义的一部分；人非有意为恶。想想看，无数的仇视、猜疑、憎恨、冲突都已随知情者灰飞烟灭，你就不要再烦恼了。

或许，是宇宙对你的安排让你烦心？再回忆一下两难推理法吧：“若非英明的神意，便是一团微粒。”想想看，大量的证据证明世界犹如一座城池。你是否因身体不适而感到痛苦？想想看，思想只有离开肉体时才认识到自己的力量，与生活中的顺畅与艰难完全无关。总之，想一下你所学到并领会的所有关于痛苦与快乐的知识。

又或许，是泡沫般虚幻的声望使你分心？记住，遗忘就在你的眼前迅速开始；记住，我们身前身后都是永恒的深渊；记住，那些喝彩的回声是多么空洞，那些自称是仰慕者的评价是多么反复无常而缺乏水准，世俗声望的传播范围又是多么狭小。整个大地不过是一个小点，而我们居住的地方又是其中极小的一个角落。那么能有多少人赞美你？而他们又是怎样的人呢？

所以，归隐到自己内心那一方小天地吧。最要紧的是，绝不要抗争或较劲，而要做自己的主人，像个男子汉，像个人，像个公民，像个凡人那样面对生活。真理如云，不如经常思考以下两条：其一，事物永远不可能触及灵魂，只是迟钝地站在灵魂之外，唯有无端的猜想才会引起灵魂的不安；其二，所有看得见的事物时刻都在变化，并终将不复存在；想想自己身上发生的无数变化。整个宇宙都在变，生活本身即是你对它的看法[6]。

4.如果人类普遍具有思考能力，那么也就普遍具有理性，由此我们也就成为理性生物。因此可以断定，告诫我们“应该做什么”或“不应该做什么”的理性也同样具有普遍性。这就是一种普世法则。反过来，它说明我们都是同胞，享有共同的公民资格，而这个世界就是一个城市。世上还有其他的公民资格可供全人类分享吗？正是从这共同的世界中产生了思维、理性、法律本身。要不然，还能从何而来？我身上土性的部分来自土地，水性的部分来自水，风来自风，而炙热的火性则来自火（因为无中不能生有，也不能归于无），所以思想必定也有来源。

5.死亡，如同出生，是大自然的一个秘密。同样的元素组合在一起，再分解开来，全然没有值得羞愧的地方。对于具有理性思维的生物来说，这既不反常，也没有违背人生的法则。

6.什么样的人行什么样的事，这是必然的。如果希望世事不是这样，就如同希望无花果树不产生浆汁一样不现实。无论如何都要记住：你和他很快就会去世，而你们的大名也将很快被人遗忘。

7.抛开“我被冤屈”的念头，冤屈感自然也会随之消失。拒绝受伤的感觉，伤痛也会消失。

8.不能腐蚀人的，也就不会腐蚀他的生活，不会对他造成任何损害，无论是外在的还是内在的。

9.集体权宜的法则促成了这种情况的发生。

10.任何事情的发生都有其合理性。仔细观察一下，就会发现此话千真万确。一桩桩事件之间，不仅存在先后顺序，还存在一种公道合理的秩序，好像有一只手让它们各就各位似的。那么，你不妨继续观察下去，让善意伴随着你的每一个举动。无论你做什么，都要注意这一点。

11.莫要仿效骄傲自大者的看法，也不要让他们的看法支配你的思想，而要按照事物的本来面貌观察事物。

12.时刻谨记以下两点：其一，只听从理性（我们的主宰和立法者）的建议，做有利于公共福祉的事情；其二，假如有人当场纠正你，并能说服你你的判断有误，你就应该重新考虑自己的决定。但是这种改变的出发点，必须是正义、公益，或其他类似的利益。这必须是唯一的考虑，而不是为了追求享受或声望。

13.“你有理性吗？”“有。”那为什么不用它呢？如果理性发挥了作用，夫复何求？

14.你生来便是宇宙的一部分。你将消失在赐予你生命的宇宙中。更准确地说，你将再次化入宇宙的创造者理性之中。

15.许多香灰落在同一个祭坛上：有的早些，有的晚些，但这没有任何区别。

16.你只要回归到原本的教义中，回归到对理性的崇敬中，用不了一周，那些现在将你归入野兽和猴子之流的人们便会尊你为神。

17.活着的时候不要以为还有千年可活。死亡近在咫尺。趁着还有时间和能力，好自为之吧。

18.—个人只要不理会别人说什么、做什么、想什么，只关心自己的行为是否公正虔诚，他就必然拥有充裕的时间和安逸的心境。有德之人从不窥探别人的污点，只会坚定不移地朝自己的目标努力。

19.为身后之名而血脉偾张的人没有思考过下面的事实：所有记得他的人不久都会离开人世，随着时间的推移，他们的后代也会离去，即使在传递之际曾闪闪发亮，最终记忆的火光也将熄灭。何况，即便那些人都能长生不死，他们的记忆也不会消亡，这对你又有何意义？对坟墓中的你显然毫无意义。即便在你的有生之年，赞美之词，除非能对某些目的有所帮助，可对你又有何用？所以，如果你一心想知道未来人们对你的评价，必定会不合时宜地拒绝现在大自然所赋予你的一切。

20.但凡称得上美的事物，其美皆源于自身，无需旁求。赞美却不是这样，它既不能使事物变得更坏，也不能使其变得更好。即便是极为平常的美，比如自然物体或艺术品，也是如此。真正的美还需要别的条件吗？当然不需要。有法律、真理、仁慈或谦虚，就已足够。这些美德会因赞美而增色，或因谴责而受损吗？绿宝石会因为没人欣赏而有损其美吗？黄金、象牙、紫色呢？七弦竖琴或短剑呢？玫瑰花蕾或小树苗呢？

21.如果人死后灵魂真能不灭，那么自时间伊始，我们头上的天空如何能容纳这么多的灵魂？而地面又如何能容纳自古至今这么多肉体？肉体入土之后很快会腐烂变质，为后面的肉体腾出了空间。同样地，升入空中的灵魂停留一段时间之后也会产生变化，弥漫开来，继而转化成火，重回宇宙的创造理性之中。这样，腾出的空间便可以接纳其他灵魂。这便是信奉灵魂不灭者的答案。况且，我们不能光计算人类肉体的数量，还要包括每天被我们和其他动物吞噬的所有生物。以这种方式消亡，从某种意义上说是被葬在动物或人的体内，并为它们提供营养。如果这样的话，这个数量该有多么庞大！不过，随着它们被融入血液，再转变成空气或火，这样，所需的空间就都具备了。

我们又是如何发现这些真相的呢？就是通过区别问题和根源。

22.绝不要让自己过分激动。一旦冲动发生，首先要保证它符合正义的要求。一旦形成某种看法，首先要使自己确信其正确。

23.世界啊，我始终亦步亦趋追随您伟大的和谐。只要对您合乎时宜，对我就恰逢其时。大自然啊，您四季生产的作物便是我的收获。万物皆源于此，长于此，归于此。当诗人高喊：“伟大的刻克洛普斯之城！”时，但愿我们不必一起高呼“伟大的神灵之城！”

24.圣人说：“假如懂得知足，就该少些作为。”也许这样更好：只做非做不可的事情，只做理性要求公民必须做的事情，只按照它所要求的去做。这样，你会产生一种做事少而精的满足感。其实，我们的言行大都可有可无，省去一些不仅节约了时间还省去了烦恼。因此，人每走一步都应自问：“这件事非做不可吗？”而且，我们不仅要抑制无聊的行为，还要抑制无聊的想法，这样不必要的事情就不会发生。

25.考验一下自己是否能像有德之人那样生活。他们满足于宇宙对他的安排，只求为人公正，处事仁慈。

26.“这一切[7]你都看到了吗？”现在这样想想：你的角色应该是性情安详、为人质朴单纯。是别人做错了吗？错误在于他自身。你遇到什么事情了吗？很好，这就是普遍的命运对你的安排，这种安排早在时间伊始便已注定。它和发生的其他事情一样，都是特意为你编织的命运之网的一部分。总之，生命短暂，遵从理性和正义的指引，珍惜如梭的时光吧。放松心情，但要有节制。

27.宇宙要么井然有序，要么是杂乱无章、随意拼凑起来、勉强成形的一团混沌。不过，你身上是否也存在着某种有序，同时从更大的整体看来却又无序？自然的各个部分尽管千差万别，可是它们之间是否又关联一体呢？

28.—颗黑暗的心！一颗任性妇人之心；一颗残暴之心，一颗野兽之心；幼稚、愚蠢而虚伪；一颗贪婪之心，一颗暴君之心。

29.如果说不了解宇宙中存在什么的人就是不懂得宇宙，那么不了解宇宙中发生什么的人同样也不懂得宇宙。这样的人是一个从理性王国自我放逐的流亡者，是一个失去自己洞察力的睁眼瞎，是一个自身没有生活来源、依附他人生活的贫民。当他拒绝接受自己的命运（毕竟，命运也是产生了他自己的大自然的一种产物），从而割裂、割断其与我们共同的自然法则的联系时，他便是世界的一个累赘。当他将自己的灵魂与全体理性生物共有的灵魂割断，任其漂泊时，他便是从整体截去的一段残肢。

30.—位哲人无衫，另一位无书，还有一位衣衫仅遮住一半身体，他说：“虽无面包果腹，我依然坚守理性。”对我来说，虽然学无所成，但依然坚持不辍。

31.要热爱自己所学的专业，从中汲取养分。像全心侍奉神灵的人那样度过余生，从此既不做他人的主人，也不为他人的奴仆。

32.让我们回想一下维斯帕先统治的时代。你看到了什么？男人和女人忙于婚配、抚养子女、患病、垂死、争斗、吃喝、讨价还价、耕作、阿谀奉承、自吹自擂、相互妒忌、筹划诡计、诅咒谩骂、怨天尤人、谈情说爱、积存钱财、觊觎王位。如此这般的生活，今天踪影全无。再看看图拉真统治的时代。那样的生活，今天同样不复存在。同样再看看其他时代和人物的记录，你会看到他们每一个人经过短暂的奋斗，都已逝去并化作各种元素。特别是，回想一下那些你所熟知的人。他们不是满足于坚定履行上天赋予的职责，而是追慕虚荣。在这种情况下，我们有必要提醒自己，对任何事物价值的追求，都取决于事物本身的实际价值。所以，想要避免受挫，切忌过分沉溺于那些并不最为紧要的事情。

33.曾经风行一时的用语如今已经废弃不用。曾经家喻户晓的名字如今也成了陈年古语。卡米卢斯、恺撒、沃勒塞斯、利奥拉图斯，还有更近一些的斯奇比奥和加图、奥古斯都，甚至哈德良和安东尼纳斯。一切都已成为历史传说，不久便会被人忘却。即便是那些曾熠熠生辉的人物也会如此。至于其他人，他们刚刚吐出最后一口气便如同荷马所说的那样：“同样消失在世人眼中，成了传闻。”不朽的英名究竟是什么呢？不过是空洞虚无的东西。那么，我们应该追求什么呢？只能是：公正的思想、无私的行为、真实的话语，把世间发生的一切看作命中注定，预料之中，来自同一源泉。

34.心甘情愿地把自己交给命运之神克洛索，任凭她编织你的生命之线。

35.我们都是这一天的造物，记忆者和被记忆者都一样。

36.仔细观察世间万物如何源源不断地产生于变化之中。认识到大自然最崇高的幸福蕴藏于事物的变化之中，变化的事物依其本性又形成新的事物。可以说，世间万物都是孕育新事物的种子。如果认为只有种在土地里或子宫里的才是种子，这样的人成不了哲学家。

37.你将不久于人世，却依旧不能专心致志，不能摆脱烦躁，还不能对外界危害漠不关心，对所有人怀有仁慈之心，也不相信秉公做事才是唯一的智慧。

38.悉心观察指引着智者行为的力量，看看他们在避免什么，又在追求什么。

39.对你而言，邪恶并非来自他人的心灵，也非源于你自己身体构成的任何变化。那么，它从何而来？它来自你心中对邪恶的评估。拒绝评估，便会万事大吉。让这种评估者的声音保持沉默吧，哪怕紧靠它的可怜的躯体被划破或灼烧，化脓或坏死。不要让这种声音评价善恶，无论对好人还是坏人。这是因为，无论人们是否遵从自然法则，只要事情公正地发生在他们身上，就既不会阻碍也不会促进自然之道。

40.要始终把宇宙看作一个拥有单一物质和单一灵魂的鲜活有机体。好好观察一切事物是如何服从于这一整体特有的洞察力，如何在这一整体的驱使下运动，如何在每一事件的因果关系中发挥作用的。一根根的线是如此错综复杂地交织在一个网络里。

41.“一个受着肉体拖累的可怜的灵魂。”埃皮克提图如是说。

42.处在改变过程中不是件坏事。同样，成为改变的结果也算不上是件好事情。

43.时间是一条河流，不可抗拒地带走一切神的创造。一个事物刚一出现便匆匆而逝，另一个事物接踵而至，但照样要被时间的河水卷走。

44.一切事都是平常而熟悉的，如同春天的玫瑰和夏天的果实。疾病、死亡、诽谤、阴谋，以及其他给蠢人带来快乐和烦恼的事情，也是如此。

45.后面的事情总与前面的事情紧密相关。它们并非是先后发生的一连串孤立事件，而是密切联系着的。而且，正如现存的事物都彼此和谐地联系在一起，将要发生的事情也表现出同样惊人的相互关联，而绝非一种单纯的接续过程。

46.要永远铭记赫拉克利特的名言：“土之死乃水之生，水之死乃气之生，气复生火，如此循环往复。”还要记住他的话：“徒步旅行者忘记了脚下的路通往何方”，“人总是跟自己最亲近的伙伴过不去”（主宰宇宙的理性），“尽管天天碰到，却依然当作陌生的事物”，“我们说话做事不能像睡着的人那样”（因为睡着的人的确会想象自己是在说话做事），也不能“像孩童模仿家长说话一样”。也就是说，不能盲目地信赖传统的格言。

47.假如一位神祇对你说：“明天，或者最迟后天，你将离开人世。”除非你是最绝望无助的人，否则你不会特别介意这一天究竟是后天还是明天。因为，这二者又有什么区别呢？同样，也不要认为多年以后来临还是明天来临有多大区别。

48.要时常记起那些已故的医生，他们曾经为患者的病痛绞尽脑汁。要时常记起那些占星家，他们曾经十分严肃地预言人的命运。要时常记起那些哲学家，他们曾经不厌其烦地论述着死亡和不朽的命题。要时常记起那些杰出的指挥官，他们曾经杀敌无数。要时常记起那些暴君，他们曾经极其狂傲地操纵着生死予夺的大权，俨然把自己当作永生的神灵。还要时常记起已经毁灭的赫利凯、庞贝、赫库兰尼姆和不计其数的其他城市。然后，再逐一回忆自己熟悉的人，他们是如何在短短的时间内一个埋葬了另一个，自己又被第三个埋葬的。总之，看看尘世的生活是如此的短暂而琐碎：昨日还是一滴精液，明日就化作一撮灰。所以，听从自然的召唤度过飞逝的尘世时光，然后心甘情愿地长眠于地下，如同一颗橄榄恰逢其时地落在地上，给养育它的大地带去祝福，向赐予它生命的树干表达感激。

49.要像那被海浪一次次拍打的岬角：屹立在水中，直至四周喧嚣的波浪重新恢复平静。“我是如此不幸，这样的事情竟然降临到我头上！”绝不要这样想。你不妨说：“我多么幸运，事情过去了，我却没感受到痛苦，现在没有使我动摇，未来也不会使我灰心。”事情可能发生在任何人身上，可并非人人都能摆脱痛苦。因此，为何要把它看成是一种不幸，而不是一种幸运呢？任何事情只要不违背人的本性，又怎么能称为不幸？只要没有违背本性的意志，又怎么能说违背了人的本性？好了，你已经了解本性的意志了。难道你所经历的事情会阻碍你实现人性的追求：成为一个正直、宽容、有节制、明智、审慎、诚实、自尊而独立的人？因此，以后每当有事使你感到痛苦时，记住这样一条准则：不要说“这是一种不幸”，而要说“经受住它的考验是一种幸运”。

50.想想那些贪生怕死的人吧，这是除了哲学之外，能帮助人漠视死亡的一种有效方法。比起英年早逝的人，这些人又得到了什么好处呢？这些人，无一例外都于某时某地被掩埋入土。克迪斯亚卢斯、费比乌斯、尤利安、雷比达等，他们见证了无数人走向坟墓，到头来自己也未能幸免。他们能拖延的时间毕竟不长，在这种情况下苟延残喘，既连累了众人，又弄惨了自己的身体。所以，要漠视死亡，看看身后时间的深渊，永无尽头的将来。在这种情况下，长寿的内斯特和仅活三天的婴儿又有什么不同呢？

51.始终要走近路，近路是本性之路，以追求言行的完全公正为目标。这种目标能使你避免焦虑和冲突，远离妥协和诡计。

卷五

1.清晨看见第一缕阳光，尽管不愿意起床，心里也要这样想：“我要起来去工作。”去做天生应该做的事情，这是我降临人世的目的，难道应该有怨言吗？难道我的人生目的就是暖洋洋地盖着毯子睡觉吗？“可是这样多么舒适！”那么，你生来就是为了舒服，而不是为了工作，为了奋斗？看看那些植物、麻雀、蚂蚁、蜘蛛和蜜蜂吧。它们都在忙于工作，都在为紧凑的世界秩序贡献自己的力量。可你却要拒绝人的分内工作，不立刻听从自然的召唤吗？“可人也得休息呀。”这我同意，可是本性规定休息要有限度，正如吃饭、喝水要有限度一样。而你已经超过了这些限度，远远超出足够的程度。另一方面，没有行动，就不可能有收获。

你并不真心爱自己。如果你真爱自己，你一定会热爱自己的本性，热爱本性的意愿去做。爱岗敬业的手艺人愿意穷其精力埋头苦干，达到不洗脸、不吃饭的程度。而你对自己的本性缺乏尊重，远不如雕刻者尊重其雕刻，舞蹈者尊重其舞蹈，守财奴珍视其财宝，或者虚荣者爱慕其荣耀。那些人全心全意地投入，为追求更高的境界而甘愿废寝忘食。为社会服务在你眼中就这么没有价值，不值得为之奉献吗？

2.啊，能摆脱并遗忘所有让人烦心的念头，转瞬之间得到彻底的安宁，这是多么让人欣慰的事情呀！

3.保留你合于本性的言行，哪怕可能招致批评和非议也不要放弃它们。只要有善行可做、有良言可说，就绝不放弃这样的权利。批评你的人自有他们的道理和动机。你的注意力不能被他们分散，要始终直视前方，按自己的本性和普遍本性行事（这两者其实是一回事）。

4.我遵循自然之道前行，直至倒地安息。我吐出最后一口我每天吸入的气息，然后倒在这片土地上。这片土地，使我父亲获得了种子，使我母亲获得了血液，使我乳母获得了哺育我的乳汁。这片土地，年复一年地供我一日三餐，虽被如此滥用，却依然忍受着我的践踏。

5.你绝不可能以机敏著称。那就认命吧。但你还可以拥有很多别的优点，你总不能说：“我对这些不感兴趣。”好好培养那些你完全能够做到的美德，比如：真诚和尊严，勤劳和清醒。不要牢骚满腹。要生活节俭，为人体贴、周到而又坦率。要言辞温和，举止威严。看看，眼前你就可以拥有这么多优点。你可不能以天生无能或天资笨拙为借口，选择在那不太高尚的层面继续徘徊。难道缺少先天条件，你就一定要牢骚满腹、极度吝啬、溜须拍马，一定要抱怨身体欠佳，一定要卑躬屈膝、乱夸海口、喜怒无常？肯定不是。你早就应该改正这些缺点了，这样除了理解力有些迟钝之外，你在其他方面就无可指责了。即使理解力迟钝这一点，也可以通过练习得到纠正，只要你不再轻视它，或者自甘迟钝。

6.有这样一种人，他们帮了你一点忙，便迫不及待地向你邀功请赏。还有一种人，虽然不像前者那样过分，但是暗地里认为你欠他的人情，并且把自己的功劳记得清清楚楚。然而，还有一种人，我们不妨说，他们完全意识不到自己的贡献，就像那长葡萄的藤蔓，理所应当地结出了果实，却不求更多的回报，就像跑完比赛的赛马、追逐到猎物的猎犬、酿制了蜂蜜的蜜蜂一样。同样，这种人做了好事也不会大肆宣扬，而是接着去做下一件，如同葡萄藤来年夏季会继续结出硕果一样。

“照你这么说，我们都应该这样默默无闻地做事情吗？”正是。而且，我们要有意识地这么要求自己。俗话说得好：“意识到自己的行为具有社会性正是一个公民的标志。”“那么，希望社会能意识到自己的行为，这也是公民的标志吗？”没错。但是你误解了这句箴言的意思，从而把自己等同于我前面描述的那些人，他们同样也被一种似是而非的理性误导了。要正确理解这句箴言的真正含义，这样你就不用担心它会诱使你忘记自己的社会责任了。

7.雅典人这样祈祷：“下雨吧，下雨吧。尊贵的宙斯，请把雨水降临到雅典的田地和平原上吧。”要么就根本不要祈祷，要祈祷就应该这样简洁明了。

8.正如我们所说：“医神艾斯库雷普开过骑马锻炼、冷水浴或赤脚走路这样的处方。”同样地，普遍本性也开出了疾病、断肢、损伤或其他残疾的处方。前者是为了患者的健康而采用一种特定的治疗方法，后者则是为了我们的命运而遭遇的特定事件。实际上，我们不妨说是“遇到了”不幸，如同石匠们说，砌成石墙或金字塔的方形石块是“遇到了”彼此。这种相互整合是宇宙的普遍规律。无数个体组成一个大写的个体，这就是世界。无数的原因组成一个大写的原因，这就是命运。即使普通百姓也懂得这些，他们会说：“事情落到了他的身上。”事情的确是落到了他的身上。也就是说，这是专门为他开的处方。那么，让我们接受诸如此类的事情吧，就像我们接受医神的处方那样。良药通常苦口，但是为了健康，我们也会欣然吞下。同样，我们也应该把执行和完成自然的命令看作是为了身体的健康：即便降临的命运再苦涩，为了宇宙的健康，为了宙斯神的福祉和善举，我们依然要高高兴兴地承受。若非为了整个世界的福祉，神绝不会将此降临给个人。自然不会让其治下的臣民遭受任何灾难，除非是专门为了使其受益。所以，基于下面两个原因，你应该心甘情愿地接受自己身上发生的事情。原因之一，你身上发生的事情是特别为你定制的，与你息息相关，是纷繁复杂的原始因果关系中的一部分。原因之二，每一个人的命运都关系到宇宙主宰者的兴衰、成败，甚至存亡。在原因或其他元素的链接中，任何一环脱落，哪怕是很微小的一环，都会伤及整体。每当你感到不满时，你都是在你有限的能力范围内，对整体造成这样的损害和割裂。

9.如果戒律有时得不到施行，不要痛苦，不要沮丧，更不要绝望。每次失败后再重新开始。只要在多数情况下自己总体上具有男人应有的风范，就应该心怀感激。但要真心热爱你所回归的戒律：对待自己的人生哲学不能像小学生对待老师那样，而是要像眼痛病人对待蛋黄涂剂和海绵，或者别的病人对待膏药和洗剂一样。唯有如此，你对理性的遵从才能成为私人的慰藉，而不会沦为公开的卖弄。要记住，哲学只以你自己本性的意志为意志，而你却把其他有违本性的东西当作自己的意志。“没错，可是还有什么事情能让人倍感愉悦呢？”以愉悦为诱因不就是为了迷惑你吗？好好想想吧：难道高尚的灵魂不更令人愉悦吗？难道公正、朴素、仁慈和虔诚不让人更加倍感愉悦吗？当你进行严密而流畅的推理和认知时，还有什么比这样的智力活动更令人愉快的？

10.真理总是隐藏在朦胧晦涩之中，以至许多声名显赫的哲学家[8]都曾断言无法探知。甚至斯多葛派哲学家也承认获得真理困难重重，承认我们思考得出的结论都有可能出错。确实，哪里有绝对不出错的人呢？我们不妨把目光转向更客观的事物，看看它们是多么瞬息万变，又毫无用处，因为每个肆意挥霍的人、放荡的妇人、犯罪的人都可能得到它们。再看看你同伴的性格：连他们之中脾气最随和的人都让你难以忍受，更别说容忍自己有多困难了。因此，在这种昏暗的泥潭之中，在存在与时间之河不停歇地流淌之中，在强加的变化之中，我想不出有什么东西更值得高度珍视和郑重追寻。没有。我们所要做的便是勉励自己静候它的自然消亡，同时不要因其姗姗来迟而心烦意乱，而要从以下两方面寻求安慰：其一，我们从未发生过违背本性的事情；其二，避免违背心中神灵的力量就掌握在我自己手中，因为世上没人能强迫我去违背。

11.我该如何运用灵魂的力量呢？每走一步都要这样自省，然后自问：“灵魂与我身上所谓的主宰部分如何相处呢？此时此刻，我拥有的是谁的灵魂呢？孩童的、少年的、妇人的、暴君的、不会说话的公牛的，还是野兽的？”

12.可以这样[9]来验证时下流行的“财富”概念。如果一个人把财富界定为审慎、节制、正义和坚韧，那么，他就不会留意那种关于“许多财富”的老掉牙的笑话，因为这种笑话没有一点意义。反过来，假如他对财富的构成也持有庸俗的看法，他就必然欣赏说笑者的诙谐，毫不费力能领会其中的妙处。实际上，大部分人都抱有这样的价值观，不会拒绝听这样的俏皮话，听了也不生气。如果把财富只理解为物质财产或其他奢侈、讲排场的东西，我们的确应该承认这则笑话是一种恰当而机智的见解。因此，现在考验就来了：问问自己，假如我们内心对事物的描绘赋予了“财富多到使其拥有者无处容身的地步”这一嘲讽现实的意义，那么我们是否还应该看重它们，并将其视为“财富”。

13.我是由因缘和物质构成的。两者皆不能消逝转化为无，正如它们都不是从无而来一样。所以说，我的各个组成部分有朝一日都会转变为宇宙中其他的部分，其他部分再依次转变为另外的部分，如此循环直至无穷。我本身也是通过同样的过程来到人世，我的父母也是如此，往前再循环到无穷。（纵然世界本是由无穷的循环所主宰，“无穷”一词本身也会消失。）

14.理性，还有推理，在属性和运作方式上都具有自给自足的功能。它们来源于自身，自己产生原始的动力，并且径直奔向自己选定的目标。由此产生的行为被称为“一往无前”，是说其运行的路线不偏离正道。

15.除非事物从属于人，否则就不能合理地称其为人所有。它们不需要人，因为人的本性既不能保障它们，也不会因它们而变得完美。所以，它们不可能代表人生的首要目标，甚至也算不上实现这一目标的“有效”途径。况且，假如人的自然传承中包括这样的事物，就不可能同时又蔑视和抛弃它们，那种没有它们照样能成功的能力也就没有值得赞扬的理由。倘若它们的确很好，不能完全拥有它们也不见得就不好。实际上，类似的事物，人类失去得越多，获得的美德就越多。

16.你的心灵会和你平时的思想一样，因为思想会将灵魂染上自己的颜色。那么，沉浸在这样的思考中吧，比如：如果能生活，就一定存在好的生活；如果在宫廷生活，即使在宫廷中也一定存在好的生活。或者这样想：每一事物产生的目的决定它的发展；它的发展指向它的最终状态，最终状态又暗示着它的主要优点。所以说，理性人的首要优点，是与人友好相处。友好相处是产生我们的目的，这在很久以前就已经明确了。（低等事物为高等事物而存在，而高等事物为彼此而存在，这难道不是显而易见的吗？有生命的比无生命的高级，而理性生物则更高一等。）

17.追求得不到的东西是愚蠢，然而愚蠢的人却不可能不进行这样的追求。

18.如果其本性没有使某人具备承受能力，事情就不会发生在他的身上。别人与你的经历毫无差别。不过，抑或他还不完全明白所发生的事情，抑或他更渴望展示自己的勇气，他坚定不移，无所畏惧。真是怪事，无知和虚荣竟然比智慧更强大！

19.外在的事物丝毫不能触及人的灵魂。它们不知晓通往灵魂的路径，也没有能力动摇或者改变灵魂。只有灵魂自身的力量才能使其动摇或改变。灵魂有自己的判断标准，并用这些标准安排它控制下的外界事物。

20.—方面，仁爱对我影响很深，使我注定要善待、宽容我的同胞。另一方面，就他人对我正当行为的束缚而言，仁爱就像太阳、风，或野兽一样对我漠不关心。的确，别人也许能束缚我的某些行为，但无法阻止我的意志和性情，因为意志和性情能使我有所保留而始终保护自己，使自己适应各种情况。心灵能克服一切限制行动的障碍，将其转化成实现主要目标的促进力量。这样一来，任何障碍都能变成助力，路上遇到的层层关卡也会变成推动前进的手段。

21.在宇宙中有至高无上的东西。它使其他一切都处于从属地位，它将自己置于其他一切之上。同样，在你的内心也有至高无上的东西。在你内心，它与前者一样，使其他一切都处于从属地位，它指引着你的人生。

22.对城市无害的东西也不会有害于市民。当假设有危害时，要遵循这样的原则：“如果城市不会受到危害，我也一样不会受到危害。”然而，一旦城市真的受到危害，决不要迁怒于加害者，而要找出他错在哪里。

23.要时常想想，现存的一切事物和将要出现的一切事物，从我们眼前经过和消逝的速度是多么迅速。存在这条大河，一直奔流不息，它的活动一直在变化，它的缘起缘落无穷地在转化，几乎没有一个事物静止不动。同时，无穷也出现在过去和未来：一切都将消逝于这一深渊。如此说来，一个人如果总是愤忿、困扰或烦躁，似乎他的苦恼会持续很久，那么他就是愚不可及。

24.想想世间万物，自己只是其中微乎其微的一部分；想想古往今来的时间长河，属于自己的只是那么转瞬即逝的一段；想想恢宏的天命，自己的命运只是其中微不足道的一部分。

25.有人错待我吗？让他自己留意吧，他清楚自己的脾气和所作所为。而我，只是接受普遍本性要我接受的东西，做自己本性要我做的事情。

26.无论是痛苦还是快乐，都不要让情感影响至高无上的、独立自主的灵魂。务必不要让灵魂受它们的影响。心灵必须固守自己的领地，使情感不能超越应有的范围。万一感情（通过任何完整的生物都怀有的同情）弥漫到心灵，也不必试图压抑肉体的感受。只是，主宰心灵的理智不要妄自猜测情感的善与恶。

27.与神灵一起生活。与神灵一起生活，意味着要时刻向神灵展示自己的灵魂；满足于神灵的赐予，全心全意实现那个内心神灵的意愿，那个自身微粒的意愿。那微粒就是心灵与理性，为宙斯所赐，供每个人掌管和引导自己的行动。

28.有腋臭和口臭的人让你感到恼火吗？你这样有何益处？但凡长了这样的口腔和腋窝，就必然会发出这种气味。“不论怎样，这人毕竟还有理性，他只要想想就完全会明白自己遭嫌弃的原因。”那好吧。可你自己也是有理性的人，用你的理性去影响他，使之产生同样的理性，详细地为他讲解，耐心地提出劝告。如果他肯听，你就治愈他。没有必要感情用事，让那些戏子和妓女去感情用事吧。

29.如果你想今后继续生活在世上，这并非不可能。如果人家不允许，就放弃这生命的躯壳，只是不要感觉受了虐待。“茅屋起火则弃之。”无需小题大做。然而，如果没有类似的事情迫使我离开，我依然是自己的主人，什么都无法阻止我自己的选择，即按照本性对一个有理性的社会成员的要求去生活。

30.宇宙的理性具有社会性。不管怎样，它创造出低等事物以服务于高等事物，并把高等事物联系在一起形成相互依赖的关系。注意观察，有些事物隶属于别的事物，其他一些事物则彼此相联，所有事物都各得其所，更为高级的事物则彼此和谐相处。

31.从前你是怎样侍奉神灵，对待父母、兄弟、妻子、儿女、老师、朋友、亲戚和仆役的呢？有诗云：“决不说一句刻薄话，绝不委屈一个人。”迄今为止，上述这些关系中，哪些能真正引起你对这句诗的共鸣呢？想想你所经历的一切，所忍受的一切。深思之后要明白，你的生命篇章已经结束，你的服务之旅走到了尽头。想想自己看到过的美景，藐视过的痛苦与欢乐，你所不屑的众多荣耀，以及以德报了多少怨。

32.没有本领、没有学问的人怎么可能困扰行家和圣人呢？什么人才真正称得上是行家和圣人呢？只有这样的人，他懂得万物的开始与结束，懂得无处不在的理性以特定的周期管理着宇宙，直至时间的终点。

33.转瞬之间，你将化为尘土或白骨，只留下一个名字，甚至连一个名字也没有留下，纵然彼时名字也不过是空洞的回响而已。人们毕生倾心追求的不过是虚荣、腐朽和垃圾。人们好比打成一团的小狗，或者争吵不休的孩童，刚才还笑容满面，转眼便泪水涟涟。信任和宽容、正义和真理，都“从广袤的大地飞上了高高的奥林匹斯山”。那么，是什么让你还留在这里？感官对象变化无常、转瞬即逝，感觉器官迟钝又易被误导，不幸的灵魂不过是血液里升腾起的蒸汽[10]，举世的赞誉不过是幻梦一场。那该怎么办？振作起来，等待结局，不管这一结局是消亡还是转化。那么，你认为大限来临前我们需要做什么呢？只有心怀敬畏、向神灵祈福；只有善待人们；只有忍受和克制；还要记住：除了区区肉体和气息之外，一切都不属于你，不在你的掌控之中。

34.稳步前行，沿着笔直的大道去思考和行动，你今后的岁月将一帆风顺。人的灵魂和其他理性生物的灵魂一样，与神灵的灵魂有两点共同之处：它永远不会被外来力量挫败；它的善包括品格和行为的端正，以及对一切欲望的控制。

35.假如这件事不是我的过错，也不是因我的过错而起，而社会也不会因此而变得更糟，那何必再为此耗费心思？它怎么可能危害社会呢？

36.不要过于草率地相信第一印象。向需要帮助的人们伸出援助之手，只要你力所能及而他们也值得你帮助。不过，要是他们并非在道德上栽了大跟头，你就不要认为他们真正受到了伤害，因为那并非是一个善举。但在这种情况下，应该像一个老头在临终前总不断回忆他童年的拨浪鼓，尽管他知道那不过是一只拨浪鼓[11]。

我的朋友，当你站在讲台上大喊大叫拉选票的时候，是否忘记了它的终极价值？“我知道，可是这些人如此重视它。”这不是证明你和他们一样愚蠢吗？

无论被流放到多么偏僻荒凉的地方，我始终都是命运的宠儿。所谓命运的宠儿，即是获得命运之神恩赐的人，这些恩赐是良好的性情，善良的动机和善意的行为。

卷六

1.宇宙的物质灵活而顺从。主宰物质的理性无意为恶，因为理性本身没有恶意，不会蓄意伤害，也不会构成伤害。万事万物皆依照它的指令产生，并获得完满。

2.只要自己行为端正，就决不要在意自己被冻得发僵，还是置身温暖的火旁；睡眼蒙眬，还是刚从梦中醒来；遭到谩骂还是受到赞扬；濒临死亡，还是忙于其他事务（因为就连死亡也是人生事务的一部分，对我们的要求无非是“确保眼前的任务圆满完成”）。

3.要透过表面看本质：绝不要让事情的本质特征或价值逃过你的眼睛。

4.一切有形物体的变化都非常迅速：要么升华（假如宇宙的物质确是一个统一体），要么消散。

5.理性这一主宰，对各种环境、目的及其所需的材质了如指掌。

6.避免模仿就是最好的报复。

7.有神灵常驻心间，就能把你一次次为公众效力的快乐和舒畅传递下去。

8.我们理性的主宰，可反省和主导自身。它不仅能按照自己的意愿塑造自身，而且能使任何事情朝着自己选定的方向发展。

9.在普遍本性指导下，一切事物皆会各展所长。世上再无与之分庭抗礼的其他本性，无论这种本性是从外部包含她，还是被她从内部所包含，甚至是独立于她而存在。

10.世界要么是一个由聚合与分散无序组成的大杂烩，要么是一个由秩序和天意组成的统一体。如果是前者，我为何想继续生活在如此毫无意义的混沌之中？为何还要在意而不把风度留到最终归于尘土的时候？何必再劳心费神？因为不管我做什么，幻灭迟早都会落到我的头上。如果事实恰恰相反，那我就要心怀崇敬，立场坚定，全心全意信赖那主宰。

11.如因形势所迫，内心的宁静被打破，要抓紧时间恢复自制力。只要可能，就不要继续受其干扰。经常回归和谐，你就能更多地拥有和谐。

12.假如你同时拥有一位继母和一位生母，你会对前者履行应尽的义务，但却会经常求助于后者。同样地，你也同时拥有宫廷和哲学。不断用哲学充实自己。这样，即使是宫廷生活和置身其中的自己，彼此都会变得较能忍受了。

13.当肉和其他珍馐美味摆在你面前，你会想：这是死去的鱼、家禽或猪；这种法勒纳斯的名酒产自葡萄的汁液；我的紫袍是用羊皮以某种贝类的血染色而成；交配不过是器官的摩擦和精液的喷射。这样的想法触及事物的根源，洞穿并揭示出事物真实的本质。对待整个生活也应该保持同样的警觉。当一件事物的表象十分可信时，要揭开它的真相，研究它的细节，撕掉它华丽的外衣。自命不凡是最大的欺骗。认为自己正在从事最值得称赞的事，没有比这更具有欺骗性了。注意克拉底斯本人是如何评价色诺克拉底的。

14.平庸之辈大都喜欢初级的事物。这类事物，比如木料与石材、无花果树、葡萄藤与橄榄树，往往是靠无机聚合或自然过程而存在。开化程度稍高一些的人会被诸如鸟群和牛群这样具有活动能力的事物所吸引。更高层次的人则欣赏具有理性的灵魂。不过，这种理性并不是普遍理性，而仅仅是指拥有一定技能或其他才能，甚至仅仅指拥有大量奴隶。但是一个人若是重视灵魂的理性、普遍性和社会性，他就不会再看重其他的东西，而只专注于保持自己的心境以及一切行为的理性与社会性，并且和同伴一起为此目标而共同奋斗。

15.—个事物匆匆产生，另一个事物匆匆消亡。即便一个事物正在产生的过程中，它的某些部分也已经不复存在。连续不断的变化更新着宇宙的结构，正如永不停歇的时间使这个世界万古常新。在这奔流不息的河流中，没有稳定的立足点。面对飞逝而过的诸多事物，还有什么值得人们珍惜的呢？这就好比把感情寄托在身边飞过的麻雀身上，在看见它的同时便不见了它的踪影。人的生命无非是空气的吸入，血气的蒸发。正如我们每时每刻都在吸入空气，只是为了再把它呼出去；或者正如你往日出生时获得了呼吸的能力，也只是为了有朝一日将其归还原主。这二者根本没有实质区别。

16.蒸发不值得珍视，我们和植物都具有这种功能。呼吸也是如此，我们和森林里、田野间的动物都会。感观认知能力、脉搏的跳动、群居的本能、汲取营养的过程，这一切其实并不比排泄过程更精彩。那么，我们应该珍惜什么呢？众人的掌声？不是，当然也不是平庸之辈的交口称赞。除去虚妄的名声，还有什么值得珍惜的呢？我个人的看法是这样的：弄清我们自然构造的作用，无论它们在运动还是不在运动都应如此。毕竟，这才是一切训练和技能的目的。每一项技能都是为了使产品能更好地服务于生产它的目的。农夫照料葡萄藤，马夫驯马，狗场管理员训练猎犬，都是出于这一目的。家庭教师和学校老师的工作也是出于同样的目的。这就是我们在寻找的值得珍视的东西。一旦真正认同它，你就不会再被其他目标所诱惑。放弃你怀有的其他雄心壮志吧。否则，你永远也不会成为自己的主人，永远也不会独立于他人，永远也抵御不了欲念的驱使。你肯定会以艳羡、妒忌、猜疑的目光看待可能夺走那些东西的人，并对拥有你所觊觎的那些珍宝的人图谋不轨。如果认为这些东西必不可少，这种念头肯定会引起内心的混乱，往往会使你抱怨神灵。然而，如果尊重自己的理智，则能让你心平气和，与人无争，与神灵和谐相处。也就是说，欣然接受神灵的任何赐予和命令。

17.各种元素在我们上下、周围旋转着。而美德却不这样运动，她更为神圣，她以常人无法理解的方式沉着地前进着。

18.人们的行为方式是多么奇怪呀！他们会吝于赞美生活在他们之中的同代人，而自己却贪婪地渴望得到后世的赞誉，哪怕那些人与他们过去从未谋面，将来也不会谋面。这种人甚至还要抱怨没有得到自己祖先的赞扬！

19.不要因为一件事情对你来说很难，就认为它非人力所能办到。反之，假如一件事人既能做又适合做，就应当认为它一定是你力所能及的事。

20.当我们在竞技场上被对手的指甲划伤或是磕破头时，我们不会抗议或生气，也绝不会事后疑心人家心怀歹意。但是，我们确实会对他加以小心，不是对他怀有敌意或者猜忌他，而是心平气和地与他保持距离。那么，在生活中的其他场合也应如此。让我们原谅竞争伙伴的种种不是吧。我们总可以做一些简单的回避，不带丝毫猜疑或敌意。

21.只要有人能指出并证明我的想法或做法不对，我会很乐于改正。我追求的是真理，而真理绝不会伤害任何人。唯有固执地自欺欺人和愚昧无知才会害人。

22.我只做我必须做到的事情。我不会为其他任何事情分神，因为那些不是无生命、无理性的事，就是会导致误入歧途的事。

23.对非理性生物和客观事物，要慷慨善良、宽容大度，因为你有理性而它们没有。从另一方面说，人是有理性的，因此要以伙伴之心待之。凡事皆可向神灵求助；只是不要顾忌祈祷时间的长短，三小时足矣。

24.马其顿的亚历山大之死和他的马倌之死没有丝毫区别。他们要么一同被宇宙同一衍生原则所接纳，要么就一同被分解成原子微粒。

25.想一想，我们每个人同时发生着多少精神和肉体上的事情。这样你就不会感到惊讶：比这数目大得多的事物（实际上是我们称之为宇宙的那个巨大统一体里的一切事物），都可以同时存在。

26.假如有人要你拼读出安东尼纳斯这个名字，你会大声拼出每一个字母，让听众生气也让你自己跟着生气吗？相反，为何不心平气和地依次拼出这几个字母呢？请记住，在生活中，每一项职责同样也由多项独立成分所组成。要仔细留意每个成分，不要大惊小怪，也不要以怒对怒，要确保分配给你的任务能按部就班地完成。

27.不允许人们追求属于自己的正当权益，这是多么野蛮的行为！然而，如果别人犯错时你对他怒发冲冠，你的行为在某种意义上讲就属于这一性质。说到底，他们只是在追求自己显而易见的权益。你说他们错了吗？如果是这样，那就告诉他们，解释给他们听，而不要怒火中烧。

28.死亡是对感官知觉的一种解脱，是对食欲冲动的一种解脱，是对思维旅程的一种解脱，是对肉体所服劳役的一种解脱。

29.羞愧啊，身体还在坚持，灵魂却在生命之路上徘徊不前。

30.当心不要对君王过分施加影响，也不要受君王影响太深，因为这样的事情很可能发生。要保持简朴、善良、纯洁、庄重、谦逊的本色，要与正义和虔诚为伴，要为人和蔼、宽厚仁爱、坚定地忠于职守。要始终尽自己最大的努力去达到哲学对你的要求。要崇敬神灵，要救助同胞。人生短暂，尘世的存在只不过是为了结出一枚果实：内心圣洁，外行无私。各方面都要做安东尼纳斯的信徒，记住他始终坚持用理性约束行为，他在任何场合都能沉着冷静，保持他个人的圣洁；他面容安详，态度亲切；他轻视虚名，热衷于掌握事实；他遇事悉心研究，直到透彻理解方才罢休；他容忍不公正的指责，从不反唇相讥；他从不草率行事，不与散播谣言者为友；他对各种人、各种举止的判断精确，但从不吹毛求疵；他完全脱离了神经紧张、疑神疑鬼、过分敏感等情况；他对房屋、床铺、衣着、膳食和仆人要求不高，容易满足；他兢兢业业，颇具耐心；由于饮食节俭，他可以从早到晚忙于工作，甚至不到习惯的时间不去如厕；他对待友情坚定不移、始终如一，能容忍对自己意见最直言不讳的反对，能够欢迎任何人提出更好的意见；他对神灵的崇敬，不掺杂丝毫迷信的色彩。铭记所有这一切，当你的最后时刻来临时，你的良心会像他一样清白。

31.现在，你要恢复清醒的知觉，找回真实的自己。从沉睡中醒来，认清困扰你的不过是梦魇。用你看待梦魇的方法，来看待自己清醒的眼睛所看到的一切。

32.我由肉体和灵魂构成。对肉体而言，一切都无关紧要，因为它无法分清彼此。对灵魂而言，唯一要紧的是自己的行为，它们都要置于自己的掌控之中。而且，即便在这些行为中，它也只关心现在发生的。一旦它们过去了，或者还停留在未来之中，它们便立刻变得无足轻重了。

33.手脚疼痛算不上反常，只要它们还能发挥作用。同样，疼痛并不违背人的本性，只要他还能从事自己的工作。既然符合本性，也就不会造成伤害。

34.强盗、变态者、弑亲者、暴君对自己享有的一切是多么异乎寻常的高兴呀！

35.注意，就连最平庸的工匠多少也能满足无技能的雇主的要求，然而却坚守行规毫不让步。建筑师或医生对行规的尊重，竟然更甚于对自己与神灵共有的准则的尊重，这难道不可悲吗？

36.在宇宙中，亚洲和欧洲只不过是两个小角落，浩渺海洋只不过是一滴水，圣山阿陀斯不过是一个小土丘，现在只不过是永恒中的一个针尖。一切都很渺小，易变，易消亡。一切皆源起一处，直接源于或派生于至高无上的普遍理性。甚至连狮子的血盆大口、致命的毒药、其他有害的东西，乃至荆棘、沼泽，统统都是其他高尚美好事物的产物。因此，不要认为它们和你所崇敬的东西格格不入，而要记住万物同源。

37.看到眼前的事物即是看到了现在的一切，即是看到了时间伊始就已存在的一切，即是看到了直至世界尽头将要存在的一切。这是因为，一切皆同宗同源。

38.时常想一想把宇宙万物联系在一起的纽带，以及万物之间的相互依存。可以说，万物相互交织，相互影响；它们之间井然有序的因果关系来自于张力作用和所有物质的统一。

39.调整自己以适应命中注定的环境，真心关爱命运所赐予的你周围的同胞。

40.—种工具、仪器或器皿只要能发挥应有的作用就很不错，尽管它们的制造者并不在场。可是，就大自然形成的东西而言，创造它们的力量依然蕴含其中，并且还会继续蕴含其中。进一步而言，假如你尊崇大自然，并确保遵循大自然的意愿生活、做事，那么一切事物皆能如你所愿。宇宙也是以同样的方式让万物皆如其所愿的。

41.要是你认为你无法掌控的事物对你非好即坏，那么当你错过一件事或者遇到另一件事的时候，你必定会对神灵愤愤不平，并且对那些你认为或怀疑造成你失败和不幸的人充满仇恨。事实上，我们就是由于过分看重这类事情而冤枉了很多人。然而，只要我们把是非观念严格置于我们自己能力范围之内，就没有理由指责神灵或是敌视他人。

42.我们都在为同一个目标而共同奋斗。有人心知肚明地自觉工作，而有人则毫不知情（我想，正如赫拉克利特说过的“他们在睡梦中仍在工作”，为宇宙的进程贡献自己的力量）。有人承担这部分工作，有人承担那部分工作。但没有一丁点工作是由极力阻挠和破坏自然趋势，对现状十分不满的人来完成的，尽管宇宙也需要这种人。那么，你就要考虑自己将与何人为伍。因为无论如何，统管全局的人会让你有用武之地，接纳你为他的助手或同伴。只是要注意，你的角色可不是那种可悲的角色，可不是克律西波斯所说的舞台丑角的差事[12]。

43.太阳想过要承担降雨的工作吗？阿斯克勒庇俄斯想过要承担德墨忒耳的工作吗？还有那些星星？尽管各不相同，还不是齐心协力地朝着同一个目的努力吗？

44.如果众神要一起讨论我和我的命运，那么这种讨论是好的，因为很难设想神灵的讨论会不明智。毕竟，他们有什么伤害我的动机呢？对神灵自身或对他们最为在意的宇宙来说又有何益处呢？即便他们不特别顾及我，至少也会顾及宇宙。因此，我理应欢迎并乐意接受任何可能的结果。当然，万一他们什么都不顾及（这种想法大为不敬），那么让我们停止献祭、祈祷、宣誓，以及其他所有能够使我们感知神灵与我们同在的行为。即便如此，即便他们当真不在乎我们凡人的命运，我仍然能够照顾好自己，照管好自己的利益。每一个生灵的利益也都与它自己的身体和本性相一致。我自己的本性是理智而平民化的本性。我拥有城市，也拥有国家。作为马可，我拥有罗马；而作为人类一员，我拥有宇宙。因此，对这些共同体有益的东西，才是对我唯一有益的东西。

45.发生在个人身上的一切对整体也都是有益的。对我们来说，这一理由本身就已足够充分。不过，如果你仔细想想，你也会发现：一般说来，对个人有益的东西，对其同胞也有益。（尽管，此处“有益”一词具有更为通俗的意义，即还包括道德意义上不好不坏的事物。）

46.马戏团和其他娱乐场所千篇一律地上演着同样的演出，这种演出单调乏味、令人厌倦。其实整个生活也同样如此。不管是在上坡路上还是在下坡路上，经历的事情总是千篇一律。其原因和结果都一样。这种状况还要持续多久？

47.要经常思考已故的各种国籍、各种职业的民众，甚至要追溯到腓力斯逊、福玻斯、奥里更尼安的时代。然后再把思路从最近的转到众多其他人身上。想想我们怎样才能追随众多早已长眠的伟大演说家、众多可敬的智者——赫拉克利特、毕达哥拉斯、苏格拉底——那些早期的英雄，那些后世的船长与国王，以及跟随他们的欧多克斯、喜帕恰斯、阿基米德和其他众人。他们头脑机敏，具有崇高的精神，孜孜不倦，足智多谋，意志坚定。他们还曾模仿迈尼普斯及其学派，开心地讲述关于人生短暂易逝的笑话。经常想想那些早已故去的人们，他们如今的境况为什么更加糟糕，尤其是那些姓名早已被人遗忘的人？此生只有一件事弥足珍贵：那就是真实公正地度过人生，即使对不诚实和不公平的人也要有恻隐之心。

48.当你想吃有兴奋作用的药物来提神时，想一想朋友身上的优点：有人很能干，有人很谦逊，还有人很慷慨，等等，不一而足。看看我们身边的人所展现的种种美德，没有比这更有效的治疗忧郁的灵丹妙药了。因此，要经常以他们为榜样。

49.你会抱怨自己体重过轻，还不到300磅吗？那么为何要抱怨寿命过短，没有活得更长呢？既然你对所能得到的物质数量感到满意，也应该对时间数量感到满意。

50.争取说服人们。然而如果为了正义的需要，也可违背他们的意愿。但假如有人用武力阻碍你，就要采取另一种做法了。毫无痛苦地接受现实，然后把阻碍转化为培养其他美德的机会。记住，你的尝试始终要有所保留，不要知其不可为而为之。那应该怎么做呢？只要尝试就可以了。这样你就成功了，你的人生目标也就实现了。

51.有野心的人认为，能从别人的活动中受益。贪图享乐的人认为，能从自己的感受中受益。而有理性的人则认为，能从自己的行动中受益。

52.你不必对眼前的事情形成看法，也不必扰乱你内心的平静。事情本身没有能力强迫你作出任何判断。

53.要习惯仔细倾听别人的谈话，要尽力从说话人的立场来理解他的谈话。

54.对蜂房没有好处的东西，绝不会对蜜蜂有好处。

55.假如船员胆敢中伤舵手，或者病人中伤医生，那他们还会听其他人的话吗？怎见得那个其他人就能保证水手的安全，或者病人的健康呢？

56.那么多和我一同出生的人已经离开了这个世界！

57.对于患黄疸病的人来说，蜂蜜似乎是苦的。对于被疯狗咬伤的人来说，水是可怕的。对年幼的孩童来说，一个小球仿佛就是无价之宝。那么，我为何还要发怒呢？难道可以认为错误思想对人的影响不如黄疸病的胆汁和狂犬病的病毒？

58.无人能阻止你按照自己的本性生活，无事能违背普遍理性的规律在你身上发生。

59.人们尽力讨好的那些人都是可怜虫！他们追求的目标是那样的可悲，他们采取的方式也是那样的可悲！时间将很快覆盖一切！甚至此刻它就已经覆盖了许多！

卷七

1.什么是恶？恶是你已经见过无数次的东西。同样，每当遇到其他事情的时候，立即提醒自己：这种情形你已经司空见惯了。你会发现相同的事情无处不在，它们充斥着古代、近代、当代的全部历史，如今又充斥着我们的城市和家园。这种事情毫无新奇可言，一切都是转瞬即逝的老生常谈。

2.只有当产生原则的最初认识逐渐消失时，原则才会失去活力，只能靠你来继续煽动，使它重新燃起火焰。我完全有能力对事物产生正确的看法。掌握了这种能力，我就无需感到不安（对于那些我无法理解的事情，我根本就不放在心上）。一旦学会它，你就可以屹立于天地之间。崭新的人生就在你的手中。你只需再次根据最初的印象和早期的视角看待事物，生活便会翻开新的篇章。

3.空洞的盛装游行，舞台剧，成群的牛羊，持矛士兵的争斗，扔向恶狗群中的骨头，撒向鱼池的面包屑，负重劳作的蚂蚁，惊慌失措、四散奔逃的老鼠，颤动的拉线木偶，这就是生活。置身其中，你必须心平气和，不带有一丝轻蔑地表明态度，但要始终意识到，雄心壮志乃是人的最大价值。

4.交谈时，要仔细留意正在说什么。行动时，要仔细留意正在做什么。对于后者，要立刻弄清做这事的意图是什么。对于前者，则要弄清说这话的含义是什么。

5.我的理解力能否胜任这项工作？如果能，我就将它作为大自然赐予我的工具运用到工作中。如果不能，我要么让位给更能胜任的人（如果我的职责允许的话），要么在助手的帮助下全力以赴，他将借助我的灵感，及时有效地为公众效力。我所做的一切，无论是凭一己之力或是和别人联手，都必须以服务公众和社会和谐为唯一宗旨。

6.多少曾经被高度赞颂的人如今已经被人遗忘，多少赞颂者自己也早已从我们的视线中消逝！

7.不要认为接受帮助是可耻的事情。你的任务是完成既定使命，犹如突围中的战士。假如因为腿瘸，你无法独自爬上城垛，有了战友的帮助，不就可以上去了吗？

8.切莫为未来而烦恼。即便以后不得不面对未来，也要用应对今天的理智武器来应对未来。

9.所有的事物互相交织一起，神圣的纽带将它们连在一起，互相孤立的事物几乎没有。万事万物相互配合，共同作用，构成了统一的宇宙。世界秩序是由多样性构成的统一体：神灵是统一体，遍及万物；所有生命是统一体；所有法律是统一体（即所有会思考的生灵所共有的理性）；所有真理是统一体。正如我们所信仰的那样，要是只有一条供相同种类和理性的存在通往完美的路，那就好了。

10.每一颗微小的物质都会很快化为普遍物质的一部分，每一种因果关系都会很快再次回归到普遍理性之中，对一切事物的记忆也将很快湮灭于永恒的深渊之中。

11.对于有理性思维的人而言，符合本性的行为就是符合理性的行为。

12.是自己站起来，还是被人扶起来？

13.在由多种成分组成的某一体系中，具有理性的部分起着相同的作用，这与各肢体在有机统一体中所起的作用相仿。它们都是为了相互协作而存在。假如你经常对自己说：“我是整个复杂的理性事物的‘一肢’。”这种看法就会对你产生更强的印象。如果你认为自己仅仅是一个“局部”，那说明到目前为止你还没有从内心产生对人类的热爱，也没有体验到为他们行善的快乐。你行善只是应付差事而已，还没有把它当作是对自己有益的事情。

14.将要发生的事情，就让我这身躯可能受到影响的部分去承受吧。只要愿意，就让它们抱怨吧。至于我，只要不把它当成邪恶，我就不会觉得痛苦。而且，也没有任何东西能迫使我把它当成邪恶。

15.无论世人如何评说、如何行事，我都将保持本色。如同金块、祖母绿、紫色长袍始终坚持的那样：“任凭世人如何评说、如何行事，我仍然是一块祖母绿，保持着自己的本色。”

16.主宰我们的理性绝不会受自扰之害。例如，它绝不会引发内心的激情。如果别人能以恐惧和痛苦刺激理性，那就由他去吧。但是理性自己却绝不允许自己的判断误导自己陷入这样的情绪之中。如果可能，理性会尽量让肉体为自己操心，免受伤害。如果肉体已受伤害，那就让它说出来。可是，灵魂却毫发无伤，因为它自己就能了解恐惧和痛苦，并且能判断是否存在恐惧和痛苦。你无法强迫它作出判断。主宰我们的理性能够自给自足，除了自己为自己创造的事物之外别无他求。由于同样的原因，它不会经受干扰和阻碍，除非这些干扰和阻碍是它自身所为。

17.根据词源，幸福是“内心万能的神灵”[13]的意思，也就是指万能的理性主宰。那么，空虚的幻想，你在此有何贵干？看在神灵的份上，走开吧，就像你来时一样。我不需要你。我知道，是长期的习惯使你来到这里。我并无恶意，只是请你离开。

18.我们总是害怕变化。可是，没有变化，何来万物？还有什么是大自然更为珍视，并使其自身更为特别的呢？木柴不发生变化，你怎能洗上热水澡？食物不发生变化，你怎能汲取营养？没有变化，有用的东西从何而来？难道你看不出来，你自身也同样发生着变化，这些变化对你、对大自然同样必不可少？

19.所有的物体都要穿过普遍物质，如同出入激流一样。它们与整体相互聚合、相互协作，就像人体的各个部分彼此协作一样。多少个克律西波斯、苏格拉底、埃皮克提图已被时光淹没！不论对待什么人，处理什么事，你都要牢记这一点。

20.只有一件事困扰着我：我担心自己要做的事非人力所及，或者必须以其他某种方式去做，或者须得在将来某日去做。

21.你很快就会忘记这个世界，而这个世界也很快就会忘记你。

22.爱那些犯错或误入歧途的人是人类独有的特征。你要意识到他们是你的兄弟，意识到他们犯错是由于无知而非故意，意识到不久之后你们都将不复存在，更重要的是要意识到，由于主宰你的理智毫发无伤，你本身并没受到伤害。一旦意识到这些，爱便会油然而生。

23.大自然用普遍物质就像用蜡一样，做成了一匹小马，随即将其打碎后又做了一棵树，接着又做了一个人，然后还做成其他的东西。它们的生命周期都很短暂。至于模具本身，打碎它并不比把它拼凑起来更困难。

24.怒气冲冲的容颜完全有违本性。倘若经常如此，美貌便开始枯萎，最终消失殆尽，不复重生。你必须设法认识到这种行为并不理智。因为如果我们丧失了洞察缺点的能力，活着还有什么意义呢？

25.只消片刻工夫，大自然这个宇宙处置者便会让你看到的一切面目全非，用旧物质产生新事物，新事物而后又将产生新事物，不断更新使宇宙永葆青春。

26.当别人冒犯你的时候，你首先要想到，这是否涉及善恶问题。一旦弄清楚，惊诧和愤怒便会化作怜悯。这是因为，你对善的看法并不比他高明，或者至少和他有相似之处。在这种情况下，你显然应该原谅他。否则，从另一方面讲，你已经变得不关心这种行为是善是恶了。这样的话，那就更容易原谅别人的愚昧。

27.不要沉浸在贪婪的梦里。还是想想已经拥有的神灵的主要恩赐吧。然后再怀着感激之情想想，假如你还未拥有这些恩赐，你会多么渴望得到它们。同时也要谨记，不要因喜欢它们而过分珍视它们，以防它们一旦失去，就会打破你内心的平静。

28.归隐于心。主宰我们的理性只要求我们行为端正以获得内心的宁静，此外别无他求。

29.抛开那些异想天开的念头。不要再做激情的傀儡。将时间限制在眼前。学会按每一经历的本来面目认识它们，无论这些经历是自己的还是别人的。将感官对象按根源和内容加以分类。想想自己的最后时刻。邻人的不端留给他自己去。

30.集中精力关注正在说的话，全神贯注地考虑正在做的事和谁正在做。

31.树立质朴自重的光辉形象，作出对正邪范围以外的事情漠不关心的样子。热爱人类，走神灵指引的路。圣人云：“一切从法。”虽然他指的是微粒，但那又何妨？对我们而言，记住万物确实从法就足够了。尽管只有三个单词，但已经够了。

32.关于死亡：如果世界是由微粒聚合而成，死亡即是消散；如果世界是个统一体，死亡则是灭绝或蜕变。

33.关于痛苦：痛苦如果达到无法忍受的程度就会终结我们的生命；生命若是继续存在，则说明痛苦还可以忍受。高高在上远离肉体的心灵始终保持着平静，主宰我们的理性毫发无伤。至于被痛苦伤害的部分，如果可能，让它们自己表达悲伤吧。

34.关于名声：看看追逐她的那些人的心灵吧，看看他们的野心和可恶行径吧。再想想，今生今世，今天的事物很快便被明天的事物埋葬，就像一层流沙很快被另一层覆盖。

35.“如果一个人拥有伟大的思想和开阔的视野去沉思古往今来，他会把人生看作是举足轻重的大事吗？”“不，他不会。”“所以，他就不会认为死亡是件可怕的事了？”“不会。”（出自柏拉图）

36.行善举却遭诟病，这就是王子们的宿命。（出自安提泰尼）

37.遗憾的是，五官一味地听从心灵的指挥，任其处置，而心灵却不听从自己的指挥和处置。

38.“不要对事物的进程而烦恼；它们不理会你的烦恼。”

39.“让永生的神灵快乐，同样也让我们自己快乐。”

40.“人的生命犹如成熟待收的玉米，留下这个，砍倒那个。”

41.“如果上天不肯眷顾我和我那两个儿子，那必定有充分的理由。”

42.“正义和好运都与我同在。”

43.“不与痛哭的人一起流泪，脉搏的跳动也不会加快。”

44.“我可以公正地回答他：我的朋友，如果你认为一个有价值的人应当把时间花在掂量生与死的前景上，那你就错了。采取任何行动之前，他只需考虑一件事情：即他的行为是正确还是错误，他像个好人还是像个坏人。”（出自柏拉图）

45.“先生们，事情的真相是这样的。一个人一旦决定表明立场，不是因为这样做似乎对他最为有利，就是因为要服从命令。而我相信，他必然要留下来面对险境，在耻辱面前已将自己的生死或其他事情置之度外。”（出自柏拉图）

46.“我的朋友，我恳求你好好想一想，高尚和善良也许不等于让自己和朋友远离危险；好好想一想，一个纯粹的人是否应该把能活多久这样的问题从自己脑海中消除，而不是不惜一切地贪生怕死。让他把那个问题交给神灵决定吧。女人告诉我们没人能逃脱宿命，要相信她们是正确的。让他专心思考下一个问题吧：如何才能最好地度过自己的一生。”（出自柏拉图）

47.仰望环绕的群星，仿佛自己置身其中。经常想象元素的那些变化和重组的舞蹈。这种想象能涤清我们世俗生活的污垢。

48.柏拉图有句话说得精辟。他说，论述人性的人应该站在高高的瞭望塔上眺望人间百态。他会看到有关是战是和的各种集会、农业耕作、繁衍交配、离别、出生、死亡、喧嚣的法庭、人迹罕至的蛮荒之地、陌生的各色人等、欢宴、哀悼、讨价还价。观察这纷繁混杂的景象和矛盾对立所产生的和谐秩序。

49.回首往昔，看到一个个王朝兴衰更迭，你就能预见到未来。未来的模式依旧，甚至连细枝末节也都一样，因为它不可能偏离宇宙稳健前行的步伐。因此，看待四十年后的人生和四万年后的人生，别无二致。此外，你还有什么可看的呢？

50.“凡是生于土的必定归还于土；诞生于天国的种子也将回归天国。”——即通过原子结构的瓦解和元素的扩散来实现。

51.“撇开美酒珍馐和绝色佳人，命运的潮水能逃离死亡吗？”

“神灵送来了阵阵微风，我们应该以无怨无悔的心灵摇着橹去迎接。”

52.“竞技场上的奸诈诡计越来越多。”没错，但是却看不到越来越多的公益精神、自我谦虚、临场应变、对他人疏忽的宽容。

53.只要一个人的行为能够符合人神共有的理性，就没什么可担心的。当能够效力的机会出现，而且已经付诸行动、进展顺利并完全符合我们人的规则时，我们就不必担心会受到伤害。

54.你随时随地都有能力虔诚地接受当天发生的事情，公正地对待当天的同伴，一丝不苟地关注当天的印象，以防它们未经检验而混入你的内心世界。

55.面对能支配别人的种种本能，要做到目不斜视，心无旁骛地认准本性指给你的目标：普遍本性通过环境说话，而你自己的本性则通过使命感说话。人的行为要符合与生倶来的本性，其他造物要服务于理性生物（这和低级事物是为高级事物的利益而存在这一普遍规律相一致），而后者则是为了相互服务。因此，人的本性的首要特征是对同类怀有责任感。其次是有抵御肉体低声诱惑的义务。这是因为人的理性与智慧具有一种特定功能，那就是筑起一道藩篱，保护其运转不被那些动物般的感觉和冲动所征服。理智必须占据统治地位，决不能向束缚低头。这是天经地义的，因为本性产生理智就是为了让其统领全局，物尽其用。第三是理性生物的本性应该使其具备谨慎行事、防止欺诈的能力。让理性这一舵手坚守以上三项原则，将我们引向笔直的航程，并且坚信这一航程将会自己出现。

56.假设你今天离开人世，你的生命篇章便就此结束。从今以后，把未来的时间当成不受约束的盈余，依照本性的要求生活下去。

57.只热爱那已经编织进你命运图案的东西，还有什么比它更符合你的需要？

58.当你身处困境的时候，想想那些以愤怒、震惊、尖叫面对类似危机的人们。如今他们身在何处？无处可寻。那为何还要步他们的后尘？不如把别人的情绪留给它们的主人或仆从，而你则集中精力争取把事情向好的方向转化。这样，你就能充分利用它，把它作为劳动材料为你效劳。每一次行动，都要以自己满意为努力和动机的唯一目标。记住，促使你行动的事情本身对这二者并不重要。

59.反观自省。那里有善的源泉：不断探究，善便不断涌出。

60.无论是动还是静，你的仪态举止要坚定有力，不要歪歪扭扭。镇静得体的神态反映着内心世界。因此，全身都应该如此。不过，务必不要矫揉造作。

61.生活的艺术更像摔跤而非舞蹈，因为它同样需要站稳脚跟，以防突如其来的袭击。

62.如果渴望赢得人们的赞赏，你就要始终了解他们的性格及其做人原则的本质，研究他们的看法和动机。这样，你就不会责怪他们无心的冒犯，或者企盼得到他们的赞许。

63.有人曾说：“没有人会故意放弃真理。”正义、自制、仁慈及其他美德也是如此。没有比这些更值得常记于心间的了。它们会帮助你在人际交往中拥有更大的亲和力。

64.当你感到疼痛的时候，要及时提醒自己这并不是件丢脸的事情，而且无论是从理性还是从社会性的角度来说都无损于掌舵的理智。在多数情况下，伊壁鸠鲁的话都十分有道理。他说：“疼痛绝非是不可忍受或永无止境的，只要你记住它是有限的，并且不要任意夸大其辞。”还要记住，尽管我们还没意识到，但是很多令我们不快的事情其实在本质上跟疼痛是一回事。比如，没精打采的感觉、高烧的体温、失去食欲。每当要开口抱怨的时候，就告诉自己这么做就是在向痛苦低头。

65.如果有人作出不近人情的事情，注意不要步其后尘。

66.我们如何知晓泰格拉斯的人品也许不如苏格拉底呢？我们完全可以说，苏格拉底之死更体面，与智者的辩论更为巧妙，熬过寒冷的长夜更坚强，英勇地拒绝执行命令逮捕萨拉米斯的利昂[14]，昂首阔步走在大街上[15]（尽管此事的真实性有待证实）。然而，真正值得思考的问题是，他的灵魂究竟怎样？他是否真如人们看到的那样待人公正，对神灵虔诚，此外别无他求？他是否真的对别人的缺点不怨恨，对别人的愚昧不苟同？他是否真的听天由命，不把命运看作反常的事情或无法忍受的苦难，也不允许肉体的经历影响自己的心灵？

67.大自然没有把心灵和肉体完全混为一谈，以致使心灵无法确定自己的边界，主宰自己的领域。尽管没有获得承认，但心灵完全可能像神灵一样神圣。这一点要时刻铭记在心。还要记住，幸福生活所需不多。你也许没有掌握辩证法或物理学，但决不能对获得自由、自尊、无私、顺应天意失去。

68.在不受打扰的宁静中度过余生，拒绝向胁迫屈服，哪怕全世界的要求震耳欲聋，哪怕野兽把可怜的肉体躯壳撕得粉碎。即便如此，也不能阻止心灵获得平静、正确评估周围发生的事情、及时利用得到的资源。所以，判断力会对事件说：“这就是你的本质，无论谣言怎样粉饰你。”而效劳会对机遇说：“我寻找的正是你。”此刻发生的事情往往是运用理性和兄弟情谊的绝好机会。总之，这样处事，对人或神灵都是很恰当的。因为，没有一件事情的发生是专门针对人或者神灵的。这种事情的到来，不是什么新奇棘手的难题，而是一个用得上的老朋友。

69.把生命中的每一天都当成最后一天来过。既不紧张不安、不无动于衷，也不装腔作势。这就是完美性格的写照。

70.尽管神灵能够永生，但他们不会因为要永远忍受代代世人及其不端行为而心怀不满。不仅如此，神灵甚至会竭尽所能地关怀他们。那么，没有长性的你会失去耐心吗？你自己就是罪犯中的一员呀。

71.能避免自己的罪恶而不去避免，反而徒劳地尽力避免他人的罪恶，这是多么荒唐可笑的事情。

72.无论理智与社会功能发现了什么轻率或不友善的事情，它都能合情合理地宣布其低于自身。

73.当你做了件好事使别人从中受益，为何还要像个傻瓜一样奢求更多：众人的喝彩，或者某种形式的回报？

74.没人会对接受好处感到厌倦。只是，好处要来自契合本性的行为。那么，对通过给予好处的行为来接受这样的好处，永远也不要感到厌倦。

75.普遍本性的冲动是为了创造一个井然有序的世界。由此可以断定，现在发生的一切事情必定遵循某种逻辑顺序。如若不然，那么普遍本性的冲动的首要目的，就会是非理性的目的。记住这点，将帮助你更冷静地面对很多事情。

卷八

1.假如有人说，自己的一生，哪怕是成人之后，一直过着哲学家的生活。那绝对是无稽之谈。记住这一点，你就不会产生自鸣得意的情绪。实际上，即使现在，哲学显然对于你和很多其他人来说仍然非常遥远。因此，你的思想还处在一种混乱状态，想赢得哲学家的头衔就更加不易了。况且，你的身份地位也时常会产生不利的影响。一旦了解了真相，你就应该抛开在人前表现的想法，满足于依照本性的要求生活。学会理解她的意志，心无旁骛。迄今为止，你一直在徒劳地漫无目的地寻找着高尚的生活。它既不存在于诡辩的逻辑中，也不存在于财富、名声、世俗的享受或其他事物中。那么，秘诀究竟在哪儿？在于遵循人的本性行事。如何才能做到？用严格的原则约束自己的冲动和行为。哪些原则？关于是非善恶的原则。比如，唯有能使人变得公正、自律、勇敢、独立的事物才是对人有益的，反之则对人有害。

2.做任何事之前先问自己：这件事对我会产生怎样的后果？我会后悔吗？我将不久于人世，一切都将被人遗忘。同时，如果这件事情适合一个有理性和社会性的人去做，而他与神灵共处同样的法律之下，夫复何求？

3.亚历山大、恺撒、庞贝与第欧根尼、赫拉克利特、苏格拉底相比，有什么不同？后面几位关注事物的根源及构成，他们的主导思想如出一辙。至于其他几位，他们有太多的烦恼，无穷的束缚！

4.你也许会伤心，但人们将一如既往地前进。

5.第一条规则是保持精神世界不受打扰。凡事都得遵守大自然的法则，很快你就消失得无影无踪，就像哈德良和奥古斯都一样。第二条规则是遇事要勇敢面对，弄清事情的本质，莫忘以成为有德之人为己任。按本性行事，不要畏缩，陈述自己认为最公正的看法，但要彬彬有礼、谦虚中肯、真心诚意。

6.普遍本性的使命是改组、变换、交换、将一种状态转化为另一种状态。变化无处不在。我们无需害怕意外，因为万物都遵循着古老的习惯，就连分配它们的方式都未改变。

7.只要在自己追求的道路上一帆风顺，本性就会觉得心满意足。对具有理性的本性而言，这意味着不赞成带有误导性或含混不清的印象，不放任非社会行为的冲动，约束所有的欲望，限制对力所能及之事的拒绝，以同等的热情迎接大自然分派给你的每个任务。这些分派的任务是大自然的一部分，如同树叶的本性是植物本性的一部分一样，只是植物的本性没有感情也没有理性，容易遭受挫折，而人的本性不但不会被挫败，还具有智慧和正义，因为它公平地赋予每个人恰当的时间、生命、因果报应、活力和经验（虽然不能指望每个人的每一方面都绝对的公平，但大致比较起来，整体上还算公平）。

8.你不可企望自己成为学者。你能做到的是克制傲慢的态度，你能做到的是从快乐和痛苦中超脱出来，你能抵御名望的诱惑，也能对愚昧无知和忘恩负义的人耐住性子，甚至会喜欢他们。

9.不要再让任何人，包括你自己，听见你对宫廷生活破口大骂。

10.懊悔是对失去某个有利时机感到悔恨。高尚的事物总是很有用的，也必定是每个高尚的人所关注的。然而，高尚的人从来不后悔放过了享受的机会。由此可以断定，享受既不高尚也对人无益。

11.问问自己，这东西的样子这么特别，其中到底是什么？其实质、结构和内容各是什么？到底有什么功能？能存在多久？

12.当你难以摆脱睡意的时候，就提醒自己，要履行对社会的责任就是要遵从人性的法则和自己的本性，而睡觉则是我们和非理性的野兽共有的行为。再者，遵从本性才是更恰当、更合适、更令人愉快的行为方式。

13.如果有可能，养成好习惯，去发掘每种印象的本质特点，它对自我的影响，以及它对逻辑分析的反应。

14.无论遇见谁，都要先问问自己，此人的是非观是什么？如果他对快乐、痛苦及其根源的认识，对名誉和耻辱的看法，对生与死的态度，都属于某种类型，那么发现他的行为和他的信念一致时，我就不会感到惊讶或愤慨，我会告诉自己，他这么做是别无选择。

15.无花果树结出无花果，没人会觉得诧异。同理，对世间正常发生的事情，如果我们大惊小怪或者愤慨不已，则应该为此感到羞愧。要是医生发现病人发烧就大惊小怪，要是船长碰到逆风就惊诧不已，他们都应该感到脸红。

16.转变思想、听从纠正，并不意味着丧失独立性。因为这种转变是你的主动行为，是依据自己的冲动、自己的判断力和自己的思考而作出的决定。

17.假如你有选择权，为何要做这种事？如果选择权在别人手中，你又能责怪谁呢？责怪神灵吗？责怪原子微粒吗？怪谁都很荒谬。所有怪罪别人的想法都不恰当。如果有可能，就去纠正犯错误的人。如果不行，就纠正错误的行为。如果还不行，那相互指责又有什么意义呢？毫无意义的事情是不值得做的。

18.死去的并未退出这个世界。它会继续存在下去，发生变化，分解成微小的颗粒，即分解为组成宇宙和我们自身的元素。元素本身也在发生着同样的变化，但却毫无怨言。

19.任何事物，不论是一匹马还是一株藤，它们的诞生皆有使命。这并不奇怪。就连太阳神本身都会告诉你：“我来是有使命要完成。”天上其他诸神也是如此。那么，你的诞生是为着什么使命呢？是为了享乐吗？人们能容忍这种思想吗？

20.大自然始终记着一个宗旨。这个宗旨包括事物的始末及持续时间。她就像个掷球者。球向上会变得更好吗？球向下或落地之后，会变得更糟吗？泡沫聚集在一起时得到了什么？破灭之后又会失去什么？对蜡烛，道理也是一样。

21.将血肉之躯从里向外翻转过来，再看看是什么样的景象。人变老、生病、腐烂又会变成什么样子。赞扬者和被赞扬者的生命同样短暂易逝，纪念者和被纪念者也是如此。对于广博的地球而言，他们占据的不过是沧海一粟。即便如此，他们也不能彼此和睦相处。而整个地球也只是宇宙中最微不足道的一个点。

22.无论对一个物体、一种行为、一项原则，还是别人的话，你都应该全神贯注。

你觉得失望理所当然，因为你宁可坐等明日上天赐福，也不愿今天积极争取。

23.我做任何事，都是为了服务人类。发生在我身上的任何事，我都会以对神灵及普遍之源的敬意接受它。一切环环相扣的命运都出自普遍之源。

24.沐浴让你想到了什么？油垢、汗渍、尘土、油腻腻的脏水，以及所有令人作呕的东西。这就像生活的方方面面，其中每一种物质都是如此。

25.死神从露西拉身边夺走了维鲁斯，继而又带走了露西拉；从瑟孔达身边夺走了马克西姆斯，继而又带走了瑟孔达；从埃皮梯恩查努斯身边夺走了戴奥提莫斯，继而带走了埃皮梯恩查努斯；从安东尼纳斯身边夺走了福斯娜，继而带走了安东尼纳斯。这样的事情总在重演。塞勒掩埋了哈德良，自己也被后人掩埋。古代的那些显贵、那些有先见之明的人、那些骄傲的人，如今他们身在何处？机敏者如沙哈克斯、柏拉图主义者德米特里厄斯、尤德蒙，以及其他类似的人，都只活了一天，都早已作古。有的人刚走便被人遗忘，有的人则变成了传说，还有的人甚至淡出了传说。想一想，你复杂的身体有朝一日也会分解消散，维持生命的呼吸也必然会停止，或转移、转化到别处。

26.人的真正乐事是实现人的使命。人的使命不外乎善待同类、超越感官刺激、辨别表象与事实、研究普遍本性及其作用。

27.我们要面对三种关系：其一，与容纳我们的皮囊的关系；其二，与神圣的万物之源的关系；其三，与我们身边同胞的关系。

28.无论对于我们的肉体还是对于我们的灵魂，痛苦必定是邪恶。如果是前者，就由肉体自己来说吧。只是灵魂始终拒绝认为痛苦是邪恶，以此保持内心世界晴朗无霾，平静安宁。这是因为一切决定、冲动、前进或是后退的举动皆由内而发，邪恶绝不可能从外面强行侵入。

29.忘掉不切实际的幻想，经常对自己说：“只有我才能保证邪恶、贪婪和一切混乱的想法在我心中找不到容身之处，只有我才能洞悉天地万物之本质，并以与之相称的方式对待它们。”牢记这一权力，这是本性赐予你的礼物。

30.不论是在元老院讲演，还是与个别人谈话，用词都要得体，不要花哨浮夸。讲话要合乎情理，言而有益。

31.想想奥古斯都的朝廷：妻子、女儿、孩童、祖先、姐妹、阿格里帕、宗族、亲属、朋友、阿雷夫斯、米西奈斯、医护人员、祭司，整个朝廷，统统烟消云散。再看看其他已经湮灭的记录：不光是个人的毁灭，而是整个家族的覆灭，例如庞贝家族。我们在墓碑上看到这样的铭文：“此家族中的最后一位。”想想他的祖先为了死后留下一位继承人所耗费的心血。然而到头来，某人必须成为这最后一位，又一个家族覆灭了。

32.你的每一个行为，都应该为完整的人生作出贡献。如果每一行动都能做到这一点，只要它做了，你就应该感到心满意足，因为这是无法阻挡的事情。你也许会说：“受到外界的干扰。”即便如此，这些干扰也不会影响到你意图的公正、慎重、合理。“不，现实中某种行动是可以阻挡的。”也许吧，不过只要你能以良好的心态面对挫折，明智地接受出现的替代条件，就能找到同样符合前面提到的完整人生的替代办法。

33.谦逊地接受，得体地放弃。

34.你也许见过断手、断脚、身首异处的头颅。如果一个人拒绝命运的安排，脱离伙伴，或者做事只图一己私利，他就是尽其所能使自己落得这样的下场。于是，你就沦为大自然统一体的弃儿。尽管你生来就是其中的一员，但你却亲手把自己与整体割离开来。即便如此，还是有一个美好的想法：你依然有能力让自己重新回到整体。神灵从来没有如此偏爱过其他生灵，被分离之后还允许他重归整体。看神灵以自己的仁慈美化着人类：他将权力交给世人，不仅首先使他不与整体分离，而且后来一旦分离，还能重回整体，恢复以往的身份。

35.—切由理性事物构成的大自然，使每个理性生命都具备各种本领。我们从她手中得到的本领之一，便是如她一样能够转变遇到的每个阻碍或对抗，将其纳入命运的轨道，同化为自身的一部分。因此，一个理性的生命有能力将障碍转化成为己所用的材料，借以向自己的奋斗目标前进。

36.千万不要急于去想象整个人生，这样会让自己很困惑。就是说，不要把一生可能遇到的各种不幸都想个遍。相反地，每当遭遇不幸，要问问自己：“这件事中让我无法容忍、难以承受的是什么？”然后，你会发现自己羞于承认失败。还要记住，压在你心头的不是未来或过去的重负，而始终都是现在的负重。就连这份负重也有可能减轻，只要你严格限制它，并且对连这种小事都无法承受的脆弱心理采取严厉的措施。

37.潘瑟和佩尔加蒙至今还端坐在维鲁斯的墓旁吗？卡布里亚斯和戴奥梯莫斯至今还端坐在哈德良的墓旁吗？荒唐之极！就算他们还端坐在那里，死者能感觉到吗？即便能感觉到，他们会高兴吗？况且，就算死者高兴，能指望悼念者长生不老吗？他们不是一样注定要变老，并离开人世吗？到那时，悼念者都不存在了，被悼念者还能怎么样呢？这一切不过是一堆恶臭腐烂的尸体罢了。

38.圣人克里托说过：“你要是长着眼睛能看，就自己看吧。”

39.在理性生命的结构中，我没有发现植有反抗正义的道德，倒发现植有反抗享受的自制力。

40.忘掉你凭空想象痛苦的念头，这样你的自我才能立于刀枪不入的境地。“自我——那是什么？”它就是你的理性。“可是，我身上不全是理性。”也许是这样。在这种情况下，至少要让理性不给自己带来痛苦。另外，如果你的其他部分有麻烦，就让那部分自己去操心好了。

41.对于维持肉体活力的本性来说，任何感官上的挫折都是有害的，任何努力遇到的挫折也是如此。植物的本性照样会有自己的挫折与危害。同样，心灵受到的挫折也会对心灵的本性造成伤害。将这一切应用到你自己身上。痛苦或者快乐对你有影响吗？感官会注意到。在你努力的过程中，是否曾经畏缩不前？如果付出的努力只许成功不许失败，那么作为理性生命，这种挫折对你的确有害。然而，一旦你认可了普遍的必然性，你就不会受到伤害，也不会觉得沮丧。在心灵自己的领地内，没人能让它受挫。烈火、刀剑、压迫、污蔑等等都不能伤害到它。“地球，一旦成为真实的球形，便永远是球体。”

42.我从来不会有意伤害别人，更没有理由伤害自己。

43.每个人都应该有自己的幸福。对我而言，幸福就是具有健全的自我主导能力——理性，就是不躲避人类及人类的兴衰变迁，就是能够以仁慈的眼光审视并接受一切事物，并根据各自的表现分别对待。

44.充分利用今天。追求明日赞扬的人们忘记了：与耐心经受巨大考验，不比他们短寿的当代人相比，子孙后代没有任何不同。既然如此，子孙后代的评说或对你怀有的看法，对你来说有什么要紧的呢？

45.带上我，随你将我抛弃在哪里。我内心依然拥有灵性，安详而满足，只要它还能感受，并以恰当的方式行事。我的灵魂会受到折磨，堕落下去，变成一个畏首畏尾的懦弱之辈，无精打采地哀求别人。这真的有这么重要吗？真会出现这样的后果吗？

46.人类只可能经历符合自身条件的事情，如同公牛、葡萄藤、石头只会经历符合它们本性的事情一样。既然发生的事情对他们来说都习以为常、合乎自然，那有什么可抱怨的？你和他们共有的大自然绝不会让你经历无法忍受的事情。

47.假如外界的事情使你感到苦恼，那么这痛苦并非来自事情本身，而是源于你对它的判断。你有能力随时消除这种痛苦。如果痛苦的根源是你自身的性格，那就着手改变你的道德观念。有谁会阻止你呢？如果你的苦恼在于没能采取明确理智的行动准则，那为何不采取，反而妄自烦恼呢？“因为中途遇到不可逾越的障碍。”既然这样，不必担心，不作为的责任不在你。“可是，不完成这件事情，生活便失去了意义。”唉，那就愉快地永别人生吧，得体地承认失败，像其他行为不受约束的人一样走向死亡。

48.记住一旦你更高的自我回归本位，冷静地拒绝做违背自己意愿的事，它就将立于不败之地，即便这种对抗完全不合理性。那么，当它经过理性思考、慎重作出决定时，就更加不可战胜！因此，脱离了激情的心灵堪称堡垒，没有比这更坚固的堡垒可以庇护人类、抵御攻击的了。认识不到这一点就是无知；认识到了，却不寻求它的庇护，则是一种不幸。

49.对最初形成的印象一定要加以辨别。那些印象告诉你，某人在讲你的坏话。这就是它们要传递的信息。它们没有进而说明这一信息已经对你造成伤害。我看见自己的孩子病了，我的眼睛告诉我的，但并没有表明孩子有生命危险。所以，要牢记最初的印象，不要添枝加叶，你就不会有危险。即便要加，至少也要添加对万能的普世秩序的认识，因为万物皆要遵从这一秩序。

50.你的黄瓜味道很苦？扔掉它。你走的路上有欧石南吗？那就走别的路好了。这就够了。不要进而抱怨：“世上怎么会有这种东西呢？”本性的学生只会嘲笑你，就好比在木匠或是鞋匠的铺子里挑剔人家的产品有刨花或碎屑，会遭到他们的耻笑一样。不过，至少他们还有地方放置垃圾，而大自然却没有这样的闲地方。她的方法神奇之处就在于：尽管有这种自我限制，她却能把所有破旧磨损、老而无用的东西转化成自己的一部分，再重新打造成新的产物，这样就永远不需要外部供给新鲜的原料，也不需要丢弃垃圾的地方。她自己的空间、自己的原料、自己的手艺就已经足够了。

51.行动拖拖拉拉、说话语无伦次、观点模糊不清、内心深受束缚、感情过于外露、生活没有闲暇，这些现象都应该避免。殉难、损毁、诅咒，这些怎能削弱一个人保持内心纯洁、清醒、温和、公正的能力呢？人可能会站在一泓清泉旁边破口大骂，然而泉眼中依然汩汩涌出清澈、有益于健康的泉水；他甚至会把污泥和赃物投入水中，可是泉水会很快将其溶解冲走，不留一丝污渍。何不让自己拥有长流不息的清泉呢？只要时刻以恻隐、质朴、谦逊之心守护好自己做主的权利就行。

52.—个人不懂得宇宙的本性，就不会明白自己身在何处；不懂得宇宙的意志，他就不懂得自己的本质，也不懂得宇宙的本质。让他发现不了这些道理，他甚至无法对自己的存在给出合理的解释。他们既不知道自己身在何处，也不知道自己的本质，却刻意寻找或者回避民众喧嚣的喝彩声，对这样的人，我们应该如何评价呢？

53.如果一个人一小时之内咒骂自己三次，你会希望得到这种人的夸奖吗？你愿意取悦那种对自己都不满意的人吗？几乎后悔自己做过的所有事情，这样的人能对自己满意吗？

54.你的呼吸参与空气的循环，同样让你的思维也参与圣灵的交流。有一种精神力量可供他汲取，这种力量无处不在，就如同他呼吸的空气一样。

55.人类平常的不端行为伤害不了宇宙，一个人特定的不端行为也伤害不了同胞。这种不端行为伤害不了别人，只能伤害犯过者自己。而且他只要愿意，就能从中解脱出来。

56.我邻居的意愿如同他的身体和呼吸一样，与我毫不相干。无论我们相互之间多么默契，各自仍然具有独立的权利。否则，他的不端行为便会成为我的罪恶。神灵不希望这样的事情发生，以防别人恣意毁掉我的幸福。

57.人们看到，太阳将光和热撒向四方，自己却从不枯竭。这种普照是一种自我扩展。实际上，日光之名，来源于“可扩展”一词。想要了解日光的性能，就去观察黑暗房间里从狭窄小缝中透过的光线。日光延长成一条直线，直至碰上某一固体挡住了它的去路。它便停留在那儿，既不落下，也不离开。思想也应该像阳光一样发射和扩散永不枯竭，只扩展自己，碰到障碍物不是一味地横冲直撞，不是绝望地离开，而是站稳立场，照亮它所停留的物体。不让日光穿过，就是自己不要日光。

58.怕死的人要么害怕失去所有的感觉，要么对新感觉有恐惧。实际上，你要么什么都感觉不到，也就没有邪恶；要么，如果你能感觉到任何新鲜事物的话，就会脱胎换骨，生命也就不会停止。

59.人为彼此而存在。所以，要么提升他们，要么就容忍他们。

60.箭矢以一种方式飞行，而思想则以另一种方式传播。即使当思想摸索着谨慎行事、从不同角度寻找解决问题的方法时，它也是径直前行，直奔目标的。

61.仔细研究一下别人心灵的主导原则，并允许他也研究你心灵的主导原则。

卷十

1.啊，我的灵魂，你不愿永远善良真诚，完整坦诚，比包裹着你的肉体更加清晰地呈现在人们面前？你不愿永远体验充满关爱和柔情的心灵的甜蜜？你不愿永远充实，毫不匮乏，一无所求，既不渴求给你带来享受的人和物，也不希望延长享受他们的时光，不向往任何地方或国家、怡人的气候，不与佳人为伴吗？你何时才能安于现状，心满意足，相信一切皆属于你，皆为神灵所赐，现在和将来都会与你同在？为确保这生机勃勃的完美世界的安全和福祉，它们愿意授予你这一切。这世界多么高尚、公平、美好，它赋予万物生机，支持保护它们，等到它们消亡时再将它们聚集到自己的怀抱里，让其他更多同类涌现出来。你不愿永远成为神灵和人类的伙伴，对他们无怨无悔，也不使他们对你产生不满吗？

2.注意自己特殊本性的要求，要像完全臣服于大自然主宰的人一样。履行职责，接受命运，只要它能确保不伤害你的自然本性。还应该注意自然本性的需求，一一满足它们，只要它们能确保不伤害理性的本性（理性也直接意味着社会性）。遵守这些规则，不要在其他事物上枉费精力。

3.无论发生什么事情，大自然也许已经使你具备了面对它的能力，也许没有。一旦发生不幸，只要能够承受，就不要心生怨恨，就要以大自然赐予的能力去承受它。如果它超出了你的能力，依然不要心生怨恨，因为虽然它打败了你，但它自身也将不复存在。但要记住，其实自然已经让你具备了承受一切的能力，只要你将承受不幸当成对自身有益而且是职责所在的事情，你自己就会断定，它是可以承受、可以忍受的。

4.如果有人出了差错，要温和地提醒他，指出他的错误。如果说服不了他，就责怪自己吧，或者谁也不要指责。

5.你可能遭遇的一切，从时间伊始就已为你准备就绪。在错综复杂的因果关系中，你的生命之线一直就与某个特定事件交织在一起。

6.无论宇宙是由一团混乱的微粒组成，还是自然长成，我的第一信念是，我是大自然主宰下的宇宙整体的一部分。我的第二信念是，我和同类之间有着同胞关系。只要我铭记这两点，无论这个整体分配给我什么，作为其中的一部分，我首先不会感到委屈，因为有益于整体的事物绝不可能对局部有害，而整体也不会接纳对自己无益的事物（这也适用于每一个自然有机体；不过，宇宙的本性还具有更深一层的特征，即没有任何外因能迫使自己产生对自己有害的事物）。牢记自己是这一整体的一部分，我就会欣然接受任何可能的命运安排。其次，由于我和我的同类有着同胞关系，我不会作出任何有损于他们共同福祉的事情。相反，我会永远有意地为这些同胞着想，对他们有利的冲动就要鼓励，对他们不利的事情就要避免。这样一来，我的生活也会一帆风顺。这就如同我们想到的那些公务人员的生活那样一帆风顺。他们一贯服务于自己的同胞，并随时迎接自己的城市分派的任何使命。

7.整体的各个部分，我指的是宇宙自然包含的一切事物，迟早都会衰败。更准确地说，都会改变形态。一旦这种不可避免的改变在本质上对局部肯定有害，那么这个整体就无法继续正常运转。这是因为，这些局部始终都在形态上发生这样那样的变化，而且都在以各自的方式走向衰败。那么，是大自然有意加害自己的组成部分，使得它们不仅容易而且不可避免地受到伤害吗？或者，她对发生的一切并不知情？这两种猜测都不可信。就算我们把大自然本身完全排除在外，转而用正常的自然秩序来解释这一问题。如果我们认为这种局部的易变性很正常，同时又把这种易变看作非自然事件而感到震惊或愤恨，这种看法仍然荒谬。如果考虑到局部的变化不过是分解回它们原来的结构成分，这种看法就更加荒谬。说到底，如果分解不是组成元素的简单分解，那一定是肉体微粒转化为土的形态，精神微粒转化为气的形态，这样它们就能被普遍理性重新吸收（无论是定期被火焰吞噬，还是通过永无止境的变化周期不断更新自己）。但是记住，我们不能把这些微粒，不论是肉体的还是精神的，想象成我们出生时得到的那些微粒。我们现在整个身体结构的增加，得益于昨天或前天摄入的肉类和呼吸的空气。所以，承载这些变化的，早已不是我们母亲最初生下的身体，而是此后我们所接纳的物质（事实上，即便我们承认出生时就带有相当多先天的易变微粒，我也不认为这会影响我上述的观点）。

8.如果你认为自己配得上这些称赞，例如，善良、谦逊、真诚、敏锐、正直、高尚，就不要辜负它们。如果不小心失掉它们，要赶紧找回来。但要记住，“敏锐”就意味着能够思考鉴别出事物的细枝末节，并审慎地关注它们，“正直”意味着心甘情愿接受自然给你的一切，而“高尚”意味着理智的升华，它超越了或舒适或难受的肉体活动，也超越了极度的虚荣、死亡和其他使你分心的事物。不要辜负这些称赞，也不要热衷于别人对你的赞美，这样，你就会与众不同，你的人生也将与众不同。继续现在这种状态，被现在的生活所折磨、所玷污，那是傻瓜和懦夫的行为。就像武士在角斗场被野兽撕扯得血迹斑斑、遍体鳞伤，却仍然恳求把自己关起来，等到翌日再带着满身伤痕，被投入场中，丢给同样的獠牙和利爪。不如登上这个由形容词构成的小木筏吧，要是你能做到，就待在上面，只当被送到了福佑之岛。如果感到摇摇晃晃，控制不住自己的方向，就振作精神冲向宁静的避风港，在那儿你就能把握住自己。抑或就彻底告别人生，不在盛怒之下，而是简单、自由、低调地离开人世，这样看上去你的人生结束了，但至少人生中还有一件值得赞扬的事情。永远将这些形容词牢记在心，这会帮你记住神灵。还要牢记，神灵不愿受到恭维，而是希望有理性的万物都能像他们一样。另外还要记住，无花果树有无花果树的使命，狗有狗的使命，蜜蜂有蜜蜂的使命，人也如此。

9.日复一日，你周围尽是那些插科打诨、争吵斗嘴、胆小怯懦、散漫懒惰、卑躬屈膝的现象，这会让你忘却那些神圣的箴言。你没有深刻领会却漫不经心地丢弃了它们。你的使命要求你，在观察每件事物、进行每个行动时，不但要充分考虑环境的客观要求，还要充分运用自己的思维能力。此外，还要保持一切细节尽在掌握的自信（供备用，但绝不能忘记）。你永远不想得到一个真正诚实高贵的人所拥有的幸福吗？不想弄清每个事物最深层的本质，它在世界秩序中的位置，它自然存在的条件，它的组成结构，它的归属，以及谁有能力给予或收回它吗？

10.蜘蛛逮到苍蝇就觉得了不起。一个人捕到一只野兔，第二个人网到一条小鱼，第三个人俘获野猪、熊或是萨尔马提亚人，[17]也会自以为了不起。倘若深究一下原则性问题，这些行为岂不是与强盗无异？

11.养成习惯，定期观察宇宙的变化过程，一丝不苟地关注它，深入研究这门学问。没有比这更能提高智力的了。这是因为，当人意识到自己随时可能被迫放弃一切，离开同伴的时候，他就会抛开肉体，按照大自然的安排，以自己的行动全心全意地效力于正义事业。不再浪费精力去考虑别人会对自己说什么，想什么或做什么。能做到两件事就足矣：在日常行为中正派，对命运的安排满意。将烦心的事情、分心的事情统统搁置一边。唯一的雄心壮志就是在守法的大道上径直前行，由此成为神灵的追随者。

12.既然使命摆在你眼前，又何需猜测？只要道路清晰可见，就心怀善意大步前行，不要回头。如果不是这样，那就等待一下，听从最好的建议。倘若阻力继续出现，始终沿着正义指引的方向，尽量审慎地前进。获得正义就是无上的成功，因为人们通常会铩羽而归。

13.每天伊始都要自问：“别人正义、公正的行为对我有何影响？”没有。记住，那些人自以为是地愿意赞美或贬损别人，在生活中、睡觉时、饭桌旁也是一样。回想一下他们的所作所为，他们回避或追求的事物，他们的偷窃和掠夺行径。他们干这些时，并不是用手和脚，而是用他们最为宝贵的东西，那就是信仰的源泉、谦逊、真理、法律以及内心神灵这一宝贵财产，只要一个人想这样做。

14.面对大自然这一万物之源和归宿，一个谦顺、有教养的人会大声恳求：“如您所愿赐予，如您所愿收回。”但是在说这话时，不能哗众取宠，而要怀着纯粹的恭顺和善意。

15.如今你来日无多。那就如同置身山巅一样去度过它们吧。命运将人抛向何方并不重要，假如他无论身在何处，都将世界视为一座城市，将自己视为城市的公民。让人们有机会认识并了解一个遵循万物之法生活的纯粹的人。倘若有人看不惯，任凭他们将他除掉。这比像他们那样生活更好。

16.不要再浪费时间讨论高尚的人应该是什么样子。去做那样的人。

17.不断思考所有时间和所有存在，从而领悟到每个独立的事物和所有存在相比不过是一粒沙，和所有时间相比也只是拧紧一下螺丝的瞬间。

18.要认识一切实物的本性，观察每个事物现在还经历的变化和分解过程，已经处在其中的衰败和消散的过程，以及等待它的其他命运。

19.他们进餐、就寝、交媾、排泄，诸如此类。这都是一伙什么人呀！那么自以为是，那么傲慢无礼，那么专横跋扈，暴虐无道，那么目空一切，百般挑剔！刚才他们还在对那么多的人献媚拍马。为了同样的目的，用不了多久，他们还会这么做！

20.大自然创造万物众生，是为了他们的福祉，而且从他们诞生的那一刻起便已造福于他们。

21.“土地爱上了从天而降的阵雨，神圣的天国也沉浸于爱河之中。”这就是说，宇宙真的热爱创造一切事物的使命。因此，我对宇宙的回答必定是：“只要是您热爱的，我也热爱。”（这是不是跟人们通常说的某事物“乐于发生”是同一个意思？）

22.你可以继续生活在这里，毕竟你已经非常适应这里的习俗了。你也可以移居到你自由选择的任何其他地方。再不然就一死了之，这也意味着你使命的终结。除此之外，再无别的选择。所以随遇而安吧。

23.你应该明白，无论身在何处，你都能够拥有绿色田野般的宁静。在山上、在海边、在任何你想去的地方，情况都和这里一样。柏拉图有同样的观点，他曾说，生活在城墙之中“犹如在高山上的羊圈里给羊群挤奶”。

24.我的主宰理性对我意味着什么？此时此刻我理解它吗？我会如何使用它？它缺乏判断力吗？它是否脱离了伙伴之谊？它是否受肉体影响太深，还在回想肉体的多变与摇摆不定？

25.仆人挣脱了主人就是逃跑。对我们而言，我们的主人就是法律。因此，犯法的人就是逃犯。然而，悲伤、愤怒、恐惧都是对某种事物的排斥，这种事物不论过去，现在还是将来都是由主宰宇宙的力量来规定的。也就是说，由法来规定的。法规定，一切生灵皆有权益[18]。所以，屈服于恐惧、悲伤或愤怒，便是逃跑。

26.男人在子宫里下种之后便扬长而去。然后另一个因缘接手，开始工作，使其发育成为一个完美的婴儿。这是多么奇妙的转变！这个男子咽下食物，某种其他因缘再次接手，把食物转化成感觉、动作以及，简言之，生命、精力和其他各种各样的产物。想想这些过程是多么奇妙。观察其中发挥作用的力量，就像观察让事物向上或向下运动的力量一样。当然并非用眼睛观察，但一样能看得清晰。

27.经常回想一下，今天的生活就是以往生活的重复。你会注意到这也预示了将来要发生的事情。再看看很多戏剧和场景，它们都是如此地相似，那是因为你已经从亲身经历和过去的历史中熟悉了它们。例如，哈德良皇帝的整个朝廷，安东尼纳斯皇帝的朝廷，还有菲利普、亚历山大、克罗伊斯[19]的朝廷。演出都一样，只是演员不同罢了。

28.如果看到有人烦恼或者愤怒，就想象一下宰牲屠刀下又踢又叫的猪。如果看到另外一个人独自卧病在床，默默哀叹着我们对他的束缚。这种情形也好不到哪里去。唯有理性生命具备主动适应环境的能力，而适应本身则是世间万物必须服从的苛刻要求。

29.无论处理什么事情，每走一步都要停下来问自己：“是不是因为害怕丧失它，我才会畏惧死亡？”

30.如果别人的错误冒犯了你，就反省一下自己是否也有同样的毛病。你是不是也从财富、享受、名声以及类似的东西中受益？想到这里，你的怒气很快就会烟消云散，因为他的行为不过是重压之下的反应，否则他还能怎么做呢？或者，如果你有能力，就设法把他从压力下解救出来。

31.看见萨特隆就想起了已故的苏格拉底派学者欧迪奇和许门，看见幼发拉底河就想起埃夫蒂希翁和西尔法努斯，看见阿尔齐弗隆就想起特罗佩奥福鲁斯，看见西弗勒斯就想起克里托和色诺芬，看见自己就想起在你之前的那些帝王。所以，每个人都应该想想和自己相对应的人，然后再想想：“他们现在身在何处？”无处可寻或者无处不在。于是，你渐渐习惯将尘世的一切视为蒸汽或者虚无。而且，你还应该记住，世事一旦改变就不可挽回。既然如此，何苦还要挣扎较劲，何不以恰当得体的方式度过短暂的人生？想想你都永远拒绝了什么物质和可能，因为只要你的理性学会用适当的哲学眼光看清人生的真谛，你所经受的苦难不过是对自己理性的磨练。耐心一些，直到你对它们习以为常，就如同强健的胃能够消化吸收各种食物，或者明亮的火焰能够把投入其中的一切化作热能和烈焰一样。

32.不要让任何人有权理直气壮地指责你不守诚信或不善良。即便有人这么想，也要确保他们的想法毫无根据。这完全取决于你自己，试想谁能阻止你做一个善良诚实的人呢？如果你不能这样生活，就只能决心一死了之。因为这种情况下，即使理性本身也不允许你继续存在。

33.对你拥有的物质应该如何评价或处置才最恰当呢？不管怎样，你都有权对它们评价或处置。但是不要假装做不了主。你的这些烦恼会无休无止，直至一个人以所能得到的物质履行自己天职对你的意义，就像他的享乐对骄奢淫逸者的意义一样（的确，我们每次按照正当的、与生倶来的本能行事，都应该看作是一种享乐，而现在这样的机会无处不在）。诚然，滚轮并不总是能够随意滚动，水不能，火不能，其他受自己本性或非理性灵魂主宰的事物也都不能。有诸多因素制约着它们。但是，心灵和理性却能跨越一切障碍，因为本性使它们具备这样的能力，而意志也促使它们这么做。想象一下，理性是如何不费吹灰之力跨越每一个障碍的，就如同火焰上窜、石头下落或者滚轮滚下斜坡一样。除此之外，别无所求。不管怎样，干扰只能影响身体（即无生命的事物），否则就不能压垮或伤害我们，除非我们抱有成见和丧失理智。如若不然，它们将危及主体。尽管纵观宇宙，我们知道，灾难的发生往往牵涉到受害者自身的某种堕落。但就人而言，只要他能正确利用逆境，我们甚至可以断言他会因祸得福，变得更高尚，更值得赞扬。总之，永远不要忘记，不能伤害城市的事情必定不能伤害城里真正的公民，不能伤害法律的事情必定不能伤害城市。我们所说的厄运并不伤害法律，因而也不能伤害城市或公民。

34.真正的原则一旦被人铭记在心，即便是最常见的事情都足以让他回想起遗憾和恐惧的无用。例如：

“人类的孩子是什么？无非是被风吹落的树叶。”

这些树叶就是你们心爱的孩子。树叶也是民众，是那些尖声喝彩、大声咒骂或者暗地讥讽的具有潜在说服力的声音。从此你的声望将落入这些树叶的手中。它们都是“春天的花朵”，大风将它们吹落，不久森林又在它们原来的地方添上新绿。短暂是每个人的标记，而你却追逐或避开它们，仿佛它们将万世永生。不久以后，你将闭上双眼，而那些送你入土的人，很快也会有人为他们流下泪水。

35.健康的眼睛能看清所有可见的物体，而不会要求只看绿色，因为那样只能说明视觉有了问题。同样，健康的听觉和嗅觉应该对各种声音和气味都很敏感，健康的胃能够接纳各种肉类，就好比碾子会碾碎任何谷物一样。同样，健康的心灵也应该对于任何事情都有所准备。“让我的孩子获得赦免吧。”或者“让我的每一个行为获得举世的赞美吧。”提出这种要求的心灵，就如同只想看见绿色的眼睛，只想吃到柔软食物的牙齿一样。

36.—个人临终前，如果有人在他床边高兴地为即将失去他而欢呼，他就是一个十分幸运的人了。就算此人品德高尚、聪明睿智，到头来就不会有人这样小声嘀咕吗？“总算摆脱了主人，我们又能自由地呼吸了！其实他对我们从来不疾言厉色，但我总觉得他背地里瞧不起我们。”德高望重者的命运尚且如此，至于我等之辈，很多朋友都有充足的理由高兴地摆脱我们！当大限来临时，想想这些吧。“那些我为之辛劳、为之祈祷和为之牵挂的亲密伙伴，竟然都盼着我离开，从而获得解脱。这就是我要告别的世界。这种情况下谁还会渴望延年益寿？”想到这些，你的离开就要轻松得多。然而，不要因此在临终前减少对他们的仁慈，要保持惯有的友好、善意和仁慈，不要把离开当成悲伤的事情，而要把你的离开就看作是灵魂轻松飘离肉体的无痛终结。从前，大自然把你和这些人连在一起，变成他们中的一员。如今，她松开了这一纽带。于是，我被松开，脱离自己的亲族，毫无抵抗，毫无强迫。死亡只是大自然的又一个方式而已。

37.对于每一个行动，不论执行者是谁，都要养成习惯问问自己：“他做这件事的目的是什么？”就从自己开始，首先要问自己这个问题。

要记住，主宰我们的是深藏于我们内心的神秘力量。那里有劝导，有真实的生命，也可以说有我们自己。绝不要幻想，这种力量会被外面包裹的肉体和附着的器官所困扰。它们只是附在身体上生长，就如同木匠的斧子一样只是工具罢了。失去推动或者遏制它们的介质，它们就像离开了织匠的梭子，离开了作家的笔，或者没有车夫的鞭子一样毫无用处。

卷十一

1.理性的灵魂具有以下这些特性。她会自我思考，自我分析，根据自己的意愿塑造自己，享受自己的成果（树上结的果实，和动物产子一样，是供他人享用的），无论生命在何时终结，她总能完美地完成自己的使命。而舞蹈、戏剧或是其他类似的东西则不然，一旦中途被打断，演出就不完整了。灵魂无论何时被终止，都能心满意足地完成使命，并能够宣称：“我完全主宰自己的人生。”而且，她能够随意包容整个宇宙，包括它自身的结构和外层空间，一直延伸到永远，接受并理解伟大的周期性重生，因此懂得后世子孙看到的世界并不新奇，就像我们的父辈看到的世界并不比我们现在看到的多。而且，一个年近四十的人，只要具有一些领悟力，由于事物的相似性，他实际上就已经预见到过去和将来可能发生的一切事情。最后，热爱他人、真诚、谦虚、尊重自我甚于一切，这些都是理性的灵魂具有的优点。尊重自己甚于一切，这也是法律的特性之一。由此可以断定，理性原则和正义原则是完全一致的。

2.面对歌舞或者竞技表演的诱惑，你很快就会无动于衷了，只要你把美妙的乐曲分解成几个音节，再依次问问自己：“我抵御不了这些吗？”你会不愿意承认。对舞者的每一动作和姿态、运动员的每一表现也同样如法炮制。总之，除了美德及其内涵之外，永远记住，直奔它们的组成部分，通过拆分，就能摆脱迷恋。现在，再把这种方法运用到整个生活中去。

3.如果不管何时接到脱离肉体的命令，灵魂都能随时准备就绪，面对毁灭、消散，或是生存下去。这样的灵魂是多么幸福。不过，是否准备就绪必须取决于它自己。这绝非是像那些基督徒[20]那样因要抗命而起的念头，而是经过了严肃的深思熟虑。而且为了让人信服，不要有任何豪言壮语。

4.我做过无私的事情吗？如果有，我已经得到了回报。要时常这么想，并且坚持下去。

5.你有什么本事？善良。除非具有哲学家的洞察力，能看透宇宙的本性和人的特性，否则你又如何能够凭善良取得成功呢？

6.戏剧最初采用悲剧的形式来表现人生的变迁，以提醒我们不幸事件的发生是多么合情合理。而且，既然悲剧在舞台上能给我们带来快乐，在现实生活这一更广阔的舞台上我们就无权因为不幸事件的发生而感到悲伤。这些戏剧告诉我们，尽管人的行为会带来不可避免的后果，尽管人们会痛苦地脱口而出：“啊，西塞隆山[21]！”但是他们依然承受得起。而且，悲剧作家笔下经常能诞生一些颇有裨益的词句，特别是这些：

“如果上天不眷顾我和我那两个儿子，那必定有充足的理由。”

还有：

“不要为事情的发展进程劳神费心。”

或者：

“生命的收获与收割玉米别无二致。”

还有很多诸如此类的名言警句。

除了悲剧，还有语言犀利如学校教师的旧喜剧[22]，它以其独特的直言不讳，无情鞭挞了人性的傲慢（第欧根尼在某种程度上也采用了同样的手法）。然而，后来的中期喜剧[23]和最终的新喜剧[24]很快就衰落为矫揉造作的摹拟剧[25]。诚然，正如我们所知，这些后来的剧作家也曾说过一些名言警句。可是，他们诗歌和戏剧的眼界和立意又有多大分量呢？

7.显然，你现在碰到的生活条件用于哲学实践再合适不过了。

8.从临近树枝上断开的树杈，必然与整棵树木分离。同样，与同伴分离的人也就脱离了整个社会。只不过，树枝是被人砍下来的，人则是出于憎恨与厌恶而疏远自己的邻居，他并不知道他同时也就脱离了整个社会。尽管如此，仰仗着创造伙伴之谊的宙斯的仁慈，我们依然有能力与邻里重修旧好，融入其中，为整体社会的融合再尽一份力量。一旦这种分离的行为经常发生，分离者就很难再回归整体并重修旧好了。一根从头到尾陪伴树木成长、一直分享树木生命的枝杈，跟砍断之后嫁接起来的枝杈，有着天壤之别。正如园丁所说，出于同一棵树，却不是出于同一灵魂。

9.虽然有人可能阻止你走理性之路，但他绝不能干扰你理智的行为。要确信他们同样不能摧毁你对他们的仁慈之心。你还要同样坚守以下两种立场：决策行事要坚定，同时对试图阻挠或者干扰你的人要温和。因他们而恼怒，与放弃自己的行动方针和被逼投降，都是极为软弱的表现。这两种情形都属于擅离职守。一种是由于缺乏勇气，另一种是由于疏远自己天生的兄弟和伙伴。

10.任何自然的表现形式都远胜于艺术，因为每一种艺术都只是对自然的模仿。至高无上的大自然，比一切凡人都更完美更全面，比他们的技艺更超群。而且，艺术只不过是以高于事物的眼光创造出的低级作品，这与大自然的手法如出一辙。从这里我们能看到正义之源，其他美德都取决于此。如果我们一心追求具有次要价值的事物，并甘心停留在上当受骗、刚愎自用、反复无常的状态，我们就永远无法获得真正的正义。

11.凡是让你苦恼或者愤怒继而想追求或者回避的事情，往往不会自己找上门，而是你主动招惹的。尽量不要对它们进行评判，这样它们就不会轻举妄动，你也就不会追求或者躲避它们了。

12.只要灵魂既不向外张扬拼命追求，也不向内收缩，既不零星地散布自己，也不凹陷垮塌下去，而是沐浴在展示世人和她本色的光辉之中，她就能保持自己完美的球形。

13.有人会嘲笑我吗？那是他的事情。我要做的事是，不做可以让他嘲笑的事情，不说可以让他嘲笑的话。他会不会恨我？那也是他的事情。我要做的事是，和所有的人友好和睦地相处，随时指出这个人错误在哪里，既不对他反唇相讥，也不故作宽容，而是像老福基翁[26]那样心胸坦荡、宽宏大量（我们姑且假设他的话不是纯粹的谎言）。这才是人应该具有的正确精神。他绝不应让神灵看到自己对自己的遭遇心怀不满或喊冤叫屈。只要你遵循正确的做人准则，随时接受大自然认为恰当的东西，就像一个尽力促进世界福祉的纯粹的人那样，邪恶又怎么可能伤害到你呢？

14.他们鄙视对方却又互相讨好。每人都想胜过对方，却在其面前表现得畏首畏尾、卑躬屈膝。

15.假如有人说：“我决心对你知无不言，言无不尽。”这话听起来多么空洞，多么虚伪。哎呀，伙计，何必如此费事？这种事情不言自明，根本无须开场白。它就写在你的额头上，回荡在你的语调里，闪耀在你的眼神里，宛如深爱的恋人只需秋波一送，对方便已心知肚明。真诚和善良自有其毋庸置疑的味道，能让遇到它的人立刻就能不由自主地意识到它的存在。伪装的直率是一把隐藏的匕首。狼一般虚情假意最为卑劣，也最应该避之而唯恐不及。真正善良、真诚、好心的人，相由心生，没人看不出来。

16.任何灵魂，只要对无关紧要的事情采取漠不关心的态度，就能够完美地过上高尚生活。为此，首先要仔细查看事物的组成因素，然后再看事物本身。你还要记住，我们对它们看法如何，它们自己毫无责任，它们并未主动接近我们，它们依然处于静止状态，是我们对它们形成看法，并把这些看法铭记在心。事实上，我们完全能够不在心中留下任何印记，至少也能够迅速删除无意留下的任何印记。你还要记住，你没有多少时间来关注这些事情，我们的赛跑马上就要开始了。如果事情不总是尽如你意，也不要觉得委屈。只要它们符合本性，就该感到欣慰，就不要提出异议。如果它们不符合本性，那就找出自己本性要求你做的事情，并且全力以赴地去做。人总有理由去寻求自己的利益。

17.思考每一个事物的起源、构成、变化、变化之后的状态；发生变化对它并无丝毫损害。

18.当你被冒犯时，首先，要听取别人的意见。牢记自己和同伴之间的亲密关系。这是公认的做法，因为我们为彼此而生。还有另一个原因，我天生就是他们的领袖，如同公羊天生就要领导羊群，公牛天生就要领导牛群。或者回到最初的法则，因为世界不仅仅是微粒，它必定要受大自然的主宰，低级事物必然要为高级事物而存在，高级事物必然要为彼此而存在。

其次，要想想他们的性格，居家就寝时的表现，尤其是他们的思维方式所施加的压力以及随之而来的自恃。正是这种自恃导致他们作出如此行径。

第三，如果他们的行为正当，你就不应该生气。反之，就只能是无心所致，无意为之。正如“无人会故意犯错”，同样无人会故意使他人得不到应得的待遇。倘若有人指责他们不公正、忘恩负义、小气吝啬，或者其他对邻居的不端行为，要观察他们是否愤怒。

第四，你自己也会以各种方式冒犯别人，跟他们毫无区别。诚然，你能够避免某些错误，但是出错总是难免的。即使出于对自己名声的顾忌或其他卑鄙的动机，你没有效仿他们的卑劣行径，情况也是如此。

第五，你没有十足的把握判定人家就是行为不端。要知道人的行为动机并非总像表现出来的那样。对别人的行为，通常还要了解很多东西才能作出正确的判断。

第六，如果你气急败坏，快要失去耐心，就告诉自己这种尘世生活是短暂的，不久我们都会长眠地下。

第七，并不是这些人的行为令我们恼火，那是他们自己的理性应该关注的事情；我们恼火的原因是我们自己给这些人的行为添加了色彩。去掉色彩、去掉所有认为他们十恶不赦的想法，怒气便会立刻烟消云散。去掉色彩有什么作用呢？想想看，至少不会使你蒙羞。因为，如果道德上蒙羞不算一种罪恶，你就会作出很多作奸犯科的事情，比如抢劫和其他恶行。

第八，怒气和烦恼，比让我们生气和烦恼的事情本身更有害。

第九，仁慈之心难以抗拒，只要它是出自真心，不带虚假笑容和口是心非。只要你始终以仁慈之心对待冒犯你的人，有机会就对他好言相劝，最放肆无理的行径也无法对你造成伤害。如果他要对你恶语相加，你就悄悄地把他拉到一边，对他说：“不要这样，我的孩子。我们天生不该如此。你伤害不了我，只会伤害你自己。”彬彬有礼地用平实的语言向他说明理由，告诉他连蜜蜂和其他群居动物都不会像他这样行事。但是，不要使用讽刺挖苦或者挑剔的语言，而要怀有真情实感和一颗远离怨恨的心。既不要像学校老师的那种做派，也不要想博取旁观者的仰慕。尽管有他人在场，也要仿佛只有你和他单独相处。

牢记住这九条建议，就当是缪斯女神赐予你的礼物。既然你的生命还在继续，那就学着成熟起来。在避免与人斗气时，还要小心提防谄媚者。谄媚和冒犯别人一样违背公共福祉，二者皆会导致祸害。每当怒气上冲，就这样想：发脾气绝非男子气概的表现，而温柔平和的人不仅更显得有人情味而且更具男子气概。只有这种人，而非他怒气冲冲、心怀不满的伙伴，才能证明自己的强大、勇敢和阳刚。愤怒和悲伤一样都是软弱的表现，它们只会给人带来伤害，让人屈从于失败。

此外，如果愿意，就把下面的话当作第十份礼物。这份礼物直接来自缪斯女神的上司本人。指望坏人永远不做坏事是不明智的，就等于期待不可能发生的事情发生一样。容忍他们冒犯别人，却指望他们不冒犯你，这种想法不仅荒谬而且武断。

19.灵魂的舵手有四项毛病，你必须时常留心提防，一旦发现要立即制止。你要一一对它们这样说：“这种想法毫无必要”“这人会暗中破坏伙伴之谊”“这不是我内心的真实想法”（记住，不说自己的真实想法是最不合时宜的事情）。还有第四条，当你想作自我批评的时候，想道：“这样将证明我内心的神性曾经被迫臣服于卑鄙腐朽的肉体的粗俗想法”。

20.尽管你身体里气性和火性的微粒天生具有上冲的倾向，但仍然臣服于宇宙的法则，受制于它们所组成的机体。另一方面，你身体里水性和土性的微粒，尽管也有下沉的趋势，但是也被托住，处于一种感到不自然的状态。因此，连微粒都遵守宇宙的法则，一旦被送到某个位置，必然停留在那儿，直至解散的信号将它们再次召回。那么，你身体中只有一个部分不服从命令，在既定领域内制造摩擦，而它竟然是你的思想，这难道不令人悲哀吗？不要它作出极端的行为，只要求它符合自己的本性。但它不肯听从，反而向相反的方向奔跑。这种奔向不公、放纵、愤怒、悲伤或是恐惧的行为不就是故意背离本性吗？一旦灵魂的舵手对发生的事情感到不满，它就立刻擅离职守。它存在的目的是为了表现神圣，为了表达对神灵的崇敬，同样也是为了正义。而作为宇宙的伙伴关系的一部分，前两者必须置于正义之前。

21.如果人生没有始终如一的统一目标，它就不会保持一贯和统一。但仅有这种说法还不够，还要补充说明人生目标应该是什么。意见的统一并不体现在那些我们通常认为好的事情上，而是体现在某种特定的事物上：即那些关系到社会福祉的事情上。所以，我们给自己确定的人生目标应该是有利于同胞和社会的。无论谁指引他朝着这一方向努力，都会把这种统一贯彻到他的一切行为之中，从而实现一贯性。

22.别忘了乡下耗子遇见城里耗子的寓言[27]，那次相见给他带去多少不安和焦虑。

23.苏格拉底的名字对于普通人而言，就是吓唬孩童的“妖怪”。

24.斯巴达人在公共场合看演出的时候，总是让客人坐在阴凉的地方，而自己随便坐哪儿都行。

25.苏格拉底曾经以这样的理由拒绝佩尔狄卡斯朝廷的邀请，他说：“我不想带着耻辱走进坟墓。"意思是，他不会接受偿还不起的恩惠。

26.以弗所人的经文有一条劝世良言，要人们经常回顾过去道德生活的典范。

27.毕达哥拉斯学派的人每天早上都要凝视上苍，以此提醒他们自己那些物体在始终如一、按时按点地履行着自己的使命，同时也让他们自己记住天空井然有序、纯净无瑕、袒露无疑的质朴。毕竟，轻纱遮不住繁星。

28.想想苏格拉底，妻子披着他的毯子走后，他只能以羊皮裹身。想想朋友们看见他这副打扮都尴尬地躲着他，而他对朋友们是怎么说的。[28]

29.在读书写字的时候，你只有学会遵守规则之后才会制定规则。生活中更是如此。

30.“天生奴性十足，理性与你无缘。”

31.“……我在心中朗声大笑。”

32.“他们只知道挑衅美德，并对美德恶言相向。”

33.“傻瓜才会在冬天寻找无花果；错过了时节才寻找孩子的人也是如此。”

34.埃皮克提图曾经说过：“一边亲吻孩子一边小声嗫嚅着明天也许他就会死去。”人们对他说：“这是不祥的言辞。”他回答道：“绝对不是。只是说明一种自然行为。能说收割成熟的玉米也是不祥之兆吗？”

35.“绿色葡萄，累累熟果，葡萄干。一步一个变化，不是变成其他，而是变成未来。”

36.埃皮克提图写道：“没人能剥夺你的自由意志。”

37.他还说，我们应该演化出某种恰当的制度来表示赞许。对于冲动，我们必须小心对待，使它们不断修正，摆脱自私自利，根据是非曲直秉公办事。欲望也该极度受到限制，厌恶也应该仅限于我们能够掌控的事情。

38.他还说：“这里争论的不是琐事，而是明智与荒谬的问题。”

39.苏格拉底会问：“你想要哪种人的灵魂，通情达理的还是不讲道理的？”

“通情达理的人。”

“通情达理的人是健全的，还是有病的？”

“健全的。”

“那为何不去寻找他们？”

“因为我们已经找到了。”

“既然如此，为何还要争来斗去？”

卷十二

1.你祈求今后获得的所有祝福现在就能实现，只要你不拒绝它们。你只需彻底告别过去，将未来交给天意，设法把眼下的时间恰当地引入神圣和正义的轨道：神圣是指满怀爱心接受命运的安排，那是大自然专门为你匹配的命运；正义是指说话直截了当，真实坦诚，做事尊重法律和所有人的权利。不能允许蓄意害人、误解别人，或者诽谤他人的行为阻挠自己，也不允许肉欲成为绊脚石。受折磨的部分将会照料自己。大限临近，如果你能忘掉一切，只专注于灵魂的舵手和内心闪光的神性，如果能放下早晚会有一死的恐惧，转而担心至今未能按照本性的原则生活，你还来得及成为无愧宇宙赐予你生命的真正的人，而不是成为自己家乡的陌生人，对每天发生的事情都不知所措，就像遇到奇迹时始终不知该相信哪一个那样。

2.神灵审视着人的内心世界，剔除一层层物质的包裹、外壳和渣滓。他只通过思想，同人们心中发源于他的部分接触。你也如此这般地训练自己，能省去很多分心的事情。一个既然不在意肉体躯壳的人，还会为服饰、住宅、名声，或者生活中其他外在表现和布景而烦恼吗？

3.你由三部分构成：肉体、呼吸、心灵。前两项属于你，仅仅因为你有责任照料它们。只有最后一项才真正属于你。那么，如果你能从真正的自我，也就是说从你的理智，摒除别人的一切言行，摒除自己过去的一切言行，摒除你对未来的一切焦虑，摒除影响肉体及其伙伴呼吸的，你无法掌控的一切东西，摒除像旋涡一样在你周围打转的一切外部事物，这样，你那远离这些命中注定之事的心灵，就有能力独立生活，行正事，认天命，说真话。如果你能从自己的主宰理性中摒除一切附着物，摒除未来或过去发生的一切，像恩培多克勒所说的那样，学会当“一个自得其乐的彻头彻尾的球体”，只关心你目前的生活、现世的人生，那么你将平静仁慈、与内心的神性和谐一致地度过余生，直至大限来临。

4.我经常感到惊奇，明明人人都爱自己甚于别人，但他们却重视别人的评价甚于自己。假如神灵或是智者站在旁边，吩咐他内心有什么想法和动机就应当立刻公之于众，他肯定一天都忍受不了。因此，他人的评价在我们心目中的分量，比自我评价要重得多。

5.神灵把一切筹划得天衣无缝，如此仁慈的他唯独会忽略了这件事吗？那就是，即使那些德高望重的人，那些与神灵关系最密切的人，那些因杰出贡献和献身精神而与神灵关系密切的人，死后都不能重生，并且注定要彻底消失。不过，如果他们果真命该如此，可以肯定的是，但凡需要改变计划，神灵一定自有安排，但凡符合大自然的意志，大自然早就安排好了。如若不然（假如事实也的确不是如此），你就可以相信这件事情本不该如此。因此你肯定能看出，你提出这样无聊的问题，就是在指责神灵。如果这些问题不是极端高尚与正义，我们怎能这样把它们与神灵联系在一起呢？如果它们是极端的高尚与公正，神灵在安排宇宙时又怎能允许发生这样不公或不合情理的疏漏呢？

6.即便看起来成功无望，也要坚持练习。左手因疏于练习而在其他方面显得不够灵活，但是却能比右手更有力地抓住缰绳，这正是勤于练习的结果。

7.要冥想死神来临时自己的肉体和灵魂应该处于怎样的状态，冥想生命之短暂以及生前、死后永恒的无尽深渊，冥想物质世界的脆弱。

8.剥去事物的外壳，勘察最深层的本源；注意行为背后的动机；研究痛苦、快乐、死亡、荣耀的实质；看看人类的不安完全是咎由自取；看看麻烦绝不可能出自他人之手，麻烦和其他事物一样，都是我们主观意念的产物。

9.运用原则时，要学职业拳师，而不要学剑客。剑客放下刀剑之后，还得重新捡起来；而拳师绝不会没有手，他要做的只是攥紧拳头。

10.想想事物的构成，将其分解为内容、形式和目的。

11.神灵赐予人类的恩惠何其丰厚。只做神灵赞许的事情，接受神灵分配的一切！

12.不要因世间的秩序而责怪神灵，因为无论是有意还是无心，他们都没有做错。也不要责怪人类，他们实属无心犯过。抛开所有兴师问罪的念头。

13.对生活中发生的一切都感到震惊，这是多么荒唐可笑又稀奇古怪的事情！

14.劫数不可阻挡，规律不可侵犯，老天尚且慈悲，否则天地便沦为毫无意义、不受管束的混沌世界。如果命运无法抗拒，为何还要奋力抗争？如果上天慈悲，你要竭尽所能对得起神灵的救助。如果世界漫乱不堪，在狂风暴雨的汪洋之中，你应心存感激，因为你还拥有心灵的舵手。如果海水吞没了你，就让污水吞没你的肉体、呼吸和其他一切，但是永远无法颠覆心灵。

15.灯笼的火焰闪耀着明亮的光芒直至熄灭，而真理、智慧、正义却在你的生命湮灭之前消失在你心里吗？

16.如果感觉有人做了错事，就这样想：“我凭什么断定人家做得不对呢？”况且，即便他真的错了，难道他就不可能已经自责过吗？否则他的指甲为什么明显地抓破了自己的面容呢？指望流氓不再做坏事就好比希望无花果的汁液不带酸味，希望婴儿不啼哭，希望马儿不嘶叫，或者希望生活中其他不可避免的事情永远不发生。请问，他性格如此，怎么能作出别样的事呢？如果你觉得这太让人生气，那就改变它吧。

17.不对的事绝不要做。不是真话绝不要说。要控制自己的冲动。

18.看问题始终要看整体。找到真正给你留下印象的东西，把它解剖成原因、内容、目的、持续的时间。

19.趁着还来得及，努力发觉自己内心比本能更高尚、更神圣的东西。本能只能驱动你的情感，把你像木偶一样拉扯。那么，此时此刻它们之中到底是什么让我的理智变得阴沉暗淡？是恐惧、妒忌、欲望，还是别的什么？

20.首先，要避免随意或者漫无目的的行为。其次，要确保自己的每一个行为都只以公益为目的。

21.记住，很快你就会化作虚无，很快你眼前的一切连同生活中不可缺少的东西都将不复存在。万事万物生来都要变化、终止、消亡，这样其他事物才有可能出现。

22.万事皆出自你的主观意念，而你的主观意念则出自你自己。愿意的话就放弃它，你立刻就绕过了海岬，一切风平浪静。那是一片宁静的海洋，一个无潮的避风港。

23.无论何种行动适时地进入尾声，此时的终止对行动本身毫无损害，行动实施者也不会因此而变得更糟。所以，如果生活（无非是我们行为的总和）也适时终止，它的终止对生活毫无损害，也不会对适时终结全部行动的人产生不利影响。只是，恰当的时间和期限则由本性决定。假如不由人的本性决定，比如，年事偏高，那么就会由大自然她自己决定。大自然不断更新自己，以便让宇宙能永葆青春和活力。服务于这一整体意图的一切事物，永远会呈现一派欣欣向荣的景象。同样，生命的终结对人类无害。因为死亡不受他左右，也绝非为了追逐私利，所以死亡不会让他受辱。相反，死亡甚至可以说是件好事，因为对宇宙而言，这是件恰逢其时、有益，与其他事物都不矛盾的事情。所以，人类只要听从神灵的安排，在思想上与他保持一致，就会在神灵的推动下前行。

24.有三条忠告值得你铭记心间。第一条忠告有关行为：绝不要肆意妄为，或者作出违背正义的事情。你一定要记住，所有外部事情，无不是机缘巧合或者天意的结果。你不能指责偶然性，也不能指责天意。第二，好好思考一下世间万物的本质，从最初的种子到灵魂的产生，再到最终的回归。事物由什么物质构成，又将分解成什么物质。第三，想象一下自己突然被送入云端，将地面上人类的活动尽收眼底：置身于周围众多神灵之中，凡间的景象会令你不屑一顾。何况，无论将你托高多少次，你依然会看到同样的景象，单调而短暂。偏偏这些景象就是我们到处夸耀的东西！

25.一旦驱散你看到的景象，你就脱离了危险。那么，是谁不让你这样做呢？

26.如果你对事情感到不满，说明你已忘记：违背大自然意愿的事情是不会发生的；你的不当行为不是你自己造成的；无论过去、现在、将来，这是事物发生的唯一方式。你还忘记了同胞之间兄弟般的亲密感情，忘记了这种兄弟之情并非出自血缘关系或者人类种子，而是源于一种共同的智慧。这种智慧体现在每个人身上就是神灵，是神性的释放。你忘记了一切并非理所当然为人类所有，因为甚至包括他的孩子、他的肉体和灵魂，统统来自同一个神灵。你还忘记了，万事万物皆取决于意念，眼下正在流逝的瞬间就是人类能够拥有或失去的全部。

27.思考一下那些从不节制欲望的人和那些登上荣耀、灾难、骂名或者其他机遇之巅的人。然后想想：“他们现在身在何处？”早已灰飞烟灭，成为了传说，或许连传说都没有。好好想想那些数不胜数的例子：在自己宅邸的法比乌斯·卡特利卢斯、在自家花园的卢修斯·卢柏斯、在巴亚的斯德丁尼阿斯、在卡普里的台比留、贝利亚斯·鲁弗斯，以及一切在傲慢驱使下卖力追求事物的例子。他们的努力多么卑鄙可耻！以正义、节制和对神灵的忠诚为宗旨才符合哲学家的身份。要始终保持淳朴，因为谦恭的外表下膨胀起来的傲慢是最让人无法容忍的。

28.有人固执地问我：“你在何处见过神灵，为何对他们的存在这么肯定，还如此崇拜他们？”我的回答就是：“首先，肉眼就能看到他们[29]。其次，我也从未见过自己的灵魂，但我依然崇敬它。对神灵也是如此，我每天的经历都证明着他们的力量，所以我确信他们的存在，我崇敬他们。”

29.为了过上健康安全的生活，要培养透彻的洞察力，以发掘事物的本质、内容和根源；要全心全意地投入正义的事业，不说假话；除此之外，还要积累善行直到没有空隙和裂缝为止，这样你才能体会到生活的乐趣。

30.阳光是完整的，尽管被墙、高山和众多其他事物所阻断。物质是完整的，尽管被划分成无数不同的、各具独特性的生命机体。灵魂是完整的，尽管它按照数不胜数的不同比例分布于数不胜数的生物体内。即便是别具思维能力的灵魂，尽管看不见，同样也是完整的。一切有机体的其他部分，比如呼吸，则是物质的，不具备感知能力，彼此没有亲和性，仅仅是靠统一的引力才聚集在一起。然而，思维因其自身的特性，会自发地趋向同类并与之融合。因此，统一的本能是无法挫败的。

31.你为何要渴望延年益寿，是为了体验感官刺激、满足欲望，还是为了促进或中止成长的过程？或者为了运用说话和思维的能力？这些事情真的值得你贪恋吗？如果认为它们都不值一顾，那就坚决争取实现终极目标，即追随理性和神灵。然而你要记住，珍视这一目标，就不要有任何不满情绪，不要认为死亡夺走了你的其他一切。

32.我们每个人得到的时间，只是无限永恒之中极其微不足道的一部分。眨眼之间，它便消失在永恒之中。你所得到的物质，与全世界相比也是极其微不足道的一部分；你的灵魂，同样也是全世界灵魂中极其微不足道的一部分；你所走过的土地跟整个世界相比极其渺小。在你仔细思考这些事物时，打定主意依照自己本性的指引做事，承受自然赐予你的一切。除此之外，一切都毫无意义。

33.我灵魂的舵手如何发挥作用？一切皆源于它。其他一切，无论我能否掌控，都是累累白骨和空气。

34.—想到把快乐看作善、把痛苦看作恶的人都能做到藐视死亡，没有比这更能激发对死亡的蔑视了。

35.当人在冥冥之中注定的那个时刻发现了自己唯一的美德，他不在意自己做得太多还是太少，只要所做之事严格符合理性的要求，他凝视世界的时间长短对他已无关紧要的时候，死亡本身已不再让他感到恐惧。

36.人啊，你享有这个伟大的世界之城的公民权利，五年还是一百年，对你又有什么意义？那个城市制定的所有法律，对所有人一视同仁。那你的悲伤又从何而来？驱逐你的并非不公正的法官或者无道的暴君，而是将你带到这里的同一个大自然，就像演员被雇佣他的经理开除一样。“可是，五幕的演出我只演了三幕。”那就只演三幕好了，你的生命剧本来就只有三幕。它的落幕时刻，是由过去让你出生、现在让你死亡的人来决定的。这些决定非你所能左右。那么，微笑着上路吧，他也会微笑着送你上路的。

[1]指古罗马竞技场上参赛双方的战车御手身着的服饰颜色。罗马人对这种比赛的热情是无限的。获胜的选手会赢得大笔奖金，并成为公众的偶像。

[2]在角斗士比赛中，色雷斯人一方的选手佩带圆形轻盾，萨姆尼人佩带椭圆形重盾。

[3]此处不是指他的亲生父亲，而是指他的养父，古罗马皇帝安东尼·皮乌斯。

[4]此处指路奇乌斯·西安尼斯·康茂德，即后来的路奇乌斯·维鲁斯。他与马可一起被皇帝安东尼·皮乌斯收养，并与他并列为共治皇帝，还娶了马可的女儿卢西拉。起初他是个勇敢而有才干的人，后来变得懦弱而自我放纵。在对波斯的战争中，他作为罗马军队的司令官，表现懒惰无能，仅凭手下将军们的才干才得以免受耻辱。他带领军队从东方回来时，还带回了瘟疫，并随后蔓延到了整个帝国。维鲁斯于公元169年去世——据说，死于下毒者之手。

[5]意指他人赞成或是反对你的行为。

[6]生活本身就是你认为的那样。哈姆雷特（第二幕，第二场）说：“世上的事情本无善恶之分，都是世人的看法把它们这样区分。”在此，马可用两个希腊词更为简洁地表达这种思想，字面意思为“生活（即）观念”。

[7]指最近突然遇到的令人不愉快的事情。

[8]这一段落出现了语义含混的词“财富”，街上的人将其理解为世俗的占有物，而不是生活中真正美好的品德。另一方面对于哲学家而言，这个词自然是指后面的含义；于是，当说到“财富多到无处容身的地步”时，他会觉得困惑。

[9]此处指所谓的“怀疑论者”或皮浪学派的哲学家，该学派由艾里斯的皮洛创建。他们主张人的认识只能反映事物的表象，而不是本质，因此搁置判断才是对待事物的唯一态度。

[10]按照斯多葛派的观点，构成人灵魂的圣火的微粒是有鲜血滋养的。

[11]“老头”假装和小孩的想法一样，认为拨浪鼓是珍贵的宝物。马可说，我们同样应该同情他人的不幸，即便无上的智慧告诉我们，他们并非真在受罪。

[12]即为了更清晰地衬托高尚而扮演卑贱的角色。包括道德意义上不好不坏的事物。

[13]这是希腊语“幸福”的意思。

[14]公元前403年雅典的民主政治被推翻，继之以三十人僭主集团的恐怖统治时期。在这期间，很多无辜的人被处死。苏格拉底等人接到要逮捕诚实的市民——萨拉米斯的利昂的命令，他坚决拒绝执行。

[15]这是阿里斯托芬对苏格拉底的嘲笑之一（见喜剧《云》第362页）。

[16]上上下下，即连续由火变成气，气变成水，水变成土，然后再反向循环。

[17]萨尔马提亚人是位于西徐亚/斯基泰（Scythians）西部的一个多部落联盟，根据希罗多德《历史》中提到的传说，萨尔马提亚人是斯基泰人与神话中的亚马逊女战士的后裔。约在公元前五世纪从中亚细亚迁移至乌拉尔山，最终定居在俄罗斯南部、乌克兰和巴尔干东部。在罗马帝国时期，罗马的军队中曾大量雇用萨尔马提亚人作为辅助骑兵征战四方。——译者注

[18]希腊语法律（nomos）应该来源于一个动词，意思是分配（nemein）。

[19]亚历山大大帝是古代马其顿帝国的国王，世界古代史上著名的军事家和政治家。十八岁随父菲利普出征，二十岁继承王位。雄才大略，足智多谋，建立了版图跨越欧亚大陆的马其顿帝国。克罗伊斯是里底亚最后一代国王，以财富甚多闻名。——译者注

[20]如果这些是原话，而非后世添加，那马可仅仅在此提到一次基督徒。但是，C.R.海恩斯在Loeb版《沉思录》中指出，此从句与结构不符，语法也不通。只能是一个旁注，极似强塞进原文的一个注解。

[21]古希腊三大悲剧作家之一索福克勒斯的作品《俄狄浦斯王》中，国王痛苦地醒悟到自己的罪过，自残的眼睛血流如注，他呼喊着：“啊，西塞隆山！西塞隆山！你为何要庇护我？为何不杀掉我？”他的母亲正是在西塞隆山里生下了他。

[22]伯里克利时代三位伟大的雅典诗人被称为古希腊喜剧的三大作家，他们是：克拉提诺斯、欧波利斯、阿里斯托芬。只有阿里斯托芬的作品传世；根据历史学家格罗特的记载，若非亲眼所见，“无法想象古代喜剧对神灵、宪政、政治家、哲学家、诗人、普通公民甚至雅典妇人惊人而犀利的肆意讽刺”。

[23]阿里斯托芬之后，古典戏剧遭到法律的严禁，作家们纷纷放弃昂贵的合唱队；因而为中期喜剧让出了道路（公元前400—前388）。中古时期的喜剧没有合唱队，而保留人物——士兵、守财奴、政妓——代替现实生活中的人成为讽刺对象。这一时期的主要作家据说有欧布洛斯、安提法奈斯、亚历克西斯。

[24]希腊臣服于马其顿帝国之后，新喜剧兴起，是中古时期喜剧的进一步发展。政治从舞台上消失了，虚构人物的情爱纠纷成为首要的主题。这一批作家中的佼佼者是米南德，他写了近百部喜剧，公认被罗马诗人普劳图斯和特伦斯所效仿。

[25]希腊和罗马正规的喜剧总是不如摹拟剧受百姓欢迎。摹拟剧是由单个演员通过肢体语言和动作来进行表演，而合唱队则担任旁白的工作。索弗龙的摹拟剧长期深受希腊人喜爱；在罗马，这种娱乐形式盛行于奥古斯都皇帝及其继任者执政时期，并最终取代了正规的戏剧。

[26]福基翁是雅典的将军和政治家，被控叛国罪并被人民判处死刑。当被问到还有什么临终遗言时，他回答道：“我只想说，我不恨雅典人。”

[27]马可以此来提醒哲学家不要以自己内心的平静去交换花花世界的烦躁不安。

[28]没有关于这则轶事的文字记载。但是我们知道苏格拉底一直不懈地避免被他妻子的粗暴态度激怒。据第欧根尼·拉尔修，苏格拉底曾经被问到是否无法容忍妻子不断的斥责，他回答说：“你会觉得自家的鹅嘎嘎的叫声无法忍受吗？”对方回答：“当然不会，因为鹅给我下蛋，还给我孵小鹅。”苏格拉底笑了笑：“同样，我妻子也给我生儿育女呀。”马可经常要求自己同样具有好脾气，能容忍别人，他可能是借用苏格拉底的例子指出二人的相似之处。

[29]斯多葛派的学者认为群星是神性的体现。

Book One

1. Courtesy and serenity of temper I first learnt to know from my grandfather Verus.

2. Manliness without ostentation I learnt from what I have heard and remember of my father.

3. My mother set me an example of piety and generosity, avoidance of all uncharitableness — not in actions only, but in thought as well — and a simplicity of life quite unlike the usual habits of the rich.

4. To my great-grandfather I owed the advice to dispense with the education of the schools and have good masters at home instead — and to realize that no expense should be grudged for this purpose.

5. It was my tutor who dissuaded me from patronizing Green or Blue[〔1〕] at the races, or Light or Heavy[〔2〕] in the ring; and encouraged me not to be afraid of work, to be sparing in my wants, attend to my own needs, mind my own business, and never listen to gossip.

6. Thanks to Diognetus, I learnt not to be absorbed in trivial pursuits; to be sceptical of wizards and wonderworkers with their tales of spells, exorcisms, and the like; to eschew cockfighting and other such distractions; not to resent outspokenness; to familiarize myself with philosophy, beginning with Bacchius and going on to Tandasis and Marcian; to write compositions in my early years; and to be ardent for the plank-and-skin pallet and other rigours of the Greek discipline.

7. From Rusticus I derived the notion that my character needed training and care, and that I must not allow myself to be led astray into a sophist's enthusiasm for concocting speculative treatises, edifying homilies, or imaginary sketches of The Ascetic or The Altruist. He also taught me to avoid rhetoric, poetry, and verbal conceits, affectations of dress at home, and other such lapses of taste, and to imitate the easy epistolary style of his own letter written at Sinuessa to my mother. If anyone, after falling out with me in a moment of temper, showed signs of wanting to make peace again, I was to be ready at once to meet them half-way. Also I was to be accurate in my reading, and not content with a mere general idea of the meaning; and not to let myself be too quickly convinced by a glib tongue. Through him, too, I came to know Epictetus's Dissertations, of which he gave me a copy from his library.

8. Apollonius impressed on me the need to make decisions for myself instead of depending on the hazards of chance, and never for a moment to leave reason out of sight. He also schooled me to meet spasms of acute pain, the loss of my son, and the tedium of a chronic ailment with the same unaltered composure. He himself was a living proof that the fieriest energy is not incompatible with the ability to relax. His expositions were always a model of clarity; yet he was evidently one who rated practical experience and an aptitude for teaching philosophy as the least of his accomplishments. It was he, moreover, who taught me how to accept the pretended favours of friends without either lowering my own self-respect or giving the impression of an unfeeling indifference.

9. My debts to Sextus include kindliness, how to rule a household with paternal authority, the real meaning of the Natural Life, an unselfconscious dignity, an intuitive concern for the interests of one's friends, and a good-natured patience with amateurs and visionaries. The aptness of his courtesy to each individual lent a charm to his society more potent than any flattery, yet at the same time it exacted the complete respect of all present. His manner, too, of determining and systematizing the essential rules of life was as comprehensive as it was methodical. Never displaying a sign of anger nor any kind of emotion, he was at once entirely imperturbable and yet full of kindly affection. His approval was always quietly and undemonstratively expressed, and he never paraded his encyclopaedic learning.

10. It was the critic Alexander who put me on my guard against unnecessary fault-finding. People should not be sharply corrected for bad grammar, provincialisms, or mispronunciation; it is better to suggest the proper expression by tactfully introducing it oneself in, say, one's reply to a question or one's acquiescence in their sentiments, or into a friendly discussion of the topic itself (not of the diction), or by some other suitable form of reminder.

11. To my mentor Fronto I owe the realization that malice, craftiness, and duplicity are the concomitants of absolute power; and that our patrician families tend for the most part to be lacking in the feelings of ordinary humanity.

12. Alexander the Platonist cautioned me against frequent use of the words 'I am too busy' in speech or correspondence, except in cases of real necessity; saying that no one ought to shirk the obligations due to society on the excuse of urgent affairs.

13. Catulus the Stoic counselled me never to make light of a friend's rebuke, even when unreasonable, but to do my best to restore myself to his good graces; to speak up readily in commendation of my instructors, as we read in the memoirs of Domitius and Athenodotus; and to cultivate a genuine affection for my children.

14. From my brother Severus I learnt to love my relations, to love the truth, and to love justice. Through him I came to know of Thrasea, Cato, Helvidius, Dion, and Brutus, and became acquainted with the conception of a community based on equality and freedom of speech for all, and a monarchy concerned primarily to uphold the liberty of the subject. He showed me the need for a fair and dispassionate appreciation of philosophy, an addiction to good works, open-handedness, a sanguine temper, and confidence in the affection of my friends. I remember, too, his forthrightness with those who came under his censure, and his way of leaving his friends in no doubt of his likes and dislikes, but of telling them plainly.

15. Maximus was my model for self-control, fixity of purpose, and cheerfulness under ill-health or other misfortunes. His character was an admirable combination of dignity and charm, and all the duties of his station were performed quietly and without fuss. He gave everyone the conviction that he spoke as he believed, and acted as he judged right. Bewilderment or timidity were unknown to him; he was never hasty, never dilatory; nothing found him at a loss. He indulged neither in despondency nor forced gaiety, nor had anger or jealousy any power over him. Kindliness, sympathy, and sincerity all contributed to give the impression of a rectitude that was innate rather than inculcated. Nobody was ever made by him to feel inferior, yet none could have presumed to challenge his pre-eminence. He was also the possessor of an agreeable sense of humour.

16. The qualities I admired in my father[〔3〕] were his lenience, his firm refusal to be diverted from any decision he had deliberately reached, his complete indifference to meretricious honours; his industry, perseverance, and willingness to listen to any project for the common good; the unvarying insistence that rewards must depend on merit; the expert's sense of when to tighten the reins and when to relax them; and the efforts he made to suppress pederasty.

He was aware that social life must have its claims: his friends were under no obligation to join him at his table or attend his progresses, and when they were detained by other engagements it made no difference to him. Every question that came before him in council was painstakingly and patiently examined; he was never content to dismiss it on a cursory first impression. His friendships were enduring; they were not capricious, and they were not extravagant. He was always equal to an occasion; cheerful, yet long-sighted enough to have all his dispositions unobtrusively perfected down to the last detail. He had an ever-watchful eye to the needs of the Empire, prudently conserving its resources and putting up with the criticisms that resulted. Before his gods he was not superstitious; before his fellow-men he never stooped to bid for popularity or woo the masses, but pursued his own calm and steady way, disdaining anything that savoured of the flashy or new-fangled. He accepted without either complacency or compunction such material comforts as fortune had put at his disposal; when they were to hand he would avail himself of them frankly, but when they were not he had no regrets.

Not a vestige of the casuist's quibbling, the lackey's pertness, the pedant's over-scrupulosity could be charged against him; all men recognized in him a mature and finished personality, that was impervious to flattery and entirely capable of ruling both himself and others. Moreover, he had a high respect for all genuine philosophers; and though refraining from criticism of the rest, he preferred to dispense with their guidance. In society he was affable and gracious without being fulsome. The care he took of his body was reasonable; there was no solicitous anxiety to prolong its existence, or to embellish its appearance, yet he was far from unmindful of it, and indeed looked after himself so successfully that he was seldom in need of medical attention or physic or liniments. No hint of jealousy showed in his prompt recognition of outstanding abilities, whether in public speaking, law, ethics, or any other department, and he took pains to give each man the chance of earning a reputation in his own field. Though all his actions were guided by a respect for constitutional precedent, he would never go out of his way to court public recognition of this. Again, he disliked restlessness and change, and had a rooted preference for the same places and the same pursuits. After one of his acute spasms of migraine he would lose no time in taking up his normal duties again, with new vigour and complete command of his powers. His secret and confidential files were not numerous, and the few infrequent items in them referred exclusively to matters of state. He showed good sense and restraint over the exhibition of spectacles, construction of public buildings, distribution of subsidies, and so forth, having always more in view the necessity for the measures themselves than the plaudits they evoked. His baths were not taken at inconvenient hours; he had no mania for building; he was quite uncritical of the food he ate, of the cut and colour of the garments he wore, or of the personableness of those around him. His clothes were sent up from his country seat at Lorium, and most of his things came from Lanuvium. His well-known treatment of the apologetic overseer at Tusculum was typical of his whole behaviour, for discourtesy was as foreign to his nature as harshness or bluster; he never grew heated, as the saying is, to sweating-point; it was his habit to analyse and weigh every incident, taking his time about it, calmly, methodically, decisively, and consistently. What is recorded of Socrates was no less applicable to him, that he had the ability to allow or deny himself indulgences which most people are as much incapacitated by their weakness from refusing as by their excesses from appreciating. To be thus strong enough to refrain or consent at will argues a consummate and indomitable soul — as Maximus also demonstrated on his sick-bed.

17. To the gods I owe good grandparents, good parents, a good sister, and teachers, comrades, kinsmen, and friends good almost without exception; and that I never fell out with any of them, in spite of a temperament that could very well have precipitated something of the sort, had not circumstances providentially never combined to put me to the proof. To them, too, I owe it that the responsibility of my grandfather's mistress for my upbringing was brought to an early end, and my innocence preserved; and that I was not impatient to reach manhood, but contented myself with an unhurried development. I thank heaven also that under my father the Emperor I was cured of all pomposity, and made to realize that life at court can be lived without royal escorts, robes of state, illuminations, statues, and outward splendour of that kind, but that one's manner of life can be reduced almost to the level of a private gentleman's without losing the prestige and authority needful when affairs of state require leadership. The gods, too, gave me a brother[〔4〕] whose natural qualities were a standing challenge to my own self-discipline at the same time as his deferential affection warmed my heart; and children who were neither intellectually stunted nor physically misshapen. It was the gods who set a limit to my proficiency in rhetoric, poetry, and other studies that might well have absorbed my time, had I found it less difficult to make progress. They saw to it that at the first opportunity I raised my tutors to such rank and station as I thought they had at heart, instead of putting them off with prospects of later advancement on the plea of their youth. To the gods I owe my acquaintance with Apollonius, Rusticus, and Maximus. To them, too, my vivid and recurrent visions of the true inwardness of the Natural Life; indeed, for their part, the favours, helps, and inspirations I have received leave my failure to attain this Natural Life without excuse; and if I am still far from the goal, the fault is my own for not paying heed to the reminders — nay, the virtual directions — which I have had from above.

To the gods it must be ascribed that my constitution has survived this manner of life so long; that I never got entangled with a Benedicta nor a Theodotus, and also emerged from other subsequent affairs unscathed; that although Rusticus and I frequently had our differences, I never pushed things to a point I might have regretted; and that the last years of my mother's life, before her early death, were spent with me. Furthermore, that on occasions when I thought of relieving somebody in poverty or distress, I was never told that I had not the necessary means; as also that I myself never had occasion to require similar help from another. And I must thank heaven for such a wife as mine, so submissive, so loving, and so artless; for an unfailing supply of competent tutors for my children; and for remedies prescribed for me in dreams — especially in cases of blood-spitting and vertigo, as happened at Caieta and Chrysa. Finally, that with all my addiction to philosophy I was yet preserved from either falling a prey to some sophist or spending all my time at a desk poring over textbooks and rules of logic or grinding at natural science.

For all these good things 'man needs the help of Heaven and Destiny'.

Among the Quadi, on the River Gran.

注　释

〔1〕　The colours of the rival charioteers in the Circus. Roman enthusiasm for these races was unbounded; successful drivers earned large fortunes and became popular idols.

〔2〕　In one form of gladiatorial combat (the 'Thracian') the opponents were armed with light round bucklers; in another (the 'Samnite') they carried heavy oblong shields.

〔3〕　Not his natural father Annius Verus, but the emperor Antoninus Pius, his adoptive father.

〔4〕　This was Lucius Ceionius Commodus, afterwards known as Lucius Verus. He was adopted by Antoninus Pius along with Marcus, with whom he was associated as co-emperor and whose daughter Lucilla he married. Originally a man of courage and ability, Verus degenerated into weakness and self-indulgence. As commander of the Roman armies in the Parthian war he proved indolent and incapable, and was only saved from disgrace by the skill of his generals. When he returned with his legions from the East, they carried back the seeds of a pestilence which spread with terrible effect throughout the Empire. Verus died in 169 — as some said, by the hand of a poisoner.

Book Two

1. Begin each day by telling yourself: Today I shall be meeting with interference, ingratitude, insolence, disloyalty, ill-will, and selfishness — all of them due to the offenders' ignorance of what is good or evil. But for my part I have long perceived the nature of good and its nobility, the nature of evil and its meanness, and also the nature of the culprit himself, who is my brother (not in the physical sense, but as a fellow-creature similarly endowed with reason and a share of the divine); therefore none of those things can injure me, for nobody can implicate me in what is degrading. Neither can I be angry with my brother or fall foul of him; for he and I were born to work together, like a man's two hands, feet, or eyelids, or like the upper and lower rows of his teeth. To obstruct each other is against Nature's law — and what is irritation or aversion but a form of obstruction?

2. A little flesh, a little breath, and a Reason to rule all — that is myself. (Forget your books; no more hankering for them; they were no part of your equipment.) As one already on the threshold of death, think nothing of the first — of its viscid blood, its bones, its web of nerves and veins and arteries. The breath, too; what is that? A whiff of wind; and not even the same wind, but every moment puffed out and drawn in anew. But the third, the Reason, the master — on this you must concentrate. Now that your hairs are grey, let it play the part of a slave no more, twitching puppetwise at every pull of self-interest; and cease to fume at destiny by ever grumbling at today or lamenting over tomorrow.

3. The whole divine economy is pervaded by Providence. Even the vagaries of chance have their place in Nature's scheme; that is, in the intricate tapestry of the ordinances of Providence. Providence is the source from which all things flow; and allied with it is Necessity, and the welfare of the universe. You yourself are a part of that universe; and for any one of nature's parts, that which is assigned to it by the World-Nature or helps to keep it in being is good. Moreover, what keeps the whole world in being is Change: not merely change of the basic elements, but also change of the larger formations they compose. On these thoughts rest content, and ever hold them as principles. Forget your thirst for books; so that when your end comes you may not murmur, but meet it with a good grace and with unfeigned gratitude in your heart to the gods.

4. Think of your many years of procrastination; how the gods have repeatedly granted you further periods of grace, of which you have taken no advantage. It is time now to realize the nature of the universe to which you belong, and of that controlling Power whose offspring you are; and to understand that your time has a limit set to it. Use it, then, to advance your enlightenment; or it will be gone, and never in your power again.

5. Hour by hour resolve firmly, like a Roman and a man, to do what comes to hand with correct and natural dignity, and with humanity, independence, and justice. Allow your mind freedom from all other considerations. This you can do, if you will approach each action as though it were your last, dismissing the wayward thought, the emotional recoil from the commands of reason, the desire to create an impression, the admiration of self, the discontent with your lot. See how little a man needs to master, for his days to flow on in quietness and piety: he has but to observe these few counsels, and the gods will ask nothing more.

6. Wrong, wrong thou art doing to thyself, O my soul; and all too soon thou shalt have no more time to do thyself right. Man has but one life; already thine is nearing its close, yet still hast thou no eye to thine own honour, but art staking thy happiness on the souls of other men.[〔1〕]

7. Are you distracted by outward cares? Then allow yourself a space of quiet, wherein you can add to your knowledge of the Good and learn to curb your restlessness. Guard also against another kind of error: the folly of those who weary their days in much business, but lack any aim on which their whole effort, nay, their whole thought, is focused.

8. You will not easily find a man coming to grief through indifference to the workings of another's soul; but for those who pay no heed to the motions of their own, unhappiness is their sure reward.

9. Remembering always what the World-Nature is, and what my own nature is, and how the one stands in respect to the other — so small a fraction of so vast a Whole — bear in mind that no man can hinder you from conforming each word and deed to that Nature of which you are a part.

10. When Theophrastus is comparing sins — so far as they are commonly acknowledged to be comparable — he affirms the philosophic truth that sins of desire are more culpable than sins of passion. For passion's revulsion from reason at least seems to bring with it a certain discomfort, and a half-felt sense of constraint; whereas sins of desire, in which pleasure predominates, indicate a more self-indulgent and womanish disposition. Both experience and philosophy, then, support the contention that a sin which is pleasurable deserves graver censure than one which is painful. In the one case the offender is like a man stung into an involuntary loss of control by some injustice; in the other, eagerness to gratify his desire moves him to do wrong of his own volition.

11. In all you do or say or think, recollect that at any time the power of withdrawal from life is in your own hands. If gods exist, you have nothing to fear in taking leave of mankind, for they will not let you come to harm. But if there are no gods, or if they have no concern with mortal affairs, what is life to me, in a world devoid of gods or devoid of Providence? Gods, however, do exist, and do concern themselves with the world of men. They have given us full power not to fall into any of the absolute evils; and if there were real evil in life's other experiences, they would have provided for that too, so that avoidance of it could lie within every man's ability. But when a thing does not worsen the man himself, how can it worsen the life he lives? The World-Nature cannot have been so ignorant as to overlook a hazard of this kind, nor, if aware of it, have been unable to devise a safeguard or a remedy. Neither want of power nor want of skill could have led Nature into the error of allowing good and evil to be visited indiscriminately on the virtuous and the sinful alike. Yet living and dying, honour and dishonour, pain and pleasure, riches and poverty, and so forth are equally the lot of good men and bad. Things like these neither elevate nor degrade; and therefore they are no more good than they are evil.

12. Our mental powers should enable us to perceive the swiftness with which all things vanish away: their bodies in the world of space, and their remembrance in the world of time. We should also observe the nature of all objects of sense — particularly such as allure us with pleasure, or affright us with pain, or are clamorously urged upon us by the voice of self-conceit — the cheapness and contemptibility of them, how sordid they are, and how quickly fading and dead. We should discern the true worth of those whose word and opinion confer reputations. We should apprehend, too, the nature of death; and that if only it be steadily contemplated, and the fancies we associate with it be mentally dissected, it will soon come to be thought of as no more than a process of nature (and only children are scared by a natural process) — or rather, something more than a mere process, a positive contribution to nature's well-being. Also we can learn how man has contact with God, and with which part of himself this is maintained, and how that part fares after its removal hence.

13. Nothing is more melancholy than to compass the whole creation, 'probing into the deeps of earth', as the poet says, and peering curiously into the secrets of others' souls, without once understanding that to hold fast to the divine spirit within, and serve it loyally, is all that is needful. Such service involves keeping it pure from passion, and from aimlessness, and from discontent with the works of gods or men; for the former of these works deserve our reverence, for their excellence; the latter our goodwill, for fraternity's sake, and at times perhaps our pity too, because of men's ignorance of good and evil — an infirmity as crippling as the inability to distinguish black from white.

14. Were you to live three thousand years, or even thirty thousand, remember that the sole life which a man can lose is that which he is living at the moment; and furthermore, that he can have no other life except the one he loses. This means that the longest life and the shortest amount to the same thing. For the passing minute is every man's equal possession, but what has once gone by is not ours. Our loss, therefore, is limited to that one fleeting instant, since no one can lose what is already past, nor yet what is still to come — for how can he be deprived of what he does not possess? So two things should be borne in mind. First, that all the cycles of creation since the beginning of time exhibit the same recurring pattern, so that it can make no difference whether you watch the identical spectacle for a hundred years, or for two hundred, or for ever. Secondly, that when the longest- and the shortest-lived of us come to die, their loss is precisely equal. For the sole thing of which any man can be deprived is the present; since this is all he owns, and nobody can lose what is not his.

15. There are obvious objections to the Cynic Monimus's statement that 'things are determined by the view taken of them'; but the value of his aphorism is equally obvious, if we admit the substance of it so far as it contains a truth.

16. For a human soul, the greatest of self-inflicted wrongs is to make itself (so far as it is able to do so) a kind of tumour or abscess on the universe; for to quarrel with circumstances is always a rebellion against Nature — and Nature includes the nature of each individual part. Another wrong, again, is to reject a fellow-creature or oppose him with malicious intent, as men do when they are angry. A third, to surrender to pleasure or pain. A fourth, to dissemble and show insincerity or falsity in word or deed. A fifth, for the soul to direct its acts and endeavours to no particular object, and waste its energies purposelessly and without due thought; for even the least of our activities ought to have some end in view — and for creatures with reason, that end is conformity with the reason and law of the primordial City and Commonwealth.

17. In the life of a man, his time is but a moment, his being an incessant flux, his senses a dim rushlight, his body a prey of worms, his soul an unquiet eddy, his fortune dark, and his fame doubtful. In short, all that is of the body is as coursing waters, all that is of the soul as dreams and vapours; life a warfare, a brief sojourning in an alien land; and after repute, oblivion. Where, then, can man find the power to guide and guard his steps? In one thing and one alone: Philosophy. To be a philosopher is to keep unsullied and unscathed the divine spirit within him, so that it may transcend all pleasure and all pain, take nothing in hand without purpose and nothing falsely or with dissimulation, depend not on another's actions or inactions, accept each and every dispensation as coming from the same Source as itself — and last and chief, wait with a good grace for death, as no more than a simple dissolving of the elements whereof each living thing is composed. If those elements themselves take no harm from their ceaseless forming and re-forming, why look with mistrust upon the change and dissolution of the whole? It is but Nature's way; and in the ways of Nature there is no evil to be found.

注　释

〔1〕　That is, on whether others decide to approve or censure your actions.

Book Three

1. The daily wearing away of life, with its ever-shrinking remainder, is not the only thing we have to consider. For even if a man's years be prolonged, we must still take into account that it is doubtful whether his mind will continue to retain its capacity for the understanding of business, or for the contemplative effort needed to apprehend things divine and human. The onset of senility may involve no loss of respiratory or alimentary powers, or of sensations, impulses and so forth; nevertheless, the ability to make full use of his faculties, to assess correctly the demands of duty, to coordinate all the diverse problems that arise, to judge if the time has come to end his days on earth, or to make any other of the decisions that require the exercise of a practised intellect, is already on the wane. We must press on, then, in haste; not simply because every hour brings us nearer to death, but because even before then our powers of perception and comprehension begin to deteriorate.

Another thing we should remark is the grace and fascination that there is even in the incidentals of Nature's processes. When a loaf of bread, for instance, is in the oven, cracks appear in it here and there; and these flaws, though not intended in the baking, have a rightness of their own, and sharpen the appetite. Figs, again, at their ripest will also crack open. When olives are on the verge of falling, the very imminence of decay adds its peculiar beauty to the fruit. So, too, the drooping head of a cornstalk, the wrinkling skin when a lion scowls, the drip of foam from a wild boar's jaws, and many more such sights, are far from beautiful if looked at by themselves; yet as the consequences of some other process of Nature, they make their own contribution to its charm and attractiveness.

2. Thus to a man of sensitiveness and sufficiently deep insight into the workings of the universe, almost everything, even if it be no more than a by-product of something else, seems to add its meed of extra pleasure. Such a man will view the grinning jaws of real lions and tigers as admiringly as he would an artist's or sculptor's imitation of them; and the eye of discretion will enable him to see the mature charm that belongs to men and women in old age, as well as the seductive bloom that is youth's. Things of this sort will not appeal to everyone; he alone who has cultivated a real intimacy with Nature and her works will be struck by them.

3. Hippocrates cured the ills of many, but himself took ill and died. The Chaldeans foretold the deaths of many, but fate caught up with them also. Alexander, Pompey, and Julius Caesar laid waste whole cities time and again, and cut down many thousands of horse and foot in battle, but the hour came when they too passed away. Heraclitus speculated endlessly on the consumption of the universe by fire, but in the end it was water that saturated his body, and he died in a dung-plaster. Democritus was destroyed by vermin; Socrates by vermin of another kind. And the moral of it all? This. You embark; you make the voyage; you reach port: step ashore, then. Into another life? There are gods everywhere, even yonder. Into final insensibility? Then you will be out of the grip of pains and pleasures, and thrall no longer to this earthen vessel, so immeasurably meaner than its attendant minister. For the one is a mind and a divinity; the other but clay and corruption.

4. Do not waste what remains of your life in speculating about your neighbours, unless with a view to some mutual benefit. To wonder what so-and-so is doing and why, or what he is saying, or thinking, or scheming — in a word, anything that distracts you from fidelity to the Ruler within you — means a loss of opportunity for some other task. See then that the flow of your thoughts is kept free from idle or random fancies, particularly those of an inquisitive or uncharitable nature. A man should habituate himself to such a way of thinking that if suddenly asked, 'What is in your mind at this minute?' he could respond frankly and without hesitation; thus proving that all his thoughts were simple and kindly, as becomes a social being with no taste for the pleasures of sensual imaginings, jealousies, envies, suspicions, or any other sentiments that he would blush to acknowledge in himself. Such a man, determined here and now to aspire to the heights, is indeed a priest and minister of the gods; for he is making full use of that indwelling power which can keep a man unsullied by pleasures, proof against pain, untouched by insult, and impervious to evil. He is a competitor in the greatest of all contests, the struggle against passion's mastery; he is imbued through and through with uprightness, welcoming whole-heartedly whatever falls to his lot and rarely asking himself what others may be saying or doing or thinking except when the public interest requires it. He confines his operations to his own concerns, having his attention fixed on his own particular thread of the universal web; seeing to it that his actions are honourable, and convinced that what befalls him must be for the best — for his own directing fate is itself under a higher direction. He does not forget the brotherhood of all rational beings, nor that a concern for every man is proper to humanity; and he knows that it is not the world's opinions he should follow, but only those of men whose lives confessedly accord with Nature. As for others whose lives are not so ordered, he reminds himself constantly of the characters they exhibit daily and nightly at home and abroad, and of the sort of society they frequent; and the approval of such men, who do not even stand well in their own eyes, has no value for him.

5. In your actions let there be a willing promptitude, yet a regard for the common interest; due deliberation, yet no irresolution; and in your sentiments no pretentious over-refinement. Avoid talkativeness, avoid officiousness. The god within you should preside over a being who is virile and mature, a statesman, a Roman, and a ruler; one who has held his ground, like a soldier waiting for the signal to retire from life's battlefield and ready to welcome his relief; a man whose credit need neither be sworn to by himself nor avouched by others. Therein is the secret of cheerfulness, of depending on no help from without and needing to crave from no man the boon of tranquillity. We have to stand upright ourselves, not be set up.

6. If mortal life can offer you anything better than justice and truth, self-control and courage — that is, peace of mind in the evident conformity of your actions to the laws of reason, and peace of mind under the visitations of a destiny you cannot control — if, I say, you can discern any higher ideal, why, turn to it with your whole soul, and rejoice in the prize you have found. But if nothing seems to you better than the deity which dwells within you, directing each impulse, weighing each impression, abjuring (in the Socratic phrase) the temptations of the flesh, and avowing allegiance to the gods and compassion for mankind; if you find all else to be mean and worthless in comparison, then leave yourself no room for any rival pursuits. For if you once falter and turn aside, you will no longer be able to give unswerving loyalty to this ideal you have chosen for your own. No ambitions of a different nature can contest the title to goodness which belongs to reason and civic duty; not the world's applause, nor power, nor wealth, nor the enjoyment of pleasure. For a while there may seem to be no incongruity in these things, but very quickly they get the upper hand and sweep a man off his balance. Do you then, I would say, simply and spontaneously make your choice of the highest, and cleave to that. 'But what is best for myself is the highest,' you say? If it is best for you as a reasonable being, hold fast to it; but if as an animal merely, then say so outright, and maintain your view with becoming humility — only be very sure that you have probed the matter aright.

7. Never value the advantages derived from anything involving breach of faith, loss of self-respect, hatred, suspicion, or execration of others, insincerity, or the desire for something which has to be veiled and curtained. One whose chief regard is for his own mind, and for the divinity within him and the service of its goodness, will strike no poses, utter no complaints, and crave neither for solitude nor yet for a crowd. Best of all, his life will be free from continual pursuings and avoidings. He does not care whether his soul in its mortal frame shall be his to possess for a longer or a shorter term of years; this very moment, if it be the hour for his departure, he will step forth as readily as he performs any other act that can be done in self-respecting and orderly fashion. No other care has he in life but to keep his mind from straying into paths incompatible with those of an intelligent and social being.

8. In a mind that is disciplined and purified there is no taint of corruption, no unclean spot nor festering sore. Such a man's life fate can never snatch away unfulfilled, as it were an actor walking off in mid-performance before the play is finished. There is nothing of the lackey in him, yet nothing of the coxcomb; he neither leans on others nor holds aloof from them; and he remains answerable to no man, yet guiltless of all evasion.

9. Treat with respect the power you have to form an opinion. By it alone can the helmsman within you avoid forming opinions that are at variance with nature and with the constitution of a reasonable being. From it you may look to attain circumspection, good relations with your fellow-men, and conformity with the will of heaven.

10. Letting go all else, cling to the following few truths. Remember that man lives only in the present, in this fleeting instant: all the rest of his life is either past and gone, or not yet revealed. This mortal life is a little thing, lived in a little corner of the earth; and little, too, is the longest fame to come — dependent as it is on a succession of fast-perishing little men who have no knowledge even of their own selves, much less of one long dead and gone.

11. To these maxims add yet another. When an object presents itself to your perception, make a mental definition or at least an outline of it, so as to discern its essential character, to pierce beyond its separate attributes to a distinct view of the naked whole, and to identify for yourself both the object itself and the elements of which it is composed, and into which it will again be resolved. Nothing so enlarges the mind as this ability to examine methodically and accurately every one of life's experiences, with an eye to determining its classification, the ends it serves, its worth to the universe, and its worth to men as the members of that supreme City in which all other cities are as households. Take, for example, the thing which is producing its impression upon me at this moment. What is it? Whereof is it composed? How long is it designed to last? What moral response does it ask of me; gentleness, fortitude, candour, good faith, sincerity, self-reliance, or some other quality? In every instance learn to say, This comes from God; or, This is one of Fate's dispensations, a strand in the complex web, a conjunction of fortuities; or again, This is the work of a man who is of the same stock and breed and brotherhood as I am, but is ignorant of what Nature requires of him. I myself, however, can plead no such ignorance, and therefore in accordance with Nature's law of brotherhood I am to deal amiably and fairly with him — though at the same time, if there be no question of good or evil involved, I must aim my shafts at the proper merits of the case.

12. If you do the task before you always adhering to strict reason with zeal and energy and yet with humanity, disregarding all lesser ends and keeping the divinity within you pure and upright, as though you were even now faced with its recall — if you hold steadily to this, staying for nothing and shrinking from nothing, only seeking in each passing action a conformity with nature and in each word and utterance a fearless truthfulness, then shall the good life be yours. And from this course no man has the power to hold you back.

13. As surgeons keep their lancets and scalpels always at hand for the sudden demands of their craft, so keep your principles constantly in readiness for the understanding of things both human and divine; never in the most trivial action forgetting how intimately the two are related. For nothing human can be done aright without reference to the divine, and conversely.

14. Mislead yourself no longer; you will never read these notebooks again now, nor the annals of bygone Romans and Greeks, nor that choice selection of writings you have put by for your old age. Press on, then, to the finish; cast away vain hopes; and if you have any regard at all for self, see to your own security while still you may.

15. They do not know all that is signified by such words as 'stealing', 'sowing', 'purchasing', 'being at peace', 'seeing one's duty': this needs a different vision from the eye's.

16. Body, soul, and mind: the body for sensation, the soul for the springs of action, the mind for principles. Yet the capacity for sensation belongs also to the stalled ox; there is no wild beast, homosexual, Nero, or Phalaris but obeys the twitchings of impulse; and even men who deny the gods, or betray their country, or perpetrate all manner of villainy behind locked doors, have minds to guide them to the clear path of duty. Seeing, then, that all else is the common heritage of such types, the good man's only singularity lies in his approving welcome to every experience the looms of fate may weave for him, his refusal to soil the divinity seated in his breast or perturb it with disorderly impressions, and his resolve to keep it in serenity and decorous obedience to God, admitting no disloyalty to truth in his speech or to justice in his actions. Though all the world mistrust him because he lives in simple, self-respecting happiness, he takes offence at none, but unswervingly treads the road onward to life's close, where duty bids him arrive in purity and peace, unreluctant to depart, in perfect and unforced unison with fate's apportionment.

Book Four

1. If the inward power that rules us be true to Nature, it will always adjust itself readily to the possibilities and opportunities offered by circumstance. It asks for no predeterminate material; in the pursuance of its aims it is willing to compromise; hindrances to its progress are merely converted into matter for its own use. It is like a bonfire mastering a heap of rubbish, which would have quenched a feeble glow; but its fiery blaze quickly assimilates the load, consumes it, and flames the higher for it.

2. Take no enterprise in hand at haphazard, or without regard to the principles governing its proper execution.

3. Men seek for seclusion in the wilderness, by the seashore, or in the mountains — a dream you have cherished only too fondly yourself. But such fancies are wholly unworthy of a philosopher, since at any moment you choose you can retire within yourself. Nowhere can man find a quieter or more untroubled retreat than in his own soul; above all, he who possesses resources in himself, which he need only contemplate to secure immediate ease of mind — the ease that is but another word for a well-ordered spirit. Avail yourself often, then, of this retirement, and so continually renew yourself. Make your rules of life brief, yet so as to embrace the fundamentals; recurrence to them will then suffice to remove all vexation, and send you back without fretting to the duties to which you must return.

After all, what is it that frets you? The vices of humanity? Remember the doctrine that all rational beings are created for one another; that toleration is a part of justice; and that men are not intentional evildoers. Think of the myriad enmities, suspicions, animosities, and conflicts that are now vanished with the dust and ashes of the men who knew them; and fret no more.

Or is it your allotted portion in the universe that chafes you? Recall once again the dilemma, 'if not a wise Providence, then a mere jumble of atoms', and consider the profusion of evidence that this world is as it were a city. Do the ills of the body afflict you? Reflect that the mind has but to detach itself and apprehend its own powers, to be no longer involved with the movements of the breath, whether they be smooth or rough. In short, recollect all you have learnt and accepted regarding pain and pleasure.

Or does the bubble reputation distract you? Keep before your eyes the swift onset of oblivion, and the abysses of eternity before us and behind; mark how hollow are the echoes of applause, how fickle and undiscerning the judgements of professed admirers, and how puny the arena of human fame. For the entire earth is but a point, and the place of our own habitation but a minute corner in it; and how many are therein who will praise you, and what sort of men are they?

Remember then to withdraw into the little field of self. Above all, never struggle or strain; but be master of yourself, and view life as a man, as a human being, as a citizen, and as a mortal. Among the truths you will do well to contemplate most frequently are these two: first, that things can never touch the soul, but stand inert outside it, so that disquiet can arise only from fancies within; and secondly, that all visible objects change in a moment, and will be no more. Think of the countless changes in which you yourself have had a part. The whole universe is change, and life itself is but what you deem it.[〔1〕]

4. If the power of thought is universal among mankind, so likewise is the possession of reason, making us rational creatures. It follows, therefore, that this reason speaks no less universally to us all with its 'thou shalt' or 'thou shalt not'. So then there is a world-law; which in turn means that we are all fellow-citizens and share a common citizenship, and that the world is a single city. Is there any other common citizenship that can be claimed by all humanity? And it is from this world-polity that mind, reason, and law themselves derive. If not, whence else? As the earthy portion of me has its origin from earth, the watery from a different element, my breath from one source and my hot and fiery parts from another of their own elsewhere (for nothing comes from nothing, or can return to nothing), so too there must be an origin for the mind.

5. Death, like birth, is one of Nature's secrets; the same elements that have been combined are then dispersed. Nothing about it need give cause for shame. For beings endowed with mind it is no anomaly, nor in any way inconsistent with the plan of their creation.

6. That men of a certain type should behave as they do is inevitable. To wish it otherwise were to wish the fig-tree would not yield its juice. In any case, remember that in a very little while both you and he will be dead, and your very names will quickly be forgotten.

7. Put from you the belief that 'I have been wronged', and with it will go the feeling. Reject your sense of injury, and the injury itself disappears.

8. What does not corrupt a man himself cannot corrupt his life, nor do him any damage either outwardly or inwardly.

9. The laws of collective expediency required this to happen.

10. Whatever happens, happens rightly. Watch closely, and you will find this true. In the succession of events there is not mere sequence alone, but an order that is just and right, as from the hand of one who dispenses to all their due. Keep up your watch, then, as you have begun, and let goodness accompany your every action — goodness, that is, in the proper sense of the word. In all your operations pay heed to this.

11. Do not copy the opinions of the arrogant, or let them dictate your own, but look at things in their true light.

12. At two points hold yourself always in readiness: first, to do exclusively what reason, our king and lawgiver, shall suggest for the common weal; and secondly, to reconsider a decision if anyone present should correct you and convince you of an error of judgement. But such conviction must proceed from the assurance that justice, or the common good, or some other such interest will be served. This must be the sole consideration; not the likelihood of pleasure or popularity.

13. Have you reason? 'I have.' Then why not use it? If reason does its part, what more would you ask?

14. As a part, you inhere in the Whole. You will vanish into that which gave you birth; or rather, you will be transmuted once more into the creative Reason of the universe.

15. Many grains of incense fall on the same altar: one sooner, another later — it makes no difference.

16. You have only to revert to the teachings of your creed, and to reverence for reason, and within a week those who now class you with beasts and monkeys will be calling you a god.

17. Live not as though there were a thousand years ahead of you. Fate is at your elbow; make yourself good while life and power are still yours.

18. He who ignores what his neighbour is saying or doing or thinking, and cares only that his own actions should be just and godly, is greatly the gainer in time and ease. A good man does not spy around for the black spots in others, but presses unswervingly on towards his mark.

19. The man whose heart is palpitating for fame after death does not reflect that out of all those who remember him every one will himself soon be dead also, and in course of time the next generation after that, until in the end, after flaring and sinking by turns, the final spark of memory is quenched. Furthermore, even supposing that those who remember you were never to die at all, nor their memories to die either, yet what is that to you? Clearly, in your grave, nothing; and even in your lifetime, what is the good of praise — unless maybe to subserve some lesser design? Surely, then, you are making an inopportune rejection of what Nature has given you today, if all your mind is set on what men will say of you tomorrow.

20. Anything in any way beautiful derives its beauty from itself, and asks nothing beyond itself. Praise is no part of it, for nothing is made worse or better by praise. This applies even to the more mundane forms of beauty: natural objects, for example, or works of art. What need has true beauty of anything further? Surely none; any more than law, or truth, or kindness, or modesty. Is any of these embellished by praise, or spoiled by censure? Does the emerald lose its beauty for lack of admiration? Does gold, or ivory, or purple? A lyre or a dagger, a rosebud or a sapling?

21. If souls survive after death, how has the air above us found room for them all since time began? As well ask how the earth finds room for all the bodies interred through immemorial ages. There, after a short respite, change and decay make way for other dead bodies. Similarly, souls transferred to the air exist for a while before undergoing a change and a diffusion, and are then transmuted into fire and taken back into the creative principle of the universe; and thus room is made for the reception of others. Such will be the answer of any believer in the survival of souls. Moreover, we must reckon not only the number of human corpses so buried, but also that of all the creatures daily devoured by ourselves and the other animals. What multitudes, perishing in this way, are in a manner of speaking buried in the bodies of those whose nutriment they furnish! And yet, by their assimilation into the blood and afterwards by the subsequent transmutation into the air or fire, all the needful space becomes available.

How do we discover the truth of all this? By distinguishing between the matter and the cause.

22. Never allow yourself to be swept off your feet: when an impulse stirs, see first that it will meet the claims of justice; when an impression forms, assure yourself first of its certainty.

23. O world, I am in tune with every note of thy great harmony. For me nothing is early, nothing late, if it be timely for thee. O Nature, all that thy seasons yield is fruit for me. From thee, and in thee, and to thee are all things. 'Dear city of God!' may we not cry, even as the poet cried 'Dear city of Cecrops!'

24. 'If thou wouldst know contentment, let thy deeds be few,' said the sage. Better still, limit them strictly to such as are essential, and to such as in a social being reason demands, and as it demands. This brings the contentment that comes of doing a few things and doing them well. Most of what we say and do is not necessary, and its omission would save both time and trouble. At every step, therefore, a man should ask himself, 'Is this one of the things that are superfluous?' Moreover, not idle actions only but even idle impressions ought to be suppressed; for then unnecessary action will not ensue.

25. Test for yourself your capacity for the good man's life; the life of one content with his allotted part in the universe, who seeks only to be just in his doings and charitable in his ways.

26. You have seen all that?[〔2〕] — now look at this. Your part is to be serene, to be simple. Is someone doing wrong? The wrong lies with himself. Has something befallen you? Good; then it was your portion of the universal lot, assigned to you when time began; a strand woven into your particular web, like all else that happens. Life, in a word, is short; then snatch your profit from the passing hour, by obedience to reason and just dealing. Unbend, but be temperate.

27. Either a universe that is all order, or else a farrago thrown together at random yet somehow forming a universe. But can there be some measure of order subsisting in yourself, and at the same time disorder in the greater Whole? And that, too, when oneness of feeling exists between all the parts of nature, in spite of their divergence and dispersion?

28. A black heart! A womanish, wilful heart; the heart of a brute, a beast of the field; childish, stupid, and false; a huckster's heart, a tyrant's heart.

29. If he who knows not what is in the universe is a stranger to the universe, he is no less so who knows not what takes place in it. Such a man is an exile, self-banished from the polity of reason; a sightless man, having the eyes of his understanding darkened; a pauper dependent on others, without resources of his own for his livelihood. He is an excrescence on the world, when he dissociates and dissevers himself from the laws of our common nature by refusing to accept his lot (which after all is a product of the self-same Nature which produced yourself); he is a limb lopped from the community, when he cuts his own soul adrift from the single soul of all rational things.

30. One philosopher goes shirtless; another bookless; a third, only half-clad, says, 'Bread have I none, yet still I cleave to reason.' For my part, I too have no fruit of my learning, and yet cleave to her.

31. Give your heart to the trade you have learnt, and draw refreshment from it. Let the rest of your days be spent as one who has whole-heartedly committed his all to the gods, and is thenceforth no man's master or slave.

32. Think, let us say, of the times of Vespasian; and what do you see? Men and women busy marrying, bringing up children, sickening, dying, fighting, feasting, chaffering, farming, flattering, bragging, envying, scheming, calling down curses, grumbling at fate, loving, hoarding, coveting thrones and dignities. Of all that life, not a trace survives today. Or come forward to the days of Trajan; again, it is the same; that life, too, has perished. Take a similar look at the records of other past ages and peoples; mark how one and all, after their short-lived strivings, passed away and were resolved into the elements. More especially, recall some who, within your own knowledge, have followed after vanities instead of contenting themselves with a resolute performance of the duties for which they were created. In such cases it is essential to remind ourselves that the pursuit of any object depends for its value upon the worth of the object pursued. If, then, you would avoid discouragement, never become unduly absorbed in things that are not of the first importance.

33. Expressions that were once current have gone out of use nowadays. Names, too, that were formerly household words are virtually archaisms today; Camillus, Caeso, Volesus, Dentatus; or a little later, Scipio and Cato; Augustus too, and even Hadrian and Antoninus. All things fade into the storied past, and in a little while are shrouded in oblivion. Even to men whose lives were a blaze of glory this comes to pass; as for the rest, the breath is hardly out of them before, in Homer's words, they are 'lost to sight alike and hearsay'. What, after all, is immortal fame? An empty, hollow thing. To what, then, must we aspire? This, and this alone: the just thought, the unselfish act, the tongue that utters no falsehood, the temper that greets each passing event as something predestined, expected, and emanating from the One source and origin.

34. Submit yourself to Clotho[〔3〕] with a good grace, and let her spin your thread out of what material she will.

35. All of us are creatures of a day; the rememberer and the remembered alike.

36. Observe how all things are continually being born of change; teach yourself to see that Nature's highest happiness lies in changing the things that are, and forming new things after their kind. Whatever is, is in some sense the seed of what is to emerge from it. Nothing can become a philosopher less than to imagine that seed can only be something that is planted in the earth or the womb.

37. Very soon you will be dead; but even yet you are not single-minded, nor above disquiet; not yet unapprehensive of harm from without; not yet charitable to all men, nor persuaded that to do justly is the only wisdom.

38. Observe carefully what guides the actions of the wise, and what they shun or seek.

39. For you, evil comes not from the mind of another; nor yet from any of the phases and changes of your own bodily frame. Then whence? From that part of yourself which acts as your assessor of what is evil. Refuse its assessment, and all is well. Though the poor body, so closely neighbouring it, be gashed or burned, fester or mortify, let the voice of this assessor remain silent; let it pronounce nothing to be bad or good if it can happen to evil men and good men alike — for anything that comes impartially upon men, whether they observe the rules of Nature or not, can neither be hindering her purposes nor advancing them.

40. Always think of the universe as one living organism, with a single substance and a single soul; and observe how all things are submitted to the single perceptivity of this one whole, all are moved by its single impulse, and all play their part in the causation of every event that happens. Remark the intricacy of the skein, the complexity of the web.

41. 'A poor soul burdened with a corpse,' Epictetus calls you.

42. To be in process of change is not an evil, any more than to be the product of change is a good.

43. Time is a river, the resistless flow of all created things. One thing no sooner comes in sight than it is hurried past and another is borne along, only to be swept away in its turn.

44. Everything that happens is as normal and expected as the spring rose or the summer fruit; this is true of sickness, death, slander, intrigue, and all the other things that delight or trouble foolish men.

45. What follows is ever closely linked to what precedes; it is not a procession of isolated events, merely obeying the laws of sequence, but a rational continuity. Moreover, just as the things already in existence are all harmoniously coordinated, things in the act of coming into existence exhibit the same marvel of concatenation, rather than simply the bare fact of succession.

46. Always remember the dictum of Heraclitus, 'Death of earth, birth of water; death of water, birth of air; from air, fire; and so round again.' Remember also his 'wayfarer oblivious of where his road is leading', his 'men ever at odds with their own closest companion' (the controlling Reason of the universe), and his 'though they encounter this every day, they still deem it a stranger'. Again, 'we are not to act or speak like men asleep' (for indeed men in their sleep do fancy themselves to be acting and speaking), nor 'like children at their parents' word'; that is, in blind reliance on traditional maxims.

47. If a god were to tell you, 'Tomorrow, or at best the day after, you will be dead,' you would not, unless the most abject of men, be greatly solicitous whether it was to be the later day, rather than the morrow — for what is the difference between them? In the same way, do not reckon it of great moment whether it will come years and years hence, or tomorrow.

48. Remind yourself constantly of all the physicians, now dead, who used to knit their brows over their ailing patients; of all the astrologers who so solemnly predicted their clients' doom; the philosophers who expatiated so endlessly on death or immortality; the great commanders who slew their thousands; the despots who wielded powers of life and death with such terrible arrogance, as if themselves were gods who could never die; the whole cities which have perished completely, Helice, Pompeii, Herculaneum, and others without number. After that, recall one by one each of your own acquaintances; how one buried another, only to be laid low himself and buried in turn by a third, and all in so brief a space of time. Observe, in short, how transient and trivial is all mortal life; yesterday a drop of semen, tomorrow a handful of spice or ashes. Spend, therefore, these fleeting moments on earth as Nature would have you spend them, and then go to your rest with a good grace, as an olive falls in its season, with a blessing for the earth that bore it and a thanksgiving to the tree that gave it life.

49. Be like the headland against which the waves break and break: it stands firm, until presently the watery tumult around it subsides once more to rest. 'How unlucky I am, that this should have happened to me!' By no means; say rather, 'How lucky I am, that it has left me with no bitterness; unshaken by the present, and undismayed by the future.' The thing could have happened to anyone, but not everyone would have emerged unembittered. So why put the one down to misfortune, rather than the other to good fortune? Can a man call anything at all a misfortune, if it is not a contravention of his nature; and can it be a contravention of his nature if it is not against that nature's will? Well, then: you have learnt to know that will. Does this thing which has happened hinder you from being just, magnanimous, temperate, judicious, discreet, truthful, self-respecting, independent, and all else by which a man's nature comes to its fulfilment? So here is a rule to remember in future, when anything tempts you to feel bitter: not, 'This is a misfortune,' but 'To bear this worthily is good fortune.'

50. Philosophy aside, an effectual help towards disregarding death is to think of those who clung greedily to their lives. What advantage have they over those who died young? In every case, in some place at some time, the earth now covers them all; Cadicianus, Fabius, Julianus, Lepidus, and the rest, who saw so many to their graves, only to be seen to their own at last. Brief, after all, was the respite they enjoyed; dragged out in such conditions, and with such attendants, and in so wretched a body. Set no store by it, then; look at the abyss of time behind it, and the infinity yet to come. In the face of that, what more is Nestor with all his years than any three-days babe?

51. Ever run the short way; and the short way is the way of nature, with perfect soundness in each word and deed as the goal. Such an aim will give you freedom from anxiety and strife, and from all compromise and artifice.

注　释

〔1〕　Life itself is but what you deem it. Hamlet (Act Ⅱ, scene 2) says: 'There's nothing either good or bad but thinking makes it so.' Marcus here expresses this thought more succinctly in two Greek words, meaning literally 'life [is] opinion'.

〔2〕　The unpleasant side of some recent encounter.

〔3〕　Clotho, one of the three Fates, is she who spins the thread of men's lives; Lachesis decides their destiny; Atropos slits the thread when they must die.

Book Five

1. At day's first light have in readiness, against disinclination to leave your bed, the thought that 'I am rising for the work of man'. Must I grumble at setting out to do what I was born for, and for the sake of which I have been brought into the world? Is this the purpose of my creation, to lie here under the blankets and keep myself warm? 'Ah, but it is a great deal more pleasant!' Was it for pleasure, then, that you were born, and not for work, not for effort? Look at the plants, the sparrows, ants, spiders, bees, all busy at their own tasks, each doing his part towards a coherent world-order; and will you refuse man's share of the work, instead of being prompt to carry out Nature's bidding? 'Yes, but one must have some repose as well.' Granted; but repose has its limits set by nature, in the same way as food and drink have; and you overstep these limits, you go beyond the point of sufficiency; while on the other hand, when action is in question, you stop short of what you could well achieve.

You have no real love for yourself; if you had, you would love your nature, and your nature's will. Craftsmen who love their trade will spend themselves to the utmost in labouring at it, even going unwashed and unfed; but you hold your nature in less regard than the engraver does his engraving, the dancer his dancing, the miser his heap of silver, or the vainglorious man his moment of glory. These men, when their heart is in it, are ready to sacrifice food and sleep to the advancement of their chosen pursuit. Is the service of the community of less worth in your eyes, and does it merit less devotion?

2. O the consolation of being able to thrust aside and cast into oblivion every tiresome intrusive impression, and in a trice be utterly at peace!

3. Reserve your right to any deed or utterance that accords with nature. Do not be put off by the criticisms or comments that may follow; if there is something good to be done or said, never renounce your right to it. Those who criticize you have their own reason to guide them, and their own impulse to prompt them; you must not let your eyes stray towards them, but keep a straight course and follow your own nature and the World-Nature (and the way of these two is one).

4. I travel the roads of nature until the hour when I shall lie down and be at rest; yielding back my last breath into the air from which I have drawn it daily, and sinking down upon the earth from which my father derived the seed, my mother the blood, and my nurse the milk of my being — the earth which for so many years has furnished my daily meat and drink, and, though so grievously abused, still suffers me to tread its surface.

5. You will never be remarkable for quick-wittedness. Be it so, then; yet there are still a host of other qualities whereof you cannot say, 'I have no bent for them.' Cultivate these, then, for they are wholly within your power: sincerity, for example, and dignity; industriousness, and sobriety. Avoid grumbling; be frugal, considerate, and frank; be temperate in manner and in speech; carry yourself with authority. See how many qualities there are which could be yours at this moment. You can allege no native incapacity or inaptitude for them; and yet you choose to linger still on a less lofty plane. Furthermore, is it any lack of natural endowments that necessitates those fits of querulousness and parsimony and fulsome flattery, of railing at your ill-health, of cringing and bragging and continually veering from one mood to another? Most assuredly not; you could have rid yourself of all these long ago, and remained chargeable with nothing worse than a certain slowness and dulness of comprehension — and even this you can correct with practice, so long as you do not make light of it or take pleasure in your own obtuseness.

6. There is a type of person who, if he renders you a service, has no hesitation in claiming the credit for it. Another, though not prepared to go so far as that, will nevertheless secretly regard you as in his debt and be fully conscious of what he has done. But there is also the man who, one might almost say, has no consciousness at all of what he has done, like the vine which produces a cluster of grapes and then, having yielded its rightful fruit, looks for no more thanks than a horse that has run his race, a hound that has tracked his quarry, or a bee that has hived her honey. Like them, the man who has done one good action does not cry it aloud, but passes straight on to a second, as the vine passes on to the bearing of another summer's grapes.

'According to you, then, we should rank ourselves with things that act unconsciously?' Exactly; yet we should do so consciously; for, as the saying goes, 'awareness that his actions are social is the mark of a social being'. 'But also, surely, the wish that society itself should be equally aware of it?' True, no doubt; yet you miss the meaning of the aphorism, and so put yourself in the same class as the persons I have just described, who likewise are misled by a specious kind of reasoning. Apprehend the true significance of the saying, and you need never fear that it will betray you into omitting any social duty.

7. The Athenians pray, 'Rain, rain, dear Zeus, upon the fields and plains of Athens.' Prayers should either not be offered at all, or else be as simple and ingenuous as this.

8. Just as we say, 'Aesculapius has prescribed horseback exercise, or cold baths, or going barefoot', so in the same way does the World-Nature prescribe disease, mutilation, loss, or some other disability. In the former case, prescribing meant ordering a specific treatment, in the interests of the patient's health; similarly in the latter, certain specific occurrences are ordered, in the interests of our destiny. We may, in fact, be said to 'meet with' these misfortunes in the same sense as masons say that the squared stones in walls or pyramids 'meet with' each other when they are being fitted closely together to make the unified whole. This mutual integration is a universal principle. As a myriad bodies combine into the single Body which is the world, so a myriad causes combine into the single Cause which is destiny. Even the common people realize this when they say, 'It was brought upon him.' It was indeed brought upon him; that is, it was prescribed for him. Let us accept such things, then, as we accept the prescriptions of an Aesculapius; for they, too, have often a harsh flavour, yet we swallow them gladly in hope of health. The execution and fulfilment of Nature's decrees should be viewed in the same way as we view our bodily health: even if what befalls is unpalatable, nevertheless always receive it gladly, for it makes for the health of the universe, and even for the well-being and well-doing of Zeus himself. Had it not been for the benefit of the whole, he would never have brought it upon the individual. It is not Nature's way to bring anything upon that which is under her government, except what is specifically designed for its good. There are two reasons, then, why you should willingly accept what happens to you: first, because it happens to yourself, has been prescribed for yourself, and concerns yourself, being a strand in the tapestry of primordial causation; and secondly, because every individual dispensation is one of the causes of the prosperity, success, and even survival of That which administers the universe. To break off any particle, no matter how small, from the continuous concatenation — whether of causes or of any other elements — is to injure the whole. And each time you give way to discontent, you are causing, within your own limited ability, just such a breakage and disruption.

9. Do not be distressed, do not despond or give up in despair, if now and again practice falls short of precept. Return to the attack after each failure, and be thankful if on the whole you can acquit yourself in the majority of cases as a man should. But have a genuine liking for the discipline you return to: do not recur to your philosophy in the spirit of a schoolboy to his master, but as the sore-eyed recur to their egg-and-sponge lotion, or as others to their poultice or their douche. In this way your submission to reason will not become a matter for public display, but for private consolation. Bear in mind that, while philosophy wills only what your own nature wills, you yourself were willing something else that was at variance with nature. 'Yes, but what other thing could have been more agreeable?' — is not that the inducement wherewith pleasure seeks to beguile you? Yet consider: would not nobility of soul be more agreeable? Would not candour, simplicity, kindness, piety? Nay more; when you reflect on the precision and smoothness with which the processes of ratiocination and cognition operate, can there be anything more agreeable than the exercise of intellect?

10. As for truth, it is so veiled in obscurity that many reputable philosophers[〔1〕] assert the impossibility of reaching any certain knowledge. Even the Stoics admit that its attainment is beset with difficulties, and that all our intellectual conclusions are fallible; for where is the infallible man? Or turn from this to more material things: how transitory, how worthless are these — open to acquisition by every profligate, loose woman, and criminal. Or look at the characters of your own associates: even the most agreeable of them are difficult to put up with; and for the matter of that, it is difficult enough to put up with one's own self. In all this murk and mire, then, in all this ceaseless flow of being and time, of changes imposed and changes endured, I can think of nothing that is worth prizing highly or pursuing seriously. No; what a man must do is to nerve himself to wait quietly for his natural dissolution; and meanwhile not to chafe at its delay, but to find his sole consolation in two thoughts: first, that nothing can ever happen to us that is not in accordance with nature; and second, that power to abstain from acting against the divine spirit within me lies in my own hands, since there is no man alive who can force such disobedience upon me.

11. To what use am I now putting the powers of my soul? Examine yourself on this point at every step, and ask, 'How stands it with that part of me men call the master-part? Whose soul inhabits me at this moment? A child's, a lad's, a woman's, a tyrant's, a dumb ox's, or a wild beast's?'

12. The popular conception of 'goods' can be tested in this way.[〔2〕] If the things a man identifies in his own mind with 'goods' are such things as prudence, temperance, justice, and fortitude, then, given that preconception, he will have no ears for the old jest about 'so many goods', for it will lack any point. On the other hand, if he shares the vulgar notion of what constitutes 'goods', he will readily appreciate the joker's quip, and have no difficulty in seeing its aptness. The majority do, in fact, entertain this idea of values, and they would never take offence at the witticism or refuse to hear it; indeed, we must accept it as an apt and clever observation if we take it to refer to wealth or things which conduce to luxury or prestige. So now for the test: ask yourself whether we do right to set store by things and think of them as 'goods', if our mental picture of them is such as to give meaning to the gibe that 'the owner of so many goods has no room left to ease himself'.

13. I consist of a formal element and a material. Neither of these can ever pass away into nothing, any more than either of them came into being from nothing. Consequently every part of me will one day be refashioned, by a process of transition, into some other portion of the universe; which in its turn will again be changed into yet another part, and so onward to infinity. It is the same process by which I myself was brought into existence, and my parents before me, and so backward once more to infinity. (The phrase 'infinity' may pass, even if the world be in fact administered in finite cycles.)

14. Reason, and the act of reasoning, are self-sufficient faculties, both inherently and in the method of their operation. It is from sources in themselves that they acquire their initial impetus; and they travel straight forward to their own self-appointed goals. Actions of this kind accordingly receive the name of 'straightforwardness', in reference to the undeviating line they follow.

15. Unless things pertain to a man, as man, they cannot properly be said to belong to him. They cannot be required of him; for his nature neither promises them, nor is perfected by them. Therefore they cannot represent his chief end in life, nor even the 'good' which is the means to that end. Moreover, had man's natural heritage included such things, it could not at the same time have included contempt and renunciation of them; nor would the ability to do without them have been any cause for commendation; nor, supposing them to be really good, would failure to claim a full share of them be compatible with goodness. As it is, however, the more a man deprives himself, or submits to be deprived, of such things and their like, the more he grows in goodness.

16. Your mind will be like its habitual thoughts; for the soul becomes dyed with the colour of its thoughts. Soak it then in such trains of thought as, for example: Where life is possible at all, a right life is possible; life in a palace is possible; therefore even in a palace a right life is possible. Or again: The purpose behind each thing's creation determines its development; the development points to its final state; the final state gives the clue to its chief advantage and good; therefore the chief good of a rational being is fellowship with his neighbours — for it has been made clear long ago that fellowship is the purpose behind our creation. (It is surely evident, is it not, that while the lower exist for the higher, the higher exist for one another? And while the animate is higher than the inanimate, the rational is higher still.)

17. To pursue the unattainable is insanity, yet the thoughtless can never refrain from doing so.

18. Nothing can happen to any man that nature has not fitted him to endure. Your neighbour's experiences are no different from your own; yet he, being either less aware of what has happened or more eager to show his mettle, stands steady and undaunted. For shame, that ignorance and vanity should prove stronger than wisdom!

19. Outward things can touch the soul not a whit; they know no way into it, they have no power to sway or move it. By itself it sways and moves itself; it has its own self-approved standards of judgement, and to them it refers every experience.

20. In one way humanity touches me very nearly, inasmuch as I am bound to do good to my fellow-creatures and bear with them. On the other hand, to the extent that individual men hamper my proper activities, humanity becomes a thing as indifferent to me as the sun, the wind, or the creatures of the wild. True, others may hinder the carrying out of certain actions; but they cannot obstruct my will, nor the disposition of my mind, since these will always safeguard themselves under reservations and adapt themselves to circumstances. The mind can circumvent all obstacles to action, and turn them to the furtherance of its main purpose, so that any impediment to its work becomes instead an auxiliary, and the barriers in its path become aids to progress.

21. In the universe, reverence that which is highest: namely, That to which all else ministers, and which gives the law to all. In like manner, too, reverence the highest in yourself: it is of one piece with the Other, since in yourself also it is that to which all the rest minister, and by which your life is directed.

22. What is not harmful to the city cannot harm the citizen. In every fancied case of harm, apply the rule, 'If the city is not harmed, I am not harmed either.' But if the city should indeed be harmed, never rage at the culprit: rather, find out at what point his vision failed him.

23. Reflect often upon the rapidity with which all existing things, or things coming into existence, sweep past us and are carried away. The great river of Being flows on without a pause; its actions for ever changing, its causes shifting endlessly, hardly a single thing standing still; while ever at hand looms infinity stretching behind and before — the abyss in which all things are lost to sight. In such conditions, surely a man were foolish to gasp and fume and fret, as though the time of his troubling could ever be of long continuance.

24. Think of the totality of all Being, and what a mite of it is yours; think of all Time, and the brief fleeting instant of it that is allotted to yourself; think of Destiny, and how puny a part of it you are.

25. Is one doing me wrong? Let himself look to that; his humours and his actions are his own. As for me, I am only receiving what the World-Nature wills me to receive, and acting as my own nature wills me to act.

26. Let no emotions of the flesh, be they of pain or pleasure, affect the supreme and sovereign portion of the soul. See that it never becomes involved with them: it must limit itself to its own domain, and keep the feelings confined to their proper sphere. If (through the sympathy which permeates any unified organism) they do spread to the mind, there need be no attempt to resist the physical sensation; only, the master-reason must refrain from adding its own assumptions of their goodness or badness.

27. Live with the gods. To live with the gods is to show them at all times a soul contented with their awards, and wholly fulfilling the will of that inward divinity, that particle of himself, which Zeus has given to every man for ruler and guide — the mind and the reason.

28. Do unsavoury armpits and bad breath make you angry? What good will it do you? Given the mouth and armpits the man has got, that condition is bound to produce those odours. 'After all, though, the fellow is endowed with reason, and he is perfectly able to understand what is offensive if he gives any thought to it.' Well and good: but you yourself are also endowed with reason; so apply your reasonableness to move him to a like reasonableness; expound, admonish. If he pays attention, you will have worked a cure, and there will be no need for passion; leave that to actors and streetwalkers.

29. It is possible to live on earth as you mean to live hereafter. But if men will not let you, then quit the house of life; though not with any feeling of ill-usage. 'The hut smokes; I move out.' No need to make a great business of it. Nevertheless, so long as nothing of the kind obliges me to depart, here I remain, my own master, and none shall hinder me from doing what I choose — and what I choose is to live the life that nature enjoins for a reasonable member of a social community.

30. The Mind of the universe is social. At all events, it has created the lower forms to serve the higher, and then linked together the higher in a mutual dependence on each other. Observe how some are subjected, others are connected, each and all are given their just due, and the more eminent among them are combined in mutual accord.

31. How have you behaved in the past to the gods, to your parents, your brothers, wife, children, teachers, tutors, friends, relatives, household? In all of these relationships, up to the present time, can you fairly echo the poet's line, 'Never a harsh word, never an injustice to a single person?' Call to mind all you have passed through, and all you have been enabled to endure. Reflect that the story of your life is over, and your service at an end; bethink you of all the fair sights you have seen, the pleasures and the pains you have spurned, the many honours disdained, the many considerations shown to the inconsiderate.

32. How comes it that souls of no proficiency nor learning are able to confound the adept and the sage? Ah, but what soul is truly both adept and sage? His alone, who has knowledge of the beginning and the end, and of that all-pervading Reason which orders the universe in its determinate cycles to the end of time.

33. In a brief while now you will be ashes or bare bones; a name, or perhaps not even a name — though even a name is no more than empty sound and reiteration. All that men set their hearts on in this life is vanity, corruption, and trash; men are like scuffling puppies, or quarrelsome children who are all smiles one moment and in tears the next. Faith and decency, justice and truth are fled 'up to Olympus from the wide-wayed earth'. What is it, then, that still keeps you here? The objects of sense are mutable and transient, the organs of sense dim and easily misled, the poor soul itself a mere vapour exhaled from the blood,[〔3〕] and the world's praise, in such conditions, a vain thing. What then? Take heart, and wait for the end, be it extinction or translation. And what, think you, is all that is needful until that hour come? Why, what else but to revere and bless the gods; to do good to men; to bear and forbear; and to remember that whatsoever lies outside the bounds of this poor flesh and breath is none of yours, nor in your power.

34. Press on steadily, keep to the straight road in your thinking and doing, and your days will ever flow on smoothly. The soul of man, like the souls of all rational creatures, has two things in common with the soul of God: it can never be thwarted from without, and its good consists in righteousness of character and action, and in confining every wish thereto.

35. If the thing be no sin of mine, nor caused by any sin of mine, and if society be no worse for it, why give it further thought? How can it harm society?

36. Do not fall a too hasty prey to first impressions. Assist those in need, so far as you are able and they deserve it; but if their fall involves nothing morally significant, you must not regard them as really injured, for that is not a good practice. Rather, in such cases be like the old fellow who pretended at his departure to beg eagerly for the slave-girl's top,[〔4〕] though knowing well that it was nothing more than a top.

When you are crying for votes on the platform, my friend, are you forgetting the ultimate worth of it all? 'I know; but these people set such store by it.' And does that justify you in sharing their folly?

No matter to what solitudes banished, I have always been a favourite of Fortune. For Fortune's favourite is the man who awards her good gifts to himself — the good gifts of a good disposition, good impulses, and good deeds.

注　释

〔1〕　The reference is to the so-called 'Sceptic' or Pyrrhonian school of philosophers, founded by Pyrrho of Elis. They maintained that our perceptions can only show us things as they appear, and not as they are, and that a suspension of judgement is therefore the only correct attitude to anything.

〔2〕　This paragraph turns on the ambiguous meaning of the word 'goods'. The man in the street understands it to signify worldly possessions, rather than those virtues of character which are the true 'goods' in life. To a philosopher, on the other hand, the word would naturally convey this latter sense; and he would accordingly be puzzled by a reference to someone 'having so many goods that he has no room to relieve himself anywhere'.

〔3〕　According to the Stoic belief, the particle of divine fire which constitutes man's soul is nourished by the blood.

〔4〕　The 'old fellow' made a kindly pretence of sharing the child's notion that its top was a precious and desirable treasure. In the same way, says Marcus, we should be sympathetic to the distress of others, even when our superior knowledge tells us that they have suffered no real harm.

Book Six

1. Matter in the universe is supple and compliant, and the Reason which controls it has no motive for ill-doing; for it is without malice, and does nothing with intent to injure, neither is anything harmed by it. By its ordinances all things have their birth and their fulfilment.

2. If you are doing what is right, never mind whether you are freezing with cold or beside a good fire; heavy-eyed, or fresh from a sound sleep; reviled or applauded; in the act of dying, or about some other piece of business. (For even dying is part of the business of life; and there too no more is required of us than 'to see the moment's work well done'.)

3. Look beneath the surface: never let a thing's intrinsic quality or worth escape you.

4. All material objects swiftly change: either by sublimation (if the substance of the universe be indeed a unity), or else by dispersion.

5. Reason, the controller, has a perfect understanding of the conditions, the purpose, and the materials of its work.

6. To refrain from imitation is the best revenge.

7. Let your one delight and refreshment be to pass from one service to the community to another, with God ever in mind.

8. Our master-reason is something which is both self-awakened and self-directed. It cannot only make itself what it will, but also impose the aspect of its choice on anything which it experiences.

9. All things come to their fulfilment as the one universal Nature directs; for there is no rival nature, whether containing her from without, or itself contained within her, or even existing apart and detached from her.

10. Either the world is a mere hotch-potch of random cohesions and dispersions, or else it is a unity of order and providence. If the former, why wish to survive in such a purposeless and chaotic confusion; why care about anything, save the manner of the ultimate return to dust; why trouble my head at all; since, do what I will, dispersion must overtake me sooner or later? But if the contrary be true, then I do reverence, I stand firmly, and I put my trust in the directing Power.

11. When force of circumstance upsets your equanimity, lose no time in recovering your self-control, and do not remain out of tune longer than you can help. Habitual recurrence to the harmony will increase your mastery of it.

12. If you had a stepmother at the same time as a mother, you would do your duty by the former, but would still turn continually to your mother. Here, you have both: the court and philosophy. Time and again turn back to philosophy for refreshment; then even the court life, and yourself in it, will seem bearable.

13. When meat and other dainties are before you, you reflect: This is dead fish, or fowl, or pig; or: This Falernian is some of the juice from a bunch of grapes; my purple robe is sheep's wool stained with a little gore from a shellfish; copulation is friction of the members and an ejaculatory discharge. Reflections of this kind go to the bottom of things, penetrating into them and exposing their real nature. The same process should be applied to the whole of life. When a thing's credentials look most plausible, lay it bare, observe its triviality, and strip it of the cloak of verbiage that dignifies it. Pretentiousness is the arch deceiver, and never more delusive than when you imagine your work is most meritorious. Note what Crates has to say about Xenocrates himself.

14. The vulgar confine their admiration chiefly to things of an elementary order, which exist by virtue of mere inorganic cohesion or processes of nature; things of timber and stone, for example, or groves of figs and vines and olives. Minds of a somewhat higher degree of enlightenment are attracted by things that have animation, such as flocks and herds. A further step in refinement leads to admiration of the rational soul: rational, however, not yet in the sense of being part of the universal Reason, but simply as possessing certain skills in handicraft or other such talents — or even merely as owning large numbers of slaves. But the man who values a soul that is rational and universal and social no longer cares for anything else, but aims solely at keeping the temper of his own soul and all its activities rational and social, and works together with his fellows to this end.

15. One thing hastens into being, another hastens out of it. Even while a thing is in the act of coming into existence, some part of it has already ceased to be. Flux and change are for ever renewing the fabric of the universe, just as the ceaseless sweep of time is for ever renewing the face of eternity. In such a running river, where there is no firm foothold, what is there for a man to value among all the many things that are racing past him? It would be like setting the affections on some sparrow flitting by, which in the selfsame moment is lost to sight. A man's life is no more than an inhalation from the air and an exhalation from the blood; and there is no true difference between drawing in a single breath, only to emit it again, as we do every instant, and receiving the power to breathe at all, as you did but yesterday at your birth, only to yield it back one day to the source from which you drew it.

16. Transpiration is not a thing to be prized; we share it with the plants. Nor is respiration; we share that with the beasts of field and forest. Nor the perceptions of the senses, nor the twitchings of impulse, nor the instinct for gregariousness, nor the process of nutrition — which is in fact no more wonderful than that of excretion. So what, then, are we to value? The clapping of hands? No; and not the clapping of tongues either, which is all that the praise of the vulgar amounts to. Excluding then the delusions of fame, what is there left to be prized? In my judgement, this: to work out, in action and inaction alike, the purpose of our natural constitutions. That, after all, is the object of all training and all craftsmanship; for every craft aims at adapting a product to the end for which it was produced. The husbandman tending his vine, the groom breaking in his horse, the kennelman training his hound, all have this purpose in view. The labours of tutors and teachers, too, are directed to the same end. Here then is the prize we are looking for. Once make this truly your own, and no other objective will tempt you. Abandon all the other ambitions you cherish, or else you will never be your own master, never be independent of others or proof against passion. You will be bound to look with envy, jealousy, and suspicion at anyone who might rob you of those things, and to intrigue against anyone who happens to possess the treasure you covet for yourself. The belief that things of that kind are indispensable is sure to make for turmoil within, and too often leads on to murmuring against the gods as well; whereas a respect and esteem for your own understanding will keep you at peace with yourself, at one with mankind, and in harmony with the gods; gladly acquiescent, that is, with whatever they dispense or ordain.

17. Above, below, and around us whirl the elements in their courses. But virtue knows no such motions: she is a thing more divine, moving serenely onward in ways past understanding.

18. How strange are the ways of men! They will spare no word of praise for their contemporaries, who live in their very midst, and yet they covet greatly for themselves the praise of future generations, whom they have never seen and never will see. Almost as well grumble at not having praise from one's ancestors!

19. Because a thing is difficult for you, do not therefore suppose it to be beyond mortal power. On the contrary, if anything is possible and proper for man to do, assume that it must fall within your own capacity.

20. When an opponent in the gymnasium gashes us with his nails or bruises our head in a collision, we do not protest or take offence, and we do not suspect him ever afterwards of malicious intent. However, we do regard him with a wary eye; not in enmity or suspicion, yet good-temperedly keeping our distance. So let it be, too, at other times in life; let us agree to overlook a great many things in those who are, as it were, our fellow-contestants. A simple avoidance, as I have said, is always open to us, without either suspicion or ill will.

21. If anyone can show me, and prove to me, that I am wrong in thought or deed, I will gladly change. I seek the truth, which never yet hurt anybody. It is only persistence in self-delusion and ignorance which does harm.

22. I do that which it is my duty to do. Nothing else distracts me; for it will be either something that is inanimate and irrational, or somebody who is misled and ignorant of the way.

23. Be generous and liberal in your attitude to irrational creatures and to the generality of material things, for you have reason and they have none. Human beings, on the other hand, have reason; so treat them in a spirit of fellowship. In all things call upon the gods for help — yet without too many scruples about the length of your prayers; three hours so spent will suffice.

24. In death, Alexander of Macedon's end differed no whit from his stable-boy's. Either both were received into the same generative principle of the universe, or both alike were dispersed into atoms.

25. Think of the number of things, bodily and mental, that are going on at the same moment within each one of us; and then it will not surprise you that an infinitely greater number of things — everything, in fact, that comes to birth in this vast One-and-All we call the universe — can exist simultaneously therein.

26. If you were asked to spell the name Antoninus, would you rap out each letter at the top of your voice, and then, if your hearers grew angry, grow angry yourself in turn? Rather, would you not proceed to enumerate the several letters quietly one by one? Well then; remember that here in life every piece of duty is likewise made up of its separate items. Pay careful attention to each of these, without fuss and without returning temper for temper, and so ensure the methodical completion of your appointed task.

27. How barbarous, to deny men the privilege of pursuing what they imagine to be their proper concerns and interests! Yet, in a sense, this is just what you are doing when you allow your indignation to rise at their wrongdoing; for after all, they are only following their own apparent concerns and interests. You say they are mistaken? Why then, tell them so, and explain it to them, instead of being indignant.

28. Death: a release from impressions of sense, from twitchings of appetite, from excursions of thought, and from service to the flesh.

29. Shame on the soul, to falter on the road of life while the body still perseveres.

30. Be careful not to affect the monarch too much, or to be too deeply dyed with the purple; for this can well happen. Keep yourself simple, good, pure, serious, and unassuming; the friend of justice and godliness; kindly, affectionate, and resolute in your devotion to duty. Strive your hardest to be always such a man as Philosophy would have you to be. Reverence the gods, succour your fellow-mortals. Life is short, and this earthly existence has but a single fruit to yield — holiness within, and selfless action without. Be in all things Antoninus's disciple; remember his insistence on the control of conduct by reason, his calm composure on all occasions, and his own holiness; the serenity of his look and the sweetness of his manner; his scorn of notoriety, and his zeal for the mastery of facts; how he would never dismiss a subject until he had looked thoroughly into it and understood it clearly; how he would suffer unjust criticisms without replying in kind; how he was never hasty, and no friend to tale-bearers; shrewd in his judgements of men and manners, yet never censorious; wholly free from nervousness, suspicion, and oversubtlety; how easily satis fied he was in such matters as lodging, bed, dress, meals, and service; how industrious, and how patient; how, thanks to his frugal diet, he could remain at work from morning till night without even attending to the calls of nature until his customary hour; how firm and constant he was in his friendships, tolerating the most outspoken opposition to his own opinions, and welcoming any suggested amendments; what reverence, untainted by the smallest trace of superstition, he showed to the gods. Remember all this, so that when your own last hour comes your conscience may be as clear as his.

31. Come back now to your sober senses; recall your true self; awake from slumber, and recognize that they were only dreams that troubled you; and as you looked on them, so look now on what meets your waking eyes.

32. A body and a soul comprise myself. To the body all things are indifferent, for it is incapable of making distinctions. To the mind, the only things not indifferent are its own activities, and these are all under its control. Even with them, moreover, its sole concern is with those of the present moment; once they are past, or when they still lie in the future, they themselves at once come to be indifferent.

33. Pain of hand or foot is nothing unnatural, so long as hand and foot are doing their own work. Likewise no pain is contrary to the nature of man, as man, so long as he is doing man's work. And if it accords with nature, it cannot be an evil.

34. In what extraordinary pleasures do robbers, perverts, parricides, and tyrants find their enjoyment!

35. Notice how common artificers will meet the wishes of an unskilled employer up to a certain point, but none the less stand fast by the rules of their trade and refuse to depart from them. Is it not deplorable that a builder or a physician should have more respect for the canons of his craft than man has for his own, which he shares with the gods?

36. In the universe Asia and Europe are but two small corners, all oceans' waters a drop, Athos a puny lump of earth, the vastness of time a pin's point in eternity. All is petty, inconstant, and perishable. All proceeds from the one source, springing either directly or derivatively from the universal sovereign Reason. Even the lion's open jaws, the deadly poison, and all other things that do hurt, down to the bramble-bush and the slough, are by-products of something else that is itself noble and beautiful. Do not think of them, then, as alien to That which you reverence, but remember the one origin that is common to them all.

37. To see the things of the present moment is to see all that is now, all that has been since time began, and all that shall be unto the world's end; for all things are of one kind and one form.

38. Think often of the bond that unites all things in the universe, and their dependence upon one another. All are, as it were, interwoven, and in consequence linked in mutual affection; because their orderly succession is brought about by the operation of the currents of tension, and the unity of all substance.

39. Adapt yourself to the environment in which your lot has been cast, and show true love to the fellow-mortals with whom destiny has surrounded you.

40. All is well with a tool, instrument, or utensil when it serves the use for which it was made, though in this case its maker is not present. But with things formed by Nature, the power that fashioned them is still within them, and remains in them. All the more, then, should you have it in reverence, and be assured that if only you live and act according to its will, you have all things to your liking. That is the way in which the universe, too, has all things to its liking.

41. If you suppose anything over which you have no control to be either good or bad for you, then the accident of missing the one or encountering the other is certain to make you aggrieved with the gods, and bitter against the men whom you know or suspect to be responsible for your failure or misfortune. We do, in fact, commit many injustices through attaching importance to things of this class. But when we limit our notions of good and evil strictly to what is within our own power, there remains no reason either to bring accusations against God or to set ourselves at variance with men.

42. All of us are working together for the same end; some of us knowingly and purposefully, others unconsciously (as Heraclitus, I think, has remarked that 'even in their sleep men are at work' and contributing their share to the cosmic process). To one man falls this share of the task, to another that; indeed, no small part is performed by that very malcontent who does all he can to hinder and undo the course of events. The universe has need even of such as he. It remains for you, then, to consider with whom you will range yourself; for in any case he who directs all things will find some good use to make of you, and give you your place among his helpmates and fellow-labourers. Only, have a care that yours is not that sorry function which, according to Chrysippus, is performed by the clown's part on the stage.[〔1〕]

43. Does the sun think to do the rain's work? Or Asclepius that of Demeter? And how is it with the stars? Are they not all different, yet all work in concert to the one end?

44. If the gods took counsel together about myself, and what should befall me, then their counsel was good. For it were hard to conceive of divinity counselling unwisely. After all, what incentive would they have to work my hurt? Where would be the gain, either to themselves, or to the universe which is their chief care? Even if they took no special thought for myself, at least they took thought for the universe; and I ought to welcome and feel kindly disposed towards anything that happens as a result. If, of course, they took no thought for anything at all — an impious thing to believe — why then, let us make an end of sacrifice and prayer and vow, and all other actions whereby we acknowledge the presence of living gods in our midst. Yet even so, and even if it is true that they care nothing for our mortal concerns, I am still able to take care of myself and to look to my own interests; and the interest of every creature lies in conformity with its own constitution and nature. My own nature is a rational and civic one; I have a city, and I have a country; as Marcus I have Rome, and as a human being I have the universe; and consequently, what is beneficial to these communities is the sole good for me.

45. All that befalls the individual is for the good of the whole. That by itself is warrant enough for us; but if you look closely you will also notice that, as a general rule, what is good for one man is good for his fellow-men as well. ('Good', though, must be taken here in the more popular sense, as inclusive of things that are morally indifferent.)

46. As the performances in the circus or in other places of entertainment tire one with their perpetual repetition of the same sights, the monotony of which makes the spectacle a weariness, so it is with the whole experience of life: on our upward and downward path all things prove to be ever the same — causes and effects alike. How long then...?

47. Often ponder in your mind the multitudes of the dead of every calling and nation, down even to Philistion and Phoebus and Origanion. From these latest, let your thoughts pass to the hosts of others; think how we must follow whither so many great orators are gone before, so many reverend sages — Heraclitus, Pythagoras, Socrates — the heroes of early days, the captains and the kings of after-ages, and with them Eudoxus, Hipparchus, Archimedes, and many another; keen wits, sublime spirits, men unwearied, resourceful, and resolute; those too who made a merry jest of the transience and brevity of this mortal life in the fashion of Menippus and his school. Muse often on these men, all long since laid low in death. How, pray, are they the worse for it now — more especially those whose very names have been forgotten? In this life one thing only is of precious worth: to live out one's days in truthfulness and fair dealing, and in charity even with the false and unjust.

48. When you would have a cordial for your spirits, think of the good qualities of your friends: this one's capability, that one's self-effacement, another's generosity, and so forth. There is no surer remedy for dejection than to see examples of the different virtues displayed in the characters of those around us, exhibiting themselves as plenteously as can be. Wherefore keep them ever before you.

49. Do you make a grievance of weighing so many pounds only, instead of three hundred? Then why fret about living so many years only, instead of more? Since you are content with the measure of substance allowed you, be so also with the measure of time.

50. Try to move men by persuasion; yet act against their will if the principles of justice so direct. But if someone uses force to obstruct you, then take a different line; resign yourself without a pang, and turn the obstacle into an opportunity for the exercise of some other virtue. Your attempt was always subject to reservations, remember; you were not aiming at the impossible. At what, then? Simply at making the attempt itself. In this you succeeded; and with that, the object of your existence is attained.

51. The man of ambition thinks to find his good in the operations of others; the man of pleasure in his own sensations; but the man of understanding in his own actions.

52. You are not compelled to form any opinion about this matter before you, nor to disturb your peace of mind at all. Things in themselves have no power to extort a verdict from you.

53. Accustom yourself to give careful attention to what others are saying, and try your best to enter into the mind of the speaker.

54. What is no good for the hive is no good for the bee.

55. If the crew took to vilifying their steersman, or the patients their doctor, is there any other they would listen to instead; and how would such another be able to ensure the safety of the sailors, or the health of the sick?

56. How many who came into this world with me have already left it!

57. To a man with jaundice, honey seems bitter; to one bitten by a mad dog, water is a thing of horror; to little children, a ball is a treasure of great price. Why then do I give way to anger? For can it be supposed that a man's erroneous thinking has any less effect on him than the bile in jaundice, or the virus in hydrophobia?

58. No one can stop you living according to the laws of your own personal nature, and nothing can happen to you against the laws of the World-Nature.

59. What sorry creatures are the men folk seek to please! What sorry ends they pursue, and by what sorry means! How quickly time shall cover all things! How many has it covered even now!

注　释

〔1〕　i.e. to provide that element of baseness against which nobility shows up more clearly.

Book Seven

1. What is evil? A thing you have seen times out of number. Likewise with every other sort of occurrence also, be prompt to remind yourself that this, too, you have witnessed many times before. For everywhere, above and below, you will find nothing but the selfsame things; they fill the pages of all history, ancient, modern, and contemporary; and they fill our cities and homes today. There is no such thing as novelty; all is as trite as it is transitory.

2. Principles can only lose their vitality when the first impressions from which they derive have sunk into extinction; and it is for you to keep fanning these continually into fresh flame. I am well able to form the right impression of a thing; and given this ability, there is no need to disquiet myself. (As for things that are beyond my understanding, they are no concern of my understanding.) Once learn this, and you stand erect. A new life lies within your grasp. You have only to see things once more in the light of your first and earlier vision, and life begins anew.

3. An empty pageant; a stage play; flocks of sheep, herds of cattle; a tussle of spearmen; a bone flung among a pack of curs; a crumb tossed into a pond of fish; ants, loaded and labouring; mice, scared and scampering; puppets, jerking on their strings — that is life. In the midst of it all you must take your stand, good-temperedly and without disdain, yet always aware that a man's worth is no greater than the worth of his ambitions.

4. In talk, mark carefully what is being said, and when action is afoot, what is being done. In the latter case, look at once to see what is purposed; and in the other, make certain what is meant.

5. Is my understanding equal to this task, or not? If it is, I apply it to the work as a tool presented to me by Nature. If not, then either I make way — if my duty permits it — for someone more capable of doing the business, or else I do the best I can with the help of some assistant, who will avail himself of my inspiration to achieve what is timely and serviceable for the community. For everything I do, whether by myself or with another, must have as its sole aim the service and harmony of all.

6. How many whose praises used once to be sung so loudly are now relegated to oblivion; and how many of the singers themselves have long since passed from our sight!

7. Think it no shame to be helped. Your business is to do your appointed duty, like a soldier in the breach. How, then, if you are lame, and unable to scale the battlements yourself, but could do it if you had the aid of a comrade?

8. Never let the future disturb you. You will meet it, if you have to, with the same weapons of reason which today arm you against the present.

9. All things are interwoven with one another; a sacred bond unites them; there is scarcely one thing that is isolated from another. Everything is coordinated, everything works together in giving form to the one universe. The world-order is a unity made up of multiplicity: God is one, pervading all things; all being is one, all law is one (namely, the common reason which all thinking creatures possess) and all truth is one — if, as we believe, there can be but one path to perfection for beings that are alike in kind and reason.

10. Swiftly each particle of matter vanishes into the universal Substance; swiftly each item of causation is reassumed into the universal Reason; swiftly the remembrance of all things is buried in the gulf of eternity.

11. To a reasoning being, an act that accords with nature is an act that accords with reason.

12. To stand up — or be set up?

13. In a system comprising diverse elements, those which possess reason have the same part to play as the bodily limbs in an organism that is a unity; being similarly constituted for mutual cooperation. This reflection will impress you more forcibly if you constantly tell yourself, 'I am a "limb" (melos) of the whole complex of rational things.' If you think of yourself as a 'part' (meros) only, you have as yet no love from the heart for mankind, and no joy in the performance of acts of kindness for their own sake. You do them as a bare duty, and not yet as good offices to yourself.

14. Come what will upon such parts of me as can be affected by its incidence; they may complain of it if they will. As for myself, if I do not view the thing as an evil, I take no hurt. And nothing compels me to view it so.

15. Whatever the world may say or do, my part is to keep myself good; just as a gold piece, or an emerald, or a purple robe insists perpetually, 'Whatever the world may say or do, my part is to remain an emerald and keep my colour true.'

16. The master-reason is never the victim of any self-disturbance; it never, for example, excites passions within itself. If another can inspire it with terror or pain, let him do so; but by itself it never permits its own assumptions to mislead it into such moods. By all means let the body take thought for itself to avoid hurt, if it can; and if it be hurt, let it say so. But the soul, which alone can know fear or pain, and on whose judgement their existence depends, takes no harm; you cannot force the verdict from it. The master-reason is self-sufficient, knowing no needs except those it creates for itself, and by the same token can experience no disturbances or obstructions unless they be of its own making.

17. Happiness, by derivation, means 'a good god within';[〔1〕] that is, a good master-reason. Then what, vain Fancy, are you doing here? Be off, in heaven's name, as you came; I want none of you. I know it is long habit that brings you here, and I bear no ill-will; but get you gone.

18. We shrink from change; yet is there anything that can come into being without it? What does Nature hold dearer, or more proper to herself? Could you have a hot bath unless the firewood underwent some change? Could you be nourished if the food suffered no change? Is it possible for any useful thing to be achieved without change? Do you not see, then, that change in yourself is of the same order, and no less necessary to Nature?

19. All bodies pass through the universal substance, as it were into and out of a rushing stream; cohering and cooperating with the whole, as do our physical members with one another. How many a Chrysippus, a Socrates, an Epictetus has been engulfed by time! Remember this when you have to do with any man or thing whatsoever.

20. One thing alone troubles me: the fear that I may do something which man's constitution disallows, or would wish to be done in some other way, or forbids till a future day.

21. Soon you will have forgotten the world, and soon the world will have forgotten you.

22. It is man's peculiar distinction to love even those who err and go astray. Such a love is born as soon as you realize that they are your brothers; that they are stumbling in ignorance, and not wilfully; that in a short while both of you will be no more; and, above all, that you yourself have taken no hurt, for your master-reason has not been made a jot worse than it was before.

23. Out of the universal substance, as out of wax, Nature fashions a colt, then breaks him up and uses the material to form a tree, and after that a man, and next some other thing; and not one of these endures for more than a brief span. As for the vessel itself, it is no greater hardship to be taken to pieces than to be put together.

24. An angry look on the face is wholly against nature. If it be assumed frequently, beauty begins to perish, and in the end is quenched beyond rekindling. You must try to realize that this shows the unreasonableness of it; for if we lose the ability to perceive our faults, what is the good of living on?

25. Only a little while, and Nature, the universal disposer, will change everything you see, and out of their substance will make fresh things, and yet again others from theirs, to the perpetual renewing of the world's youthfulness.

26. When anyone offends against you, let your first thought be, Under what conception of good and ill was this committed? Once you know that, astonishment and anger will give place to pity. For either your own ideas of what is good are no more advanced than his, or at least bear some likeness to them, in which case it is clearly your duty to pardon him; or else, on the other hand, you have grown beyond supposing such actions to be either good or bad, and therefore it will be so much the easier to be tolerant of another's blindness.

27. Do not indulge in dreams of having what you have not, but reckon up the chief of the blessings you do possess, and then thankfully remember how you would crave for them if they were not yours. At the same time, however, beware lest delight in them leads you to cherish them so dearly that their loss would destroy your peace of mind.

28. Withdraw into yourself. Our master-reason asks no more than to act justly, and thereby to achieve calm.

29. Do away with all fancies. Cease to be passion's puppet. Limit time to the present. Learn to recognize every experience for what it is, whether it be your own or another's. Divide and classify the objects of sense into cause and matter. Meditate upon your last hour. Leave your neighbour's wrongdoing to rest with him who initiated it.

30. Fix your thought closely on what is being said, and let your mind enter fully into what is being done, and into what is doing it.

31. Put on the shining face of simplicity and self-respect, and of indifference to everything outside the realms of virtue or vice. Love mankind. Walk in God's ways. 'All under law,' quoth the sage; and what though his saying had reference to atoms alone? For us, it suffices to remember that all things are indeed under law. Three words, but enough.

32. Of Death. Dispersion, if the world be a concourse of atoms: extinction or transmutation, if it be a unity.

33. Of Pain. If it is past bearing, it makes an end of us; if it lasts, it can be borne. The mind, holding itself aloof from the body, retains its calm, and the master-reason remains unaffected. As for the parts injured by the pain, let them, if they can, declare their own grief.

34. Of Fame. Take a look at the minds of her suitors, their ambitions and their aversions. Furthermore, reflect how speedily in this life the things of today are buried under those of tomorrow, even as one layer of drifting sand is quickly covered by the next.

35. 'If a man has greatness of mind, and the breadth of vision to contemplate all time and all reality, can he regard human life as a thing of any great consequence?' — 'No, he cannot.' — 'So he won't think death anything to be afraid of?' — 'No.' (From Plato.)

36. 'It is the fate of princes to be ill spoken of for well-doing.' (From Antisthenes.)

37. It is a shame for the features to order and dispose themselves obediently as the mind directs, while the same mind refuses to order and dispose itself.

38. 'Vex not thy spirit at the course of things;

They heed not thy vexation.'

39. 'To the deathless gods and likewise to ourselves give joy.'

40. 'Like ears of corn the lives of men are reaped;

This one is left to stand, and that cut down.'

41. 'If Heav'n care nought for me and my two boys,

There must be some good reason even for this.'

42. 'Right and good fortune both are on my side.'

43. 'No tears with those who wail, no quickening of the pulse.'

44. 'I might fairly reply to him, You are mistaken, my friend, if you think that a man who is worth anything ought to spend his time weighing up the prospects of life and death. He has only one thing to consider in performing any action: that is, whether he is acting rightly or wrongly, like a good man or a bad one.' (From Plato.)

45. 'The truth of the matter is this, gentlemen. When a man has once taken up his stand, either because it seems best to him or in obedience to orders, there I believe he is bound to remain and face the danger, taking no account of death or anything else before dishonour.' (From Plato.)

46. 'But I beg you, my friend, to think it possible that nobility and goodness may be something different from keeping oneself and one's friends from danger, and to consider whether a true man, instead of clinging to life at all costs, ought not to dismiss from his mind the question how long he may have to live. Let him leave that to the will of God, in the belief that the womenfolk are right when they tell us that no man can escape his destiny, and let him devote himself to the next problem, how he can best live the life allotted to him.' (From Plato.)

47. Survey the circling stars, as though yourself were in mid-course with them. Often picture the changing and rechanging dance of the elements. Visions of this kind purge away the dross of our earth-bound life.

48. Plato has a fine saying, that he who would discourse of man should survey, as from some high watchtower, the things of earth; its assemblies for peace or war, its husbandry, matings, and partings, births and deaths, noisy law courts, lonely wastes, alien peoples of every kind, feasting, mourning, bargaining — observing all the motley mixture, and the harmonious order that is wrought out of contrariety.

49. Look back over the past, with its changing empires that rose and fell, and you can foresee the future too. Its pattern will be the same, down to the last detail; for it cannot break step with the steady march of creation. To view the lives of men for forty years or forty thousand is therefore all one; for what more will there be for you to see?

50. 'All born of earth must unto earth return;

All growths of heav'nly seed to heav'n revert.'

— by the disintegration, that is, of their atomic structure and the dispersion of their uncaring elements.

51. 'What, turn aside with meats and drinks and charms

The tides of Destiny, and so 'scape Death?'

'The gales that blow from God must needs be faced

With labouring oars and uncomplaining hearts.'

52. 'More crafty in the ring,' no doubt — but not more public-spirited, more self-effacing, more disciplined to circumstance, more indulgent to a neighbour's oversights.

53. If a deed can be accomplished to accord with that reason which men share with gods, there is nothing to fear. Where a chance of service presents itself, by some action that will go smoothly forward in obedience to the laws of our being, we need look for no harm.

54. In your power at all times and places there lies a pious acceptance of the day's happenings, a just dealing towards the day's associates, and a scrupulous attention to the day's impressions, lest any of them gain an entrance unverified.

55. Cast no side-glance at the instincts governing other men, but keep your eyes fixed on the goal whereto nature herself guides you — the World-Nature speaking through circumstance, and your own nature speaking through the calls of duty. The acts of man should accord with his natural constitution; and while all other created things are constituted for the service of rational beings (in accordance with the general law by which the lower exists for the good of the higher), these latter are constituted to serve one another. Chief of all features in a man's constitution, therefore, is his duty to his kind. Next after that comes his obligation to resist the murmurs of the flesh; for it is the particular office of his reason and intellect to maintain such a fence around their own workings that they are not overborne by those of the senses or the impulses, both of which are animal in quality. Mind demands the premier place, and will not bow to their yoke; and rightly so, since nature has formed it to make use of all the rest. And thirdly, the constitution of a rational being should make him incapable of indiscretion, and proof against imposture. Let but Reason, the helmsman, steer a straight course, holding fast by these three principles, and be sure it will come by its own.

56. Take it that you have died today, and your life's story is ended; and henceforward regard what further time may be given you as an uncovenanted surplus, and live it out in harmony with nature.

57. Love nothing but that which comes to you woven in the pattern of your destiny. For what could more aptly fit your needs?

58. In any predicament, have before your eyes the case of other men who greeted a like crisis with indignation, astonishment, and outcry. Where are they now? Nowhere. Then why wish to follow their example? Rather, leave another's humours to their own master or servant, and give all your attention to turning the event itself to some good account. In this way you will be making the best use of it, and it will serve you as working material. In every action let your own self-approval be the sole aim both of your effort and of your intention; bearing in mind that the event itself which prompted your action is a thing of no consequence to either of them.

59. Dig within. There lies the well-spring of good: ever dig, and it will ever flow.

60. Also let your bodily carriage be firm, and without contortions, whether in motion or at rest. As the mind reveals itself in the face, by keeping the features composed and decent, so the same should be required of it in respect of the whole body. All this, however, must be ensured without any sort of affectation.

61. The art of living is more like wrestling than dancing, in as much as it, too, demands a firm and watchful stance against any unexpected onset.

62. Always get to know the characters of those whose approval you wish to earn, and the nature of their guiding principles. Look into the sources of their opinions and their motives, and then you will not blame any of their involuntary offences, or feel the want of their approbation.

63. 'No soul', it has been said, 'forfeits truth wilfully.' And the same holds good for justice, self-control, kindliness, or any other virtue. Nothing needs to be kept in mind more constantly than this; it will help you to greater gentleness in all your dealings with people.

64. When in pain, always be prompt to remind yourself that there is nothing shameful about it and nothing prejudicial to the mind at the helm, which suffers no injury either in its rational or its social aspect. In most cases the saying of Epicurus should prove helpful, that 'Pain is never unbearable or unending, so long as you remember its limitations and do not indulge in fanciful exaggerations.' Bear in mind also that, though we do not realize it, many other things which we find uncomfortable are, in fact, of the same nature as pain: feelings of lethargy, for example, or a feverish temperature, or loss of appetite. When inclined to grumble at any of these, tell yourself that you are giving in to pain.

65. When men are inhuman, take care not to feel towards them as they do towards other humans.

66. How do we know that Telauges may not have been a better man than Socrates? It is all very well to argue that Socrates died a finer death, or disputed more acutely with the sophists, or stood up more hardily to the rigours of a frosty night; that he spiritedly resisted the order to arrest Leon of Salamis,[〔2〕] or 'stalked the streets in majesty'[〔3〕] (though the truth of this last may well be questioned) — but the real point to consider is, What kind of a soul did he have? Did he ask nothing more than to be found just towards men and pure before the gods? Did he avoid either resentment at the vices of others or submission to their ignorance? Did he accept what destiny assigned to him, not looking on it as something unnatural, nor suffering it as an unbearable affliction, nor allowing his mind to be influenced by the experiences of the flesh?

67. Nature has not blended mind so inextricably with body as to prevent it from establishing its own frontiers and controlling its own domain. It is perfectly possible to be godlike, even though unrecognized as such. Always keep that in mind; and also remember that the needs of a happy life are very few. Mastery of dialectics or physics may have eluded you, but that is no reason to despair of achieving freedom, self-respect, unselfishness, and obedience to the will of God.

68. Live out your days in untroubled serenity, refusing to be coerced though the whole world deafen you with its demands, and though wild beasts rend piecemeal this poor envelope of clay. In all that, nothing can prevent the mind from possessing itself in peace, from correctly assessing the events around it, and from making prompt use of the material thus offered; so that judgement may say to the event, 'This is what you are in essence, no matter how rumour paints you,' and service may say to the opportunity, 'You are what I was looking for.' The occurrence of the moment is always good material for the employment of reason and brotherliness — in a word, for the practices proper to men or gods. For not a thing ever happens but has its special pertinence to god or man; it arrives as no novel intractable problem, but as an old and serviceable friend.

69. To live each day as though one's last, never flustered, never apathetic, never attitudinizing — here is the perfection of character.

70. The gods, though they live for ever, feel no resentment at having to put up eternally with the generations of men and their misdeeds; nay more, they even show every possible care and concern for them. Are you, then, whose abiding is but for a moment, to lose patience — you who are yourself one of the culprits?

71. How ridiculous not to flee from one's own wickedness, which is possible, yet endeavour to flee from another's, which is not.

72. Whatever the reasoning and social faculty finds unthinking or unbrotherly, it can reasonably pronounce inferior to itself.

73. When you have done a good action, and another has had the benefit of it, why crave for yet more in addition — applause for your kindness, or some favour in return — as the foolish do?

74. No man tires of receiving benefits. But benefit comes from doing acts that accord with nature. Never tire, then, of receiving such benefits through the very act of conferring them.

75. Universal Nature's impulse was to create an orderly world. It follows, then, that everything now happening must follow a logical sequence; if it were not so, the prime purpose towards which the impulses of the World-Reason are directed would be an irrational one. Remembrance of this will help you to face many things more calmly.

注　释

〔1〕　This is the meaning of eudaimonia, the Greek word for happiness.

〔2〕　During the reign of terror by the Thirty which succeeded the overthrow of democracy at Athens in 403 BC, many unoffending persons were put to death. When Socrates, with four others, was commanded to arrest an honest citizen, Leon of Salamis, he sturdily refused to carry out the tyrants' bidding.

〔3〕　One of Aristophanes's many gibes at Socrates (Clouds, 362).